<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Daniel Titus letter to Ann Evans, 1794 6mo 28: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Lyra Ederington</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 7 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were created and/or prepared by the <hi rend="italic" >Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</hi> and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <hi rend="italic"> Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College </hi>.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
                <idno type="local">A00187152</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Friendly Networks</title>
                <title level="s" type="series">
                    <title level="s" type="main">The Correspondence of John Hunt and Joshua Evans</title>
                </title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Joshua Evans papers, SFHL-RG5-190</collection>
                        <idno type="local">A00187152</idno>
                        <idno type="IslandoraNodeid">457168</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>2 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The correspondence of Quaker ministers John Hunt and Joshua Evans are stored at the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College. With the generous support of H. David and Joyce E. Hunt, Library staff scanned and transcribed these letters in 2023 and encoded the text in TEI. The 2023 project also included researching individuals mentioned in the text to create and update records about them in the <ref target="https://snaccooperative.org/">Social Networks and Archival Context website</ref></p>           
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written <date when="1794-06-28">28th of 6th month 1794</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <term>Travel</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#lcnaf">
                    <term ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2020100384">Evans, Joshua, 1731-1798</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item><date/></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
            <pb n="001" facs="457169"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>Greenwi<damage><supplied>ch</supplied></damage> State <damage><supplied>of</supplied></damage> Connecticut, <date when="1794-06-28">28th of 6th <damage><supplied>month, 1794</supplied></damage></date></dateline>
                <salute>Respected Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
                although I am a stranger to thee, yet from the acquaintance I had with <rs key="w6c82qz0">thy husband</rs> while in our parts I take the freedom to write to thee, having the request of <rs key="w6c82qz0">thy husband</rs> therein. I may inform thee that I accompanied him from near New York through Connecticut and to the yearly meeting at Rhode Island, and was at diverse meeting on our way where the kind reception of his services and company amongst Friends and others where our lot was cast was comfortable to me. And I may say it hath been satisfactory to me that I have had the opportunity of bearing him company so far, as well as also when I parted with him to find that he was likely to have suitable company.
            </p>
            <p>
                We parted on Rhode Island at the house of our friend <persName key="w6301xxd">Thomas Robinson</persName> the <date when="1794-06-18">18th of this month</date>. He was then in good health and often admired that he had been so much favored therewith in his travels since he left home, considering the weak state he was in a little before he <del>left <gap/></del> set out. He then set forward for Bedford, expecting to take the meetings in his way <add>thereto</add> in company with <persName key="w6qg9m2x">Jacob Mott</persName>. From Bedford he expected to go to Nantucket Quarterly Meeting, and at his return a Friend that seemed very agreeable to him (as well as Friends) by the name of <persName key="w67m1bxt">Thomas Roach</persName> expected <add>to</add> bear him company on the further part of his visit. I have not any doubt <add>but</add> it would be very agreeable to thee to know the sympathy he met with amongst his friends as well as their care in endeavoring to make him comfortable, which appeared far beyond what I can express. Therefore I hope thou may be as comfortable in his absence as possible for a person to be when thus separated from their dear companion.
            </p>
            
            <closer>
                <salute>This from thy friend although stranger,</salute>
                <signed><persName key="w6b38mqv">Daniel Titus</persName></signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>To Ann Evans</trailer>
            </div>
            
            <closer>
                <pb n="002" facs="457170"/>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>To Ann Evans, wife of <persName key="w6c82qz0">Joshua Evans</persName> </addrLine><addrLine>at Haddenfield</addrLine> 
                    <addrLine>To the care of <persName key="w6427nc6">William Savery</persName></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Philadelphia</addrLine>
                </address>
            </closer>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
