<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>George Churchman &amp; Jacob Lindley letter to Evesham Monthly Meeting, 1785 1mo 7: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Lyra Ederington</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 8 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were created and/or prepared by the <hi rend="italic" >Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</hi> and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <hi rend="italic"> Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College </hi>.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
                <idno type="local">A00187150</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Friendly Networks</title>
                <title level="s" type="series">
                    <title level="s" type="main">The Correspondence of John Hunt and Joshua Evans</title>
                </title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Joshua Evans papers, SFHL-RG5-190</collection>
                        <idno type="local">A00187150</idno>
                        <idno type="IslandoraNodeid">457162</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>2 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The correspondence of Quaker ministers John Hunt and Joshua Evans are stored at the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College. With the generous support of H. David and Joyce E. Hunt, Library staff scanned and transcribed these letters in 2023 and encoded the text in TEI. The 2023 project also included researching individuals mentioned in the text to create and update records about them in the <ref target="https://snaccooperative.org/">Social Networks and Archival Context website</ref></p>           
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written <date when="1785-01-07">7th of the 1st month 1785</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <term>Quakers--Conduct of life</term>
                    <term>Simplicity-Religious aspects</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item><date/></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <pb n="001" facs="457163"/>
            
			<head>To Friends of the <del>Monthly Meeting</del> Committee appointed at Evesham Monthly Meeting the <date when="1785-01-07">7th of the 1st month 1785</date> to consider the advices of last Yearly Meeting.</head>
            <opener>
                <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            
            <p>
                From a degree of that <damage><gap/></damage> love and lively hope that accompanied our minds when <damage><gap/></damage> at your Monthly Meeting &amp; often revived since, we feel earnest desires that the cause <damage><gap/></damage> righteousness may prosper <damage><gap/></damage> your hands, and believe much depends on the proper discharge of the important trust committed to your care by the Monthly Meeting <damage><supplied>and</supplied></damage> felt easy to commit a few hints to writing, with much humility <damage><supplied>on</supplied></damage> our own accounts, yet strong desires for the promotion of the pure <damage><supplied>tes</supplied></damage>timony in our day: and in order to be strong in this work, we <damage><supplied>be</supplied></damage>lieve it to be of absolute necessity that our own hands be in a degree clean from pollution of every kind, and especially fr<damage><supplied>om</supplied></damage> that which prompts the spirit, or defrays the expense of <damage><gap/></damage> and it is our hope &amp; be<add>l</add>ief that some who in time of weakness or darkness may have given way to pay requisitions of this kind, may yet come fruitfully to bear their pure testimony, in which we trust, faithful Friends, may be useful<del>ness</del>. Believing also that as deep thoughtfulness takes place, many things will appear for the honest-hearted to be exercised in; &amp; to consider how far it consists with the plainness, simplicity, &amp; purity of truth, to have or use in our families for furniture, or garments, calicoes, printed, stamped, <add>or striped</add> cloths, large scalloped and sometimes gilded frames for looking-glasses, with curling or carving on clock cases &amp; other things, capes on men or women’s coats or cloaks; or suffering minor children to appear with highish bonnets, new fashioned gauze caps, scarlet coloured handkerchiefs, with spots, carved buckles, and other things, which close examination, perhaps we shall find that the purity of truth will not unite with: and how far our <damage><gap/></damage> hands can be strong in treating with the youth under their libertine appearances, may be well to be deeply pondered by those who are entrusted with the weighty concerns of truth. From a lively hope that the pure testimony is as Likely to arise amongst you as in most places, we are encou<damage><supplied>raged</supplied></damage> to communicate these tender hints, hoping they may <damage><gap/></damage> harm, and desiring honest care, and right<damage><gap/></damage>
            
            <pb n="002" facs="457164"/>
                    accompanied with true knowle<add>d</add>ge &amp; meekness, may increase &amp; abound among you, to your mutual comfort and joy, &amp; to the increase of gospel fellowship &amp; union. 
            
            </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>
                    We are your sincere friends, who crave to be your companions in the tribulations of our day &amp; testimony,
                </salute>
                <signed><persName key="w6jd66gz">George Churchman</persName></signed>
                <signed><persName key="w6xf1s5t">Jacob Lindley</persName></signed>
                <dateline>
                    Wrote from <persName key="w66f6jrx">Joseph Kaighn’s</persName> in Newtown Township the <date when="1788-01-12">12th of the 1st month 1788</date>
                </dateline>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
