<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Seth Coleman letter to Joshua Evans, 11mo 15, 1795: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Lyra Ederington</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 9 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were created and/or prepared by the <hi rend="italic" >Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</hi> and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <hi rend="italic"> Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College </hi>.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
                <idno type="local">A00187166</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Friendly Networks</title>
                <title level="s" type="series">
                    <title level="s" type="main">The Correspondence of John Hunt and Joshua Evans</title>
                </title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Joshua Evans papers, SFHL-RG5-190</collection>
                        <idno type="local">A00187166</idno>
                        <idno type="IslandoraNodeid">457218</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>2 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The correspondence of Quaker ministers John Hunt and Joshua Evans are stored at the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College. With the generous support of H. David and Joyce E. Hunt, Library staff scanned and transcribed these letters in 2023 and encoded the text in TEI. The 2023 project also included researching individuals mentioned in the text to create and update records about them in the <ref target="https://snaccooperative.org/">Social Networks and Archival Context website</ref></p>           
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written <date when="1795-11-15">11th month 15th 1795</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <term>Religious gatherings</term>
                    <term>Diseases</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item><date/></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="457219"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>Dartmouth Nova Scotia <date when="1795-11-15">11th month 15th 1795</date></dateline>
                <salute>Esteemed Friend <persName key="w6c82qz0">Joshua Evans</persName></salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
                We hope by the time this may reach thy place of abode thou may be favored to happily join thy family &amp; friends, and would not take it amiss through so direct a conveyance to hear from us &amp; be informed of the present situation of poor Dartmouth. Our friends have almost deserted us two families except our children (of Nantucket<add>Russel</add>) remain which renders it rather disagreeable but yet I cannot conform to leave the few brethren in society behind I at times feel a religious tie on their accounts, and am not without the pleasing prospect of an addiction to our little number in society. Job Young from Anapolis &amp; Andrew Crawford of Halifax &amp; one of Thomas Green’s daughters Thane &amp; son-in-law Elliot has (since thy departure from this) made application to our preparative Meeting to be received members, but their requests have not yet been communicated to our Monthly Meeting. Two of Job’s sons the last account were in prison for nonattendance of military duties and one <del>of</del> more of, Widow Parker’s sons were or had been in confinement on the same account, thou art a better judge than I am, but it appears there is a work on the wheel in them parts, Job is almost a stranger to us consequently more so to our Monthly Meeting, which I think will render it necessary for the Monthly Meeting to have a recommendation of him from some persons that may be more acquainted with his life &amp; conversation. <persName key="w6xf1t3b">Sam Moore</persName> is a neighbor &amp; speaks well of his conduct, Sam was with us a few days ago inform us he has wrote to the Monthly Meeting from when he removed requests they would forward a certificate to Nantucket <add>Monthly Meeting</add> recommending him to its care &amp; membership with them, Friend Crawford appears a well disposed steady man &amp; has been such since our knowledge of him which is about 5 or 6 years past, on the 5th just, was consummated the marriage of our eldest single daughter Elizabeth with a young man by the name of William Raddish was present at the time thou was with us, we had the company of our friend Hartshorne &amp; a number of our Halifax &amp; Dartmouth friends that were strangers to our form of marriage but appeared well pleased and highly applauded the order and decency in which it was conducted. I must not omit mentioning that I lately received
            
            <pb n="2" facs="457220"/>
                a letter from our brother Folger dated Millford 8th month, 3rd last informing of their general good states of health. He further says last first day we had the company of our worthy friends Nicholas Waln &amp; David Bacon both from Philadelphia Robert Grub &amp; Joshua Beal from Ireland with whom they had good satisfaction, I just mention this as it may be the latest account you may of had of the two above named friend &amp; we entertained a hope that we might favored with {some} the company of some traveling friends but as it is not yet the will of our great Master, hope we shall be patient &amp; quie<damage><supplied>t</supplied></damage> sate his time which we ought ever to think the best, I had a letter from our worthy friend Ann King since thou left us the sickness then making it appear in the city, since have heard nothing of the family but hope they may of be<damage><supplied>en</supplied></damage> favored to escape the dreadful pestilence. We in general have been favored with health &amp; very good crops in the country. <persName key="w6xf1t3b">Samuel Moore</persName> told me he had 80 bag<damage><supplied>s</supplied></damage> or more of Indian corn of two acres, common flour is 6 dollars, <damage><gap/></damage> beef 3½ dollars &amp; 4 dollars po<damage><gap/></damage> by &amp; hog 6 dollars &amp; 5 dollars other provisions in proportion which we think tolerable, least I intrude on thy patience being late at night must conclude in love to thee and thine in which my wife &amp; family unite thy affectionate Friend
            </p>
            <closer>
                <signed>S. H Coleman</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
             <p>
             Thomas Green wish to be remembered to thee &amp; thine. This conveyance is by a by a brig belonging to Halifax by which passably thou may have opportunity of breting
             </p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
