<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader></teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="A0011533_001"/>
{1821-08}
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-05"><dateline><date when="1821-08-05">5th of the Eighth Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> First Day. A more lively, open, owning meeting than common, I believe – but I am very jealous and afraid of being deceived, as thousand and tens and hundreds of thousands and millions, I verily believe, are in their state as to religions. We have very deceitful hearts and a subtle, deceitful enemy to deal with, and of all deceivers self deception is the worst. How often is the caution repeated in Scripture: be ye not deceived, beware lest your hearts deceive you,<note resp="transcr">Deuteronomy 11:16</note> etc., etc.</p>
<p>It is a very pinching time of drought just here with us, although there has been rain almost all round us. The corn and buckwheat and potatoes seem to languish very much – some potato vines quite dead, and it looks as there would be no corn if rain does not come soon, even where it looked very promising but a few days ago.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-06"><dateline><date when="1821-08-06">6.</date></dateline><p> I went to the blacksmith's, my son John's, to get my wagon mend[ed], and whilst I was waiting for that I went to see Benjamin Burroughs, a poor old man that has lost his reason and seems very likely to starve himself to death. [He] is now very poor and lean of flesh. [He] does not speak to any one; has never paid any attention to religion of any sort, but been industrious, and raised up a family of children. So shall thy poverty come as one that travelleth, and thy want as an armed man.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 6:11</note></p>
<p>Then I went to see their school next the meeting house, and had no cause to repent it – for the better, I hope. Then I went to see John Evans, died Twelfth Month. An old acquaintance and companion. In folly, he had a large plantation [indecipherable] to him, but has never done any good, neither in church or state. He has of latter time been very much afflicted with the gravel, and is very feeble. He seemed disposed to read religious books, and told me if he had his time to live over again, it would not be as it had been. I once heard an old man say his future state must be as it is, I cannot alter it now. It is too late for me to alter it now. What need there is to work while it is called today.</p>
<p>Then I went to see the widow Dudley, a young widow with 4 children. And called to see a poor widow whose husband died very sudden and left 3 children lately. All in sight of the meeting house.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Benjamin Burrow died in the Ninth Month.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_002"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-09"><dateline><date when="1821-08-09">9th of the Eighth Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> John Evans died last of the Twelfth Month 1821. Was our Monthly Meeting, which was for the most part satisfactory to me, but not all together so – some matters did not go to my mind. What small matters disturbs our peace, small matters disturbs still waters.</p>
<p>It holds remarkably clear: still hot, dry weather. The pastures are in places turned brown. Although we hear of fine rains in divers places, round about us it looks as if our Indian corn and buckwheat would be much cut off.</p>
<p>The following is a list of ecclesiastical officers in the Church of England with the revenue attached to each per annum:
<table> <title>Philadelphia March 27, 1812 by Elias Smith's <emph rend="italic">Herald of Gospel Liberty</emph></title>
<row><cell>2 arch Bishops</cell><cell>35,000 £</cell></row>
<row><cell>24 Bishops</cell><cell>500,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>24 Deans</cell><cell>20,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>60 Arch Deacons</cell><cell>15,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>200 Prebends</cell><cell>100,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>200 Canons</cell><cell>30,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>24 Chancellors</cell><cell>7,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>500 Rectors</cell><cell>1,000,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>500 Vicars</cell><cell>500,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>10000 Church Clerks</cell><cell>50,000</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell>£1,857,000</cell></row>
<title>Exclusive of rural deans, officers in collegiate churches, lecturers, etc.</title></table>
What a mercy we are delivered from such a priest's yoke! We read that men were first created pure, but they have sought out many inventions, many many indeed, to their own hurt – things which the Lord never commanded them.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-11"><dateline><date when="1821-08-11">11th: Seventh of the week.</date></dateline><p> My daughter Abigail and I, with Mary Gibbs of Philadelphia, went to Upper Evesham Monthly Meeting, which, on retrospection, is not unpleasant to think of. A great favor to be so far preserved. Dined at John Stokes; had a little pause at parting – for the better, I hope, although the waters seemed low. Very dry weather.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_003"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-12"><dateline><date when="1821-08-12">12 of the Eighth Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Waters very low. A dry time, both outwardly and as to religion. Very destitute of life, yet there seemed some things of life at last. Rebecca Price of Philadelphia had acceptable service.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-13"><dateline><date when="1821-08-13">13.</date></dateline><p> It is so dry; all our mills round about us cannot grind. This day I took a grist to Benjamin Tomlinson's mill at Timber Creek, about eight miles south of us. There seemed something like scrambling work about getting grain ground, there being so very few mills that can grind any now. I was very kindly entertained, although amongst a people where no religion prevails. I found [that] they lived on the failings of religious professors and I thought of a short sermon of Robert Walkers, which was: starve the Devil. So I wish we might not feed those who live on the failing of others, for it is very poor diet. One said, many go constant to meeting and not for the better. This is the very place where old Ephraim lived, an extraordinary elder and an excellent, exemplary friend.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-16"><dateline><date when="1821-08-16">16.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. I did think we should have a quite shut up, silent meeting (and it was so to me), but there was several little appearances just at last – savory and lively.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-19"><dateline><date when="1821-08-19">19.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Josiah Roberts went with me to Rancocas meeting. The waters appeared to me to be very low, I could [not] see nor feel any signs of any growth in true religion but a match for anything in caring for the outward man, which made hard work getting along. Yet through mercy it was an open, owning time at last, and openness, sweetness, and feeling nearness at last to general satisfaction, I believe.</p>
<p>Seventh Day night. There was a fine soaking shower about Moorestown and further northward, but we had but very little here.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-23"><dateline><date when="1821-08-23">23.</date></dateline><p> At our preparative meeting. Lively and open, if it was of the right sort. Holds most awfully dry weather. Pastures scorched up.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-26"><dateline><date when="1821-08-26">26.</date></dateline><p> First Day Morning. Vice stings us even in our pleasures, but virtue consoles us even in our pains.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_004"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-26"><dateline><date when="1821-08-26">26.</date></dateline><p> First Day, Eighth Month, 1821. At our meeting. Hannah Smith of Burlington had savory, acceptable service. A satisfactory meeting to me at last. This afternoon, I went to see the First Day boys' school close to the meeting house and also went to see their girls' school. About fifty little girls, mostly about five, six or seven years old, and several Black children. And went to see Nathan Morgan, and it was not unpleasant to look over the day's work at night.</p>
<p>A certain author on the education of children says: they should serve as to the Lord and not to men, and think not of their pensions or perspicuities, so much as that the most important, the most honorable, of all employments is committed to your care. Reflect how great will be your reward for the exact discharge of your duties as you educate these children; they will educate theirs, and so on, till time shall be no more. And if you thus turn many to righteousness, you will shine the stars for ever for so doing, and those under your care become blessings to the world in every station of life and bright angels to all eternity.</p>
<p>It is said of John Pemberton, who was a wealthy man, that health, wealth, strength of body, and the comforts of this life were sacrificed to the service of his Divine Master. But as to our schools, I fear we have lost sight of what they should be or what the teachers of schools should be. Let them read the account of Waltham Abbey School taught by John Mattron, who was a worthy minister and deeply concerned for the children's improvement in religion as well as school learning. And his earnest concern was wonderfully blessed, for the Lord did manifest himself amongst them in their meetings, in their school, in a distinguished, powerful manner to the tendering their hearts in a wonderful manner. And when their teacher died, many of the children gave testimonies concerning their teacher and spoke of the mysteries of the Kingdom of Heaven – more like men and women established in religion than like children in their minority! I wish we might not sit down contented until we attain to the same religious experience, which would be the greatest blessing to the succeeding generation and also to the whole nation.</p>
<p>It is education forms the tender mind, / Just as the twig is bent, to so it's inclined. As one said, he supposed if he had been breed amongst the heathens, pagans, Turks, or Mehomits [Muslims] he should have been one of that sort.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_005"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-28"><dateline><date when="1821-08-28">28th of Eighth Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> I went to Burlington Quarterly Meeting with my two daughters. Poor and empty, begging for preservation, and although the house was full, I thought poverty prevailed and Burlington seemed lowering instead of rising. There was no <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> there, nor George Dillwyn. Burlington is now much stripped of their old standard bearers, yet there were divers young ministers appeared: Edwin Atley of Philadelphia appeared in prayer, and <persName key="w6b01gx6">John Coxe</persName> expressed that he thought there was something owning attended the meeting. I was so far preserved as not to do any thing that I wished undone when I came at midnight to look over the day, which I count a very great favor. Had some pretty close remarks on the state of society and also in the sitting for worship.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-30"><dateline><date when="1821-08-30">30.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. No satisfaction. Our standing is in slippery places.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-31"><dateline><date when="1821-08-31">31.</date></dateline><p> Our select meeting [was] a mortifying time to me. Mortifying things from different quarters, what a world of troubles and dangers it is! I am told that the drought is very severe and divers distant places, especially in some of the West India islands and Cuba. That the Negroes cannot raise enough to keep themselves, and it is said many of them starve to death for want of sustenance. It is said these accounts are in the newspapers.</p>
<p>A few days ago Samuel Cooper, son of Benjamin, a young man just arrived to age, died. An orderly, steady, young man with a kind of a fever. And another by the name of Anderson about 17, they died near together on the river shore. And it is said that this fever (some different from what they called the typhus fever) prevails very much over a great part of Pennsylvania.</p></div>
{1821-09}
<div type="entry" when="1821-09-02"><dateline><date when="1821-09-02">2nd of the Ninth Month, First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Rebekah Burr of Evesham had a pretty deal to say, savory and acceptable, I believe. A young man of Byberry tells me some fields of corn is quite spoiled with the drought, so that they turned the cattle into the fields of corn. This day the rain seemed to come more freely than it has done since harvest. Looks like a change of weather from very dry to wet, though we hear of there being rain in places round about us. We hear of three drowned – a steamboat ran over them. A man and two sons; and left a widow and seven children. How many solemn calls and how soon forgotten!
<pb n="A0011533_006"/>
We hear of many being drowned in the storm in the late storm of wind I hear that Joseph Swett's mill is swept all away with this last sudden great flood of rain: it is very likely there was a great deal of grain in it how many solemn calls to humility after divers ways and manners: and yet how much pride and ingratitude abounds may we not say with the Prophet pride hath budded<note resp="transcr">Ezekiel 7:10</note> iniquity hath blossomed and brought forth a plentiful crop: although some now say they think there will not be more than half a crop of Indian corn and potatoes and buckwheat less.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-09-06"><dateline><date when="1821-09-06">6 of the Ninth Month, 1821, Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our monthly meeting most of which was satisfactory but one matter before our monthly made very difficult troublesome work; many troubles might be easily avoided if we would take the right way for it.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-09-09"><dateline><date when="1821-09-09">9.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Mariah Embree of Trenton had considerable to say and some thought it a good satisfactory time but to me it was but a low time I want to feel our meetings crowned with life and with we might not sit down contented without it. Here is a remark I just now met with in a letter from a friend, piety and pride can no more thrive together than health and sickness: if so what will become of our religion in our days wherein there is such a rapid growth in pride. Nothing pleases a man more than to think he has avoided a foolish action it is a great mercy and favor to be so far preserved as to do nothing we shall have cause to wish undone and not be crying out (as some do all their life) we have done that which we ought not to have done and left undone that which we ought to have done. Our select meeting middling some satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-09-12"><dateline><date when="1821-09-12">12 of the Ninth Month.</date></dateline><p> At our quarterly meeting. The house pretty full and our galleries pretty well filled with able, amicable ministers, and we had a great deal of preaching. Several from Philadelphia and several from Nine Partners, Isaac Thorn and his wife. But preaching seems to do but little where people are set down and conclude [to] go no further, which seems to be the case with the professors of religion in the present day. If there was a desire to enquire of the Lord a right way for them and their little one to walk in, their state would be different. Some satisfaction, although not that life as at some times.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_007"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-09-14"><dateline><date when="1821-09-14">14.</date></dateline><p> Ninth Month, 1821. A young man returned just now from Salem tells me it is a very sickly time there-a-way, and he says many wealthy families cannot get nurses to take care of them. <persName key="w6fv9b6q">William Rogers's</persName> son of Evesham brought up a corpse from there yesterday, a young man. How often humbling things overtake poor mortals, and how does pride and luxury look and an afflicting, humbling, circumstances. See <emph rend="italic">Select Lives</emph>, page 95, Fenelon: The true riches and prosperity of a state consists in pruning the luxuries of living, and being content with simple and innocent things or pleasures. By this the demonstrates that true virtue does not only fit men for a state of happiness hereafter, but that it actually makes societies of people happy even in this life, as far as it is capable of being so. No doubt it is the will of our great Creator that his people should be happy, and is there not a way cast up whereby they may attaint to present and future happiness? But it is not to be attained in pride and luxury, but in resignation and humility. <quote type="poem">
<l>What cannot resignation do?</l>
<l>It wonders can perform</l>
<l>That powerful charm thy will be done</l>
<l>Can lay the lowest storm.</l>
</quote><note resp="transcr">Edward Young</note></p>
<p>I am grown old and not able to carry on business. Crops fail and my wife very poorly. All prospects as to the outward looks gloomy; whilst my neighbors all round are carrying on business all around me, I feel like one of the hindmost amongst human beings. Blessed is the man that walketh not in the council of the ungodly nor standeth in the way of sinners.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 1:1</note> Blessed, blessed, blessed indeed are they who walk in the way that leads to the abodes of the blessed. But for want of this, oh, to see and feel the unhappiness, disorder, misery, and confusion that abounds amongst us poor mortals, which might be easily avoided by taking heed to the reproofs of instruction, the way of life. But for want of this may we not say, the quadruped, the insect, and the fly fill up their station better far than I.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-09-15"><dateline><date when="1821-09-15">15.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting quite silent, which is rare with us. This afternoon at 4th hour Isaac Thorn and his wife, from Nine Partners, had a meeting here at Moorestown house. Full crowded. They both had a great deal to say, she especially. Much pertinent council they preached till sundown, but alas, how little good it seems to do, how soon all forgotten! Yet we don't know it may be as bread cast upon the waters and found after many days with some.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_008"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-09-16"><dateline><date when="1821-09-16">16th of the Ninth Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> Second Day. I went to Micajah Will's to get some shingles for our kitchen. Whilst I was there waiting for him to come home, I picked up some newspapers (which the children were throwing about the floor) wherein I found accounts of the late great sudden fall of rain and hard wind. It appears it was a very great deal harder eastward than it was here. At New York and Long Island and in New England it is said the roofs were blown off many houses. Some houses blown down, and people killed, and divers barns blew down, and many cattle killed, and their cellars and stores filled and spoiled with the sudden inundation of water, ruined their wharves and stores. Thus they were visited with a violent storm, and it is said forty vessels or more were shipwrecked on their coasts and many lives lost. Many dead bodies were found on their shores – 30 or 45, it is said, found on Long Island. Ships were wrecked and torn to pieces in many places and ports.</p>
<p>See Psalms 50 chapter 22 verse: Now consider this, ye that forget God, lest I tear you in pieces and there be none to deliver. If we did but consider how many ways for humbling things to overtake, and how often they do overtake people, it would seem a wonder that pride, ingratitude, and forgetfulness should ever prevail amongst human beings, which brings such destruction often and misery upon many in these days as we read in Scripture it did on the people in days of old. And yet I read in the same papers an account of most grievous sorrowful work in the southern states, of their kidnapping and grievously oppressing the poor Negroes – although call after call has been given, warning after warning has been sent from heaven.</p>
<p>See Deuteronomy 7 and 21: the Lord thy God is a mighty God and terrible; 10 and 21: hath done for the terrible things. Job says 37 and 22: with God is terrible majesty. And see Psalms 65 and 5: by terrible things in righteousness will he answer us; [66 and] 5: terrible in his doings towards the children of men; 146 and 6: men shall speak of thy terrible ones is as a storm; the branch of the terrible ones shall be brought low.<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 25:4-5</note> No doubt many have been brought very low and much reduced by the late terrible storm in a few minutes, and many drowned and very suddenly taken away, and many left in sorrow and mourning and very bitter, humbling circumstances.</p>
<p>[marginal note] This storm was after many weeks very severe drought.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_009"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-09-20"><dateline><date when="1821-09-20">20th of the Ninth Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> We went to Evesham meeting, which was very large. Isaac Thorn and his wife were there and had abundance to say – both of them, but she especially. And the people were very attentive and still. But although we could say their conduct was most decorous, how much better it would be if it could be said they were evidently making the best use of their time to make their peace with God, as was said of one very near his end? And of another, who was so devoted to do all the good he could that they said of him they did not believe he lost one minute? And of another, devoted, dedicated servant of the Lord that he said he did not desire to spend one minute to please himself? If the people were like-minded with the people in the days of Ezra, when they sat down by the river Ahava to enquire of the Lord a right way for them and their little ones to walk in,<note resp="transcr">Ezra 8:21</note> they would be in a much more fit and more favorable state to hear the tidings of the Gospel preached than they now are, set down at ease where they now are, seemingly not desirous to go any further. But if we were all so much in earnest to make our calling and election sure as not to be desirous to spend one minute to please ourselves – as William Hunt said he was, or as they said of Fenelon or Du Renti [?] so intent upon doing all the good he could as not to lose one minute – would it be too much to obtain the answer of will done at last or should we ever have cause to repent it? No, no, is it not the way everlasting which David prayed to be led into,<note resp="transcr">Psalm 139:24</note> never to be repented of?</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-09-24"><dateline><date when="1821-09-24">24.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. I thought it was the most evidently owning that I have seen latterly. But alas, to think that Noah was a preacher of righteousness, we are told, an hundred years before the flood – yet wickedness prevailed until it was said all flesh had corrupted their ways and the flood was sent that swept them all away except Noah and his family. And Moses was called a prophet, and his people were a gainsaying, backsliding people, and all fell in the wilderness and were not suffered to enter the promised land except Caleb and Joshua. And were the people Christ had to preach to any better? Very many of them [were not], for see how they crucified him at last. We now in our days have abundance of preaching, line upon line and precept upon precept, but are we coming up out of the wilderness or are we going back into it, conforming to the spirit of the world, which is enmity with God?</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_010"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-09-28"><dateline><date when="1821-09-28">28 of the Ninth Month.</date></dateline><p> Sixth of the week. Wallace Lippincott, who has been several weeks in an afflicted state, mostly confined to his room and bed, sent word that he desired I would come and see him this day. Joseph Cowperthwaite went with me to see him, and he seemed pleased with our visit and I believe we had no cause to repent it.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-09-30"><dateline><date when="1821-09-30">30.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. I went to Vincintown with Josiah Roberts, which they say was smaller than common. Religion is at a low ebb at that place and has been so many years, although they have lately built a new meeting house and I hope are in some little way of improving, but great room for more. Yet however it was an open satisfactory time in general, I believe. They showed loving, kind, and inviting at parting. We dined at George Chandler's, whose wife had sent word to me wishing I would come and see her. Has been many weeks very poorly and very much afflicted and confined with the rheumatism. Better, but cannot walk yet. She expressed satisfaction with the visit.</p>
<p>On our way home, we called to see Jemime Hurley, my sister's daughter, who stays at her brother-in-law's, James Hileis; very ill with the dropsy, and appears near her end. We got well home just at dark, and had no cause to repent the way in which we spent the day. George Chandler's wife is George Churchman's daughter, granddaughter to the worthy John Churchman, and is lately recommended a minister. This night and Second Day morning a soaking, heavy rain.</p>
<p>See the words of James Meikle, page 35: I found that to live near God was the sweetest life in the world, and sweetens every condition; but I find that although the world could say but little against me, conscience could say a great deal. But oh, what a black life was mine when narrowly surveyed, when by meditation it was, as it were, taken to pieces. And see, page 32nd, were men as stupid about the things of this life as they are about the world to come, they would be a burden to society and useless in their generation. How deplorable is it then that they should be prudent in matters not of the last but of the least importance, and that even those who otherwise are indolent should perpetrate sin with the greatest activity when neither judgment nor mercies, promises or threatenings, patience nor examples of vengeance can prevail. Nothing can let them see their folly till awakened by the flames of Hell, when it is too late. Vanity of vanities, emptiness, and vapor are all the enchanting, delusive joys and pleasures, riches and treasures of this delusive world.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Fever and chill much prevalent.
<pb n="A0011533_011"/>
See [Henry] Scougal <emph rend="italic">Life of God in the Soul of Man</emph>, page 86: oh! what a poor thing would the life of man be if it were capable of no higher enjoyments than the things of this world can afford. Some call it a mere animal life, which is not influenced with the inspiration of the Almighty. Be ye not as the horse or as the mule, who have no understanding, says David the prophet [Psalm 32:9]. And how many there are who spend their days like the mole graveling in the earth, partaking daily of the bountiful gifts of Heaven; who like the swine eat the fruit under the tree, but never look up from whence it comes. But how will this do in the end?
I have heard of one of this sort who at last cropped out: of darkness, darkness, darkness and so died away. The language of another earthly world being was: at last now I must go and oh, that I might go in peace! Ten thousands of worlds, one upon the back of another, would not tempt me to live in this world as I have done! Although this was one who supported a good name amongst men and filled conspicuous stations in civil society, yet this was his language when he came to be awakened, to see the necessity of a truly religious life, the inward life, the life of God in the soul of man that is hid with Christ in God. As I once heard a poor, benighted, belated creature say, ten thousands of worlds would I now give if I had it in my power, if my peace was but made with the Lord. One says the life of those wholly devoted to earthly concerns may well be compared Nebuchadnezzar ate grass<note resp="transcr">Daniel 4:33</note>; earthly things feed, fill, and satisfy both of them.</p></div>
{1821-10}
<div type="entry" when="1821-10-04"><dateline><date when="1821-10-04">4 of the Tenth Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting, and I believed was not alone in thinking it was a right good meeting – sweetness, solidity, weight, and savor. Who can set forth the excellency of a peaceful, tranquil mind? We read of the dew of Hermon that descended upon the mountains of Zion where the Lord commanded the blessing ever life forever more.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 133:3</note> I thought I should not dare say we were not favored with something like it.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-10-07"><dateline><date when="1821-10-07">7th was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Very poor and low forepart, but ended better.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-10-08"><dateline><date when="1821-10-08">Second Day morning.</date></dateline><p> See <emph rend="italic">The Traveler</emph>, by James Meikle, page 128: the man whose conscience is awakened shall find a constant companion and unwearied reprover, who will either reprove to purpose or reproach forever. Again, nothing in the world can preserve from or enable to support a wounded spirit; if the stroke comes from above, so must the relief. How poor are all possessions to a person who has no peace!</p>
<p>[marginal note] Direful are the consequence of desires misplaced; set your affections on things above.
<pb n="A0011533_012"/>
Paul and Silas could sing praises in a prison [Acts 16:25] because when God giveth quietness none can cause trouble. Oh, how poor a thing would the life of man be if it were capable of no higher enjoyments than the joys and pleasures, riches and treasures this word can afford, says [Henry] Scougal (as remarked on the other side of this leaf). And the words of Meikle also: Oh, how poor are all earthly possessions to a person who has no peace within! See the Traveler, page 130: there is as great difference between a man in a renewed and unrenewed state as between a man fast asleep and broad awake. Think of the man we read of, who concluded he had goods laid up in store for many years, that would say: lo, his soul, eat drink and be merry or take his rest. So lo in the lap of pleasure, but the language was: thou fool, this night shall thy soul be required of thee, and then whose shall these things be which thou hast provided? And so shall it be with all those who lay up treasures for themselves and are not rich towards God.<note resp="transcr">Luke 12:19-21</note> And again, see page 136: They are to beware that they do not stick on the sands of carnal security, or run into the shallow waters of lukewarm indifferency, or be blown on the rocks of bold confidence by the high winds of spiritual delusion. See what the Scriptures say concerning rejoicing in the Lord, and consider how such talk sounds in the ears of the earthly worldly minded.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-10-11"><dateline><date when="1821-10-11">11 of the 10th month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting smaller than common. Much sickness in the neighborhood – chill and fever. Several of my son Benjamin's family sick with it, but now some better. It was very low and poor forepart, but a woman from Plainfield rose up and did speak excellently well, and it ended savory and satisfactory.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-10-12"><dateline><date when="1821-10-12">12.</date></dateline><p> Rainy stormy day. [Henry] Scougal <emph rend="italic">Life of God in the Soul of Man</emph>, page eighty: it is an advice worthy of a Christian though it did first drop from a heathen. Penn thought before we betake ourselves to rest we [should] renew and examine all the passages of the day, that we may have the comfort of what we have done aright and may redress what we find to have been amiss, and make the shipwrecks of one day be as marks to direct our course in another. This may be called the very part of victorious living, and would contribute wonderfully to advance our reformation and preserve our innocency. But with all we must not forget to implore the divine assistance, especially against those sins that most easily beset us.
<pb n="A0011533_013"/>
Again see [Henry] Scougal, page 74. No wonder then if souls overpowered with Divine love despise inferior pleasures and be almost ready to grudge the body it's necessary attention for the common accommodations of life, judging all these imperatives to their main happiness. I have read of divers of our first friends who were so enamored with the Divine life that were very desirous to make as little do for the body as would suffice nature (bread to eat and raiment to put on, etc.) that they might be the better enabled to do good and communicate to the poor and needy and be at liberty to serve the Lord. But alas, how few of that sort to what there have been of those whose language is what shall we eat what shall we drink, etc. And oh, how precious the effects and fruits of the one, and how direful the consequence of desires misplaced.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-10-14"><dateline><date when="1821-10-14">14 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> 9th hour we went to the burial of Samuel Roberts, a stout, healthy, corpulent man – he has been all his lifetime. Aged about seventy, an orderly, quiet, peaceable man, and a constant attender of meetings and had great store of earthly treasures. There was a great concourse of people. I had satisfaction in undone [undoing] nothing, nor leaving undone what I thought I ought to do. At the meeting, Hinchman Haines had considerable to say and I thought it ended reputably. He died with this fall fever, which we hear is very prevalent.</p>
<p>I hear of the death of Joshua Bourton, who a very few weeks ago went with Josiah Roberts and me in a boat from his house up to Samuel Wells' to Ancocas meeting. A constant attender of meeting, a very innocent man, 75. See Meikle, page 215: a grey head and a carnal, worldly heart is a wounding sight, but a young man and an agued loved one in his prime and all his graces flourishing is comely to behold. Henceforth begone the bewitching vanities and all the enchantments of the world; the evening of my life is not to be trifled away by you. Death attends me, the grave awaits me, and eternity is at hand. Therefore may my purified affections river-like enlarge as they approach the ocean. Page 237: Why did I prostitute the temple of my soul to the idols of time? Why permit the world and self a place in that temple which the godhead is to inhabit forever? Page 239: Ah, was I ever so stupid, so brutish as to make any comparison between riches and righteousness, gold and glory, earth and heaven the creature and the creator or God!
<pb n="A0011533_014"/>
It is dangerous to swim in hot seas where sharks along shores, where alligators devour – and doubly so to wallow in wealth and ease, where lusts and Satan destroy. 139: Jeshurun, who when he waxed fat, kicked, and in his greatness forgot him that make him great.<note resp="transcr">Deuteronomy 32:15</note> More venomous creatures crawl in these countries which never felt a cold day than in such as annually feel a pinching winter. So, generally speaking, more corruption (pride, lust, carnal security, wrath etc.) abound among such as are finally clothed and fare sumptuously every day than among those that sit down to one meal and know but little how to provide the next.
Seneca says prosperity, like a strong gale, soon carries a man out of sight of peace. Let us compare our lives with the faithful truly in earnest to give all diligence to make their calling and election sure so as not to lose one minute nor desire to expend one minute to please ourselves and keep our selves continually upon the stretch in doing all the good we could, both to the bodies and souls of men according to our ability of bodily strength and worldly wealth and estate. As it has been said of some, should we ever have cause to repent it or would it be too much to obtain the answer of well done, at last enter thou into the joys of thy Lord? But instead of a life so spent, [we] have to say: alas, what precious time and sweet meditation have I wasted on toys and trifles, and despised the joy of angels and the work of Heaven. When time is at an end here, may we not say: where are all the things of time now, which once made such great demands upon us? How they then sink into an insignificant nothingness, hardly a name little enough to call them by! And [we] have to say with Grotius: Alas, I have consumed much of my time in laborious doing of nothing; no treasure laid up in Heaven, nothing done to purpose, all vanity and vexation of spirit, bound on a voyage of awful length and dangers little known, a stranger to superior strength. Can man vainly trust his own? But oars alone can ne'er prevail to reach the distant cast; the breath of Heaven must swell the sail or all the toil is lost.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_015"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-10-17"><dateline><date when="1821-10-17">17th of the Tenth Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> Went to the burial of Thomas Lippincott of Westfield, an elder in good esteem. Has traveled a pretty deal with ministering Friends, and has been a very kind friend to me, in going with me visiting families at East Branch above Crosswicks, and at Springfield and Ancocas meeting, and about to meetings in divers places. Hichman Haines had a good deal to say both at the house and at the meeting, and Thomas Kite of Philadelphia and Elizabeth Coleman of Burl[ington] and myself had a share in the labor to good satisfaction. A solemn time it seemed to be.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-10-18"><dateline><date when="1821-10-18">18 was Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Small but for me not the worst. An invitation was given to the burial of David Walton's wife, a daughter of Granvil Woolman's. [She] has been married but a few months.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-10-21"><dateline><date when="1821-10-21">21.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. I should not dare say there was no savor of life attended, but oh, how little of that we experience in our meetings and when our hands are upon our labor and on our pillows to what we might do if we were not wanting our part! Remember Marmaduke Stevenson when he was following the plows, and Elijah also. And the prophet says when he was by the river Chebar the Heavens were opened and he saw visions of God.<note resp="transcr">Ezekiel 1:1</note> I now hear of the death of several young men, two buried in one day in one graveyard at Woolwich or Mullica Hill, and two ancient women upwards of 90 years, Katharine Slimn and A. Ivins, near Westfield.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-10-25"><dateline><date when="1821-10-25">25.</date></dateline><p> At our preparative meeting. Very small, but I hope some little life. gathering corn, which [is] the poorest crop I ever had. Some have none, we hear. In places, many say they have not half a crop. Buckwheat very small, and some [have] none at all. Potatoes some better.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-10-28"><dateline><date when="1821-10-28">28.</date></dateline><p> The scale turned for me and my daughters to go to Evesham meeting, which was pretty full, and through mercy it was a favored, open, owning time. I do not remember ever having a meeting there so savory and lively. Oh, how sweet and pleasant, kind and exciting, they were when meeting broke up. I had cause to think it was to general satisfaction.
<pb n="A0011533_016"/>
Several meeting days past I have [had] nothing material to remark, except it was poverty, leanness, and lowness – so that I thought of David's words, make haste to help me, restore me to the joy of thy salvation and uphold me by the free spirit.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 51:12</note> For indeed we are poor, helpless creatures without it. Some are like what Stephen Crisp says, up and down, full and empty, joyful and sorrowful, just as things go well or ill in the world. And some are like Armelia Nicolas, who said: When I found the Lord was pleased with me I was happy, but without that nothing in this world could content me. Oh, what poor creatures! See the last words of David, he says: the spirit of the Lord spake by me; his word was in my tongue.<note resp="transcr">2 Samuel 23:2</note> And then in the very next chapter, complaining of his sins and iniquities, which brought such grievous trouble and destruction on him and his people. In thy presence is fullness of joy, said David; thy kindness is better than life.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 63:3</note> Is there anything in this world worth living for without it?</p></div>
{1821-11}
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-08"><dateline><date when="1821-11-08">8 of the Eleventh Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting. Hannah Smith, wife of Daniel, and Hannah Smith, wife of James, and Elizabeth Coleman of Burlington, and William Ridgway. The women all had short, sweet testimonies, and I do believe there was something of the ownings of truth and savor of life attended the meeting throughout, to right good satisfaction. A healing, strengthening since it seemed to be to me.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-11"><dateline><date when="1821-11-11">11.</date></dateline><p> First Day. We went to Evesham meeting; an open owning time to general satisfaction it appeared to be. This afternoon, went to the burial of Jemime Hurly, my sister's daughter. She married a man with a plantation and settled with a hopeful prospect, but he proved to be a lazy, good-for-nothing fellow; left her to bring up her children herself. She wearied trough the world somehow and brought up her family of children, six or seven of them. Lived mostly in Philadelphia, joined the Baptists, and her sister A. Stiles, the Methodists. So there was at the burial, mixed company of Baptists, Methodists, and Quakers. They were very orderly, but very destitute of life or the ownings of truth, so not much satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-12"><dateline><date when="1821-11-12">Second Day.</date></dateline><p> Joseph Foulk of Gwynedd or North Wales and his companion came to see me. He is visiting the meetings here in Jersey. I went with them to Haddonfield Monthly Meeting. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> and Joseph had very acceptable service, and some savor of life attended. But their meeting for discipline was very lean, poor, and low. About 15 years ago I had a meeting where J.F. lives, which he spoke much of. The most favored time [I have] ever seen.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_017"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-13"><dateline><date when="1821-11-13">13.</date></dateline><p> The Eleventh Month. I took a log to the saw mill for lash to shingle our kitchen.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-14"><dateline><date when="1821-11-14">14.</date></dateline><p> We went to Westfield meeting appointed for Joseph Foulke, who had good service – but the waters are low. There we spent the afternoon together at widow Lippincott's, had a little sitting at parting – for the better, I hope – at Lidia Lippincott's.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-16"><dateline><date when="1821-11-16">16.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day have been at several meetings; we were ready to conclude to omit attending our own meeting, but yet did get there and had no cause to repent it. Though the meeting was small, some thought it was a lively good meeting; something of the ancient dew of Hermon that descended on the mountains of Zion.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 133:3</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-17"><dateline><date when="1821-11-17">17.</date></dateline><p> Soled Mary's shoes, although a good deal unwell with the colic, vomiting, and sick stomach. Joseph Foulke mentioned a meeting I was at about 15 years ago where he lives; I suppose it was one of the most owning, favored meetings I ever had. William Blake said it was the best meeting he ever seen at that place: this is the cap sheaf, this crowns all. It was the concluding or last I had in that visit to them parts. Jacob Paxton said he wished he had got more of this family along to that meeting. Returned home with sweet peace.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-19"><dateline><date when="1821-11-19">19.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Ebenezer Roberts and our daughter and myself at last had something to say, and I believe it ended well. But I am afraid of being deceived with a counterfeit peace, as it is to be feared thousands and tens and hundreds of thousands are, for we have very treacherous, deceitful hearts and a deceitful, unwearied enemy to war with, and of all deceivers self-deception is the worst. Is it not said that if it were possible Satan would.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-21"><dateline><date when="1821-11-21">[21.]</date></dateline><p> Third Day I went to mill. The weather dry and cold.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-22"><dateline><date when="1821-11-22">[22.]</date></dateline><p> Fourth Day I have had but little time of late to read or write. But see the words of Armella Nicholas – when the soul is blest with the approbation of God and experiences the effects of his grace, everything which can befall it is easily supportable. But without his favor, without support or hope, how pitiable! In thy presence, said David, is fullness of joy; his loving kindness is better than life.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 63:3</note> One thing have I desired and that will I seek, after I have esteemed the words of his mouth more than my necessary food.<note resp="transcr">Job 23:12</note> Said another: man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God.<note resp="transcr">Luke 4:4</note> Martha, Martha, thou art careful about many things; one thing is needful.<note resp="transcr">Luke 10:41-42</note> Let me feel thy presence or else my time is lost and my life a snare to my soul.
<pb n="A0011533_018"/>
Her body being reduced to a weak state from the great concerns of her soul.
And further, says A. Nicolas, wherever anything of the creature is found, so much there is of defect and human weakness and imperfection! Remember well meaning Uzza, who was struck dead for attempting to put his hand to steady the ark<note resp="transcr">1 Chronicles 13:10</note> and again if though lift up thy tool upon it, thou hast polluted<note resp="transcr">Exodus 20:25</note><emph rend="italic"> </emph> it. What is it we wait for in silence at our Monthly Meeting before we enter on the business of the discipline, and how is it and what is the consequences, fruits, and effects? Where, as Robert Walker says, the discipline is carried on in the strength and will of the man's part certainly it must be very poor doings, and he said it was too generally the case. And I thought Robert Walker was one of the greatest seers or prophets that ever visited America in my time.
I might add James Nayler's words to these exercised deep travelers: days of mourning and nights of watching. And Dorothy Owin who, it is said, kept herself up on the stretch to the utmost of her ability as to her natural strength and personal estate. To do good and communicate forget not, said the apostle.<note resp="transcr">Hebrews 13:16</note> And how many might I mention of these devoted, deeply exercised servants of the Lord? How different is their state from those that are lolling in the lap of ease and slumbering in the bosom of carnal security! A great difference between thou fool, this night shall thy soul be required of thee and then it be with all who lay up treasure for themselves and are not rich towards God.<note resp="transcr">Luke 12:19-21</note>: and to [indecipherable] done thou good and faith servant enter thou into the joy of thy Lord and into thy masters everlasting rest<note resp="transcr">Matthew 25:21</note> I think Thomas à Kempis says while Jesus is present, all things are pleasant. As I just now noted, Armella Nicolas words: when the soul is blessed with the approbation of God whatever may befall it is easily supportable. But what would it profit a man if he gain the whole world and loose the favor of this almighty supporting power last? And what would a man give in exchange for his soul? Why this I have heard from one on a dying bed: then thousand of worlds would I give if it was in my power for peace with the Lord. And it has been the case with very many; likely it will be with many more.
[Addition] Thomas Ross says if friends think to do the Lord's work as they do their own, they will greatly fail.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_019"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-22"><dateline><date when="1821-11-22">22 of the Eleventh Month.</date></dateline><p> At our preparative meeting which I believe would have been better if less had been said although I came off without much condemnation.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-23/1821-11-24"><dateline><date when="1821-11-23/1821-11-24">23 and 24.</date></dateline><p> Shingling our kitchen rain and snow at night.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-25"><dateline><date when="1821-11-25">25.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting almost silent not the poorest to me.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-02"><dateline><date when="1821-11-02">2 and Third Day.</date></dateline><p> And a little before I have been reading some precious accounts lately printed at New York concerning public Friends and others deceased divers, of them I was intimately acquainted with very precious, animating accounts; they are manifesting these sayings great peace have they that love thy law etc..<note resp="transcr">Psalm 119:165</note> The voice of rejoicing and salvation is in the tabernacles of the righteous.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 118:15</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-11-29"><dateline><date when="1821-11-29">29.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting somewhat satisfactory to me although almost silent. Next day at our select meeting. Waters very low and I rubbed harder an account of its being so than they could well bear: is it etc. a few days ago I had an instructing lesson in a silent meeting; oh how poor a thing is the life of man if he were capable of no higher enjoyments than this world can afford it illustrated on my mind in an instructing manner: the enjoyment of the mere sensualist is no higher than that of the pampered horse in the stable or the fattened pig in the sty. Indeed the brute has much the advantage as it lives according to its nature and destination while the man is haunted with a perpetual consciousness of the shameful degradation of his moral and intellectual faculties: be ye not like the horse or the mule that hath no understanding says David.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 32:9</note> The sensualist wholly given up to the things below is compared to Nebuchadnezzar at grass when a bests [beast's?] heart was given him.<note resp="transcr">Daniel 4:33</note>; the people nowadays can hardly bear to hear such talk although real happiness consists in placing our affection on things above is there not abundant evidence of the truth of this and of the direful effects of desires misplaced yet how many are bemired and entangled with their accommodations and conveniences making temporary heavens here and as <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> say they like them so well they would never leave them if they could help it: and some have said they did wish a better Heaven than they enjoyed in the midst of their prosperity but who does Solomon say vanity of vanities all is vanity<note resp="transcr">Ecclesiastes 1:2</note></p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_020"/>
{1821-12}
<div type="entry" when="1821-12-02"><dateline><date when="1821-12-02">2 of the 12th month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. I find I fare best when I am most clear of a will of my own a favored, satisfactory, strengthening meeting I felt as if I was not afraid to be had up a little like Robert Nesbit after he had been delivering some pretty close doctrine said now I feel as if you could not hurt me: 3rd killing hogs weather moderate.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-12-03"><dateline><date when="1821-12-03">3.</date></dateline><p> Oh how poor a thing is the life of man if he were capable of no higher enjoyments than this world can afford; although all are gifted with a capacity for higher enjoyments than this world can afford, yet how many thousands deprive themselves of that greatest of blessings by placing their love on strong drink, how do they degrade themselves below the brutal part of the creation, and how much better are those who bury their talents in the earth who mind earthly things only: who as William Edmondson says who might otherwise if they improved their talents be of great service in the church. Oh earth, earth hear oh earth the word of the Lord can<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 22:29</note> words describe their folly who part with heaven to please their taste or for any sublunary enjoyment.</p>
<p>John Pemberton was a wealthy man and they say health, wealth, strength of body and the comforts of this life were sacrificed to the service of his Divine Master a disposition very different from those who bury their talents in the earth but I could mention thousands more who were like minded who have been the salt of the earth and as lights in the world.<note resp="transcr">Matthew 5:13-14</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-12-06"><dateline><date when="1821-12-06">6.</date></dateline><p> Was Monthly Meeting. We had a shower of strangers from Pennsylvania: Amos Hillburn, Samuel Comfort and John Justice and although thing seemed low forepart it growed better at last and ended savory and well, many very pertinent remarks.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-12-08"><dateline><date when="1821-12-08">8.</date></dateline><p> Seventh Day. I went to Woodbury with Amos Hilburn. Enoch Roberts took us in his wagon we went to see a black man in prison who is to be hanged next Sixth Day. We had, I believe, some very pertinent remarks to him but his heart did not seem soft. He is condemned for shooting a Negro man. He appears to me to be a smart, sensible fellow of a fierce spirit.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_021"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-12-09"><dateline><date when="1821-12-09">9th of the Twelfth Month.</date></dateline><p> First Day. We were at Woodbury meeting and an open, favored time it was I was afraid we should quarantine them for between us we kept them till near 2 o' clock but they did sit very patient and attentive and it ended savory and well. I believe we had a little pause at Mary Allins where we dined on Seventh day and something savor and at parting at John Tatum's sons [where] we lodged – Amos Hillburn called the children together and we left Woodbury with sweet peace and satisfaction although their meeting has lately been much stripped of their ministers John Tatum and <persName key="w6x16z80">John Reeve</persName> and religion is at a low ebb at that place although they improve and shine in worldly prosperity I have wanted to be at their meeting many months past I had many acquaintance down there and great was the love and respect, inviting kindness, openness, and feeling nearness when meeting broke up as if old acquaintance and near connections had meet after long absence.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-12-10"><dateline><date when="1821-12-10">10.</date></dateline><p> We came up to Haddonfield Monthly Meeting where there were a number of strangers and forepart it seemed a very low, poor time and much shut up but one after another had something to say and it seemed to raise the life a little but to me it was a quite shut up, very poor time, yet I had a very pertinent pointed lesson but kept it.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-12-11"><dateline><date when="1821-12-11">11.</date></dateline><p> About home.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-12-12"><dateline><date when="1821-12-12">12.</date></dateline><p> At select meeting at Evesham. A number of ministers from Pennsylvania and divers had acceptable service. John Comly in particular did please me exceedingly well. I was much gratified and edified with his company. He is a great minister and had very acceptable lively service at our quarterly meeting next Day 13, but Sarah Cresson took up the greatest part of the time she has just got out of a very low, depressed, disconsolate state but appears to be now quite wholly restored and was and is now more large, lively, and powerful in her ministry than ever. There was a large number of ministers and I thought they were kept in beautiful order not disturbed with babblers. In the afternoon we had a right down, searching, scraping, lively time as with lighted candles on the state of society I had right good satisfaction at last a violent stormy day of rain and good snow.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_022"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-12-16"><dateline><date when="1821-12-16">16 of the Twelfth Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> First Day we have had several days and nights of very severe, freezing weather I was doubtful it would be too cold for me to go out to meeting but did went and had no cause to repent. I thought it ended pretty well and reputably though not that animation, life, and evident ownings of truth as at some times.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-12-20"><dateline><date when="1821-12-20">20.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting Isaiah Darnel and Mary Haines were married. Elizabeth Balderston and Ann Qucksil were there and had acceptable service and several others; and I thought it ended pretty well or as well as is common nowadays, but alas where are we but in a dreaming state to what we might be if we were not wanting on our part. David says when the Lord restored again the captivity of Zion we were as them that dream.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 126:1</note>; oh what a difference we should feel if we were favored with the company of him who turned their water into wine at the marriage of Cana of Galilee<note resp="transcr">John 2:1-11</note> I thought I had something pointed and pertinent but saw no room to open it.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-12-23"><dateline><date when="1821-12-23">23.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting came off pretty well but think it would have been better if there had been rather less said. Let each day be a critic on the last, the way to improve.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-12-13"><dateline><date when="1821-12-13">13 of last month [i.</date></dateline><p>e., November] they hanged the Negro I went to see and I hear there appeared some tokens of tenderness at last; the same evening a young woman was stabbed by a man at Philadelphia. She lived about eight days and died and was brought over the river to her father's in Gloucester County. My son Benjamin seen the corpse at the ferry it is said that the man that murdered the woman had a wife and several children yet was suspected of being too familiar with the young woman and others, and another dreadful account at Mount Holly. Two white girls with two Negro men stole some money, 30 dollars, and a wagon and horses and went as far as Trenton; there, their horses tired and they left them, and went on a foot. They pursued them and took them and brought them back to Holly goal. Another account says Caleb Bourton a native of Moorestown or near there died with a wound in his arm occasioned only by being bled; the doctor cut off the vein. He was a very tall, lusty, young man had in former years gave way to drink to excess but refrained and obtained a good name and reputation at school keeping, broke out again and gave way too much to strong drink, upon which I wrote him a letter of which I am now glad.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-12-27"><dateline><date when="1821-12-27">27.</date></dateline><p> 5th Day. At our meeting pretty lively, if it was of the right sort. Very cold, freezing weather.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_023"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-12-30"><dateline><date when="1821-12-30">30.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Our meeting was mortifying, humbling time to me for want of more evidence of the ownings of truth and savor of life, not for want of word. But it might be profitable my peace said the Divine Master I give unto you<note resp="transcr">John 14:27</note>; it is his right and he knows best when to give and when to withhold it but I conclude there is nothing in this world worth living for, without it. Weather moderate, dry and still and middling cold.</p></div>
{1822-01}
<div type="entry" when="1822-01-04"><dateline><date when="1822-01-04">4 of the First Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting Joseph Whiteall of Woodbury was there and a precious, sweet, cementing time it was: favored with that ancient dew of Hermon that descended upon the mountains of Zion<note resp="transcr">Psalm 133:3</note> to my sweet satisfaction. Very cold freezing weather I cannot bear to be much out from the stove.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-01-07"><dateline><date when="1822-01-07">7th First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting very destitute of the stirrings of life I endeavored to stir up the people to a concern and care for the poor but there seemed to be a want of animation. It is very severe freezing, cold weather many poor people must suffer very much: I have read of accounts of other societies what having they called charity sermons for the relief of the poor.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-01-10"><dateline><date when="1822-01-10">Fifth Day</date></dateline><p> it was so cold and several of us unwell, none of us got to meeting. Heard of the death of Joseph French of Moorestown, a stout, strong man shortened his days with drinking to excess, left a large family of children.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-01-13"><dateline><date when="1822-01-13">13.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting and I thought there was something of the evident owning of truth which I count a great favor: but daily labor for daily bread is necessary.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-01-14"><dateline><date when="1822-01-14">14.</date></dateline><p> I went to Haddonfield Monthly Meeting. The yearly meetings [indecipherable] John Comly, Samuel Biddle, Jonathan Evans and Hinchman Haines were but were much shut up. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> spoke and seemed to help or would have appeared a very poor, low time it appeared to be a very low time as to discipline; great weakness appeared.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-01-15"><dateline><date when="1822-01-15">15.</date></dateline><p> Our meeting was adjourned to suit the committee. We had a much more open time and more satisfactory, but the testimony was not raised into dominion as I could wish. Although John Comly spoke very well, yet not that pointed, pressing work I thought necessary. I had good satisfaction though but a small share of the labor.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011533_024"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-01-01822"><dateline><date when="1822-01-01822">1822.</date></dateline><p> Heard of the death of John Mitchell an old man and hard drinker, yet from accounts there seemed room to hope for he seemed composed and said he was willing to die and requested a tin coffin. Anthony Benezet used to say never give any man out, remember the thief on the cross.<note resp="transcr">Luke 23:39-43</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-01-20"><dateline><date when="1822-01-20">20 of the First Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> First Day. I went with Josiah Roberts and wife to Cropwell meeting. It was discouraging to see it so small and poor, yet there is a little remnant a little seed. Mariah Embree of Trenton was there and had a pretty deal to say and I thought it ended pretty well although I did not get relief fully. We went to Joseph Evans to dine Josiah Robert's brother-in-law in the evening had a sitting with the large family of children; I believe to general good satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-01-21"><dateline><date when="1822-01-21">21.</date></dateline><p> I believe people are so accustomed to hear of their neighbors killing themselves with strong drink that there is less notice taken of it than if a wolf from the wilderness should come and kill a few sheep or if a bear should kill a few hogs and far less care to prevent it than there would be to preserve their sheep and hogs.</p>
<p>See <emph rend="italic">Youth's Instructor</emph> by George Dillwyn so far as a rational creature is conformed to the imitable attributes of his creator, so far and no farther is he advanced on the way to the highest happiness he is capable of. Joseph White said I never found that when I will did predominate in me that I ever stood rightly situated for divine instruction – so it appears that so far as we attend to the reproofs of instruction so far we are advanced towards the highest happiness we are capable of. Jacob saw a ladder whose top reached to heaven.<note resp="transcr">Genesis 28:12</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-01-22"><dateline><date when="1822-01-22">22.</date></dateline><p> Third Day, Thomas Grissel of Salem, State of Ohio, appointed a meeting. It was pretty full and he had sound doctrine and inquired what all we had heard had done for us etc. Not much animation; our people are used to hear sound doctrine: take heed how you hear [Mark 4:24] was the ancient caution.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-01-23"><dateline><date when="1822-01-23">23.</date></dateline><p> Second Day. Thomas Story and George Keith both say to this effect that Quakerism, so called in derision, is no other than primitive Christianity revived in its ancient beauty after so long a night of gross darkness and apostasy.</p></div>
[The manuscript covering the period from late January to mid June 1822 has not been located.  For an account of Hunt's life during this period, refer to the published version of the journal in <emph rend="italic">Friends Miscellany.</emph>]
</body></text>
</TEI>