<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader></teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="A0011237_01"/>
{1820-07}
Self the greatest deceiver and greatest thief and greatest enemy.
<div type="entry" when="1820-07-14"><dateline><date when="1820-07-14">This morning, 14th of the Seventh Month, 1820</date></dateline><p>, something opened on my mind respecting selfishness or a selfish spirit. See Mark 8th chapter 34 verse: And when he had called the people unto him with his disciples also, he said unto them “Whosoever will come after me, let him deny himself and take up his cross and follow me: and glorious the fruits thereof.” See Isaiah 28 and 15: and under falsehood have we hid ourselves, and direful the effects. 2 of Timothy, 3 and 2: Men shall be lovers of their own selves, and woeful the effects. A certain writer, I think Fletcher, on self knowledge says: Of all imposters, self-deception is the greatest. See <persName key="w6t72g07">John Woolman's</persName> <emph rend="italic">Caution to the Rich</emph>, page 43: holding treasure in the self-pleasing spirit is a strong plant, the fruit whereof ripens fast. A day of outward distress is coming, and divine love calls to prepare against it. Again, see J. Woolman, page 37, to the rich: when our eyes are so single as to discern the selfish spirit clearly, we behold it the greatest of all tyrants. So he considers and concludes that all the persecutions and dreadful oppression of the African race and all the destructive desolating wars as the effects and fruits of a selfish spirit, far surpassing all the power of the greatest tyrants.</p>
<p>Thomas Chalkley, I think, calls it cursed self. And as Alice Hays and Benjamin Lay says, a selfish spirit is Satan's spirit. Thomas à Kempis says: know that thy own self, thy own will, hath done thee more hurt than any thing in the world, or to that effect. Anthony Benezet remarks in <emph rend="italic">Carver's Travels</emph> many thousands of miles amongst the Indians, says there is no greater or more severe reflection or stigma or reproach amongst the Indians than to say of anyone, “he loves himself.” No doubt they did see what the fruits and effects of that selfish spirit would be if suffered to grow amongst them and how contrary it was to that open, free universal spirit that breathes peace on Earth and good will to men, that is willing to live and let live and to do as they would be done by and that loves his neighbor as himself. Self is called a monster, far exceeding the greatest tyrant, although there have been tyrants that have persecuted many thousands of the righteous to death. Olery and Charron says persecution on the score of conscience has thinned the world of fifty million of human beings. See again <persName key="w6t72g07">John Woolman's</persName> <emph rend="italic">Caution to the Rich</emph>, page 37: now if we single out Domitian, Nero or any other of the persecuting emperors, the man – though terrible in his time – will appear as a tyrant of small consequence compared with this selfish spirit. For though his bounds were large, yet a great part of the world was out of his reach. And though he grievously afflicted the bodies of these innocent people, yet the minds of many were divinely supported in their greatest agonies and, being faithful unto death, were delivered from his tyranny. His reign, though cruel for a time, was soon over, and he, considered in his greatest pomp, appears to have been a slave to selfish spirit. Thus tyranny, as applied to a man, riseth up and soon has an end.
<pb n="A0011237_02"/>
But if we consider the numerous oppressions of many states and the calamities occasioned by nations contending with nations in various parts and ages of the world and remember that selfishness hath been the original cause of them all; if we consider that those who are unredeemed from this selfish spirit not only afflict others but are afflicted themselves and have no real quietness in this life nor in futurity but, according to the sayings of Christ, have their portion in that painful condition where the worm dieth not and the fire is not quenched [Mark 9:44]; if we consider the havoc that has been made among mankind, in our age and in ages past, dismal – indeed, monstrous – will that selfish spirit appear to us.</p>
<p>That worthy minister <persName key="w6b38kp0">Thomas Ross</persName> once said it is a great thing to keep self down, and indeed I have thought it was so. For I believe if we could keep self down, we should keep Satan down and that he could have no way to make an inroad upon us. To be clear of self and truly resigned is a great attainment.</p>
What cannot resignation do?
It wonders can perform.
That powerful charm, thy will be done,
Can lay the loudest storm.<note resp="transcr">Edward Young</note>

“Know thyself” is enough for man to know. “Know thyself” was a precept so much noticed amongst the Athenians that it is said that it was wrote in golden letters and set up at the corners of their streets. And I think it is Peter Charron, in his <emph rend="italic">Book of Wisdom</emph>, says that in Spain (where it seems Paul once traveled) this was a proverb amongst them: Preserve me from myself, oh, deliver me from myself. And, indeed, what can be more dreadful than to be left to ourselves, as some formerly were? As it is said, he gave them over to a reprobate mind,<note resp="transcr">Romans 1:28</note> and then what dismal fruits and effects followed. Oh, Israel, thy destruction is of thy self.<note resp="transcr">Hosea 13:19</note> And indeed, is it not very evident now in our days, the dismal direful effects and fruits of a selfish spirit? Do we not plainly see how people cast off the thing that is good and how the enemy pursues them? And how they pursue lying vanities and forsake their own mercies, so that many live not half their days by cleaving unto wicked ways? See the effects of this selfish spirit.</p>
<p>But let us consider and see the precious fruits and effects of self-denial, of those who have been willing to take up the cross of Christ, who counted nothing too near or dear to part with, although it were as a right hand or a right eye. Throughout all the accounts in Scripture, and in all ages down to these day, we may plainly see the blessed fruits and effects of a righteous life and self-denial and the blessed glorious state and happy attainments. And, on the other hand, we have seen and may clearly see – not only in individuals, but whole nations and societies – what woeful, miserable work a selfish spirit has made amongst mankind, even about religion!
<pb n="A0011237_03"/>
Hath not this selfish spirit at times made the earth to tremble? The prophet said he saw the tents of Cushan in great affliction and the curtains of the land of Midian did tremble.<note resp="transcr">Habakkuk 3:7</note> Hath it not been so many a time, and have we not seen it so in our days, when the potsherds of the earth.<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 45:9</note> have dashed one against another and made a dismal rattle, when they have grievously tormented and afflicted one another, endeavoring all in the power to destroy and make one another miserable. See here the fruits and effects of this selfish spirit: how different and contrary it is from that spirit which breathes peace on earth and goodwill to men<note resp="transcr">Luke 2:14</note></p>
<p>Remember Bonaparte, that great emperor, the great French warrior? They called him an iron-hearted man because of his hard-heartedness and great cruelty in the time of his wars in Germany. See the accounts of the most dismal destruction, desolation, and ruin in the German empire, and we there may see in our days – but a few years ago – the dismal effects and fruits of the selfish spirit, whose power to oppress and distress mankind exceeds for all the power of the greatest tyrants. George Fox says when the Lord sent him out into the world to labor in his vineyard and awaken a drowsy world, the world was like a wilderness overgrown with briars and thorns, full of hissing serpents and stinging scorpions, and no right way found out of it. And the people! Many were like lions, bears, wolves, and tigers, ready to destroy him and all the sheep and lambs of Christ. Mark now and consider the fruits and effects of this selfish spirit that has brought the world and the people in it to be worse than the voracious devouring beasts of the wilderness. And we may see how in our days it has degraded many below the beast of the field, for they will only drink till they have enough, but Anthony Benezet says it is probable that a million of people destroy themselves annually by excessive drinking yearly of strong drink. See here again the direful effects and fruits of that selfish spirit, because they will not deny themselves, take up their cross, and follow Christ.</p>
<p>See here again what this selfish spirit makes of men. See Psalms 140:3: they sharpened their tongues like a serpent. And see Isaiah 14:29: out of the serpent's root shall come forth a cockatrice; his fruit shall be as a fiery, flying serpent. See Matthew 3:7: a generation of vipers, [Matthew] 12:34, [Matthew] 23:33, Luke 3:7, and as Jeremiah 10 chapter says, as a den of dragons.<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 10:22</note> John the Baptist and afterwards our Savior called the Scribes [Sadducees] and Pharisees a generation of vipers.<note resp="transcr">Matthew 3:7 and 12:34</note> Isaiah 30:6: from whence come the viper and serpent? Again 41:24: your work is worse than of a serpent. And see Isaiah 59:5: they hatch cockatrice eggs and weave the spider's web; he that eateth of their eggs dieth; that which is crushed breaks out into viper. So here is the fruits and effects of the selfish spirit, turn saints into sinners, or make saints of sinners as in the case of St. Paul.
[marginal note] See Hosea 10:1: Israel is an empty vine he bringeth me forth fruit unto himself see not empty in making goodly image is how is it with us.
<pb n="A0011237_04"/>
See  [James Meikle's] <emph rend="italic">Solitude Sweetened</emph>, page 42, on love in God: the love of God is a fixed and unchangeable love, and the more the soul is in sorrow or distress, the more free and full are the communications of divine love. In the time of need, the world's love will give us the slip. But in the most calamitous circumstance, sacred love performs the part of two loves and sticks closer than a brother. Mortals' loves (alas how many can attest the truth of this) may today appear ardent and steadfast and sincere but tomorrow be entirely cold. Yea, converted into slander, hatred, and revenge. But let all the sons of God know that divine love shall be to them what the holy waters were to the prophet – ever on the increase, till it be an ocean to swim in forever. Against fears on every side this is comfort – that God will rest in his love.</p>
<p>Divine love is also a beneficent love. Jonathan loved David exceedingly, but could not do much for him nor save him from being expelled from his native country. But the love of God is fruitful of every blessing, is the tree that bears all kinds of fruits that nourish the soul and feasts every power. The love of poor men can bring no advantage to the persons loved. But when God sets his love upon a sinner, all at once he who had nothing of late has all things: life, liberty, friends riches, glory, a kingdom, sufficiency here and all sufficiency hereafter – in a word, all that can be named, sought after, wished for, or thought upon. Then, ye sons of earth, hug yourselves in the embrace of wealth and bless your own condition, but presume not that you are the favorites of Heaven because his common providence pours upon you. As for me, may I be the object of his love and, in spite of poverty, I am rich; in spite of sin, I am secure and walk on triumphantly to the better country. O, how very different is this love here treated as from that selfish spirit just before treated on. How precious the fruits and effects, how far transcending all earthly treasures or glory.</p>
<p>A certain writer says a selfish spirit is the worst companion. It has led very many into a most sorrowful, dismal state and condition, as it did the young man that would feign have filled his belly with the husks the swine had left.<note resp="transcr">Luke 15:16</note> They that cast of the thing that is good, the enemy shall pursue them<note resp="transcr">Hosea 8:3</note>; and they that pursue lying vanities forsake their own mercies. So it is many live not half their days by cleaving unto wicked ways.</p>
<p>Seneca says: oh, ye miserable mortals, how many afflictions you do endure, which might be easily prevented. So indeed it is. What miserable vagabonds there are, poor wretched, degraded, creatures – all for want of taking up the cross to their own wills. Oh Israel, thy destruction is of thyself, but thy help is in me.<note resp="transcr">Hosea 13:9</note> A man's worst enemies are those of his own house,<note resp="transcr">William Blake</note> and he that conquers himself conquers his greatest enemy. See Acts 14:16: who in time past suffered all nations to walk in their own ways.</p>
He is more than a prince that rules himself,
Than he who nations keep in awe:
Who yield to that which doth their souls convince,
Shall never need another law.<note resp="transcr">Katherine Phillips, “The Soul”</note></p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_05"/>
<div type="entry" when="1820-07-30"><dateline><date when="1820-07-30">1820.</date></dateline><p> 30 of the Seventh Month, First Day. At our meeting, and had no cause to repent being there. I believe it ended to general satisfaction. If our hearts condemn us not, then have confidence towards God, said the apostle.<note resp="transcr">1 John 3:21</note> But, O, alas, what room and need there is of improvement!</p></div>
{1820-08}
<div type="entry" when="1820-08-04"><dateline><date when="1820-08-04">4 was Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> Instead of going to our meeting, I felt most easy to go to the burial of a little girl, about 10 years old, at Joseph Cole's. A family brought up and professing the Church of England, a poor orphan child. I expected there would be but very few there, it being a very busy season. They buried her in the churchyard. There was but a small company, but behaved very orderly and well; and I had an open satisfactory time with them, and there was something sweet, owning, kind, and inviting at parting at the grave. Who can estimate or calculate, set a price on peace and tranquility of mind? It is to be feared very few consider the worth of it. Thy loving kindness is better than life, David said.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 63:3</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-08-05"><dateline><date when="1820-08-05">Sixth Day.</date></dateline><p> My wife and Hannah and I went to see Reuben Burroughs and wife and family. I have long wanted to go to see them, he being lately disowned at Haddonfield on account of a contentious lawsuit between him and his first cousin, S. Thorn, about a very little gore of land for which R. Burroughs offered to settle the matter with them for 10 dollars. But no, he said he would not buy that which was his own and so to law they went and spent 200 dollars at court and lawyers on each side and not ended yet. Verily, said Paul, there is a fault among you brother goes to law with brother.<note resp="transcr">1 Corinthians 6:7</note> I had some relief and satisfaction, but no prospect of doing much, if any, good. There seemed to be no room for anything but what concerns earthly affairs. Perhaps that which is better – too little sought for by any of us or desired.<note resp="transcr">At Haddonfield Monthly Meeting, 12th Month 1819, a “testimony of disunion” was presented for Reuben Burrough who “so far departed from the good order of the Society as to act improperly in the conduct and in conversation relating to a disputed case, for which breach of order he has been deal with but not manifesting a suitable disposition of mind to make an acknowledgment the meeting came to a conclusion to disown him.”</note></p>
<p>We now hear that the fever is broke out again in town in divers places, and it is said there has been a most dreadful hail storm down about Malakee [Mullica] Hill. And Woodstown, it is said the hail stones was as big as an egg that it destroyed fields of Indian corn and killed some calves. But it reached but a little ways, a mile or two.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-08-06"><dateline><date when="1820-08-06">6 of the Eighth Month First Day morning.</date></dateline><p> See the character of J[ohn]. W[oolman]. in his journal, page 273. He has given the world an instance of the possibility of living without wasting a single hour, and of the advantage of a regular distribution of time in discharging the important duties and purposes of life. Few ages have more needed such a public testimony to the value of time, and perhaps none had a more conspicuous example of the perfection to which the improvement of it may be carried.</p>
<p>At our meeting. To me a mortifying time because [there was] not that clothing ability, evident ownings of truth, and sweetness and savor of life as at some other times. I have been told that I am never content but in the best of pasture, and then like we read of Jesuran waxed fat and kicked.<note resp="transcr">Deuteronomy 32:15</note> Suffocation is as fatal as starvation.</p>
<p>[marginal note] A most mortifying time to money mongers. They cannot sell their great quantities of pork and bacon, etc. Cucumbers, they say, are sold for five pence a bushel, and now a very great prospect of great crops.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_06"/>
<div type="entry" when="1820-08-10"><dateline><date when="1820-08-10">10 of the Eighth Month.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting, to my right good satisfaction throughout.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-08-11"><dateline><date when="1820-08-11">11.</date></dateline><p> Having some business that way, I was at Evesham Monthly Meeting, and a more open, owning time I hardly ever had there, strengthening. But attending meeting two days past and the weather very hot, I was almost exhausted and overcome with feebleness and weakness.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-08-13"><dateline><date when="1820-08-13">13.</date></dateline><p> First Day. I am so poorly this morning I concluded I could not go to meeting. But feeling a little better after breakfast, my daughters and I went to Cropwell, where I have been talking of going weeks past. <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> we found there. The waters to me seemed very low, but <persName key="w6md9qck">H.H.</persName> took up almost the whole time of the meeting, and I had some little relief and satisfaction at last and hope it ended pretty well. This afternoon, having the approbation of our Monthly Meeting, I appointed a meeting at the schoolhouse near the Green Tree Tavern, which ended to my sweet satisfaction. There was some most miserable, old, distressed drunkards there who showed loving and respectfull to me, although I had dealt very plain and close with them on that great and crying sin of drunkenness. It was satisfactory to look over the day.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-08-17"><dateline><date when="1820-08-17">17.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. I thought rather smaller than common, yet there was something very lively stirring amongst us. Joseph Cowperthwaite, who has appeared in meeting several years at times and has lain ill last winter in a deep consumption, is got out again and looks like one arose from the dead or brink of the grave. Had very considerable to say, and divers others. I believe it ended to general satisfaction. I suppose there were some strangers from Philadelphia. They say there is now a very serious alarm on account of the prevalence of the fever. 4, it is said, died lately out of one house. One Ingle, a young man, it is said catched the disorder (a fat man) and died suddenly up Ancocas. And our neighbor Joseph Cole (where I was at the burial a few days ago of a girl) yesterday buried one of his boys with a strange disorder, which the doctor tells them is as catching as the measles, on which account they buried him without making a little, if any, invitation to his burial. The disorder, they say, has gone through the family, except the old folks. Several of their daughters have been very ill. I think they call it the Scarlet Fever, attended with sore throat. Oh, how many serious calls to a devout and holy life, after divers ways and divers manners, attended with too little effect.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_07"/>
<div type="entry" when="1820-08-18"><dateline><date when="1820-08-18">18.</date></dateline><p> J.M. Matlack his wife and daughter paid us a visit and tells us that there two barns burnt with lightning lately in Pennsylvania – one very large, at a great tavern, and eight horses burnt in it: And I was told a few days ago there was fifty sheep killed with the thunder under a tree. I suppose these accounts are in the news.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-08-20"><dateline><date when="1820-08-20">20.</date></dateline><p> First Day. I picked up a bit of an old newspaper dated April 15, 1818 (called <emph rend="italic">Village Record</emph>): thus it appears that in the city and liberties of Philadelphia only, within the last 4 years 1420 persons have fallen a sacrifice by the ravages of this disorder of mankind (the consumption of the lungs) as certified by the Board of Health and signed John Allison, clerk for the years 1814, 1815, and 1816, and for the year 1817 signed Joseph Prior. From the 1st of January 1814 to the last of January 1815, 274 persons have died of the consumption of the lungs. From the first of January 1816 to the first of January 1817 to December 1817, 362 died with the consumption. It is there said it appear by the bills of mortality that more people die of consumptions and disorders in the breast and lungs than any other disorder.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-08-20"><dateline><date when="1820-08-20">20.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting waters very low. Many very dull and drowsy. Amos Hilburn of Byberry was there, but it seemed as if he could or did not rise to say anything. I had a few sentences at last to good satisfaction. With leave from our Monthly Meeting, I appointed a meeting at our schoolhouse at 4th hour. A number of very raw young people who seemed to choose to stand about the door rather than come in, but we did get them in. Forepart was a very poor, stripping, trying time to me, but through mercy it growed better. Some young ministers – Joseph Cowperthwaite, Ebenezer Roberts, and Hannah Warrington – were highly favored, and I was helped beyond expectation, and a lively time it was at last, I believe to general satisfaction. There were divers there very seldom get to meeting of any sort. One of these said it was the most satisfactory meeting they was ever at in their lives.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-08-27"><dateline><date when="1820-08-27">27.</date></dateline><p> Eighth Month. First Day. I have weeks past been looking towards Haddonfield, and now, with Joseph Cowperthwaite to Haddonfield. The meeting was very large, and to me the most open, evidently owing time I ever seen there. We put up and dined at a tavern, Thomas Porter's, an old acquaintance and native of our neighborhood who kindly entertained us gratis. We had a sitting with him and wife and their ancient mother, and was at their afternoon meeting, which was very small. But we were favored to come off with good satisfaction and returned with sweet peace, although religion there is very low, trampled underfoot, kicked out of doors by very many.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_08"/>
<div type="entry" when="1820-08-29"><dateline><date when="1820-08-29">29 of the Eighth Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> My son Benjamin and daughters Abigail and Hannah and I went to Burlington Quarterly Meeting, which was very large. We had two of the very heads of the tribes and princes of the people: Elizabeth H. Walker of New York and <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> of Newtown, and both had most excellent service. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> appeared in solemn supplication at last, and a solemn, highly favored time it was thought to be. I had some share in the labor in last meeting to good satisfaction, though not the smallest part.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-08-31"><dateline><date when="1820-08-31">31 was Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our preparative meeting. It was not a very satisfactory one to me, and I hardly know the cause without it was the want of more life. Our son Joseph and his wife and son [Benjamin and Esther] were here to see us.</p></div>
{1820-09}
<div type="entry" when="1820-09-01"><dateline><date when="1820-09-01">1 of the Ninth Month</date></dateline><p> at our select meeting, one of the best (almost) I can remember. However, one of our elders thought it a good meeting to me. Satisfactory. </p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-09-03"><dateline><date when="1820-09-03">3 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> Very low water with us till near last. I believe [it] ended with some degree of the savor of life and ownings of truth.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-09-05"><dateline><date when="1820-09-05">5.</date></dateline><p> We hear of the great distress at Philadelphia. The fever, they say, rages in an alarming manner and is very mortal. They bury them, ‘tis said, in the night, and carriages going all hours of the night. People moving out and they say they are fencing up the streets. It is said the disorder is so obstinate the doctors can do nothing with it.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-09-06"><dateline><date when="1820-09-06">6.</date></dateline><p> Soliloque as John Rutty says or song in the night – The fame of wisdom: Wisdom is said to be the principal thing and the merchandise of it is better than silver and the gain thereof better than fine gold. But as we read in Job, where shall wisdom be found, and where is the place of understanding? The depths saith it is not in me and the sea saith it is not in me. No mention shall be made of coral or of pearl, the Topaz of Ethiopia cannot equal it. It cannot be gotten for gold, neither shall gold or silver be weighed for the price thereof for the price of wisdom is far above rubies.<note resp="transcr">Job 28:12-18</note> And then see the conclusion: the fear of the Lord, that is wisdom; and to depart from evil is good understanding.<note resp="transcr">Job 28:28</note></p>
<p>But alas, how is the fear of the Lord banished in our days. The cause of truth and true religion treated as a very trifling thing, even as a fable not worth much noticing, trampled under foot and kicked out of doors with very many. Christ is said to be the wisdom of God and the power of God.<note resp="transcr">1 Corinthians 1:24</note> Solomon says, see Proverbs 16 and 16 verse: how much better it is to get wisdom than gold. A house full of gold would do nothing for a dying man, but the favor of wisdom, Christ, would do all he could wish for. 19 and 8: he that getteth wisdom loveth his own soul, say[s] Solomon.
<pb n="A0011237_09"/>
1820. See Ecclesiastes 8 and 1st verse: a man's wisdom maketh his face to shine. And indeed I have often thought the folly of the poor drunkard hath made their faces to look very dismal, and many others who have given way to gross wickedness; their faces are marked with a dismal appearance. But on all the vessels of the Lord's house is this inscription: Holiness to the Lord [Exodus 39:30]. Their countenances are stamped with innocency, mildness, and benevolence. </p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-09-07"><dateline><date when="1820-09-07">Ninth Month, 7.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our Monthly Meeting we had a shower of strangers from Byberry, Pennsylvania. Sweet, worthy, amiable, able ministers: our cousin <persName key="w6g77m31">Hannah Yarnal</persName>; Amos Hilburn; Mary Walkton, a maiden; Warder Cresson a youth about 22, and they all had lively, pertinent, sweet, acceptable service. A lively, highly favored time it was, I believe.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-09-08"><dateline><date when="1820-09-08">8.</date></dateline><p> My daughter Abigail and Joseph Cowperthwaite and I went to Evesham Monthly Meeting. The above named strangers were there, and cousin Hannah was raised in great eminence in the exercise of her gift, and Mary Walkton and Warder Cresson, and an open, solemn, favored time it was. I did think something of an heavenly nature did attend throughout. But oh, how are very many set down at ease and settled on their lease [lees?], although we daily hear of the language of mortality waxing louder and louder, both to the city and country. The pestilential fever prevailing in an awful manner; several lately dying raveing [raving], districted [distracted]. It is said one so much so as to bite his pillow, and another took or 4 men to keep him on his bed, here in our neighborhood.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-09-10"><dateline><date when="1820-09-10">10.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. I went as a blank, destitute of any prospect or desire of being heard – but quite the contrary. We sat so long in silence that several left the meeting, but at last life did seem to rise into dominion, and I believe it ended very savory and reputably. There were several from Pennsylvania: James Simpson, son of <persName key="w68m543d">John Simpson</persName>, who appeared lively in the ministry. I spent several hours with him and wife at Joseph Cowperthwaite's, and then at 4 hour went to the burial of Sarah, the wife of Samuel Matlack, who has lain some weeks or days past very ill with the gravel. Left a large family of children, mostly grown up. I had a few sentences at the grave to some satisfaction.</p>
<p>We have had a long spell of very dry weather; no rain this many weeks. People could not go on with sowing their rye – but now came a very soaking rain.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-09-13"><dateline><date when="1820-09-13">13.</date></dateline><p> At select meeting at Haddonfield. William Foster from England was there, and Stephen Grellet, the Frenchman of New York, very lately returned from a vast extensive visit to the European nations, and divers others strangers. And we had a great deal of preaching, but yet not much animation as I thought. I could not find life to rise into dominion as at some times.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_10"/>
<div type="entry" when="1820-09-14"><dateline><date when="1820-09-14">14th of the Ninth Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> Was our quarterly meeting at Haddonfield. It was very large, and to me very poor and dry and dull. But as Barclay compares the wording of the spirit to throwing a little water in a pump and working it brings up the rest, so it seemed to be. For <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> rose up with life and power and it brought a change of feeling, and then William Foster, lately from England, was large in testimony. And Stephen Grellet of New York, and very lately returned the second time from a very extensive visit to the European nations, had extensive weighty service. So it seemed to grow better and better till [at] last it was a lively, searching time, as it were, with lighted candles. Especially on the subject of putting the discipline in practice I had great relief, having been burdened and been hammering and stammering at it many years past, on account of the fullness of our answers respecting putting the discipline in practice.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-09-17"><dateline><date when="1820-09-17">17.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. At our meeting. Sort of middling, not so savory as some.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-09-21"><dateline><date when="1820-09-21">21.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day meeting morning. I am thinking of the query we have concerning becoming or unbecoming behavior at meetings, and what sort of behavior is becoming the solemnity of the occasion, and what sort of men and women ought we to be, and in what manner we should attend our religious meetings. Certainly it should be in the most humble, reverent, dependant state, as our ancestors did present their bodies, a living sacrifice, in the most reverent, humble, dependant state, even to contrition, trembling, and tears (whereby they got the name of Tremblers or Quakers) – a state very different from a trifling easy, lukewarm, indifferent state overwhelmed with drowsiness.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-09-24"><dateline><date when="1820-09-24">24.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. More life and evident ownings of truth, [which] I wanted to feel. May we never be contented or satisfied without it, lest we sit down contented in an exact form without the life. For what is the chaff to the wheat?<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 23:28</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-09-28"><dateline><date when="1820-09-28">28.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Joseph Justice had considerable to say, and J. Cowperthwaite and I thought it did end pretty well, lively and savory at last. But Thomas à Kempis says we are not to depend on any one disposition of mind with which we feel ourselves affected, for this is fickle and of short duration. See <emph rend="italic">Journal of Job Scott</emph>, the ups and the downs he had to experience, sometimes so cast down as ready to question all he had ever experienced of heavenly goodness. <persName key="w6dn68k9">William Hunt</persName> and many others also.</p></div>
{1820-10}
<div type="entry" when="1820-10-01"><dateline><date when="1820-10-01">1st of the Tenth Month and 3 of the week.</date></dateline><p> Went to the burial of William Roberts Junior, a very lusty, stout, tall young man, about 25 years of age. Died with the fever now prevalent; left two young children and a sorrowful widow. There was excellent outward order, but oh the need of being like minded with David, who prayed that a right spirit might be renewed within him.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 51:10</note> Oh, the need I thought there was of more tender hearts whereon some impressions might be made, [leaves off there]
<pb n="A0011237_11"/>
[marginal note] For indeed neither mercies nor judgments seem not to have the desired effect in bring about the desired reformation. I could see but little or no signs of the inwarded life, the hidden life, the life that's hid with Christ in God, the life of God in the soul of Man. I fear the people have lost sight of it and see nothing of the necessity of it and are set down quite easy with a mere moral righteousness, although the language of mortality and waxed louder and louder in both cities and parts of the country. I am told that a malignant fever is very mortal at the town of Savannah, and that it a very sickly time in Salem County, especially at Manington etc. This was a very stormy day. A very great rain after several weeks of very pinching, dry weather and a complaint of wells getting dry.</p>
<p>Blessed are they that hunger and thirst after righteousness.<note resp="transcr">Matthew 5:6</note> But we seem to be set down, quite contented with a moral righteousness, although we see we stand in need of something more when calamity overtakes us. See Acts 17:27: That they should seek the Lord if haply they might feel after him and find him, though he be not far from everyone of us. What a strange thing it would be nowadays to recommend this to the people at burials. Oh, how foreign from their thoughts or desires, although our first friends say it was their concern when they met together to feel the Lord amongst them, and oh how he did at times manifest himself among them to the opening their hearts and contriting their spirits, even to tears, so that at times there was scarcely a dry eye amongst them – although silent and not a word spoken in their gatherings. Alas, where are we, or what is the chaff to the wheat,<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 23:28</note> the shell to the kernel? An exact decent outward form to the substance of true vital religion.</p>
<p>We sat in an old room with the corpse, just newly vamped up in the new mode. Very nice. I could but think of the corpse as it lay before us, and the new finished room, and how humble and contented the old people had lived in it, to my knowledge. How pride and superfluity looks when put together at these awful seasons.</p>
Be not proud by any means;
Build not your house too high,
But always have before your eyes
That you were born to die.

<p>Said the martyr: people may try the many ways, but they will never find a better than that the Scriptures point out, which is straight and narrow, low and humble. Oh, what wisdom there appears in it at the solemn, awful close.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_12"/>
<div type="entry" when="1820-10-07"><dateline><date when="1820-10-07">7th of the Tenth Month</date></dateline><p> at our Monthly Meeting, which was large. Many strangers or from distant meetings – Thomas Matthews of Philadelphia, <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName>, and divers others. Forepart seemed to be a shut up time, especially with the strangers. In the course of the meeting I had at several times some remarks or sentences to drop, which, on considering of on my bed, I could not wish to recall – but yet so it was at last. It was a mortifying time to me, and perhaps profitable and necessary.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-10-08"><dateline><date when="1820-10-08">8 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. To me, an open, owning, favored time. From the openness, pleasantness, sweetness, and feeling nearness that appeared in divers, I was ready to conclude it was to general satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-10-10"><dateline><date when="1820-10-10">10.</date></dateline><p> Cloudy dull wet weather. See William Smith's <emph rend="italic">Works</emph>, page 89, To such as live a single life: For that which makes all people happy and every condition sweet is to answer the light of Christ Jesus manifest in their consciences. And then – however they stand in relation to an outward state – they will have peace with God and they will possess his blessing, both inwardly and outwardly. So to be single to God in the light is a joyful state.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-10-11"><dateline><date when="1820-10-11">11.</date></dateline><p> A stormy night, but clears up fine this morning. See again William Smith's <emph rend="italic">Works</emph>, page 102, Council to the Baptists: for no satisfaction or refreshment can any find, but in that life which the holy men of God were inspired with and declared the Scriptures from. So all that you make to yourselves, profit you no how like so ever, you may make it in appearance to that which the saints practised in the power.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-10-12"><dateline><date when="1820-10-12">12 was Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. I thought it was more lively and savory than common.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-10-15"><dateline><date when="1820-10-15">15.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Ann Quicksill of Evesham was at our meeting and had sweet, pertinent, savory service – a hopeful, growing, young minister. And Lidi Lippincott also had acceptable service, and I thought it ended very well and savory, but yet not to my own peace as I could wish. Not clear of all.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-10-17"><dateline><date when="1820-10-17">17.</date></dateline><p> Third Day evening. See [Lindley Murray's] <emph rend="italic">Sequel to the English Reader</emph>, page 181: Guard well thy thoughts; our thoughts are heard in Heaven. Dr. Young: The man is yet unborn who duly weighs an hour. Thomas à Kempis says: Oh, that I could but spend an hour after the best manner! Another says he repented of all his life long but that which he spent in communion with God and doing good.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-10-19"><dateline><date when="1820-10-19">19.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. Lively enough, if it was of the right sort. Had a pretty deal said.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_13"/>
<div type="entry" when="1820-10-21"><dateline><date when="1820-10-21">21.</date></dateline><p> Seventh Day. My old friend, about one year older than me, Jonathan Kikbrite of Bucks County, Pennsylvania, and his son-in-law William Tailor, came to see me. He traveled with me when I visited the meetings in Pennsylvania about twelve years ago. They lodged with us, and very pleasant and sweetly we did seem to enjoy one another's company.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-10-22"><dateline><date when="1820-10-22">22.</date></dateline><p> First Day. They went to our meeting with us and both of them had very acceptable service, and I had some part of the time. I did think it was a good meeting and ended very savory, I believe to general satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-10-25"><dateline><date when="1820-10-25">25.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. Pretty lively and satisfactory, on deliberation.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-10-28"><dateline><date when="1820-10-28">28.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Our cousin Caleb Hunt from Redstone was there, and I don't know but it ended savory and reputably.</p></div>
{1820-11}
<div type="entry" when="1820-11-02"><dateline><date when="1820-11-02">2nd of the Eleventh Month.</date></dateline><p> Joseph Cowperthwaite went with me to Cropwell meeting. There we found John Hallock of Egg Harbor. The meeting was very small and very poor and low, not seemingly in a growing state; yet they are a match for any, [I] think, in managing their worldly concerns. John Hallack, I.C., and myself had considerable to impart, and I hope pertinent. But what must it be to raise the life when it is at so low and ebb! And if the dead are not raised (preaching it is said) is in vain.<note resp="transcr">1 Corinthians 15:14</note></p>
<p>This afternoon I mended two pumps: one for Joseph Rogers and one for his son. Got a fall from the top of the pump and I think had like to have broke my arm, so I am now very lame in my left arm.</p>
<p>I picked up a little choice book, the life of Jane Pearson, see page 61, and mine eyes saw with unspeakable astonishment that we fret for things unworthy the notice of a redeemed mind, and that if I or my Friends with whom I sat were but called upon to take their leave of everything below the sun, all these perplexing anxieties would vanish like an atom in the whirlwind and be of no weight at all. We should then only lament that we had not looked above these momentary afflictions and fixed our confidence on the invisible arm and invincible power of omnipotence. But oh! how is the natural part attracted by visible objects, while that which is born from above suffers through our not adhering to the invisible.</p>
<p>See again Jane Pearson's journal, page 72: In danger of being like Gideon, who after his great achievement made an Ephod and, idolizing it, the same became a snare to him. Sixth Month 30th 1802. – I was at our weekday meeting and was favored with a solemn silence, resembling that in Heaven, where angels and archangels adore in profound silence. I saw into the joys thereof; a place where sorrow cannot come: none of the inhabitants have any affliction and favored with Heavenly bread.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_14"/>
<div type="entry" when="1820-11-04"><dateline><date when="1820-11-04">Seventh Day.</date></dateline><p> My arm is very lame with the fall from of the top of the pump. Again, see Jane Pearson's Life, page 84: I seemed not dandled on the knee – I will bear it. For oh! I dread being at ease in Zion or trusting to anything short of what is really substantial, that feeds and nourishes the soul into everlasting life.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-11-05"><dateline><date when="1820-11-05">5 of the Eleventh Month 1820 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Not much satisfaction… search for the cause. I dread being at ease in Zion, say Jane Pearson. Well would it be if it was the case with all, but how natural it is, when we live in fullness, to sit down at ease and scuttle on our leas. Like the man we read of whose ground brought forth plentifully and he concluded he had goods laid up in store for many years and said to his soul, eat, drink. and take thy rest, etc. But see what a dangerous state it was, and how unwise. For it was said unto him: thou fool, this night shall thy soul be required of thee, and then whose shall those things be which thou hast provided? And so shall it be with all those who say up treasures for themselves and are not rich towards God.<note resp="transcr">Luke 12:19-21</note></p>
<p>Then is it not a dangerous time? For although I have seen eighty years, I think I never seen a more plentiful season for rye, wheat, Indian corn, oats, buckwheat, potatoes, and apple in abundance, and the finest, largest, and fairest I ever seen, so that there is scarcely room to contain them or casks to hold the cider. But oh, how are these precious blessing[s] turned into a destructive, poisonous spirit, a destructive man bane blast nation stuff, as a poor drunk and called it. And how little regard is paid to that dreadful war pronounced by the prophet: to them that fuel the battle to their neighbor, the cup of the Lord's right hand shall be turned unto thee and shameful spring shall be upon thy glory.<note resp="transcr">Habakkuk 2:16</note></p>
<p>If people were too openly declare they did not believe the Scriptures it would be no matter of wonder, they do as they do. But to profess to believe in the Scriptures and do as they do, what can be more diametrically opposite? What sort of a people were they whose root, the Prophet said, should be as rottenness and their blossom flee away as dust? And as Jane Pearson says, when they are called upon to bid adieu to their earthly idols then their fascinating schemes flee away as atoms in the whirlwind and leave them empty.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-11-09"><dateline><date when="1820-11-09">9</date></dateline><p> was our Monthly Meeting. A good meeting, I thought: open, owning, and savory and satisfactory and strengthening. Some time I feel so poor, low, and naked I do not want to speak to anybody, but rather to be hid. And at other times, openness – sweetness.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-11-12"><dateline><date when="1820-11-12">12.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. Snowed most all day yesterday, and rained very much in the night, and rainy stormy today. But I did get to meeting, which was small and but low and poor and quite shut up in silence as to myself. J.C. and E.R. unwell. Joseph Justice had something to communicate, but it ended abruptly.</p>
<p>We hear of a very remarkable accident or hand of providence. Mahlon Bud of Mount Holly one night was at a tavern with considerable company drinking. Stepped out to go to the necessary, which stood on the edge of the creek. He found some in the little house and went, it is said, and leaned beside the fence, which gave way and he fell into the creek and was drowned immediately. They soon missed him out of their company, searched for and found him. It is said he left one dead drunk on the floor. He bore the character of a hard drinker and great libertine. A solemn and alarming call to all.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_15"/>
<div type="entry" when="1820-11-19"><dateline><date when="1820-11-19">19th of the Eleventh Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> On Fourth Day Edward Brook of London Grove, Pennsylvania, appointed a meeting at Moorestown, our meeting, and had acceptable service. His testimony was much against formality, profession without possession, power and like. <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> also had something pertinent and savory. At last something opened to me on this wise: we have read and heard much said of the fame of religion – the Christian religion, and what great things it has done for people in days of old – and we have seen even down to these days what great things religion has done for the faithful and obedient. But what hath it done for us, and what is the state of religion in our days? We have had line upon line, precept upon precept, here a little and there a little – yea, more here a great deal and there a great deal – and what hath it done for us? We are told that where much is given, much will be required. And what was to be the doom of that servant that knew his matters will and did it not? We have been an highly favored people, favored with the upper and the nether springs,<note resp="transcr">Judges 1:15</note> favored with the dew of Heaven and the fatness of the earth (few if any more so).<note resp="transcr">Genesis 27:28</note> May not the language be applied to us: Oh Jerusalem, Jerusalem, how often would I have gathered thee as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wing.<note resp="transcr">Luke 13:34</note> Why then are we not gathered, and how shall we escape if we neglect to avail ourselves of such offers of love? And will the whole world be price enough to ransom us or countervail our loss? The meeting broke up whilst I was in fear of hurting what had been said. Very fine, moderate, dry weather again.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-11-19"><dateline><date when="1820-11-19">19 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting, and a lively, open, favored time I believe it was. It affected me to see the lively, hopeful appearance of several of our youth – Hannah Warrington, Mary Matlack, and Joseph Cowperthwaite, and A.H. I did believe there was few if any but must have had a sense of something more solemn and savory than usual. A satisfactory time to me after I got to bed.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-11-23"><dateline><date when="1820-11-23">23.</date></dateline><p> At our preparative meeting a lively zeal, if it was of the right sort. As James Simpson once told us at our quarterly meeting, here is a godly zeal: the shout of a king, the sword of the Lord and of Gideon.<note resp="transcr">Judges 7:20</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-11-24"><dateline><date when="1820-11-24">24.</date></dateline><p> I went to see Samuel Balinger on his 86th year, and found him brave – better than he was two years ago. Samuel Church went with me and he expressed great satisfaction with our visit. Then we went to see Benjamin Hopewell, in his 73rd year. He served his apprenticeship with my father. He has been greatly afflicted with a disease in his feet and ankles; had in early life given way to intemperance but is reformed from it. Then we went to see Samuel Sharp in his 91st year; he expressed gladness with our visit. Then we went to see Sibbila Duril and Rubin Haines, who have lost their reason and are 2 of the most sorrowful objects that I know of. Here away there were several others I wanted to see, but time did not admit of it. I have some months past thought of Solomon's words: it is better to go to the house of mourning than to the house of mirth.<note resp="transcr">Ecclesiastes 7:2</note> I thought I would try it and it is not unpleasant to look back and think how I spent the day.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-11-26"><dateline><date when="1820-11-26">26th Seventh Day.</date></dateline><p> Richard Bircham appointed a meeting at Moorestown and was nearly silent. He said a few words at last after holding meeting longer than common. The meeting not very satisfactory. I fear I did not stand quite clear.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_16"/>
<div type="entry" when="1820-11-26"><dateline><date when="1820-11-26">26th of the Eleventh Month First Day.</date></dateline><p> Moderate weather at our meeting. Silent as to me, but not the poorest. E.R. and J.J. had a great deal to say, with which I find all were not altogether satisfied. It is a comfort that I was preserved from doing any harm. See Jane Pearson's Diary, page 55: There is an active spirit… that takes its food upon the surface or catches at it flying in the airy regions. With food of this nature some seek to feed and be fed… although what was delivered through sound truths yet did not slay the man of sin. [Page] 56, she says at one meeting the season was too solemn for any vocal voice to be heard, the cloud and glory so great that none could minister. [Page] 57, she says and though I cannot say I never made one false step, yet he who knows my heart knows it to be weakness. Oh, how weak are we when divested of his saving help, etc. [Page] 58: This day I was silent; the fullness of glory too great to minister. Oh blessed state, far beyond and better than words. Then, next page, mentions the buffeting ups and downs she had to meet with.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-11-27"><dateline><date when="1820-11-27">Second Day morning.</date></dateline><p> See [Lindley Murray's] <emph rend="italic">Sequel to the English Reader</emph>, page 130: surely that religion to which we oweth these sentiments and hope must be the greatest blessing that ever was conferred on the posterity of Adam. Again, 131: Christianity is a doctrine in which nothing is superfluous or burdensome, and in which there is nothing wanting which can procure happiness to mankind or by which God can be glorified.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-11-29"><dateline><date when="1820-11-29">29 of the Eleventh Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> Fourth of the week went to the burial of Samuel Coles of Moorestown – he was my schoolmate and playmate. Both of us in our 81st year, nearly of an age. In his youthful days he took great liberty and was very wild in his career. He got on board a man of war and was taken to England and got reduced to great poverty, yet was favored to find friends so that he got home and applied himself to industry. Married my old master's daughter, Mary Matlack, raised up a family of children, accumulated wealth, and sustained the character of a temperate, frugal, quiet, peaceable, honest, insensitive, innocent man. There were a large concourse of people at parting at the grave. I had a few sentences to impart to the people, to peace and satisfaction of my own mind. He frequented our meetings, but never joined any religious society. Weather pretty cold.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-11-30"><dateline><date when="1820-11-30">Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. To right, good satisfaction.</p></div>
{1820-12}
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-01"><dateline><date when="1820-12-01">1 of the Twelfth Month Sixth day.</date></dateline><p> At our select meeting a lively zeal appeared, and I hope some savor. Whilst I was making ready another and another and another stepped in, which has often been the case, so that I had not full satisfaction, although not much cause of complaint.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-03"><dateline><date when="1820-12-03">3.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. Came off pretty well, some say rather more life and savor than common.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-04"><dateline><date when="1820-12-04">4.</date></dateline><p> Our little granddaughter, Bulah John's daughter, was buried. A very stormy day. My wife nor I did not go to its burial. It was a very fine, healthy child, about two years and a half old. Died very suddenly with the hives or stoppage in its stomach. See <emph rend="italic">Memoirs</emph> of Anthony Benezet, page 123.  He says: I desire to verify in myself in all cases the doctrine of one of the copies I use in my school:
<l>Just be thy thoughts and all thy words sincere,</l>
<l>And know no wish but what the world may hear.</l>
</p>
<p>They say of A. Benezet, he was favored to have on continually the armor of humility and protested by it none of these things exalted his depending spirit. Page 97 he speaks of the poisonous idolatry of self, so apt to creep in.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_17"/>
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-07"><dateline><date when="1820-12-07">7th of the Twelfth Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> At our Monthly Meeting, and if I am not mistaken an open, owning, good time it was. Many very pertinent, lively remarks were made – yet I was afraid some of our young ministers in the current over run the right landing place. </p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-08"><dateline><date when="1820-12-08">8.</date></dateline><p> Went to the burial of Samuel Laning of Moorestown, my old fellow [ap]prentice, about 4 years older than myself, about 85. He has been a very quiet, peaceable, honest man, of a good share of understanding. His only greatest failing was foolish jesting, to which he was much addicted. I went begging for preservation and resignation, and was favored to come off without condemnation, with good satisfaction in some communications to the people at the house.</p>
<p>This afternoon I went to see my old schoolmate Thomas Hooton, who is very poorly in his 87th year. He and his children expressed satisfaction with our visit and I had no cause to repent it.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-10"><dateline><date when="1820-12-10">10.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting, which was large and at first very low and poor. I was ready to conclude it would be a silent meeting till at last I thought it ended very well, open and satisfactory. Very cold again.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-14"><dateline><date when="1820-12-14">14.</date></dateline><p> Was our select meeting at Evesham, but I did not get there.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-15"><dateline><date when="1820-12-15">15.</date></dateline><p> Was quarterly meeting. Weather warmer. We all got to quarterly meeting, which was very large. Elizabeth Barton of Newtown, a maiden of a low family, appeared and did beautifully, famously, and worthily. And <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> appeared in prayer; solemnity, savor, weight attended. A solemn time it was. In the afternoon, on the state of society as reported in the queries, a lively zeal appeared and many pertinent instructing remarks were made. I had right, good satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-18"><dateline><date when="1820-12-18">18.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. The waters seemed low, I thought a good while we should have silent meeting. But at last some life and savor appeared and it seemed to end pretty well, though great room and need of improvement.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-21"><dateline><date when="1820-12-21">21.</date></dateline><p> At our preparative meeting, which I thought was lively, open, and satisfactory. Several days dry, severe freezing weather, but extreme[ly] changeable.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-24"><dateline><date when="1820-12-24">24.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Warmer and rain. At our meeting, not that peace and clothing  as at some times. This afternoon I, with several others, visited (according to our custom) Enoch Robert's family, who lately brought a certificate to pretty good satisfaction. I conclude it is not worth while to make any account of any religious performances without we can obtain a reward of peace. What does all we can say, hear, see, or do avail without life and peace? As George Fox says, what good does all your profession of the Scriptures and religion do without life?</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-25"><dateline><date when="1820-12-25">25.</date></dateline><p> What they call Christmas. Dry, clear, and very cold again.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_18"/>
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-28"><dateline><date when="1820-12-28">28th of the Twelfth Month 1820, Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> A considerable snow storm. I did not get out to meeting, having been very unwell with a complaint in my bowels.</p>
<p>Last First Day Joseph Gill's wife was buried. A young woman, left several children. He was at market the Fourth Day before she was buried. [She] got a cold and typhus fever, followed a lad, one [indecipherable], to be buried today 29 at Evesham, where it is said the scarlet fever prevails. It is a wonder such sudden deaths does not raise a concern amongst us to be prepared to leave this world. Seneca says: Oh, ye miserable mortals! The frailties of your nature are little thought of and when it is, it is in such a way it is to little purpose. I suppose to think of it to purpose we must be like minded with the prophet David when he petitioned the Lord to teach him to know his end and the number of his days, that he might know how frail he was. And again he says: Teach me so to number my days that I may apply my heart to wisdom.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 90:12</note> This would indeed be to purpose and not otherwise.</p>
<p>Samuel Fothergill speaks of a way of living to the best and wisest and happiest of purpose, without which he says people had better never have lived. And those who do live to the best of purposes obtain the hope of the righteous. As the Scripture says, the righteous hath hope in his death<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 14:32</note> and he says without this blessed hope we are of all living creatures and of all the animal creation the most miserable. For whilst man in this imperfect state of being is confined, How many pains invade his outward frame, how many sorrows vex his mind!</p>
<p>Seneca further says: Oh, ye miserable mortals, how many sorrows and afflictions do you endure which might be easily avoided by daily attending to that preserving Christian principle without which we are like sheep on the mountains in the wilderness with out a shepherd,<note resp="transcr">Mark 6:34</note> amongst briers and thorns and voracious devouring beasts, the spirits of people like wolves, bears, lions, and tigers, etc., etc. As George Fox says, when the Lord first sent him forth to labor in his vineyard to awaken a drowsy world it was like to a wilderness, and no right way found out of it. And the spirits of many were like wolves, bears, lions, and tigers, ready to destroy him and all the lambs and sheep of Christ. And will not like causes produce like effects? Are we coming up out of the wilderness, like the true church formerly and like our worthy progenitors, or are we going back into the wilderness, trampling on the testimony they so deeply suffered for?</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-27"><dateline><date when="1820-12-27">27 of the Twelfth Month.</date></dateline><p> I received a letter from my son Joseph giving an account of a gentleman from Baltimore came with his overseer to take one of his slaves about ten miles from his house at night. The slave shot his master dead and beat the overseer so that he died in a few days, for which he is now in heavy chains in Winchester [West Chester]  gaol. What dismal work amongst men, which true religion, if rightly adhered to, would easily prevent, as Seneca says.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1820-12-31"><dateline><date when="1820-12-31">31.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. I had to think of Job Scott, who say some meetings were open but not much satisfaction, and of David. I think he says he hideth himself and I am troubled [Psalm 30:7]. Peace is his to give or withhold. In the evening we dropt into silence had good satisfaction. So ended the year 1820.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_19"/>
{1821-01}
<div type="entry" when="1821-01-04"><dateline><date when="1821-01-04">4th of the First Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> Very cold, dry, hard freezing weather. Was our Monthly Meeting, the first in this year, and an open, lively time it was to my right, good satisfaction. Myself, H. Haines, Joseph Justice, and several others had a pretty deal to say, and I thought we were not destitute of life and savor attending in the afternoon. Many pertinent remarks were made tending to stir up to faithfulness. But alas what room and need there is of improvement in weightiness and solidity and wisdom.</p>
<p>A few days ago, an Indian near Haddonfield agreed with a black man to let him make baskets in his house. After some time, one evening, got some rum or whiskey and drinked too much. And as he slept by the fire they were very much afraid to leave him alone, but did put up the fire and went to bed. And in the night they heard him hallow and ran to him, and his clothes was all on fire. They tore them off, but he was badly burnt, but yet went again after more rum because the man had emptied his jug. The weather being very cold and he, exposing himself, got cold and died presently. Can they be clear that sell it to such poor creatures from the woe to them that put the battle to their neighbor.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-01-11"><dateline><date when="1821-01-11">11.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting – a very stormy, snowy day. At our meeting, Benjamin Lippincott and Martha Collins were married. Waters seemed very low, as they mostly do forepart, but I thought growed better and ended very well.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-01-13"><dateline><date when="1821-01-13">13.</date></dateline><p> Very cold, snowy winter weather. I can do little but sit by the stove and read and write, yet more favored with health than I was 6, 7, or 8 years ago. See [William] Sewel's <emph rend="italic">History</emph>, page 634, the words of Anna Maria Shurman mourning because of the deadness and formality of the vulgar Christians and said within herself: “O the pride, the lusts, the vain pleasures in which Christians live! Can this be the way to Heaven? Is this the way to glory, are these the followers of Christ? O No! O God, where is thy little flock, where is thy little family that will live entirely to thee? Make me one of that number!” See here true vital religion is one and the same in all ages and nations the world over: A life of true humility, self denial, and of the cross.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-01-14"><dateline><date when="1821-01-14">14.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Not too much satisfaction; very cold weather.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-01-18"><dateline><date when="1821-01-18">18.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. Very cold, but I did get to meeting, and a right, lively, satisfactory one it was to me. How easy our circumstances are! Heard of the death of Samuel Haines of Ancocas, my old acquaintance. A few years younger than I, and he was here to see me a few months ago. An innocent, industrious man. What a little time it is since we were boys.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_20"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-01-23"><dateline><date when="1821-01-23">23 of the First Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> We have had a long spell of very freezing cold weather, and much snow. We hear they drive over the river on the ice with wagons loaded with cord wood. Now more made [indecipherable]. I am now very poorly with my old asthma cough; have been out at meetings [in] this cold weather more than I was able to bear. <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> and Enoch Roberts, his companion, just sat of a few days ago on a visit to some meetings on the eastern shore of Maryland, and Ebenezer Roberts and Thomas Lippincott just about to start in a visit to some meetings in Pennsylvania. May they be preserved.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-01-25"><dateline><date when="1821-01-25">25.</date></dateline><p> Weather changes, more severe cold. What a pinching, suffering time it must be with very many poor, both white and black, who have very open, poor, cold houses and very scant of firewood and very scant of victuals and very scant of clothing or bedding. I think it must be a very suffering time with many in our parts, and it seems likely more so further north, where the snows are far greater and the weather colder. What a pinching time it must [be] also to the beasts of the field and wilderness and fowls of the air. But alas, how do they now drive and [indecipherable] and fly about in their sleighs in idle, unprofitable visits, unthoughtful and unconcerned how swiftly time passes away. And some hints I hear of some of whom better things are looked for are driving about from tavern to tavern and are not grieved for the affliction of Joseph.<note resp="transcr">Amos 6:6</note> I have read accounts of some of the great ones of the earth who would have [a] human skull placed on their table at their greatest feast and idolatry to keep them in remembrance of their frailty and mortality; I have wished they had one fixed on the head of every sleigh at these times when it is to be feared their mortality is least thought of or latter end least considered, although it is evident divers have shortened their days in their sleighing frolics.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-01-25"><dateline><date when="1821-01-25">25.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. I have had a very poorly spell several days and nights with my old asthma racking cough and not able to go out. We seldom see more cold, freezing weather when it is so still and clear.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-01-28"><dateline><date when="1821-01-28">28.</date></dateline><p> About this time I went to our meeting. Very cold weather. I was taken very ill with an exceeding hard cough and fever. Sent for the doctor, I was soon reduced to the greatest state of weakness I ever remember. But I was very much favored every way, both in body and mind; I never before experienced every thing removed but tranquility of mind, humility and tenderness – even like the state of a child and that spirit which breathes peace on earth and goodwill to all. And as to my poor body, I thought my nearest connections, friends, and neighbors were like the Good Samaritan we read of, who found a man half dead and took care of him and ministered to his necessities.<note resp="transcr">Luke 10:30-34</note> So they did for me day and night to uttermost.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_21"/>
{1821-04}
<div type="entry" when="1821-04-09"><dateline><date when="1821-04-09">9th of Fourth Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> I have been confined to the house and mostly to my bedroom about ten weeks past, and have been but little out of the house. Yet although I have been favored with a good appetite, I have recovered very slow and am but feeble and tottering. Yet when I was very weak and low and all thought I must go. Many kind friends came to see me and tried to comfort and encourage me, but I was afraid my spiritual state was not so good as they seemed to think it was. For one said he had not the least doubt but all would be well if I went now, another said – to encourage me when at the worst – if thee goes now the will leave a good savor; thee has done a great deal of good in the world. Another said they had no doubt but my sufferings were nearly over, both here and forever.</p>
<p>But all this will not do at such a time as this. At last as M. Haines said nothing but the Lord, nothing but [indecipherable] the Lord will do. Now although my mind was preserved pretty calm and tranquil, I wanted to feel more of the Divine Master's sweet air that John Churchman speak of at last, and of that animating, strengthening power that Joseph White mentions at last. Oh, the wisdom there is in choosing the Lord for our portion and making him our friend who is the physician of value, who can make all our bed in our sickness and strengthen us upon the bed of languishing. Who can enable one to say although I walk through the valley of the shadow of death yet will I fear no evil.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 23:4</note> Who said to Jacob, fear not: though thou passeth through the fire, it shall not kindle upon thee; or through the waters, they shall not overwhelm thee.<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 43:2</note> Who preserved Daniel in the lion's den and Shadreck [Shadrach], Masheck [Meshach], and Abednego in the midst of the fiery furnace, so that a hair of their heads were not singed nor the smell of fire upon their garments.<note resp="transcr">Daniel 3:27</note> See 11th of Hebrews, that little book of martyrs: through faith they were favored with that [which] could stop the mouths of lions and quench the violence of fire. Out of weakness were made strong, etc..<note resp="transcr">Hebrew 11:33-34</note></p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_22"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-04-10"><dateline><date when="1821-04-10">10th of the Fourth, 1821.</date></dateline><p> Weather holds very cold, very little grows or vegetation in the earth. I believe, the coldest, most backward spring I ever seen. Although I am favored with a very good appetite, I remain feeble and tottering and tender about the cold.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-04-15"><dateline><date when="1821-04-15">15.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At 3rd hour went to the burial of Phoebe Roberts, wife of John Roberts. She has been 15 years or more crippled and confined with the rheumatism; an innocent woman, and bore her great afflictions with great patience. This the 2nd time I have attempted to go out; once went to see this neighbor a few days before she died.</p>
<p>This the week of our Yearly Meeting, but I am not able to tend it. This week there was a very cold storm of rain and snow till it covered the ground and froze, so that ischickles [icicles] hung to the eaves of the house all next day. In all my late spell of sickness, I have not had any bad cold till now. I have a very heavy cold, and I observe some, at this time, of the most healthy have very bad colds.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-04-26"><dateline><date when="1821-04-26">26 of the Fourth Month.</date></dateline><p> I did get to our preparative meeting, the first time since I was sick and brought so weak and low. Elizabeth Balderston was there, and I thought something savory, sweet, and satisfactory attended to the whole. Although it is clear, dry weather, the air holds cold, and I am so weak and feeble I am hardly able to go out.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-04-29"><dateline><date when="1821-04-29">29.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. If it is too much to say it was a memorable meeting, I think I may say it has been pleasant to remember it – and that is no small favor.</p></div>
{1821-05}
<div type="entry" when="1821-05-03"><dateline><date when="1821-05-03">3 of the Fifth Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting, which I thought ended with a good degree of life and savor. A warm spell and thunder showers, but soon grows cold. We have had a very cold, backward spring. People [had] abundance of cyder [cider] to make last fall, and it made many late putting in their grain, and the winter [was] very hard. The winter grain – rye and wheat – look in many places very, very poor indeed.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_23"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-05-10"><dateline><date when="1821-05-10">10 of the Fifth Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> At our Monthly Meeting, which for the most part I thought was pretty well, yet one matter was unpleasantly exercising to me. Yet for the most part , was agreeable to look at.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-05-13"><dateline><date when="1821-05-13">13.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Very wet morning. I so unwell, I concluded I could not go to meeting. But our children concluded to go to Evesham, and I, having to been there a great while, I concluded to go with them, thinking it was better to wear away than rust away. And I had no cause to repent being there and I have some reason to believe nobody else had [either]; all well.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-05-17"><dateline><date when="1821-05-17">17.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Some savor and life, I thought.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-05-20"><dateline><date when="1821-05-20">20.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Our children went with me to Westfield meeting to a good degree of satisfaction. Dined with my old friends Thomas and Lydia Lippincott. My strength was very much exhausted at night. </p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-05-24"><dateline><date when="1821-05-24">Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> A very stormy cold rain; I did not venture out.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-05-28"><dateline><date when="1821-05-28">28.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Some savor, life, and ownings of truth, I hope. John Bilangee buried at our graveyard; died very suddenly. They say he was choked to death as he was eating his supper and thought he was a hard drinker.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-05-29"><dateline><date when="1821-05-29">29</date></dateline><p> at our select meeting. Not very satisfactory to me, though perhaps profitable. I think no condemnation.</p></div>
{1821-06}
<div type="entry" when="1821-06-03"><dateline><date when="1821-06-03">First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting poorly. I felt the effects of old and age, and understood the language of declining life. Although I had many thoughts suitable to the time and place, I had not much satisfaction. Others took the whole time, almost.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-06-07"><dateline><date when="1821-06-07">7 of the Sixth Month.</date></dateline><p> At our Monthly Meeting. I think a pretty good one, not without some misses. As <persName key="w6b38kp0">Thomas Ross</persName> used to say, the hardest thing ever he found in his life was when he was right to keep so. Oh, how prone we are to frailties and weaknesses as a [continued after inserted pages below]
<pb n="A0011237_24"/>
<floatingtext>Here I turned over two leaves, so I fill up this with some words of Thomas à Kempis. See page 223: Instead of being present at my devotions where I stand or kneel, I am carried to various places, just as my roving thoughts have led me. Where my thoughts are, there I properly am; and my thoughts are chiefly with that which I most love. (Those objects too soon recur which corrupt nature or sinful habit have made delightfull.) Upon this ground it is that thou hast declared expressly that where the treasure is, there will the heart be also.<note resp="transcr">Matthew 6:21</note> And accordingly, I find in the various resolutions of my changeable heart that when I love heaven, I take pleasure in meditating on Heavenly enjoyments. When I love the world, I think on its advantages with delight and with sorrow on its troubles. When I love the flesh, my imagination wanders through its various pleasures. When I love the spirit, my faculties are with Holy joy devoted to spiritual exercises. Whatever I chiefly love, of that I delight chiefly to hear and speak and I carry home with me the diversified images it, even to my most secret retirement.</p>
<p>It is said the Waldenses used to say that whatever people loved best, that was their god, that they delight to think and meditate upon. When I have sat in our meetings and seen signs, tokens, and indications of a wandering mind, I have often thought of a piece of an old Scotch song I have heard – My heart is in Highlands, my heart is not here; my heart is in the Highlands a-chasing of the deer; chasing of the buck and hunting of the doe. My heart is in the Highlands whilst the body is at meeting. No one can serve two masters; ye cannot serve God and Mammon.<note resp="transcr">Matthew 6:24</note>
<pb n="A0011237_25"/>
I have lately had put into my hands a book giving an account of the sect called the Shaking Quakers, and it is vastly different from the account of our first Friends coming forth. Be ye not deceived was the caution formerly. It is greatly to be feared that many, very many, are greatly deceived; they think they have attained to the greatest state of Christian perfection of any people ever have done, although they [indecipherable]. They sometimes dance naked, men and women together, and sometimes are constrained, they say, to bark like a dog and make a noise like a cat. Miracles, they say, are not ceased among them, but many great miracles are done among them. Many strange imaginations they take it to be greatly feared for revelations. Some we read of who boasted they were the children of Abraham, but were told they were of their father the Devil. So we may see how possible it is for people to be greatly deceived in their spiritual or religious state, although exceedingly] confident that they are right. They forbid marriage amongst them, or men and women lying or sleeping together, or even touching one another, and find Scripture for all this grievous sorrowful work. In many instances where families have been broken up by men or women joining their society and parting when they have had families of young children – sorrowful to relate.
[Out of order] 1st of the Seventh Month, 1821. I have lately read William Law's Address to the Clergy. A close, searching, scraping, sound piece of work. It appears to be very different from the Shakers' doctrine.
</floatingtext>
<pb n="A0011237_26"/>
[continued from several pages earlier] As a remarkable instance of human frailties, see the 23rd of the 2nd of Samuel, the last words of David 2nd. He says the Spirit of the Lord spake by me, and his word was in my tongue.<note resp="transcr">2 Samuel 23:2</note> Yet see the very next chapter, how grievously he missed his way in numbering the people, and what a dreadful calamity it brought upon him and his people. See 24, chapter 15 verse: there died with the pestilence seventy thousand men. What an awful, humbling lesson to the greatest and best of men – how unable, when they are right and highly favored of the Lord, to keep so. See how quickly and grievously David fell after being so highly favored of the Lord. And hath not this been the case with very many, since, as Isidore used to say, he that grows better, let him beware lest he grow proud and vain glory give him a greater overthrow than his former vices. For pride is as apt to grow upon our virtues as upon our vices, and pride goes before a fall,<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 16:18</note> but humility before honor. We plainly see these sayings verified in very many instances. [End out of order]</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-06-10"><dateline><date when="1821-06-10">10 of the Sixth Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting, First Day. Came off pretty well without condemnation, but great room and great need of improvement. Blots, spots, and stains with the pollutions of the world – like poor David the prophet, and much worse perhaps than he or Solomon ever was.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-06-12"><dateline><date when="1821-06-12">12 of the Sixth Month.</date></dateline><p> My dear old friend William Jackson of London Grove, Pennsylvania, and his companion John Phillips, came to see me. W. J. has always seemed to shew me respect and give me the right hand of fellowship, and I think he is one of the clearest, most unblemished character that I know of anywhere, and an able minister
<pb n="A0011237_27"/>
minister. [He] has visited England.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-06-13"><dateline><date when="1821-06-13">13 of the 6[th month], 1821.</date></dateline><p> At our select quarterly meeting at Evesham the Yearly Meeting's Committee divers of them there: Jesse Kersey, Samuel Beddle, William Jackson, Jonathan Evans, and John Comly. I thought forepart was a very dull time, but divers had lively, extensive service at last.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-06-14"><dateline><date when="1821-06-14">14</date></dateline><p> was quarterly meeting. A very full, crowded meeting. Jesse Kersey was large, lively, powerful and pertinent, and <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> and others at last favored once more to come off with satisfaction, although had met with some wounding cross occurrences. Poor creatures, we are, as <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says, always in danger of shot, like soldiers in battle. I daily see the need there is of watchfulness and prayer for preservation, and that continually. See the left hand, the words of David: he says the spirit of the Lord speaks by me, and his word was in my tongue.<note resp="transcr">2 Samuel 23:2</note> Yet see the very next chapter, what grievous affliction he brought on himself and upon his people. No wonder he cries out: Restore me to the joy of thy salvation and uphold me by thy free spirit.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 51:12</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-06-17"><dateline><date when="1821-06-17">17.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting to good satisfaction. There was sweetness and feeling nearness at parting, although pretty clost plain dealing.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-06-24"><dateline><date when="1821-06-24">24 of the Sixth Month.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our [indecipherable] meeting. Sarah Pope of Springfield was there, and had acceptable service. And Joshua Thompson, a young man – a schoolmaster from New York, has just now requested a right amongst us who appeared hopeful Fifth Day last. All as well as is common with us, but much dullness and drowsiness prevails, very much [in] this hot weather especially.</p></div>
{1821-07}
<div type="entry" when="1821-07-01"><dateline><date when="1821-07-01">1st of the Seventh Month.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Very low and poor forepart, but grows better and ended savory at last. Sarah Smith of Philadelphia had acceptable service.
<pb n="A0011237_28"/>
See William Law's <emph rend="italic">Address to the Clergy</emph>, page 31: Time and the things of time will soon have an end and the thought in time trusts to anything but the spirit and power of God working in his heart will be ill fit to enter into eternity. God must be all, in all, in us here or we cannot be his hereafter. Time works only for eternity, and poverty eternal must as certainly follow him who dies only fully stuffed with human learning as he who dies only full of worldly riches. The folly of thinking to have any divine learning but that which the Holy Ghost teaches, or to make ourselves rich towards God by heaps of commonplace learning crowded into our minds, will leave us as dreadfully cheated as that rich builder of barns in the gospel, to whom it was said: thou fool, this night shall thy soul be required of thee, and then whose shall all these things be which thou hast provided.<note resp="transcr">Luke 12:19-21</note> So is every man that treasures up religious learning that comes not wholly from the spirit of God.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-07-06"><dateline><date when="1821-07-06">6 of the Seventh Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting, and a lively, good meeting it was or else most of us were much mistaken. As James Simpson once said, here is a lively zeal amongst you, the mount of a king, the sword of the Lord and of Gideon.<note resp="transcr">Judges 7:18</note> Yet great room and need of improvement in depth of wisdom, solidity, and weightiness.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-07-08"><dateline><date when="1821-07-08">8.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Joseph Eastburn of Philadelphia, it is said he is not a member of any society, preached half an hour and some think he spoke very well. However, I thought the meeting ended pretty well.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_29"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-07-10"><dateline><date when="1821-07-10">10 of the Seventh Month.</date></dateline><p> A fine shower. Height of harvest here-a-way. The winter was very hard, the spring very cold and backward. Many was very late sowing in the fall, and the winter grain looked very poor in the spring. But there came a showery wet time, and it got up beyond all expectation and there appeared a fine prospect of a good harvest, but they say it is very light grained. There has been a kind of rust blast or mildew in some places, so that some fields where there was plenty of straw they say it is so blasted that it will hardly pay for reaping. And in some places, they say a kind of a little insect eats of the roots of young Indian corn, and has quite spoiled it in some places. How many ways there are for the fruits of the field and the labors of the husband man to be laid waste! As we read, it is said in Scripture: ten acres of vineyard shall yield but one bath, and the seed of an omer shall yield but an ephah.<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 5:10</note> Or, he can open the windows and heaven and pour down blessings until there is hardly room to contain them.<note resp="transcr">Malachi 3:10</note></p>
<p>See <emph rend="italic">Christian Magazine</emph>, page 454: surely if there be any thing that dignifies the man, it is the homage he pays to God. And if there be anything that debases us, it is the total want of a taste for spiritual and holy things. This is evidently demonstrated in the example of many being raised from a very low estate to sit among the heads of the tribes and princes of the people. And, on the other hand, how many have fallen into a poor, low, degraded state who once lived in a very reputable way? So true it is, [that] righteousness exalts a nation or an individual but sin a shame to any people. Do page 462: Nothing sets a person so much out of the Devil's reach as humility; and what does pride do?
<pb n="A0011237_30"/>
If nothing sets a person so much out of the Devil's reach as humility, then is there any thing that sets a person in Devil's reach and power as pride does? Humility goes before honor, but pride goes before destruction and a haughty spirit before a fall.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 16:18</note> This has been often verified – not only in many individuals, but whole nations. Again, page 470: shall the angels of God witness that we prefer the empty toys to the pearl of infinite, inestimable, unchangeable volume? Empty toys indeed to the riches and earthly treasure appear to be hardly a name little enough to call them by at last when they must be parted with. For one might as well try to comfort a dying person with mountains of sand as with houses full of gold, when all the things of this world must sink into an equal nothingness forever.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-07-15"><dateline><date when="1821-07-15">15 of the Seventh Month, First Day.</date></dateline><p> Clear, dry weather. The very great scarcity of birds makes me think of Jeremiah's words: the birds of the Heavens are fled.<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 4:25</note> Some sorts used to din one's ears with their noises; now scarcely one to be seen – and of some sorts, none now to be seen. I have seen upwards of eighty years, and never till this ever seen a summer but what the chimney swallows lived with us and built in our chimneys. I know not who can tell the cause why it is so. One of our largest fields, and in more early days, great flocks of turkeys, pheasants, and partridges – but no such things are to be seen in these days. <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> tells of turkeys in his days weighing forty pounds and upwards, and mentions the vast quantity of ducks in the Delaware, and other fowls and the great variety and plenty of fish with which Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob would be well content, say W. Penn.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_31"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-07-15"><dateline><date when="1821-07-15">15 of the Seventh Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting, many very drowsy. Harvest time, people work hard and, as <persName key="w6b38kp0">Thomas Ross</persName> says, when they come to sit down nature calls for rest, and are overcome with sleepiness. Although they can resist that sleep-spirit in going to market, as soon as seated in meeting, [they fall] asleep. Yet I hope there was at last some savor of life.</p>
<p>Heaven must be preferred before earth and all its enjoyments if we would be real Christians.</p>
<p>If religion be worth anything, it is worth everything. Though it is certain that true repentance is never too late, it is as certain that late repentance is seldom true.</p>
<p>Men may command thee but God may condemn thee.</p>
<p>When God punishes another, he threatens thee; when he wounds another, he warns thee.</p>
<p>If you mind nothing but the body, you lose body and soul too; If you mind nothing but earth, you lose earth and Heaven too.</p>
<p>It signifies nothing to say we will not change our religion if our religion change not us.</p>
<p>If you forget God when you are young, God may forget you when you are old.</p>
<p>Two duties must run through a Christian's life, like the warp through the woof – blessing and trusting.</p>
<p><emph rend="italic">Christian Magazine</emph>, page 16: Azariah said, the Lord is with you whilst you be with him. If ye seek him, he will be found of you; but if you forsake him, he will forsake you.<note resp="transcr">2 Chronicles 15:2</note> And as David told his son Solomon, if thou forsaketh him he will cast thee off forever<note resp="transcr">1 Chronicles 28:9</note> – a state not in the power of imagination to conceive the dreadfulness of it, says Addison. As one
<pb n="A0011237_32"/>
As one says, I have now lost what words cannot compensate: My God has withdrawn from me. His presence, oh no more.</p>
<p>Let me review and examine the direful cause of this. Wither, O my beloved, art thou gone? It needs no diligent search to find out the cause of thine absence. Well do I remember – ah awful season, [I] grew lukewarm and careless! I slighted the mercies of God and trifled with my privileges. Well, he is gone. Unhappy soul, whither shall I fly? Shall I ascend up into Heaven? He is there in his glory. Shall descend in Hell? He is there in his terrors. Shall I take the wings of the morning and dwell in the uttermost parts of the earth? There also his hand would find me. Whither then shall I go? From his presence I cannot fly. Poor man has no hiding place but in the munition of rocks. Arise, o God, for my help, nor suffer me never to rest contented without thy presence, in which David says is fullness of joy and his kindness better than life [Psalm 63:3], the loss of which the whole world cannot compensate. As <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says, thy life is upon it, thy soul is at stake. If thou neglects or abuses thyself in it, the whole world will not be price enough to ransom thee or countervail the loss. It is but once to be done.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-07-19"><dateline><date when="1821-07-19">19 of the Seventh Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting small, and a precious, owning time to me it was. I both feel and see what an excellent thing it would be to live without a will of our own, but alas, how unable we are of ourselves when we are right to keep so. Although David could say the spirit of the Lord spake by me and his word was in my tongue [2 Samuel 23:2], yet the very next chapter he charges himself with great folly and wickedness, which brought great destruction on them – seventy thousand died in 3 days of the pestilence, upwards of 23 thousand died in a day with the pestilence.<note resp="transcr">2 Samuel 24:15</note>
[marginal note] II of Samuel 23 chapter.</p>
<pb n="A0011237_33"/>
<p>Would not true humility have prevented this destruction if, like Mordecai after he had be in clothed with the king's apparel and sat upon the king's horse, he returned humbly and sat at the king's gate?<note resp="transcr">Esther 6:11-12</note> And do we not read so of Daniel, after he had been distinguished by favored of the Lord, [he] went and sat at the king's gate.<note resp="transcr">Daniel 2:49</note> What instructing lessons to keep humble after times of favor!</p>
<p>But my weakness has been such that I have been hard beset to keep from being proud after times of favor – elevated, tickled, pleased – which has brought sufferings on me many times, and made me visit to be trusted with much. For the times of favor have been the very cause of the fall of such weaklings as Isidore. Used to say he that grown better, let him beware lest he grow proud and vain glory give him a greater overthrow than his former vices. For pride is apt to grow up on our virtues as upon our vices.</p>
<p>See <emph rend="italic">Christian Magazine</emph>, page 239: he loves Christ not at all that loves him not above all. If religion be worth anything, it is worth everything. How many thousand of the martyrs and primitive Christians and our first Friends have chosen rather to suffer, to die the most cruel deaths – burned at the stake, hanged on the gallows, starved in dungeons and prisons, and banishment – rather than part with their religion. Whilst unknown numbers in prosperity are preferring the transitory treasures of this world and, like Esau, selling their birthright for a mess of pottage<note resp="transcr">Genesis 25:30-33</note> and then too late sought it with tears, but found it not.</p>
<pb n="A0011237_34"/>
<p>See <emph rend="italic">Christian Magazine</emph>, page 325: Christ is not prized at all unless he is prized above all. If we wish to grow in grace, it must be by the sincere milk of the word. Those who bring nothing but expect all things are the most welcome to come to Christ. The greatest and hardest work of a Christian is least in sight, which is the well doing of his heart. I never knew an eminent saint but he had either singular afflictions or singular corruptions to wrestle with. If I win Christ, I am rich towards God; if I am found in Christ, I am safe; if I know him, I am wise to salvation. Let the bitterness of sin make grace sweet and the sweetness of grace make sin bitter.</p>
<p>Seven arguments for contentment: (1) we have more than we deserve (2) we have more that we ever well improved (3) we have more than many of God's dear children (4) we have more of this world than the Lord Jesus Christ had (5) we have more than we brought into the world and more than we can carry out (6) we have as much as infinite wisdom thinks best for us (7) if we have Christ and grace, we have what is better than all the world.</p>
<p>It is better to beg one's bread with Lazarus on earth than to beg one's water with divers in hell. Paul counted all but dross and dung that he might win Christ [Philippians 3:8]. If we win Christ, we have all we need. If we loose Christ, we lose all. If the Lord gives himself, can they be poor – though stript of all, as Job was – who obtain his favor? But are they not poor creatures, although they may have goods laid up in store for many years? Without his favor, we are poor creatures; with it, we are rich. [He] takes what he will away.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_35"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-07-22"><dateline><date when="1821-07-22">22nd of the Seventh Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> First Day. I with my daughter Abigail went to Cropwell, in company with Joseph Cowperthwaite and Charles Stow, an elder of Philadelphia. Religion seems at a low ebb there. meeting small and but little life stirring, which makes hard work getting along. But through mercy, it seemed to end well. Few, if any, exceed them in temporal affairs, although so dull and poor in spiritual labor.</p>
<p>We went to John Haines's to dine, who has a large family of children, sons and daughters grown up; and we had a sitting with them – I hope and believe for the better. But oh, the rawness of the young generation! Their [they're] giving way to a conformity, to the fashion and conformity to the world, threatens us with desolation. Yea, and desolation has overtaken very many – not only individuals, but whole meetings. How destitute are many of the life and vital part of true religion. Let the harp hang on the willows.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 137:2</note></p>
<p>See William Law's <emph rend="italic">Address to the Clergy</emph>, page 121: that which cannot help us to all goodness, cannot help us to any goodness; nor can that take away any sin but that which can take away all sin. But many say there can be no such thing as living in this world without sin.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1821-07-26"><dateline><date when="1821-07-26">Fifth Day, 26 of the Seventh Month.</date></dateline><p> At our preparative meeting. Through mercy there was something of a feeling uniting, nearness and savory sweetness at parting. It is not always so far from it, so naked and poor we can hardly speak to one another.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011237_36"/>
<div type="entry" when="1821-07-29"><dateline><date when="1821-07-29">29 of the Seventh Month, 1821.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting very dull and drowsy. Weather very dry and very hot. I was afraid we should be completely overwhelmed with a drowsy spirit. People work hard and nature calls for rest when they sit down, as <persName key="w6b38kp0">Thomas Ross</persName> used to say.</p></div>
{1821-08}
<div type="entry" when="1821-08-02"><dateline><date when="1821-08-02">2nd of the Eighth Month, Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting very dull and heavy. Weather very dry and hot here. It seems like a threatening, awful time here, although there has been rain on each side and all around us. It is a pinching time of drought and threatens the cutting of the Indian corn and buckwheat in our parts. We read the Lord caused it to rain upon one city and not upon another city.<note resp="transcr">Amos 4:7</note></p>
<p>See <emph rend="italic">Christian Magazine</emph>, page 239: He loves Christ not at all who loves him not above all. They are justly punished that abuse lawful things, but they are most justly punished that use unlawful things. Thus Lucifer fell from Heaven, thus Adam lost his paradise. The life of man is the middle between angels and beasts. If man takes pleasure in carnal things, he is compared to beasts; but if he delight in spiritual things, he is suited with angels. How are some ever brothers of one family raised up and some degraded and cast down below the beasts, wallowing in their pollutions and drunkenness. Many shorten their days. What was that which Moses told the Children of Israel was not a vain thing: it is your life and by it ye shall prolong your days. If religion is worth any thing, it is worth all things. If it can bring us any goodness, it can bring all goodness we stand in need of, so is the one thing needful. But see Romans 1st and 31: without understanding covenant breakers, without natural affections, implacable and unmerciful. See what a miserable degraded state it is possible for mankind to fall into.</p>
<p>As you love your souls, beware of the world – it hath slain its thousands and tens of thousands. What ruined Lot's wife? The world. What ruined Judas? The world. What ruined Simon Magus? The world. What ruined Demas? The world. And what shall it profit a man if he gain the whole world and lose his own soul?<note resp="transcr">Mark 8:36</note> If nature is indulged, grace, as to sense of it, takes its flight. Is not nature greatly indulged in these days? How gloomy the prospects.</p></div>
</body></text>
</TEI>