<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader></teiHeader>
<text>
<pb n="A0011534_001"/>
<front><div><p>
<l>Benjamin Hunt</l>
<l>No. 9</l>
<l>12 of 6th [month] 1822</l>
<l>1822 - 1823</l>
</p></div></front>
<body>
<pb n="A0011534_002"/>
{1822-06}
<div type="entry" when="1822-06-12"><dateline><date when="1822-06-12">12 of the Sixth Month, 1822;</date></dateline><p> My daughter Abigail and I went to select quarterly meeting at Evesham and a poor, dull time it was. Weather very warm and we seemed to be overwhelmed with a lethargic stupor far from experiencing anything like sitting together in heavenly places or experiencing the powerful overshadowing of the Holy Ghost among us. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> and divers others able ministers but chiefly shut up or nothing said so as to raise the life in the meeting.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-06-13"><dateline><date when="1822-06-13">13</date></dateline><p> was quarterly and very large; the house well filled and an appearance like a wealthy nation in carriages and costly array. I know not any people that can and do make such a show. We read he gave them their heart's desire but sent leanness into their souls.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 106:15</note> and leanness poverty, death and barrenness did abound. Simon Gillum said considerable but in a complaining way. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> quite shut up. We had the extracts read from the Yearly Meeting and the report of the Yearly Meeting committee both plentifully complaining of the weak, poor, low state of religion in many places. There were a number of ministers from different quarters and at last, divers lively, savory sentences dropped and I had some share amongst them to right good satisfaction and I thought it ended with a degree of the ownings of truth and savor of life – our worthy progenitors say Barclay and Penn: I think to this effects that churches nor assemblies councils nor synods can do nothing only whilst and when they keep under the guidance and influence of the right spirit: is there not great room to fear very many are sat down at the halfway house and taken up their residence at the town of morality quite contented with a life of morality without aiming to get to the city of the saints solemnity and heaven to themselves cisterns that can hold no water<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 2:13</note>: and worship the works of their own hands that which their own fingers have made<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 2:8</note> A very dull drowsy time with many.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-06-14"><dateline><date when="1822-06-14">14.</date></dateline><p> Deborah Howland from Oblong appointed a meeting at Moorestown. I was almost worn down two meetings two days past I thought I would omit going but our children seemed to wish to attend the meeting and I went with them forepart was some satisfactory but it did not end fully so to me I fear there was too much said by some and to me it did not end with that sweetness, nearness, and clothing [closing?] I could wish. The gardens and fields begin to be pinched with dry weather.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_003"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-06-16"><dateline><date when="1822-06-16">16 of the Sixth Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting and quite silent as there is five of us who frequently have something to say it is but seldom we have quite a silent meeting and I have been very jealous too seldom. There are two sorts of meetings and two sorts of silent meetings. One sort is the best of all sorts as Stephen Crisp says to have communion with God is something beyond all declarations or words in which there is no need of words. Repeatedly have I endeavored to point out this best of all sorts of meetings, but the will of the creature and his contrivance will not do neither in silence nor speaking; but acceptable worship is performed in true resignation and obedience as William Dewberry says it is in the will and contrivance of man all the mischief is hatched and as the prophet said they hatch cockatrice eggs and weave the spider's web he that eateth their eggs dieth that which is crushed breaks out into a viper and as we read so they lap it up.<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 59:5</note> George Dillwyn says the good condition of the sheep praises the pasture more than words can do. David says he leadeth me by the still waters and into green pastures.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 23:2</note> But oh what is our condition and the state of religion amongst us: oh my leanness my leanness was the language of one of old and how many may adopt it in these days notwithstanding so much labor line upon line and precept upon precept not only here a little and there a little.<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 28:10</note> but here a great deal and there a great deal which we acknowledge to be very good. But alas, what hath it done for us is there any growth in vital religion among us so that I have thought of the lamentation over Jerusalem oh Jerusalem Jerusalem how often would I have gathered thee as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings but ye would not<note resp="transcr">Luke 13:34</note> and of the woe pronounced against Chorazin: woe unto the Chorazin woe unto the Bethsaida if the great and mighty works which have been done in the had been done in Tyre and Sidon they would have repented long ago in sackcloth and ashes<note resp="transcr">Matthew 11:21</note> Some of our foremost I find are jealous that things will not always go on so but a time of trial an awakening, trying time will be permitted when poor, dry form only will not do any longer: labor not for the bread that perisheth but for that bread that nourisheth the soul up unto eternal life<note resp="transcr">John 6:27</note> and again take no thought wherewithal shall be clothed<note resp="transcr">Matthew 6:31</note>: But I thought if there was no more thought for the body than there is for the soul what would be our condition.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_004"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-06-20"><dateline><date when="1822-06-20">20 of the Sixth [Month], 1822.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting very small and forepart very trying to stand against an indolent trifling spirit. Although I had wearied myself too much before meeting I was favored to get over a spirit of heaviness and it ended to a good degree of satisfaction. preparative meeting.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-06-23"><dateline><date when="1822-06-23">23.</date></dateline><p> First Day. I was reading John Woolman's <emph rend="italic">Works</emph>, see page 405. John Gratton in his journal, page 45, said the Lord is my portion I shall not want, he hath wrought all my works in me I am nothing but what I am in him. Next is an account of Gilbert Latey oh what a blessed state and glorious attainments did these servants of the Lord through the depths of self denial attain to – oh what poor dwarfs are we compared with them. But see the works of John Hoyland on the prophecies. See what misery ruin and destruction many nations, countries and cities brought on themselves for want of keeping humble and giving way to pride as Samuel Fothergill says pride has been the downfall of the greatest cities, empires and kingdoms that ever were erected in the world one reformation after another hath it destroyed: How many besides the city of Sodom, Tyre and Sidon do the Scriptures give accounts of land in utter ruins and desolation. See Hoyland's 2 volume, page 97, they shall destroy the wall of Tyrus and break down her towers such hath been the fate of this once the most famous city in the world for trade and commerce on which this observation may be made: neither kingdoms nor commonwealths, neither public companies nor private persons can long carry on a beneficial flourishing trade without virtue and what virtue teacheth: sobriety, industry, frugality, modesty honesty, punctuality, humanity, charity, the love of our country and the fear of God – But see 1st volume, page 97, the blessed state of the righteous. No evil shall befall those who make the Lord their refuge and the most high their habitation. Neither shall any plague come nigh their habitation or dwelling: They need not fear the wreck of nature nor the crush of worlds: so it seem to read Job 5 and 15 verse and of Daniel and Shadreck, Mescheck and Abednego.<note resp="transcr">Daniel 3 and 6</note> Went to our meeting. Sarah Cresson was there and preached till about 1 o'clock in a very sweet manner. Sung many to sleep as one prophesied there should be powerful preacher and dull hearers. Good sermons should be as music to a sleepy man and so it seems to be no tenderness, no contrition, no tears, but far from that dullness and drowsiness covered many: as if they was hearing a pleasant song of a pleasant voice.</p>
<pb n="A0011534_005"/>
<p>This 23 of the Sixth Month. After meeting Sarah Cresson and her brother Samuel and his wife and Samuel Church and wife and David Roberts and his wife, she is my brother Joshua's daughter, came to see us although I am so poorly today that I can hardly keep up or enjoy my friends' company. After tea we dropped into silence as Clarkson says our first Friends often did inadvertently when no one proposed it. So it was with us and Sarah did preach most sweetly a considerable time: since she has been restored from that most deplorable state of despondency. She is much more large and clear in her testimony than ever: restore me to the joy of thy salvation and uphold me by thy free spirit said David<note resp="transcr">Psalm 51:12</note> she behaves most beautifully now: no behavior like that truth teaches I hope it was better than spending our time in talking and walking after things that do not profit<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 2:8</note> which do not afford comfort, peace, and hope to reflect upon.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-06-26"><dateline><date when="1822-06-26">Third Day morning.</date></dateline><p> See Hoyland's 2 volume, page 379 no system of government however excellent in its fabric can possess any great measure of duration without that powerful cement, virtue, in the manners and principles of the people – the love of our country and the desire for its rational liberty are noble, virtuous feelings: but there is not any term which has been more prostituted than the word liberty. This day I went to my son John's to get my wagon mended and this passage accompanied my mind sweetly see Ecclesiastes 9 chapter and 7 verse: go thy way eat thy bread with joy and drink thy wine with a merry heart for God now accepteth thy works one would wonder all the world do not hunger and thirst after righteousness – seeing there are so many precious blessings and promises recorded in Scripture for them: from the utmost parts of the earth have we heard songs even glory to the righteous they can say mercy and truth have met together righteousness and peace have kissed each other: truth is sprung out of the earth and righteousness looks down from Heaven,<note resp="transcr">Psalm 85:10-11</note> bread shall be given them their waters shall be sure<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 33:16</note> the Lord is my portion I shall not want said John Gratton he hath wrought all my works in me<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 26:12</note> I am nothing but what I am in him again. It is said the angel of the Lord encampeth round about the righteous, and saveth them.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 34:7</note> but Paul tells how it fared with the wicked there and twenty thousand fall in one day<note resp="transcr">1 Corinthians 10:8</note> and it is said the angel of the Lord is one night slew one hundred and four score and five thousand in one night for their wickedness<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 37:36</note></p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_006"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-06-27"><dateline><date when="1822-06-27">Fourth Day morning.</date></dateline><p> Very like for rain.</p>
<p>As I remarked before, 23 of the Sixth Month, First Day, Sarah Cresson was at our meeting and had a great deal to say I thought the states of the people or many of them was opened to my view but no time nor opening to mention it yet it illustrated and spread until it was an instructing lesson on to me: it appeared that many were like Martha who Christ said was careful about many things and too few like minded with Mary who had chosen the good part that should never be taken from her,<note resp="transcr">Luke 10:41-2</note>; and some were like Achan and Gehazi<note resp="transcr">2 Kings 1:20-27</note> coveting the golden wedge and the Babylonish garment<note resp="transcr">Joshua 7:21</note>; and many were like Demas who had embraced this present world<note resp="transcr">2 Timothy 4:10</note> which is enmity with true religion. Some had made gold their hope and the fine gold their confidence; many had placed their affliction on things below and not on things above and direful has been the consequence of desires misplaced and like causes will always produce like effects. Many things indeed we poor mortals are very careful and busy about whilst the one thing needful is neglected, not considering how soon these many things which assume a mighty great importance and demand all our attention – may and must soon leave us or we must leave them as we see many do in the midst of their carrier as the man we read of whose ground brought forth plentifully and he concluded he had goods laid up in store for many years but it was said to him thou fool this night shall thy soul be required of thee and then whose shall these things be which thou hast provided. And so shall it be with all those who lay up treasures for themselves and are not rich towards God.<note resp="transcr">Luke 12:19-21</note> and again it is said as a partridge sitteth on eggs and hatcheth them not so he that getteth riches and not by right shall leave them in the midst of his days and in the end become a fool<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 17:11</note> and so I have seen it to be in many instances and how very different has their latter end been from those who like Mary who had chosen the good part that should never be taken from her<note resp="transcr">Luke 10:42</note> or like David who so earnestly desired to be led in the way everlasting<note resp="transcr">Psalm 139:24</note> As I have heard from some who had embraced this present world and set their minds on things below, one said if I had my time to live over again it should not be as it has been; another said I have been careful to pay everyone his due and I have frequented religious meetings but as to the great business the great work of my souls salvation, I have never done so much as move the least grain of sand; another said at last now I must go and oh that I might go in peace; and many more like these who were counted good moralists but had been careful about many things and neglected the lone thing needful, seeking acceptance with their Maker.</p>
<pb n="A0011534_011"/>
<p>Seeking acceptance with our Maker is not that the one thing needful above all others and the only way that is lasting as David calls it the way everlasting, but for want of such in after this one thing needful this way everlasting and choosing the good part as Mary did. Oh to see and think what a most miserable, unhappy like very many live wearying out their days with sorrow, misery, and affliction; but oh the blessed and happy state of those who seek after the one thing needful acceptance with their Maker: see Ecclesiastes 9 and 7 go thy way eat thy bread with joy and drink thy wine with a merry heart for God now accepth thy works. Here indeed is experienced that saying that prosperity is redoubled to a good man for what joys or pleasures, riches, or treasure (of this world) can equal a secret sense of acceptance with God who alone could say and can say neither grace nor glory nor any good thing shall be withheld from them that seek first the Kingdom of God and the righteousness thereof (the one thing the most needful) all things needful shall be added. Job says when the ear heard me then it blessed me and when the eye saw me it gave witness to me because I deliver the poor that cried and him that had none to help him: the blessing of him that was ready to perish came upon one and I caused the widow's heart to sing for joy I was eyes to the blind and feet to the lame I was a father to the poor and the cause which I knew not I searched out: they will<note resp="transcr">Job 29:11-16</note> – the righteous flourish like a tree planted by the rivers of water. And is not this the way everlasting the way to live to purpose to the greatest and most noble and most glorious of purposes without which to what purpose do we live.</p>
<p>To man in a savage, uncultivated state the earth is an abode of desolation where shelter is insufficient and even food precarious see Hoyland's first volume page 46, see the sentence above bountiful as is the hand of providence his gifts are not so bestowed as to seduce us into idleness but are calculated to rouse exertion.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_008"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-06-30"><dateline><date when="1822-06-30">3[0] of the Sixth [Month], 1822.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. I sat off early and went to see Job Cole's wife in a very weak, low, poor state of health; seems almost worn away to skin and bone although she has been a very fat corpulent body. She is so weak she cannot bear but little company. Then I went to Haddonfield to see my old acquaintance Kester Laning a poor old widow who has been blind near twenty years now almost worn away, aged 83; they expressed gladness in the visit. Then I went to Haddonfield meeting which was but small and a zeal for religion very low, yet it was through unmerited mercy the most open, owning time I ever had there till near one o' clock and when we came out we were favored with that precious cement: openness, sweetness, kindness, and feeling nearness, hearty, inviting, kindness all new after meeting. I went to see another poor, ancient widow almost worn away to skin and bone; both these last upwards of eighty and one maintained by our meeting. Last Fifth Day I went to see Joseph Cowperthwaite near 30 years of age he has been in a wasting, declining state of health his several years but now reduced to almost skin and bone I got well home but was very much wearied when I got from Haddonfield.</p>
<p>I read the news but little and really I am afraid of them [i.e., newspapers]: they come to the house as raping papers. I picked up one the other day I think it is said 36 died in one week with the consumption in the City of New York and also in Philadelphia many die with it.</p></div>
{1822-07}
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-02"><dateline><date when="1822-07-02">Third Day morning</date></dateline><p> I was reading in <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn's</persName>'s <emph rend="italic">Select Works</emph>  but it is so big and heavy we very seldom take it up, see page 463: Oh the lowness and meanness of those spirits that despise or neglect the joys and glories of immortality for the sake of the things that are seen; that are but temporal debasing the nobility of their souls abandoning the government of the Divine spirit and embracing with all ardency of affection the sensual pleasures of this life but such as persevere therein, shall not enter into God's rest forever: how many millions there are as <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says who have set their hearts and affections on things below how many could I mention who whilst they lived were careful about many things; wrenching both brains and back scuffling scrambling early and late who have been snatched away in the midst of their days, and some who lived to old age and devoted health and strength time and talents to accumulate wealth, which I see has made wings for their offspring and some of them have scattered their estates faster than their fathers and grandfather ever gathered it. Miserable folly indeed to devote all their time strength and talents: in providing for the body which is but of a few days and full of trouble and to neglect that of laying up treasures for eternity seriously to think of it what weakness and folly appears.</p>
<p>[marginal note] 14 of the Second Month. Elizabeth Coal was buried; she has been wasting by degrees some months.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_009"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-03"><dateline><date when="1822-07-03">3rd of the Seventh Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> A fine, soaking rain it has been several weeks very pinching, dry weather here away there has been very often great signs of rain and went off with very little till now this is the height of harvest and as far as I can learn a very good harvest in general although the winter was a very hard one both for winter grain and meadows hard frost and little snow: grass is said to be generally very light and like to be very scarce Indian corn looks very promising seldom if ever more so.</p>
<p>This 3rd of the Seventh Month. We were invited to the burial of Hannah Yarnall, <persName key="w6wx87x7">my wife's</persName> sister Elizabeth's daughter about 58 she has seen a great deal of trouble buried two husbands; and her father-in-law, James Thorington. She and her mother used to live with us when she was a little girl. She attained to the station of a reputable, acceptable minister and traveled considerable abroad and in particular that of visiting families. She has been but weakly and suffered much of latter time with the gavel but it is said her last disorder was something like the dysentery. We were not able to attend the burial.</p>
<p>I have often thought what very desirable things wisdom and riches are amongst men: that there are according to Scripture two sorts of wisdom and two sorts of riches: the wisdom that is from above is said to be pure, peaceable, and gentle and easy to be entreated and devilish.<note resp="transcr">James 3:15-17</note> – one sort of riches is called in Scripture the true riches, durable riches, etc.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 8:18</note> But Solomon says there is that maketh himself rich yet hath nothing there is that maketh himself poor yet hath great riches.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 13:7</note> Is it wisdom in men of understanding to set their hearts and minds and affections on things below taking more cost and pains to lay up treasures on earth which can be enjoyed for a very little while: than Heavenly treasures would cost them as <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says, Oh, the baseness and meanness of those spirits, spirits that despises or neglect the joys and glories of immortality for the things that are seen, which are but temporal, debasing the nobility of their souls, abandoning the government of this Divine Spirit, and embracing with all ardency the sensual pleasures of this life but such as persevere therein shall never enter into God's rest. Was he, who we read of, who concluded he had goods laid up in store for many years a wise man no he was called a fool and it was said to him this nigh shall thy soul be required of thee and then whose shall those things be which thou hast provided.<note resp="transcr">Luke 12:19-21</note></p>
<p>[marginal note] It makes me think how religion is treated by us like.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Clouds without rain, only wind.</p>
<pb n="A0011534_010"/>
<p>I was once with a sick man near the solemn close and he was counted a wise man and his language was oh this world, this world, it is the merest cheat and how many millions have been undone and cheated by it since the days of Balaam who it is said loved the wags of unrighteousness.<note resp="transcr">2 Peter 2:15</note> and like Achan and Gehazi<note resp="transcr">2 Kings 1:20-27</note> who coveted the golden wedg and Babylonish garment<note resp="transcr">Joshua 7:21</note> and like Demas who abandoned the Lord's cause and the government of the Divine spirit<note resp="transcr">2 Timothy 4:10</note> or like Judas who sold his master for 30 pieces of silver and was his own executioner for he went out and hanged himself<note resp="transcr">Matthew 27:5</note> It appeared to me this afternoon as a matter of wonder that so many thousands and millions of people should be so much like Martha of old careful about many things and so neglect the one thing needful the good part which Mary chose and Christ said should never be taken from her.<note resp="transcr">Luke 10:41-42</note>; especially when I consider how evidently it is demonstrated in numberless numbers of things and instances the wisdom there is above all things, to save up for ourselves treasures in Heaven, and on the other hand the unspeakable folly in neglecting it. To take this subject into serious consideration, the desire people have to obtain riches and wisdom would open a large field for consideration, meditation, and contemplation. But in short what a blessed thing it would be if all people would make choice of that riches which is durable and of that wisdom which is profitable to direct whereby the frowned and the disobedient are turned to the wisdom of the just: see Psalms 73, 22 verse: So foolish was I and ignorant I was as a beast; before thee some have compared the state of the worldly minded man to the state of Nebuchadnezzar at grass when a beast's heart was given him<note resp="transcr">Daniel 4:33</note>; be ye not like the horse or as the mule that hath no understanding said David<note resp="transcr">Psalm 32:9</note>; no sight or sense taste nor feeling or desires after Heavenly treasures oh earth earth hear oh earth etc<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 22:29</note> Nothing like the state and disposition David felt when he said as the heart panteth after the water brooks so doth my soul after thee O Lord.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 42:1</note> etc.; and again he says let my right hand forget her cunning and my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth and if I prefer not Jerusalem to my chiefest joys<note resp="transcr">Psalm 137:5-6</note>; and again see the command from highest authority if thy right hand offend thee cut it off or if thy right eye offend thee pluck it out<note resp="transcr">Matthew 5:29-30</note>; is not the state of those who have set their affections on things below very different from this; did Moses make a foolish choice when he refused the riches and honors of Pharaoh's court and chose rather to suffer affliction with the people of God than to enjoy the pleasures of sin for a season: a short season<note resp="transcr">Hebrews 11:25-26</note></p>
<pb n="A0011534_011"/>
<p>See [Lindley Murray's] <emph rend="italic">Power of Religion on the Mind</emph> by John Gough, page 70: the continual troubles and discomposures, sickness and calamities that attend our lives, the shortness and continued vexations occurring in them, and finally the common examples of death and mortality of all ages and sexes and conditions of mankind are sufficient instruction to convince reasonable men who have the seriousness and patience to consider and observe that we have no abiding city here and on the other side. If we will but give ourselves leisure to consider the great wisdom of almighty God who orders everything in the world to ends suitable and proportionable, the excellency of the soul and mind of man, the great advances and improvements his nature is capable of, the admirable means which the merciful wise God hath afforded mankind by his works of nature and providence by his word and instruments to qualify him for a nobler life than this world below can yield. We shall readily confess that there is another state, another city to come: which it becomes every good and wise and considerate man to look after and fit himself for and yet if we look up on the generosity of mankind with a due consideration they will appear to be like a company of distempered people; the greatest part of them make it their whole business to provide for a rest and happiness in this world. They make these vain of acquests wealth and honor, the preferments of this world their great if not their only business and happiness: and which is yet a higher degree of frenzy; they esteem this the only wisdom and judge the careful provision for eternity the folly of a few weak, melancholy, fanciful men. Where was it is a truth and in due time it will evidently appear that those men who are most solicitous for the attaining of their everlasting rest are the only truly wise men and so shall be acknowledged by those that now despise them – we fools counted his life madness and his end to be without honor how is he numbered among the children of God and his lot among the saints.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-04"><dateline><date when="1822-07-04">4th of the Seventh Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> At our Monthly Meeting and I think it was a – Pretty good one Joseph Foulk of Gwynned was there and had acceptable service in the afternoon there were some close, pertinent, lively – remarks and sentences to my satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-05"><dateline><date when="1822-07-05">5.</date></dateline><p> Joseph Foulk and wife come to see us and we went with them to Evesham Monthly Meeting, which was small in midst of harvest. The persecutors of our first Friends used to say they would keep up their meetings if their corn dropped in the ground; they esteemed the Lord's favor more than their necessary food but such a demonstration of zeal was wanting here yet some room for labor to satisfaction. Some of their elders said they hardly knowed a more lively time but I thought things was low.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Words of Matthew Hale.</p>
<p>[marginal note] We spent the afternoon at Hinchman Haines with Joseph Foulk and wife, not so well as I could wish but that is nothing new.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_012"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-06"><dateline><date when="1822-07-06">6th of the Seventh Month.</date></dateline><p> Was Seventh Day evening see Hoyland's 1st volume, page 237. Joseph became an illustrious example of a mind unsubdued by deepest distress, uncorrupted by the highest degree of elevation (how many thousands have fallen under such proving trials). His afflictions commenced at an early period of life; it was in its kind peculiarly better and severe; it came from a quarter which was the least to be apprehended and the transition was instantaneous: from a tranquility that knew no bounds, to anguish which no language can express, no imagination can conceive. Do we not read that it is through tribulation we must enter the kingdom if ever.<note resp="transcr">Acts 14:22</note> and again these are they that have come through great tribulation and worked their robes and made them white in the blood of the lamb<note resp="transcr">Revelation 7:14</note> What I would chiefly remark upon all this is our precarious standing as on a sea of glass mingled with fur and the great need there is of our having the favor of that all powerful being who only can preserve through all the greatest snares and dangers as in the case of Noah, Jonah, Joseph, and Jacob; Lot and Job, Daniel, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego and all the rest of the faithful servants of the Lord. How sudden indeed are the transitions, many times from the greatest riches to the greatest poverty, degradation and contempt as in the case of Haman and many others; and [no] language can express, no imagination can conceive and from a state of perfect health to a languishing bed and to the grave but see 1 volume of Hoyland's words page 97, no evil shall befall them that make the Lord their refuge and the most high their habitation – they need not fear the wreck of nature nor the crush of worlds; see what was said to Job Chapter 5 and from 15 verse to the end and of Daniel, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego and of the deliverance of all the rest. He stopped the mouths of lions quenched the violence of fire out of weakness they were made strong and put the armies of the aliens to flight<note resp="transcr">Hebrews 11:34</note> triumphed over all their enemies and had the victory over death, hell, and the grave; so says Seneca that if the earth should open her mouth and show a righteous man all the secrets of the infernal pit he would look down upon it without dismay, so it appears to read the accounts of the martyrs and Mary Dyer who could rejoice in the most dismal prospects of misery and sufferings through that Almighty power that caused Paul and Silas to sing in prison and their feet fast in the stocks<note resp="transcr">Acts 16:25</note>; like Habakkuk although the fields should yield no meat yet will I rejoice in the Lord and joy in the God of my salvation<note resp="transcr">Habakkuk 3:17</note> midst of harvest.</p>
<p>[marginal note] At destruction and famine thou hast laughed<note resp="transcr">Job 5:22</note></p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_013"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-07"><dateline><date when="1822-07-07">7th of the Seventh Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> First Day wet weather at our meeting. Thomas Kite of Philadelphia was there a considerable, smart, lively minister but all was silent; until it was time to break up I said a little and have no cause to repent it; and Thomas at last said something about the dullness and drowsiness that prevailed and also E. Roberts. It was as a poor, dull, shut up, time, midst of harvest. Weather very warm; people work hard, weary in the heat, and when they come and sit down still, nature calls for rest and. Ross observed yet at last I thought there was some savory concern appeared.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-09"><dateline><date when="1822-07-09">Third Day.</date></dateline><p> See George Dillwyn's <emph rend="italic">Youth's Instructor</emph>, page 105, To stand approved in the sight of omniscience, is the only desire which is not delusive: and it is comfortable to believe that of this desire, and consequently its entire satisfaction, every accountable being is as capable, as he is conscious of his existence and want of happiness; and as this desire to stand approved is the most important, supreme, interesting desire that ever did on will or possibly can engage the mind of mankind. Is it not strange that more people do not study to shew themselves approved in the sight of God like one formerly who said I will not give sleep to mine eyes nor slumber to mine eyelids until I find a place for the God of Jacob<note resp="transcr">Psalm 132:4</note> to dwell in seeing our state is so very precarious and unsafe and we such miserable creatures without the Lord's favor.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-10"><dateline><date when="1822-07-10">Fourth Day.</date></dateline><p> See Samuel Bownas's <emph rend="italic">Advice to Ministers and Elders</emph> page 102, he says the education, though with the strictest care and tenderness administered, will not answer what some expect from it. As to the grounding of youth in true religion and saving faith: for nothing short of the work of grace in the heart, the new birth, and the washing of regeneration by the word can make a sound right Christian and a true minister. Tertullian used to say if people depart from the discipline of the cross they cease among us to be called Christian but if that was our rule how many would it divest of that noble title in our days, how many millions are great stranger to this sort of talk about the work of grace or the new birth who concludes: they are very good Christians without understanding
<pb n="A0011534_014"/>
understanding  anything about such talk as that as one observes if they can but live on prosperity and be kept clear of gross enormities they sit down at ease and conclude all is safe and well. But oh that they may find out their mistake before it is too late, says that worthy minister Sarah Morris, what unspeakable numbers are quite contented and wholly at ease and quiet with a life of mere morality without ever so much as wishing or desiring to be acquainted with the inward life the hidden life the life of God in the soul of man, or even so much as seeing or thinking it necessary. Yet how many of these who have obtained a character amongst men and made it their chief concern to accumulate wealth and lay up treasures on earth and could say at last when they were just about to launch into the unknown regions of eternity, they had goods laid up in store for many years yet like the foolish virgins no oil in their lamps.<note resp="transcr">Matthew 25:1-3</note> And this was the language of one who bore the character of a moral honest man and no one could say anything against him, only he was too greedy after the world and his last words were oh darkness darkness darkness and so died away another very innocent, hard working, worldly-minded, money-getting man. At last said now I must go and oh that I might go in peace and they have preserved the words of another moral man in good credit amongst his neighbors but had not been enough – concerned shew himself approved in the sight of God then thousands of worlds would not tempt me to live in the world as I have done again another as I have heard ten thousands of worlds would I now give if it was in my power for peace with the Lord. Blessed is the man whose delight is in the law of the Lord and in his law delights to meditate both day and night; he shall be as a tree planted by the rivers of water that bringeth forth his fruit in his season and his leaf shall not wither [Psalm 1:1-3]. Without something of this sort one counted it a mere animal life and indeed is it not that only which distinguishes a man from a beast, beasts have no capacity gifts nor abilities to commune with their Maker, but there is a spirit in man and it is the inspiration of the almighty that giveth them an understanding and is the superior gift ever bestowed on mankind and to have communion with God, the superior excellency of the Christian religion, but how many there are that have no ears to hear such talk until they find they must leave this world.</p>
<p>[marginal note] But how different is the death of the righteous: all light all like all joy and all peace.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_015"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-11"><dateline><date when="1822-07-11">11th of the Seventh Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting which was very small midst of harvest. The persecutors said of our first Friends that they would keep up their meetings if their corn dropped in the ground, but we do not manifest such a preference to truth's cause now in these days. It was not only small but very poor, dull, and drowsy waters too low to attempt to go a step. We have many things that call for our care and attention for both soul and body the call of the Lord is gone forth as in days of old after divers ways and divers manners but it appears the world's calls outbids all, but how will that do when every source and prop of earthly comfort fails, which they surely will sooner or later. And we see they often do in many instances all round us daily, see James 4 and 4 the friendship of this world is enmity to God. Not all the persecutors and open apostates that ever rose up against us ever has done us that hurt as prosperity has done said one of our worthy progenitors; another in my hearing said that the unlawful love of lawful things was the greatest snare ever the Devil had to catch Quakers. As <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> expresses it a more subtle crafty snare the crafty Devil never had to catch people than the allurements of this world so earthly mindedness brings darkness, feebleness, weakness so many meetings have grown weakly and sickly and so have dwindled, withered, and died away and their meetings have dropped and their meeting houses left desolate, a habitation for the little owls, the moles and the bats, as I have seen to be the case with us after all the labor bestowed upon us; the Lord is with you whilst you be with him if ye seek him he will be found of you but if ye forsake him he will forsake you said Azariah.<note resp="transcr">2 Chronicles 15:2</note> They that pursue lying vanities forsake their own mercies.<note resp="transcr">Jonah 2:8</note> Will not all prove at last lying vanities but the one thing needful, all find out what that is at last; without that all cry vanity. They that cast off the thing that is good, the enemy shall pursue them, will they not have to adopt this language woe is me that I dwell in Meshach and sojourn in the tents of Kedar<note resp="transcr">Psalm 120:5</note>: arise depart hence for this is not the place of true rest it is polluted<note resp="transcr">Micah 2:10</note> and so many find it too late a fine soaking rain.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_016"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-14"><dateline><date when="1822-07-14">14 of the Seventh Month.</date></dateline><p> First Day. I heard lately of the death of William Blake: a worthy minister my old acquaintance and fellow traveler about 1814. He and Oliver Paxton, an elder in good esteem, and I went to visit the people at Stroudsburg about  miles up Delaware. Oliver has been dead several years and a very good memorial since printed concerning him. I think Oliver and William Blake were both some little younger than me.</p>
<p>[marginal note] How sorrowful many have no concern about preparing for the other world until they find they can stay no longer in this as <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> observes.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-14"><dateline><date when="1822-07-14">14th of the Seventh Month 22 First Day.</date></dateline><p> My children went with me to Cropwell meeting which was small, poor, and low. George Dillywn, see page 26, <emph rend="italic">Youth's Instructor</emph>, where vice rules, virtue is in disgrace and how is it where the world rules. The apostle James says 4 and 4 the friendship of the world is enmity to God: such farms and fields of corn anywhere are hardly to be found as there is about Cropwell ye are the Lord's husbandry no growth in religion poor, dry formality yet as in Sardis there are a few names who have not defiled their garments [Revelation 3:4] not bowed the knee to ball: I had a pretty open time amongst them but some of them can hardly bear anything said against great Diaura although there appeared to be something owning there was not that sweet cement as at some times the unlawful love of lawful things Thomas Ross said was the greatest snare ever the devil had to catch Quakers the lovers of the world are not drunkards but which of the two has been the greatest enemy and hindrance to religion the great works of the Reformation – <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> and Peter Charron both mention Cyrus (whom the Lord calls his shepherd) they say Cyrus would not suffer his people to remove from their poor, barren soil to a country more rich and fertile for fear they should be corrupted by luxury and ease as the people of Sodom were charged with pride, fullness of bread, and abundance of idleness [Ezekiel 16:49]: Can we clear ourselves of abundance of spiritual idleness the primitive Christians used to say prosperity was a very intoxicating thing and few brains were strong enough to bear it and few since the days of Job and Abraham have ever bourn prosperity unhurt uncontaminated hence the caution of worldly wealth beware a little is enough too much a snare so it has proved to many as the apostle observes drowned many in destruction and perdition.<note resp="transcr">1 Timothy 6:9</note>: man wants but little here nor wants that little long: oh earth earth hear oh earth<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 22:29</note> Samuel Fothergill says no state harder to reach than those whose minds are buried in the earth they have had line upon line, precept upon precept, and does it not seem as if it is like pouring water on a rock all runs of and makes no impression oh Jerusalem how often would I have gathered thee<note resp="transcr">Matthew 23:37</note> Remember the language to some of old: go to the gods whom ye have chosen let them deliver you if they can etc..<note resp="transcr">Judges 10:14</note>: be thou instructed oh Jerusalem lest I make thee desolate<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 6:8</note></p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_017"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-18"><dateline><date when="1822-07-18">18th of the Seventh Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting very small and very poor although I thought not so drowsy as some. I had a feeling a little like Robert Nezbet after he had been delivering some close doctrine said now I feel as If you could not hurt me and as Stephen Crisp says if I can but answer my own conscience I need fear no man yet no safety but in true humility as one says humility the spring of virtue is: Humble thyself and virtue thou cannot miss: We called to see Joseph Cowperthwaite in a deep decline, reduced to skin and bone almost. One handed me a newspaper giving an account of scarcity of bread that they believed some had starved to death for want of it they say there is accounts of their grievous distressed suffering in almost every paper and there is accounts of the great drought and failings of crops this harvest in New England Massachusetts and there away and also accounts of most dreadful wars, cruelty and barbarity in Smyrna. Oh how destitute of that all powerful preserving Christian principle are innumerable multitudes of dark heathen nations now groaning under gross darkness, idolatry and superstition and what is there that can preserve them from thus destroying, murdering and massacring one another as they do but obedience to that light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world. So see here the fruits and effects of the want of obedience. Famine, sword and pestilence sore judgments with which the people have been visited for their wickedness and disobedience in ages and nations past down to these days. Like cases produce like effects – it is a great mercy the Christian religion hath so far prevailed amongst us that we are preserved from such dreadful customs, superstition and idolatry, tumults, bustling outrageous massacring and murdering as we hear and read of amongst the heathen nations in many places where the Christian religion is but little professed and less practiced.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_018"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-20"><dateline><date when="1822-07-20">Seventh Day evening.</date></dateline><p> It is appointed for all men once to die but the time when the place where and the manner how is a secret many are drowned and we see some get burned to death very strangely indeed who to all appearance were as safe from danger as their neighbors or fellow creatures how many could I mention whose situation in life appeared as safe from danger as any: who have been some drowned and some burned to death. Divers of my neighbors and old schoolmates have starved to death as those believed who nursed them; some struck with the palsy and disabled from eating and some their mouths eaten away with cancers and numberless numbers of other ways there is but one way for people to come into world but very many ways for them to go out of it. From Scripture and other accounts how many thousand have fell by that word in one day how many thousands have perished by famine and the multitudes that have been swept away in a short time by the pestilence and the many thousands that have perished in a few minutes by earthquakes and Paul says three and twenty thousand fell in one day for their wickedness.<note resp="transcr">1 Corinthians 10:8</note> and again we read the angel of the Lord went out and slew in the Assyrian camp an hundred and four score and five thousand in one night<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 37:36</note> Happy for they who can say as one I have read of that he did not fear death in whatever way it might attack or approach him like Daniel, Shadreck, Masheck and Abeidnego and thousands of others of faithful martyrs and others of the faithful servants of the Lord as Hoyland's says they need not fear the crush of worlds and as Seneca says if the earth should open its mouth and there them all the secrets of the infernal pit they would look down upon it without dismay who would not deliver to the very uttermost as the Scriptures abundantly testify.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-21"><dateline><date when="1822-07-21">21.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting as to myself silent and I am not quite sure it was best it was so but it is best to miss it on that hand than be a babbler for Solomon says the serpent will bite and a babbler is no better.<note resp="transcr">Ecclesiastes 10:11</note> Said a good deal and I thought it end pretty well.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Several have been scalded to death in their distilling spirituous liquors. Two burnt to death dressing flax.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_019"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-23"><dateline><date when="1822-07-23">23rd Third Day.</date></dateline><p> See [Lindley Murray's] <emph rend="italic">English Reader</emph>, page 150, on the slavery of vice having no fund within himself whence to draw enjoyment his only recourse is in things without he partakes in all its vicissitudes and is moved and shaken by every wind of fortune this is to be in the strictest sense a slave to the world but shall I call that man free who has nothing of his own no property ensured: whose very heart is not his own: If the truth hath made the free then art thou free indeed so we read in Scripture: But believe it no chain bind so hard no fetters are so heavy as those which fasten the corrupted heart to this treacherous world no dependence is more contemptible than that under which vice promises as the recompense of setting us free from the salutary restraints of virtue: Blair</p>
<p>It is recorded in Scripture as the call of the Lord my son give me thy heart if the heart is for the Lord all is for him whither eating drinking marry or giving in marriage that if the heart is not for the Lord then there is nothing for him for what has man to give to the lord but his heart but oh how many are following after their lovers but can never overtake them their way being hedged up with thorns and their hearts sold to work wickedness: this was the query to some of old to which of my creditors have I sold you verily for your wickedness have ye sold yourselves<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 50:1</note> – thy lovers will despise thee they will seek thy life<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 4:30</note> is it not so said in Scripture: But that is the way of Satan first allure them with his temptations and then when he has ensnared them torment them when he has done: this is the reward of poor sinners who serve that hard master: see the words of John Hawksworth one noted for his great natural abilities. See [Lindley] Murray's <emph rend="italic">Sequel </emph>some account of him, page 272: sin hath no beginning but from pride nor fall but from humility: consider the different fruits and effects of both pride and humility: pride goes before destruction and a haughty spirit before a fall but humility goes before honor the one has plunged people into the most miserable and unhappy state and the other raised them to the most happy.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_020"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-24"><dateline><date when="1822-07-24">Fourth Day Morning.</date></dateline><p> See Paul's Epistle to the Colossians 1st and 12: give thanks unto the Father which hath made us meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the saints in light: who hath delivered us from the power of darkness and hath translated us into the Kingdom of his dear son what a blessed state and most glorious attainment: how very far from it are very many thousands and millions in different nations a young man a native of this place has just returned from sea and has been gone four or five years and has been to divers different nations Italy, Turkey, and divers others he tells me they are all together of the Papish religion and that he found savage like spirits and dispositions amongst them: and that of latter time most terrible sickness and great mortality prevails in various nations: in one nation a pestilential fever carries them off by hundreds many hundreds in a day and in other places a disorder something like the dysentery or flax purging and lax what the doctors call colery morbus sweeps them of in multitudes with very short illness. It is to be feared these multitudes of people never had very little if any opportunity of acquaintance with that religion that Paul speaks of that had brought him and them in his days to such a blessed and glorious safe and happy state what a lamentable pity it is that people who have the offer and means held out to their acceptance: of acquaintance with that religion which has been such a blessing to thousands and millions innumerable what a pity any should be so unwise like Esau of old not know how to set a price upon and so sell it for a morsel of meat<note resp="transcr">Genesis 25:32-34</note>: then at last seek it with tears too late to know the only true God and Jesus Christ whom thou hast sent is life eternal and again acquaint now thyself with him and beat peace but oh the estrangedness how little acquainted with that powerful influence of Heavenly goodness that supported and sustained and comforted the martyrs and our first Friends under all their great sufferings and trials.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-25"><dateline><date when="1822-07-25">25.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. A fine soaking rain last night a fine time for the Indian corn and buckwheat to grow: and a promising prospect.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-27"><dateline><date when="1822-07-27">27.</date></dateline><p> Seventh Day. Finished getting hay.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-28"><dateline><date when="1822-07-28">28.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting not so dull and heavy as some of late I went to see Joseph Cowperthwaite so weak and low he can hardly speak so as to be heard there was a number of neighbors there and we had a little meeting with him for the better I hope it is satisfactory to look over the day – rain again</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_021"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-29"><dateline><date when="1822-07-29">29th Seventh Month, Second Day morning.</date></dateline><p> I have seen dreadful accounts of sorrows on the seas of late as well as on land a vessel filed out on a whaling voyage from Nantucket after good success when they had procured 700 barrels of oil were afterwards shipwrecked by a mighty great whale running against their vessel with such force it caused it to let in the water so that as many as could get into their boats were in them exposed to the open sea until they were famished to death after casting lots and eating one another. Dismal is the account of their sufferings and perishing with hunger full as much so as their sufferings in Ireland of late: sorrows on land and sorrows on the seas what poor frail creatures we are. To what a state of sorrow and misery not only individuals but whole nations may suddenly be brought and after are what room is there for pride and yet how greatly does it abound what voyages they will make what journeys they will take for earthly treasures: and to accumulate wealth and lay up treasures on earth take more pains than heaven would cost them – </p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-11"><dateline><date when="1822-07-11">11 of the First Month, 1789.</date></dateline><p> I find a note in my memorandum back some Expressions of a minister preserved by John Rutty in his spiritual diary page 164, what a bigerly [niggardly?] contemptible thing would it be for any who through laziness or pride would not dig nor work for themselves – to be lounging about the doors of the rich and depend upon them for food if this be a pitiful and contemptible situation in a temporal relation see whether it be not that of several of yours in a spiritual: Even you who by your gesture manifest an uneasy expectation of being fed with words: whilst you will not beg of God himself as you ought to do with prostrated souls: I have thought none more idle and unconcerned about their souls than those who are most engaged in a care for the poor body: although the Scriptures say take no thought for that
<floatingtext>[marginal note] A vessel from New England filed out.</floatingtext>
<pb n="A0011534_022"/>
and as a worthy able minister says to dig too idle and to beg too proud<note resp="transcr">Luke 16:3</note>: yet under name of stewards feign would shroud: I once heard my cousin William Hunt that great minister once ask the people, children, says he, have you any bread? You look too idle to work for your living you look to me to be a lazy, idle pack and so it proved to be for their meeting was lost died away and come to perish. I heard that he once told the people that they knew now more about religion than his old horse. That their offerings stinked they were fit for nothing but the crows and the buzzards a lukewarm state is as loathsome as open profaneness be ye not like the horse or the mule that hath no understanding said David<note resp="transcr">Psalm 32:9</note> and again he says when the Lord restored again the captivity of Zion we were as those who dream<note resp="transcr">Psalm 126:1</note> and are not many in that dreaming state about religion: like the horse or the mule no concern about the great business of man's life which is to answer the end for which he was sent it is better to wear away than rust away: man's understanding dulled with idleness: contracts a rust which makes it daily less and less and to how many in our day may it be said ye are idle ye are idle<note resp="transcr">Exodus 5:17</note> although worn down with a care and toil for the poor moldering body: o Earth Earth hear o Earth<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 22:29</note> etc.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-07-23"><dateline><date when="1822-07-23">23.</date></dateline><p> Third Day I went to see Nehemiah Matlack far advanced in years 75 and very infirm many years past with the gravel and went to see Thomas Glover a young man very ill with a fever had lately hurt himself with strong drink: I am told there was house struck with thunder a few days ago in Philadelphia and shattered very much: and that there was two horses killed with the thunder near Cooper's Ferry. We have had but very little hard thunder here of late to what we used to have some summers years back. A man of Evesham just returned from a journey informs that in the western country Miommi [Miami?] there is a great drought very pinching, dry weather and that it is very likely.</p>
<p>Three or four and more died out of one house with the dysentery or flux it was said to be much in that country last year.</p>
<p>[marginal note] I am told the thunder melted the pewter in the house but nobody hurt.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_023"/>
{1822-08}
<div type="entry" when="1822-08-01"><dateline><date when="1822-08-01">1st of the Eighth Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> 5 Day. At our meeting small but not quite the poorest not so drowsy as in the midst of harvest and hay come off without condemnation if our hearts condemn us not then have we – confidence towards God.<note resp="transcr">1 John 3:21</note> said one of old time but alas when we are right how unable we are of ourselves to keep so what humility and watchfulness fear care and prayer: to keep so oh that thine hand might be with me and keep me from evil said good old Jabez<note resp="transcr">1 Chronicles 4:10</note></p>
<p>We have had a plentiful season here for grass and grain although in the forepart it looked discouraging Indian corn seldom ever looked more promising here away but both east and west in New England and Miami westward travelers say there is pinching, dry weather and we hear that in Ireland they are starving to death for want of bread what poor morals we are and to what a state of wretchedness and misery not only individuals but whole nations often times are soon brought.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-08-03"><dateline><date when="1822-08-03">Seventh Day.</date></dateline><p> I continue to hear of the distresses in Ireland it is said I suppose it is in the news that they are known to dig up their potatoes after they planted them they were so pinched with hunger and that they plucked the wheat before it was ripe and even gnawed the bark of trees: is there any room for pride at such a time as this world it not after many lofty looks if such a pinching time should overtake us.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-08-04"><dateline><date when="1822-08-04">4 of the Eighth Month, first Day.</date></dateline><p> As to myself silent Joseph Justice had a great deal to say and I hope it ended reputably looks very like for rain several days but all goes off.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-08-08"><dateline><date when="1822-08-08">8 of the Eighth Month.</date></dateline><p> At our Monthly Meeting. The quarterly meeting's committee appointed to attend the Monthly Meeting and to labor for a reformation against the many wrong things that generally prevail earthly mindedness, pride, and superfluity neglect of meetings to unnecessary use of strong drink, etc. Samuel Leeds of Egg Harbor was one of them and had very extensive, pertinent, savory, acceptable, lively service and there was a covering of solemnity savor of life and ownings of truth throughout a favored day Hinchman Haines and wife and Brother and Samuel Leeds paid me a visit and a remarkable one it was I had such an open time with his brother Rubin Haines I believe will not soon be forgotten he had been disowned and it was admirable how things and the way opened to impart to him such things as he stood in need of he is a smart sensible man and he took it all in good part and he and Samuel Leeds expressed good satisfaction with coming to see me which was on Fourth day last I counted it a favor for it is too rare or seldom our social visits is too much profit.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_024"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-08-09"><dateline><date when="1822-08-09">9.</date></dateline><p> We went to the burial of Joseph Cowperthwaite aged near 30 perhaps he has been wasting and wearing away this several years with a gradual decline of health or consumption he had appeared in the ministry several years savory and acceptable till towards his solemn close and there seemed room to think from some of his expression of the happiness he felt near the last beyond anything he had ever felt in his life that he made a happy change he had been out to neighboring meetings with me of latter time at the house the people were very orderly and silent none of that of talking and whispering together like they used to be at burials but oh, the poverty and leanness nothing to be seen nor felt of that quickening spirit that makes alive unto God there were several of our ministers there but all shut up. But at the close at the grave I had a pretty open, lively time to good satisfaction. Dry weather.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-08-11"><dateline><date when="1822-08-11">11.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Hannah brought some more religious tract from market some of them are most excellent it seems as if they would sow the world with them: Light is sown for the righteous and joy and gladness for the upright in heart<note resp="transcr">Psalm 97:11</note>: in one of these religious tracts is an account of the faith and constancy of the martyrs: Even that faith which – overcome the world as Daniel, Shadreck and Mesheck and Abednego did see some words of John Philpot's after exhorting his friends to keep the faith once delivered to the saints: he said to one the world wonders how we can be merry in such extreme misery but our God is omnipotent who turneth misery into felicity: believe me there is no such joy in the world as the people of Christ have under the cross I speak by experience therefore believe me and fear nothing the world can do unto you what greater joy can there be then to be in conformity to Christ: then I say what must their state be who are in conformity to the world contrary the express command be ye not conformed to this world<note resp="transcr">Romans 12:2</note> for the friendship of this world and a carnal mind are enmity to God<note resp="transcr">Romans 8:7</note> says the apostles: so Stephen Crisp says the world wondered our leaf did not wither under our great sufferings now to our [entry ends]</p>
<p>[marginal note] very dry weather.</p>
<pb n="A0011534_025"/>
<p>This 11th of the Eighth Month, 1822, at our meeting and a precious good one it was or else some of us were mistaken. Amos Peasly of Crosswicks and Hinchman Haines were there and an open owning savory time it seemed to be I had some share in the travel to good satisfaction there were some friends from different parts of Sadsbury near Susquehanna River and some from Gwynned and some and some from eastward towards Trentown [Trenton]. One of these strangers said it was comfortable being with us I fear we do not consider what a favor it is to have a free gospel ministry whilst very many are such vast expanse with their ministers Amos Peasly is an able worthy great minister our meeting ended sweet and savory what a blessed thing it is for them that can say with Caleb of old see Joshua 14 and 11th: I am this day four score and five years old said Caleb and as strong for war as ever see the promises to the righteous in old age they shall be fat and flourishing and their leaf shall not wither but shall still bring forth fruit in old age but alas how many wither and grow useless and worthless lean, poor, and withered dry and formal: these strangers inform us that sickness – abounds and great mortality in divers parts of Pennsylvania in Chester County and Bucks County in some places three and four die out of a house with the dysentery and complaint in the bowels – Collare Morbus and typhus fevers and they say that the news gives accounts of these disorders being very exceeding mortal in other distant nations: and that in divers places the drought is so piercing that their Indian corn is dried up and they have cut it up for fodder and lowed the ground and now the dry weather seems likely to cut of the buckwheat and potatoes and although our corn here away looked so promising the dry weather coming on will cut of thousands of bushels amongst us and they tell me that in Chester County the springs are so dried up that water is sold at West Chester for a 11 penny bit a barrel we read of water and wood being sold to the people in Scripture<note resp="transcr">Lamentations 5:4</note> but I do not remember of ever hearing of the like before in America this afternoon we spent with the widow Anne Cowperthwaite and large family and children 2 daughters from Pennsylvania being there we had a sitting with them I hope for the better I have been very intimate with the family from my childhood.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-08-15"><dateline><date when="1822-08-15">15.</date></dateline><p> Eighth Month. At our meeting. Rebekah Price, an ancient friend of Philadelphia, had acceptable service and<persName key="w6wx87x7">my wife</persName> thinks there was a better feeling than common though a small meeting.</p>
<p>[marginal note] a shower north of us but little here.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_026"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-08-18"><dateline><date when="1822-08-18">18th of the Eighth Month.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting all shut up but old Rebekah Price of Philadelphia I suppose it would be allowed that she did very well but alas I thought I seldom seen meeting more destitute of life or the owning of truth we attended very warm and so unwell I could hardly sit meeting.</p>
<p>Nathan Smith and wife and William Evans and his wife paid us a visit which I should hardly think worth noticing only that it was to satisfaction which social visits too seldom are for want of something that only can make any opportunities satisfactory. Nathan had a sitting with us and I hope for the better he has been much under the weather. Brought under great trouble by the bad conduct of his children but seems to not yet quite lost all his preaching when he gets up here amongst his old friends.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-08-22"><dateline><date when="1822-08-22">22.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day I went to Evesham meeting which was not very small Nathan Smith was there and I thought we had an open favored Lively time almost as ever: there seemed to be something of that precious cement openness sweetness and feeling nearness and brotherly kindness: at our son John's I found a newspaper which gave accounts of the most dreadful sufferings in Ireland for want of bread and also a mortal fever which they think is brought on them on account of being so grievously pinched with hunger and they say very many thousands are now in a most grievous suffering condition for want of food and no way to procure any for themselves but to depend on the charity and kindness of their fellow creatures it is said there is vast sums of money raised for their relief and great exertion yet very many most grievously suffer and that many die and perish with hunger they tell me that almost every newspaper gives some accounts of the sufferings in Ireland but I see but very few of them it seems as if it must be the most dreadful suffering time I ever heard of in my time.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-08-23"><dateline><date when="1822-08-23">23.</date></dateline><p> This afternoon I was reading <emph rend="italic">Piety Promoted</emph> by Thomas Wagstaff page 147, concerning Thomas Ross: Last words he was a native of Ireland but came into America when young and lived here until near his end then went to visit England, Ireland and Scotland and died there in Europe in his travels. See here some of his last words, Oh, the vileness of the land of Ireland surely if any nation ever had occasion to mourn because of oaths that has and now a most mournful miserable suffering time it is in that nation on account of scarcity of bread and fear obedience and care. Thomas Ross was a worthy acceptable minister. I have been in his company divers times and remember well his words he [entry ends]</p>
<p>[marginal note] meeting N: S: was quite unexpected.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_027"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-08-25"><dateline><date when="1822-08-25">25 of the Eighth Month, 1822, First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting which was large it is become a great practice with the people of the city to come up into the country at this season of the year and many were there some Presbyterians it is said might be distinguished by their dress and perhaps some of other sects and I did pity them for it was a very poor dull dry time forepart Nathan Smith after a while spoke largely and lively as ever he did I thought but it seemed to me to be such a low time that there seemed no ability to impart my thoughts nor a state fit to hear or receive. I did mention something of two sorts of religion, one of which will do very well in fair weather but will not do in a storm but it is evident there is a religion that can support and uphold in the greatest storms and times of trial against which the gates of Hell could never prevail and the time will overtake us when we shall stand in need of such a religion and none knows how soon and we may if we choose to take the council of the Divine Master be favored with such a religion that will do in a storm for he says whosoever heareth these sayings of min and doeth them I should be likened to a wise man that built his house upon a rock and when the storm beat upon it fell not because it was landed upon a rock but they that heard his saying and did them not should be likened to a foolish man that built his house upon the land and when the storm beat upon it it fell and great was the fall<note resp="transcr">Matthew 7:24-27</note> thereof from accounts we have no room to scruple it is a stormy time with many both by sea and land famine and pestilence has much prevailed in divers places very many thousand are pining away with hunger and are stricken through for want of the fruits of the field and had great need of such a religion as the prophet had when he said although the fields should yield no meat yet will I rejoice in the Lord and rejoice in the God of my salvation<note resp="transcr">Habakkuk 3:17</note> or such a religion as Job had see 5 of Job 18, 19, 20, 21, and 22 at destruction and famine those that laugh, etc., etc., but I was so poor I was ready to wish I had kept quite silent although I thought the meeting ended a little better but I thought it was a shame for us who make such a high profession to be so poor and destitute of a right clothing.</p>
<p>[marginal note] He, that is, Thomas Ross, once told me he believed I would be put upon business and spoke lovingly and encouraging divers times to me.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_028"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-08-29"><dateline><date when="1822-08-29">29 of the 8th Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting small and quite all shut up in silence of the poorest sort some of us thought we seldom ever seen a poorer meeting after such abundant labor from east and west, north and south and from beyond the seas.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-08-31"><dateline><date when="1822-08-31">31.</date></dateline><p> Was select meeting. Oh the want of life everhere and everywhere although from accounts we have no room to scruple. It is a trying time with many far and near. Sword, pestilence, and famine in divers places and very awful accounts near here of sudden deaths and strange disorders and divers in the midst of their days suddenly snatched away with very short sickness and some much out of their senses with such disorders that people were afraid was very infectious so that they were afraid to lay out the corpse or attend the burials of some it is said the Yellow Fever is very mortal in New York it is said that few if any recover that are taken with it and instances is reported where whole families are taken away but is difficult to know what to believe reports differ so much but there is room to fear there is too much truth in the reports.</p>
<p>See a little book called A Short and Easy Method of Prayer by Lady Guion, page 73: to serve God is to reign (then what is it to serve Satan) the end for which we were created is to enjoy God even in this life: yet alas this is the least in the thoughts of most men: so says Thomas Finch too few are under much concern and care about the souls yet Barclay says the service of Christ is perfect freed [freedom?] and [indecipherable] if so what is the service of Satan perfect bondage and slavery - page 47. Two sorts of persons are silent the one because they have nothing to say and the other because they have too much the case is the same in this degree of prayer we speak of: they are silent not for want but through fullness and excess.</p></div>
{1822-09}
<div type="entry" when="1822-09-01"><dateline><date when="1822-09-01">First Day: 1st of the Ninth Month.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting I believe there was some stirrings of life and evident tokens or marks of the work of a right spirit: I thought I was helped beyond all expectation to good satisfaction E.R. had a good deal to say and I thought it end reputably and savory.</p>
<p>[marginal note] This 29 lodged at D. Conrow's we went to see our grandchildren.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_029"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-09-05"><dateline><date when="1822-09-05">5 of the Ninth Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> At our Monthly Meeting Amos Hilburn of Berry was there his son passed meeting with one Smith – the meeting forepart much shut up the latter meeting middling not fully to my satisfaction though not much cause of complaint. Benajah Butcher's son of Mount Holly passed with A. Robert's daughter of William Roberts.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-09-08"><dateline><date when="1822-09-08">8 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting not the very poorest nor a very full tide as at some other times: fullness of bread and abundance of idleness: to dig too idle and to beg too proud yet under name of stewards feign would shroud<note resp="transcr">Luke 16:3</note>: a friend of Philadelphia tells me they hear it is a very awful time at New York the Yellow Fever is very much prevalent and mortal and we hear of a great deal of sickness all about our neighborhood and country fevers. Seven in one family the doctor says so ill they cannot sit up and twenty dangerously ill in a small distance. </p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-09-11"><dateline><date when="1822-09-11">11 of the Ninth Month.</date></dateline><p> A neighbor handed me a newspaper dated 3rd of this month. The calamities of the Irish have no way abated. Hundreds were dying daily of want and the hospitals were filled with the sick. July 8th: by the account received there is no alleviations of the diseases prevalent in Ireland the famine and fever prevails very greatly 155,000 persons were and are now receiving charitable relief: It appears that there are 3000 of the population of those parishes in great distress in consequence of want of money or means to procure subsistence a man and his wife they believe died of starvation and others must if relief and sustenance is not speedily procured for their relief that the fever is spreading to an alarming extent and those who are afflicted with the disease are in the most deplorable state of poverty. Two hundred thousand pounds sterling were voted in the House of Commons on the 23 of July for the relief of the dismissed in Ireland they say: The subscription at the London tavern for the relief of the poor in Ireland had reached the sum of near three hundred thousand pounds sterling: It is reported in the news that twenty thousand have left the City of New York on account of the prevalence of the Yellow Fever: and some say forty thousand there seems no room to scruple but the calamity is very great in New York and in Ireland both.</p>
<pb n="A0011534_030"/>
<p>See Lamentations 1 and 9: verse her filthiness is in her skirts she remembereth not her last end. Therefore she came down wonderfully she had no comforter. What a wonderful coming down there has been many and many a time amongst the people when according to Scripture accounts the judgments of the Lord have been sent upon them the sword the pestilence the famine and noisome beast storms of hail and great earthquakes wherein many thousands have perished in a few minutes and whole great cities sank. We hear of these sore judgments on the people of Ireland and New York and many other places but yet how little do we think what a coming down there would be amongst us if the Lord should turn his hand upon us and send some of these sore judgments amongst us how would our shining painted carriages, gilded harness shining like silver, and nice, matched, fine, fat horses looks when we were so starved and hungry as to wish to eat a piece of the fine horses. He adds as it is said they have been known to boil old leather, the harness of their horses; yea, we read in Scripture that the hands of the pitiful women had sodden their own children<note resp="transcr">Lamentations 4:10</note> this is wonderful coming down indeed. Read the Lamentations of Jeremiah and the 28 Chapter of Deuteronomy there we may see the blessed fruits and effects of obedience and the dreadful consequence of disobedience and what the disobedient are to expect. That eminent dignified servant of Lord Humphrey Smith who died in prison said near his end it is a fine thing for a man to have the Lord for his friend at such a times as this a fine thing – indeed and the finest of all fine things that can make all our bed in our sickness and strengthen us upon the bed of languishing and prepare them to say although I walk through
<pb n="A0011534_031"/>
through the valley of the shadow of death yet will I fear no evil<note resp="transcr">Psalm 23:4</note> although the fields shall yield no meat yet will I rejoice in the Lord and joy in the God of my salvation<note resp="transcr">Habakkuk 3:17</note> and see Job 5 and 19: He shall deliver them six troubles yea in seven there shall no evil touch thee 20 in famine he shall redeem thee from death and in war from the power of the sword. 21: Thou shalt be hid from the scourge of the tongue neither shalt thou be afraid of destruction when it cometh. 22: At destruction and famine thou shalt laugh; etc., etc., a fine thing indeed to have such a religion that brings people into the favor of such a friend that can and has done such great things for his faithful obedient children and people as we read he did for Noah, Abraham, Isaac and Jacob: Job, David, Daniel, Shadreck, Mescheck and Abednego and as we read in the 11 of Hebrews he quenched the violence of fire, stopped the mouths of lions. Out of weakness they were made strong and put the armies of the aliens to flight: a fine thing indeed to have such a religion and such a friend: and oh how many thousand at this very hour do greatly want such a religion and such a friend now they are pining away with hunger and are stricken through for want of the fruits of the field. Read now the 91st Psalm, particularly verse 4 and 5: He shall cover thee with his feathers and under his wings shall thou trust his truth shall be thy shield and buckler, thou shalt not be afraid of the terror by night nor for the arrow that flieth by day. 6: Nor for the pestilence that walketh in darkness nor for the destruction that walketh at noon day. 7: A thousand shall fall at thy side and ten thousand at thy right hand but it shall not come nigh thee. 8: Only with thine eyes shalt thou behold and see the reward of the wicked such a religion is worth having what wisdom it would be in all above all things to endeavor to make the Lord their friend. If ye do whatsoever I command you then are ye my friends<note resp="transcr">John 15:14</note> If the people in Ireland and the people of New York now under their grievous sufferings of famine and pestilence were favored to have the Lord for their friend oh how far it would tranced all the joys and pleasures, riches and treasures this world can afford and we read that formerly when under their great affliction they sought the Lord he was found of them<note resp="transcr">2 Chronicles 15:4</note> when the judgments of the Lord are in the earth they will learn righteousness.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_032"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-09-11"><dateline><date when="1822-09-11">11th of the Ninth Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> My daughter Abigail and I went to select meeting at Haddonfield all shut up in silence, dullness, leanness poverty, and lowness I counted it a mercy to be enabled to keep to the travail and exercise in answering our queries. Poor, old fashioned, dry formal, dull work and yet as I was favored to keep single I came off with good satisfaction and approbation of my friends we went to dine with Joseph Collins whose wife is Ann Edwards sister and their sister Elizabeth lives with them and our cousin Henry Warrington and his mother-in-law Lidia Lippincott came there and at parting we had a sitting with them to the satisfaction of all I believe.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-09-12"><dateline><date when="1822-09-12">12.</date></dateline><p> We went to quarterly meeting a wagon full six of us two children and two grandchildren. The meeting was very large and it is likely many were disappointed for we had but little preaching waters seemed low there were a number of valuable ministers and in the meeting for business answering queries there were many pertinent, lively remarks on the state of society and things amongst us. I expressed some concern I had on account of the growing increasing custom of reading the news and the customary unnecessary unbecoming use of tobacco. The most enormous expense our country was at to furnish themselves with these two articles: the thousands and tens of hundreds of thousands if not millions of money which if applied to the use of the poor would help many a worthy person in distress and would be an acceptable sacrifice to the Lord. I expect I exposed myself to the scorn and contempt of many although I have no doubt there is a witness placed in every heart that testifies there is a great excess and danger in them things although so little noticed which would not be pleasant to remember in a time of trouble such as they at this time experience at New York and in Ireland where they are raising money by thousands to keep the poor from starving and they say many perish for want. Our first Friends William Edmondson and <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> bore a zealous testimony against the customary unbecoming use of tobacco to see even boys and girls smoking segars many hurting their health I am informed that the expense in segars one year in the City of New York only was 20 thousand dollars I had peace.</p>
<p>[marginal note] The time Hannah Warrington was received a minister.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_033"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-09-15"><dateline><date when="1822-09-15">15th of the Ninth Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting if it deserved the name of a meeting it was pretty near full, but oh, the manner in which people come – the trifling indifferency, the unconcernedness, the lukewarmness. Richard Davies says it was their concern in all their meetings together to feel the Lord among them and he did manifest himself among them at times in a distinguished manner to the contriting their hearts even to tears so that at some of their meetings there was scarcely a dry eye amongst them although altogether silent and they could say the Lord alone was master of their assembly and they used to say when friends minds were more disencumbered with the cares of this world the powerful overshadowings of the Holy Ghost was more frequently felt amongst them but alas what do we experience of these things would it not be strange talk do we even understand such language: I have heard tell of the garment of praise – instead of the spirit of heaviness<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 61:3</note> but I thought we had the spirit of heavyness instead of the garment of praise I thought I seldom ever seen a duller, poorer time and all shut up till at last E.R. said considerable and it seemed to end a little better but I was unwell and hardly able to wrestle or labor for the arisings of life which it seems very few so much as ever think of or understand the language so no wonder poverty abounds: Last Sixth Day, the 13th, there were 3 burials at Haddonfield: Bulah Clement near 90 years of age my old acquaintance and one stout healthy man In the midst of his days with very short illness. We hear of great sickness at Salem and Woodbury and many deaths and we hear of pinching drought in Bucks County and Chester County fields of corn they say many will yield next to nothing: it has been so dry and hot here that the Indian corn is fit to husk and many are at it I believe the man is not living that ever seen the like it has been very hot weather ill now 18 of the Ninth Month it changed very cool this night a pretty smart frost for the first this fall Job Scott in his journal mentions a frost in the Eighth Month which he seem to thing – something alarming but some remarked there was frost almost every month through the summer a few years ago however I know we used sometimes to have the corn killed with the frost before it was ripe. But now it is almost all dry.</p>
<p>[marginal note] A great show for rain though we had but little here it was a heavy rain up the river and in Pennsylvania a few days ago.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_034"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-09-19"><dateline><date when="1822-09-19">19 of the Ninth Month, Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting more stirrings of life and evident ownings of truth than I have seen of late some satisfaction although waters are very low great dullness and indifferency although the calls are loud for and near sickness and mortality in many places far and near this morning </p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-09-22"><dateline><date when="1822-09-22">22 of the Ninth Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> I received a letter from Abraham Warrington of the state of Ohio giving an account of the dysentery in more or less in most places and many deaths amongst them and some blooming youth taken off with it.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-09-22"><dateline><date when="1822-09-22">22.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting and a lively open owning time it seem to be it held near half an hour longer than common and the people did not seem impatient there was a comfortable covering and feeling nearness at parting.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-09-26"><dateline><date when="1822-09-26">26.</date></dateline><p> Our preparative meeting. But so so middling some temporal concerns came before us and o how wise how capable we are fit for agents in worldly concerns but dumb and dull enough about spiritual</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-09-29"><dateline><date when="1822-09-29">29.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting where there is few to work it brings the labor hard on a few (I cannot dig and to beg I am ashamed was the language formerly<note resp="transcr">Luke 16:3</note> ) to dig too idle and to beg too proud yet under name of stewards feign would shroud we sat in poverty all shut up till late and I ventured to stand up and as I was favored to beg for help it was I thought an evident owning time then E. Roberts and A.H. so the meeting held half an hour or more longer than common and there was something that kept them from grumbling as they used sometimes to do when meeting held but a little longer than common a satisfactory time to me in a good degree.</p></div>
{1822-10}
<div type="entry" when="1822-10-03"><dateline><date when="1822-10-03">3 of the Tenth Month.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Smaller than common a very busy time getting in fall crops and seeding, etc. but the smallness was I thought not the worst of it. A spirit of heaviness instead of the garment of praise<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 61:3</note> I can hardly bear such indolence, indifferency, and dry formality with patience I thought of what William Hunt told the people once at a meeting you look to me to be a lazy idle pack.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-10-06"><dateline><date when="1822-10-06">6th of the Tenth Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> First Day. We were invited to the burial of John Haines of Cropwell, an elder, an exemplary, steady, innocent man of an unblemished character near sixty years of age left a widow and a large family of children and several grandchildren there was a large number of people and behaved very still and orderly he lived near Cropwell meeting house and they got early to meeting Hinchman Haines myself and Elizabeth Barton had considerable to say but it seemed hard getting along dullness and dryness prevails although so many calls after divers ways and divers manners.</p>
<p>[marginal note] The day our horse died.</p>
<p>[marginal note] The earth is got between us and the sun of righteousness and it causes a very great eclipses.</p>
<pb n="A0011534_035"/>
<p>My children brought home a little book from burying from H. Lippincott called <emph rend="italic">Piety Promoted</emph> giving an excellent account of the blessed and happy end of many faithful friends and some children of eight and nine years old and of the blessed happy end they were favored to make. Is it not as William Hunt said at last a wonder all the world does not seek after peace of mind it is such an excellent treasure at last what says he would all the world do for me now if I was destitute of this peace and this was the substance of the last words of many of the faithful.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-10-04"><dateline><date when="1822-10-04">4 of the Tenth Month.</date></dateline><p> I was reading that precious sweet little book, see page 195, concerning Richard Rensom some of his last words when a friend bid him farewell he said in a weighty manner fare well fare well in the Lord Jesus for in him alone it is we can fare well and we may remember what he (the Divine Master) has said in this world the shall have tribulation but in me peace<note resp="transcr">John 16:33</note> in thy presence said David is fullness of joy<note resp="transcr">Psalm 16:11</note> but is fullness of joy to be found and enjoyed without it: and again he says the Lord's loving kindness is better than life<note resp="transcr">Psalm 63:3</note> we may see that people are in a blessed happy state when favored of the Lord who delivered Jonah and Joseph out of their deepest distress and many others of the faithful but oh, to think of the dismal state of those who have forsaken the Lord and cast of the thing that is good how we may see how the enemy has pursued them and how they who have pursued lying vanities have forsaken their own mercies: weather continues very warm like summer the horses sweat like midsummer going to meeting I believe that the man is not living that can say they ever seen so little frost cold storm of high winds.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-10-13"><dateline><date when="1822-10-13">13 of the Tenth Month.</date></dateline><p> First Day. My daughters went with me to Easton meeting which was very small and very poor as to the life of truth but yet there seems to be some growth and a living remnant like a little seed I found it hard getting along not much satisfaction nor did repent being there we dined at Joseph Haines a lively young minister had a sitting at parting and got well home though weary.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-10-16"><dateline><date when="1822-10-16">16.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting Benejah Butcher and Abigail Roberts were married there was a pretty many people and I thought it appeared they had generally chosen their own ways and thought there was little or none of the Lord's ways with us there are four of us that frequently have something to say in our meetings but all quite shut up and as poor and destitute of the savor of life and ownings of truth as those who trouble themselves not at all about any religion of any sort not clothing enough to hide our nakedness but to see the parade with their fine carriages we might say with the prophet there is no end to their chariots<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 2:7</note>: jumping carriots [chariots?]: although but poor in circumstance.</p>
<pb n="A0011534_036"/>
<p>See Stephen Crisp's <emph rend="italic">Sermons</emph>, page 256, for so long as men or women stand in unity with their lusts and – concupiscence with the spirit of this world and the way of it they are not capable of receiving that which should lead them in the way of Holiness; nay, if it appears to them they cannot receive it for it is with them as with other guest there be other lovers already let in which employ the powers and faculties of their souls: so that it is no wonder we have such poor dull meetings especially at weddings where there seems no room for thirst and his disciples for their very appearance demonstrate the desire not the knowledge of his humble narrow way I thought they had forsaken the fountain of living waters and hewn to themselves cisterns that can hold no water<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 2:13</note> so we are dry, poor, and barren the apostle says the friendship of this world and a carnal mind is enmity with God<note resp="transcr">Romans 8:7</note> what will be the consequence after so much labor bestowed upon us they that pursue lying vanities forsake their own mercies<note resp="transcr">Jonah 2:8</note> and they that cast of thing that is good the enemy shall pursue them<note resp="transcr">Hosea 8:3</note> this day a lameness in my knee which I have felt something of some years ago has increased until I can hardly walk across the house or bear my weight on it I know not what it is without it is the rheumatism it is not attended with much pain yet if I keep still I was hard beset to get in the house when I got from meeting my son Joseph and his wife are now with us from Fallowfield – in Pennsylvania and he informs me that the dysentery has been so mortal near them that four and five have died out of one house and two corpses carried out of one house at one time but now abated yet it seems to have no effect or check on the pride and high-mindedness of our youth or others we used to have it in our queries are friends careful to keep to moderation on account of births, marriages, burials, and all other occasions but it is really a question whether they are not now the farthest from moderation on account of these things of any people If there are any before us we certainly are stretching hard after them: there were about 10 or 12 chairs in a train to carry the wedding guest and I suppose it is true that it is become a fashion with our young people nowadays at weddings their guest must all ride in chairs or shais [chaises?] I once seen about 12 or 14 coaches in a range in the street and they told me they were attending the burial of a young man who died suddenly many worthy Friends have been concerned to see the great parade amongst us at burials Samuel Smith and others left a charge not to give any public invitations to their burials and divers others our first Friends wrote long epistles and called them epistles against pride and often had this saying in them surely will not the Lord visit for these things.</p>
<p>[marginal note] If ye forsake him he will forsake you said Azariah.<note resp="transcr">2 Chronicles 15:2</note></p>
<p>[marginal note] Let your moderation appear in all things for the Lord is at hand we read in our Bible [Philippians 4:5].</p>
<p>[marginal note] no room for Christ and his Disciples.</p>
<pb n="A0011534_037"/>
<p>Happiness consists in being prepared to enjoy possessions not in having them see Jeremiah 6 and 10 the world of the Lord is unto them a reproach they have no delight in it: verse 13 far from the least of them even unto the greatest of them every one is given to covetousness: can we clear ourselves of such a charge as this in our days.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-10-20"><dateline><date when="1822-10-20">20 of the Tenth Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> First Day I am so lame with a pain in my knee I can hardly get from the bed to the fire: I happened to take up Hoyland's Works 1st volume, page 277. He says of religion which is the joy the guide the supporter of the universe. Page 280: For extraordinary things frequently repeated are extraordinary no longer and consequently soon lose their force is this the reason why in these days line upon line and precept upon precept have so little effect or what is it. Page 281: The man who fears God is raised above all other fear in the confidence of faith: it appears to be so in the case of Daniel, Shadreck and Abednego. Page 282: Unless the mind be under the regulating power of religion it will be perpetually losing its balance and changing its temper in substance he says some times too fast and some times too slow some times too high and some times too low in spirit. Page 285: But we need not recur to distant periods of history for an example of ruin our effects produced by inattention to religious principles the history of every man's own experience is illustration sufficient: but see the stability of the righteous see last part of the 5 of Job thou shalt not be afraid of destruction when it cometh so indeed it appears to have been with Daniel, Shadreck, Mashick and Abednego and all the faithful martyrs and our worthy progenitors they could not afright them with their utmost stretch of power to punish with prison nor dungeon, stake, gallows, whipping, or banish men and all their envy and malice could invent page 283 he says of little consequence is it to obtain the possession of expected good unless we are fitted for the enjoyment of it: this makes me think of some of our youth ho after their parents have been at great expense in schooling their children they bring forth sour grapes and what can fit children for the enjoyment of good but as John Churchman says prepare their minds to receive the power of truth without which he says they never can be happy page 284 he says there can be no good government but what is found upon religion: page 292 Happiness consists not in having possessions but in being fitted to enjoy them how have we seen the truth of this saying verified in very many instances where young people have had very great estates put into their hands they have lived very unhappy for want of being fitted to enjoy them and their minds prepared to receive the power of truth without which earthly possessions cannot make them happy: 20 First day I so lame could not go to meeting weather warm like midsummer. Quite oppressive sweaty.</p>
<p>[marginal note] horses wet with sweat standing in the stable my son Beene says</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_038"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-10-23"><dateline><date when="1822-10-23">23rd of the Tenth Month.</date></dateline><p> I hear that South Carolina has lately been visited with a most tremendous storm the like seldom ever heard of in our days many lives lost and houses torn down, roads stopped up very much and their roads stopped up in a terrible manner. I am told that one Hemingway was lately coming from Salem, Ohio says on the road she asked for water and they told her they had none she moved from Evesham not many years ago Abraham Warrington living at Ohio informs me that the drovers of cattle was forced to turn back on account of the scarcity of water and that and about Fallowfield forty or fifty miles west of Philadelphia their wells and springs were so dried up that they were sinking them in them parts that at West Chester they sold water 11 penny bit a barrel and that they carried water about to sell by the small quantity.</p>
<p>See Lamentations 5 chapter and 4 we have drunken our water for money our wood is sold unto us read the chapter I never heard the like before here.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-10-25"><dateline><date when="1822-10-25">25.</date></dateline><p> I received a letter from Redstone it informs they have had no rain to wet the ground since the 1st of the Fifth Month corn about half a crop oats and grass very short the dryest summer known since settled.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-10-28"><dateline><date when="1822-10-28">28.</date></dateline><p> First Day. I am so lame I cannot move without crutches so confined see Hoyland's works first volume page 383 Moses had a very perverse and wicked generation committed to his charge or care: he did his utmost to make the people obedient and to save them from ruin but in vain: in thy space of fourty years they all fell in the wilderness except two: Christ also was given to a generation not less wicked and pervers: his instructions were lost upon them and in about the same space after they had rejected him they were destroyed Noah I think we read was a preacher of righteousness an hundred years before the flood<note resp="transcr">2 Peter 2:5</note> and yet they went on in wickedness until it is said all flesh had corrupted their way and the imaginations of their hearts was only evil continually and the flood came and swept them all away but Noah and his family were saved in the ark.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-10-06"><dateline><date when="1822-10-06">6 of the Tenth Month.</date></dateline><p> First Day. We were at the burial of John Haines of Cropwell.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-10-28"><dateline><date when="1822-10-28">28 of the Tenth Month.</date></dateline><p> We are invited to the burial of his daughter age 20: who died with the prevailing fever with eight days illness Samuel Evans grandson of <persName key="w6c82qz0">Joshua Evans</persName> passed meeting last month at Haddonfield died since with a very few days illness appeared alarmed.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-10-31"><dateline><date when="1822-10-31">31.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. I yet so lame I can scarcely move across the floor without crutches but favored not to suffer much pain except at times I had something of this lameness in my knee fifteen years ago but it it got well until a few days ago.</p>
<p>[marginal note] his letter dated 10 of Ninth Month 1822</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_039"/>
{1822-11}
<div type="entry" when="1822-11-03"><dateline><date when="1822-11-03">3 of the Eleventh Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Although I am so lame with a weakness and stiffness in my knee I can hardly bear my weight upon it or go at all without crutches. I did get to our meeting and had no cause to repent it. I believe there was something of the ownings of truth and savor of life it was an open owning time to sweet satisfaction divers short lively pertinent savor testimonies several there from neighbouring meetings and<persName key="w6wx87x7">my wife</persName> thinks it ended savory and reputably which we think some of latter time hardly did: they were so poor and destitute of life.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-11-07"><dateline><date when="1822-11-07">7th.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting although it was rainy and not much better of my lameness I got to meeting and had no cause to repent it something owning open and savory although in the last sitting there were some very clost remarks on the deviation prevailing amongst us on looking over the day I could not recollect any thing that was said that I could wish had not been said: had something of that precious cement at last unity, sweetness, and feeling nearness.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-11-04"><dateline><date when="1822-11-04">4.</date></dateline><p> Abigail and I went to see our neighbor John Haines and wife who seem to be improving a little in religion just after we got there five of our friends came to pay them a visit and had a sitting and several spoke and broke up abruptly and I came away not satisfied this visit was in compliance of the advice of the Yearly Meeting: but to little purpose that I could see or feel our last Yearly Meeting appeared to be under a great concern for a reformation amongst us and great need there is they appointed a large committee to visit the quarterly and  monthly meetings and when they were with us I thought they found hard, dull work and in some places very much shut up and they say they found the state of some meetings very poor and low. It is a great thing to undertake to persuade people to change their customs and alter for the better custom is a tyrant he that can well bear or breat it is more than man our association of Evesham lately laboring to discourage the use of spirituous liquors drew up a very excellent paper of advice and caution on that subject and ordered it to be set up at the taverns as one was sitting some of them up at a tavern the landlady or tavern keeper's wife said you may set them up all round the house but it will do no more good than singing psalms to a dead horse but pay day must come what a pity it is that all are no concerned like John Gratton was: see his journal page 74 I wanted the Lord's presence for without that my poor soul could not be satisfied nor find true rest though my life and conversation were such that most loved me that knew me are not some as innocent as a sheep and yet content without feeling the Lord's presence.</p>
<p>[marginal note] great rains but continues warm.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_040"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-11-10"><dateline><date when="1822-11-10">10th of the Eleventh Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> First Day. My knee continues very lame cannot bear my weight on it. If I keep it still and warm it is pretty easy, except at times which is a favor I did not get out with our folks to meeting. Cloudy, dull weather.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-11-11"><dateline><date when="1822-11-11">11.</date></dateline><p> Second Day. A stranger, Isaac Hammer, [from] Tennesse country six hundred miles southwest. Isaac Hammer appointed a meeting at Moorestown a pretty many came it's likely principally to hear what the stranger had to say and were disappointed for he had nothing to say and a poorer meeting as to the stirrings of life and ownings of truth I seldom seen if people come to meet only for what they can hear with their outward ears is it any matter if they are disappointed: poor scholars indeed if they have got no further and it is to be feared it is really the case people should go to meeting more for what they need to feel than what they may see or hear: feel after him if happily ye may find him: in all our meetings together it was our concern to feel the Lord amongst us: according to his promise of being with two or three gathered in his name said Richard Davies: very come yet.</p>
<p>This stranger informed me of our cousin Margaret Minthel a worthy minister in the Genesse country, a daughter of our dear worthy kinsman William Hunt's. They say most of his large family of children follow him in the line of the ministry. I have had ten children, three died very young, two died about the twenty-fifth year of their age hopeful five are living yet and I never knew one of them accused of lying swearing fraudulent dealing – unchastity or drunkenness and mostly willing to keep to plainness in their dress and punctuality yet great room for improvement but a great mercy they have escaped the spots and stains of this world so far: true and undefiled religion is to keep ourselves unspotted from the world:</p>
<p>It is 11 of the Eleventh Month, 1822.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_041"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-11-08"><dateline><date when="1822-11-08">8 of the 11th month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> I had a little book sent to me to read the account of Archibald Robbins his being shipwrecked and taken among the Arabians where he suffered about two years the most cruel slavery by that Indian like barbarous, heathenish, idolatrous, Meksmits people but at last found one man very rich and very kind he says to know the manner in which he spends much of his immense income would be to learn that with him wealth is devoted to the noblest of all purposes diminishing human woe and augmenting human happiness he has by his munificience secured the favor even of the Mehommedans [Muslims]: with all their antipathy against Christians: how seldom is riches applied to his greatest and most noblest of purposes page 251 – in the same book page 236 giving an account of that barbarous, idolatrous, heathenish peoples: customs and manners of that place (Santa Cruz) and of the tropics and markets says one article however which is a principal one at that place is never seen among the shilluh – tobacco: this being considered by them or among them as a detestable weed and the use of it as a transgression: does not this provoke us to jealousy who are high professing Christians by them who are professed Mehommedans [Muslims] and great enemies and haters of Christians and greatly despise them. Noah was a preacher of righteousness and what become of his people people the flood destroyed them all but Noah and his family. Moses was called prophet and most deeply concerned for his people after all his care and labor and the many miracles they all felt in the wilderness but 2 Caleb and Joshua Christ also was given to a to a generation not less wicked, perverse and his instruction were lost upon them and in about the same space after they had rejected him they were destroyed says Hoyland how are many of us infatuated, besotted, and bewitched with the customary use of tobacco: high professing Christians.<note resp="transcr">Archibald Robbins, A<emph rend="italic"> Journal Comprising an Account of the Loss of the Brig Commerce, </emph>several editions published prior to this date.</note></p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_042"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-11-27"><dateline><date when="1822-11-27">27th of the 11th month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> I have been very lame with a pain and weakness in one of my knees this several weeks so that I have been forced to keep still and have been to meeting but little. Last First Day, 24 of the Eleventh Month First Day was at our meeting and had something to remark on the uncertainty of time and the happiness of them who in time wisely prepare for it and how many are suddenly taken away and three days after my dear dutiful, affectionate innocent son Benjamin was suddenly killed digging of marl. He had been at work at it with four or five hands about ten days and that day was to finish the job but this 27 of the Eleventh Month, 1822, about one o'clock, the bank caved in and covered up one of the men, all but his head and nose and whilst they were digging him out the earth caved in the second time and some ironstone being throwed up on the bank fell in and struck our dear son on the breast and covered him up to the knees. They quickly got him dug loose but he told them he was so hurt he could not live. They carried him to a house near half a mile [and] sent for a doctor. One got there very soon after he was hurt and the second in a short time but his wound was so deep they could do nothing for him and he lived hard four hours after he was hurt. They sent for his wife but he was gone before she got there they tell us he had a great deal to say raised his voice and desired them about him not to put of making preparation for such a time as that was with him and advised his little son William 11 years old to be a good boy said he was concerned for his children and not only for his own but for all the world over and told them his peace was made and had a hope of future happiness. It was believed bleeding inwardly suffocated him and took him of and that might be the reason why he appeared not to be in great misery and pain. 29 on Sixth Day we went to the burial of our dear innocent son and a solemn time it was a house of mourning indeed six children and all small but one and a very weakly helpless mother: people seemed affected.</p>
<pb n="A0011534_043"/>
<p>In memory of my dear son Benjamin Hunt who was just about forty two years of age when he died: He was a pretty little innocent goodly child from his infancy remarkably beloved by all his little brothers and sisters and all along as he grew up: he seemed to be beloved by all that knew him or had anything to do with him. His servant a coloured lad said he could live with Benne forever. A poor old widow who lived with him as an hired servant said she had lost a good friend. He was industrious enough, ingenious, gifted and very capable of managing his temporal affairs. He had a good share of natural understanding gifts and talents and seemed disposed to improve and make a right use of them he was very constant and diligent in tending all our religious meetings and very exemplary in quiet steady setting in our meetings for worship in the time of silence and sometimes spoke to the business in meetings for discipline which was acceptable to his Friends. His troubles and trials were many and very great which he bore with great fortitude and exemplary patience. Now he is gone we believe out of the reach of trouble where the wicked cease from troubling and the weary are at rest: where none of the inhabitants ever shall say I am sick: made his escape, as David says, from the windy – storm and tempest<note resp="transcr">Psalm 55:8</note>: for such this world is to very many. As he had lived, so he died, beloved and lamented by his friends and neighbors, few leavening a more unblemished character: which seems now to be a very great advantage to his poor children for it is wonderful to see the open heartedness and kindness of his friends in a care and concern to take care of his dear little children: for whom he expressed such a concern in his last moments and a very great comfort to see a prospect of the children being like to get such good places with their relations where they seem like to be kindly cared for both temporally and spiritually.</p>
<p>It is a grievous thing when some shorten their days with intemperance and leave poor families of children a burden on their friends as some do and nothing but a grief to their friends from their cradles.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_044"/>
{1822-12}
<div type="entry" when="1822-12-01"><dateline><date when="1822-12-01">1st of the Twelfth Month, 1822.</date></dateline><p> First Day. I ventured out to our meeting. Had a painful night again. Sarah Cresson was there and I recon she preached near two hours and a solemnity and heavenly sweetness attended the meeting but alas what will it do for people if they sit down content with barely hearing tell of good things without laboring to possess them for themselves will it not be like Ephraim feeding on the wind<note resp="transcr">Ephraim 12:1</note> if they do not labor to have something of their own bread in their own houses and water in their own cisterns. Without this concern and labor George Fox says people may perish for want.  We have line upon line, precept upon precept upon precept not only here a little and there a little but here a great deal and there is a great deal which we acknowledge to be very good but what has it done for us where much is given much will be required woe unto the Corasin woe unto the Bethsaida if the great and mighty works which have been done in thee had been done in Tyre and Sidon they would have repented long: ago in sackcloth and ashes<note resp="transcr">Luke 10:13</note>: Noah was a preacher of righteousness, Moses was a prophet and see what became of the people that they preached to Noah's people all perished in the flood Moses's people all fell in the wilderness but Caleb and Joshua and the people to whom Christ was given were no less perverse and wicked and his instruction were lost upon them and in about the same space of time after they had rejected him they were destroyed: says Hoyland: so see here is the effects and fruits of people sitting down contented with barely hearing tell of good things without laboring to possess them for themselves.</p>
<p>As I lay thinking of the sudden death of our dear son Benjamin it came fresh into remembrance how many times I seemed to narrowly escape being suddenly killed by accidents and how many are or have been very suddenly snatched away without a moment's warning as it were and very many by sickness with very short – warning: so that happy indeed are they that wisely prepare for it and as I had to mentions last First Day was a week the last meeting I and my dear son sat together in meeting: I said I had of ten thoughts what a fine thing it would be if I could be one of the number of the righteous then if I should be suddenly snatched away without a moment's warning as many are yet all would be well. Oh,  how little did he or I think it would so soon be his lot to be so soon and so suddenly snatched away: yet it seems to be generally believed all is well with him: for that transcends all this world can afford when we consider the length of eternity.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_045"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-12-03"><dateline><date when="1822-12-03">3rd of the Twelfth Month, 1822, and Third of the week</date></dateline><p> some say there has scarcely been a fall more moderate grass looks more fresh and green and growing even till now in the yard than it did in the dry weather in summer there has been abundance of rain of late First Day Morning the day before yesterday there was a great deal of thunder and lightning and had been a great rain in the night Now this Second Day night and Third Day morning a considerable snow storm although not very cold nor windy I could but take notice of the sudden change in the weather and how very changeable the things of this world are none knows what a day or an hour yea or a minute may bring forth – as one day goes another comes? and sometimes shews us dismal dooms? Now and then: a pleasant day? Long a coming soon away: wherefore the everlasting truth? is good for aged and for youth: for them to set their hearts upon? for that will last till time is done? see Thomas Chalkley's journal: words he has preserved of his son 10 years old: a very cold freezing time after it cleared up very winter like weather 8 of the Twelfth Month First Day weather clears up fine and moderate and my lame knee a little better I got out to meeting again and had no cause to repent being there on the whole at last there was something owning savory and satisfactory Ann Quicksil of Evesham had savory service my friends seemed glad to see me again and there was something of that precious cement of sweetness and feeling nearness at parting.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-12-12"><dateline><date when="1822-12-12">12</date></dateline><p> was our quarterly meeting at Evesham and very large there was a many aimiable, able ministers <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> <persName key="w6b01gx6">John Cox</persName> and divers others but Daniel Pucket from Indiana about 900 miles westward had a great deal to say, took up most of the time in the first meeting and a good deal in the last. He is a very great and able minister and it is said he was in army amongst the soldiers last war I had but one or two shots and to right good satisfaction my friends seemed to on me sweetness and feeling nearness at parting: which I count a great favor.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-12-15"><dateline><date when="1822-12-15">15.</date></dateline><p> Went to an afternoon meeting at 3 o'clock at Evesham for the youth. Daniel Pucket preached till it began to grow dark and the people kept very still and attentive: 3000 we read was converted at Peter's first sermon but nowadays there appears but little impression.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_046"/>
<div type="entry" when="1822-12-17"><dateline><date when="1822-12-17">17th of the 12 month.</date></dateline><p> Third of the week. Daniel Pucket appointed a meeting at Moorestown, and I believe it held about one hour longer than common, and he preached most of the time. [There were] many there who were like the dispersed of Judah and scattered of Israel,<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 11:12</note> for whom I have always had my mind much turned, but I had not time to relieve my mind towards them, but I hope what they heard may be as bread cast upon the waters, and found after many days. But a few weeks ago, Isaac Hammer from Tennessee Countery, 600 miles or more from the south west appointed a meeting at Moorestown, but had nothing to say or at least said nothing, and I am informed he was silent at several other neighbouring meetings although he is an able minister, as they profess to be led by an unerring spirit, these things may seem strange to many but the prophet speaking in the name of the Lord said, your ways are not my ways nor your thoughts my thoughts as the heavens are higher than the earth so are my ways than your ways and my thoughts than your thoughts<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 55:8-9</note> much cloudy weather and rain but holds fine and warm.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-12-22"><dateline><date when="1822-12-22">22.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day I got out to our meeting again to good satisfaction I now hear that a Negro lad who served his time with our dear son Benjamin and said he could live with him forever: is dead although it is but a few weeks since he was here at work with us stout healthy and strong and we hear of a number of very sudden deaths round about us and in Philadelphia we are told many have died very suddenly of latter time: a remarkable number.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1822-12-27"><dateline><date when="1822-12-27">27.</date></dateline><p> We went to the burial of Abigail Thorn, some older than myself, has been a healthy woman through life lived in fullness and prosperity and escaped the pollutions of the world. I do not remember I ever heard anything said against her. There was a large concourse of people and behaved solid and very orderly. I had something to say and I believe helped to good satisfaction.</p>
<pb n="A0011534_047"/>
<p>The ground that drinketh in the rain and bringeth forth briers and thorns is nigh unto cursing says the Scriptures.<note resp="transcr">Hebrews 6:7-8</note></p>
<p>I have been of late much confined to the house. Cannot bear the cold, it effects my old asthma cough, but my knee is better so that I can walk without crutches. Weather moderate.</p></div>
{1823-01}
<div type="entry" when="1823-01-09"><dateline><date when="1823-01-09">9th of the 1st [month], 1823,</date></dateline><p> was our Monthly Meeting. Elias Hicks of the state of New York was there. He is by some, if not many, counted the greatest minister in America. I scarcely ever seen our meeting House more fully crowded, and he preached one hour or more, very sound pertinent doctrine, and the people were very attentive, but alas, what does it do for us, all the abundance of preaching we have had of latter time. Our first Friends say that in early days, when the people's minds were more disengaged from the world, the powerful overshadowings of the Holy Ghost was more frequently and evidently felt amongst them to the tendering their hearts and coveting their spirits even to tears and trembling – but it is to be feared his humble tender contrite state is too little known in these days: If there was a disposition not only to hear and enquire after the right way of the Lord and a desire to walk in it there would be room for hope: but whilst people are determined to walk in their own ways like the gentiles: we will eat our own meat and wear our own apparel, etc..<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 4:1</note> It is as Stephen Crisp says; see his <emph rend="italic">Sermons</emph>, page 256: For so long as men and women stand in unity with their lusts and concupiscence with the spirit of this world and the way of it, they are not capable of receiving that which should lead them into the way of Holiness. Nay, if it appears to them they cannot receive it: for it is with them as with other guests. There are other lovers already let in which employ the powers and faculties of their souls. So these celestial showers are like pouring water upon a rock: all runs off without making any impressions, and but little fruit of all the abundance of labor bestowed upon us our first Friends say many were convinced at their meetings, and we read that 3000 were converted at Peter's first sermon and as many as made 5000 at the next. I thought the meeting for discipline was pretty well conducted and the stranger had a good deal to say and it was satisfactory to me. I thought I saw the states of the people and what they stood in need of.</p>
<pb n="A0011534_048"/>
<p>See here some words of <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName>: Blessed are they which hunger and thirst after righteousness, for they shall be filled: it is the full soul that loathes the honeycomb. Those who are overcharged with the world and the things of the world they are of an ill constitution: they are so filled with the world that they cannot hunger and thirst after righteousness. The Lord fills the hungry with good things but they that are rich and full and think they want nothing, he sends empty away. Charron says to be cloyed is to lose all: it appears a full fed cloyed state was a very loathsome state to the children of Israel. As N.W. said, too much pudding would choke a dog.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-01-12"><dateline><date when="1823-01-12">12.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Daniel Pucket and Priscilla Hunt, both of Indiana, were there. Daniel had an open, owning, favored time. The House nearly full up, stairs and down, and something solemn and savory. Margaret Allison and a young minister from Holly took up some of the time and Daniel stood up the second time and we thought he was favored and the meeting ended reputably savory and well he is a very great preacher and there might be some good done but the tenderness and contrition was but little to what it has been in some meetings the ointment of his right hand betrayeth its self.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 27:16</note> As Robert Walker said, people love to hear preaching but they do not love the cross. Little will hearing tell of the right way of the Lord do for people whilst people are determined to walk in their own ways to eat their own meat and wear their own apparel,<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 4:1 </note> etc. This appears to be the very cause or reason why the abundance of preaching has so little effect. <emph rend="italic">No Cross No Crown</emph>: hear and obey and your souls shall live. Margaret Allinson and her sister Elizabeth and their friend Rowland Jones of Burlington (all of them) paid us a pretty acceptable visit this evening.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-01-16"><dateline><date when="1823-01-16">16.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. Priscilla Hunt, a daughter in law of our cousin Nathan Hunt, came to see us with her companions. And we went with them to Cropwell meeting, where she had extensive, acceptable service. She is a young widow from Indiana, 800 miles or more westward. She appears to be a wise, able, amiable minister. We dined with them at the widow Elizabeth Haines's and had a sitting with the widow and her large family of children, which was to good satisfaction, and also the meeting was so to me in a good degree, so on retrospection.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_049"/>
<div type="entry" when="1823-01-19"><dateline><date when="1823-01-19">19.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting, which was as open and owning a time as I ever seen. There divers appeared pleased and pleasant when we came out but I find many of our raw youths and some others of whom better things might be expected can hardly bear that our meetings should hold a quarter of an hour longer than usual.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-01-23"><dateline><date when="1823-01-23">23.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our preparative meeting and I did think we were favored with something quickening, comforting, and lively although the meeting was not larger than common, notwithstanding all the great deal of preaching we have lately had preparative meeting and in a good degree satisfactory: I see no countenances or conduct or deportment marked with any more seriousness or weightiness since these great preachers have been amongst us although some went to hear them that do not go to meeting once in seven years but some countenances were marked with seriousness, sorrow, and sadness with the language of mortality and the death of near connections a just remark – There is a grandeur, a magnanimity, and glory in the primitive Christian character, which nothing on earth can ever equal. In short or in fine the most ample preparation for defense by carnal weapons endangers life and that of peace of mind without which life is of little value, nay, some have said life is not worth having without peace how then can it be purchased too dear: it has been said they can loose but little that save themselves and they who lose peace of mind sustain the greatest loss.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-01-26"><dateline><date when="1823-01-26">26.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting, Lydia Lippincott had acceptable service and I thought there was something lively and evidently owning so that it was pleasant to look back and look over the day.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-01-30"><dateline><date when="1823-01-30">30 of the First Month.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting not to any satisfaction although the silent part seemed to me pretty well but oh the trifling indifferency unconcernedness and lukewarmness none of that ancient dew of Hermon that descended on the mountains of Zion<note resp="transcr">Psalm 133:3</note> – the breath of Heaven must swell the sail or all the toil is lost far from the state of the prophet who could say let my right hand forget her cunning if I prefer not Jerusalem to my chiefest joy<note resp="transcr">Psalm 137:3</note> or like our first Friends who counted nothing to dear to part with for the sake of their religion.</p>
<pb n="A0011534_050"/>
<p>The meeting small I cannot see that the abundance of preaching we have lately had has made any impressions or had a tendency to gather the people: it was said of old the ointment of his right had berwayeth itself<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 27:16</note> but I fear there is little of that in these days too few let their lights so shine before men that others seeing their good works are animated with the ways of truth and Holiness.</p></div>
{1823-02}
<div type="entry" when="1823-02-02"><dateline><date when="1823-02-02">2.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting so low and poor nearly all shut up.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-02-06"><dateline><date when="1823-02-06">6.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our Monthly Meeting, and a satisfactory one it was to me. Simon Gilum was there and had sweet acceptable service. I dined with him and his companion Joseph Wright at Josiah Roberts and it was pleasant to look over the day.</p>
<p>See Hoyland's second volume, page 240. No place is frightful to a good man, but the dungeon of a wounded conscience or an evil conscience it is the favor or displeasure of an Almighty judge that makes this or the other place or spot: comfortable or irksome. Where the spirit of the Lord is there is liberty, but to the guilty, the whole world is a place of confinement. 24: How much wiser, how much more happy and safe and noble are they who live in communion with God than other men. See Proverbs 28 and 1st: The wicked flee when no man pursueth but the righteous are bold as a lion. See Job 5th, 21 verse: Neither shalt be afraid of destruction when it cometh so indeed it appears to have been with thousands of the martyrs since the days of Daniel and Steven: and see the 91 Psalm 5th: verse Thou shalt not be afraid for the terror by night nor for the arrow that flieth by day etc. read the chapter and see the great displays of Almighty power and wisdom in the destruction of the wicked and also in the preservation and deliverance of the righteous set forth in the 11th of Hebrews: He stopped the mouths of lions quenched the violence of fire out of weakness they were made strong waxed valiant in fight and put the armies of the aluns to flight. But it is said fearfulness shall surprise the hypocrite.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-02-09"><dateline><date when="1823-02-09">9th of the Second Month.</date></dateline><p> First Day. We went to Cropwell meeting. Simon Gilum was there and had pertinent except, acceptable, savory service and it was an open, owning time with us to my satisfaction we dined with the stranger at Joseph Evans's: with many others had a sitting with the family to good satisfaction: all ended well.</p>
<p>[marginal note] very sharp cold weather and still.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_051"/>
<div type="entry" when="1823-02-10"><dateline><date when="1823-02-10">Second Day Morning, 10 of the Second Month, 1823.</date></dateline><p> As the word of the Lord to the people of old we read in Scripture that he said my spirit shall not always strive with man [Genesis 6:3] there is evidence that his spirit is yet striving, wooing, and inviting notwithstanding their heathenish, outlandish, idolatrous appearances in worshiping that great idol the fashions and a conformity to this world's ways and spirit: the friendship of this world and a carnal mind are enmity with God.<note resp="transcr">Romans 7:8</note> and oh how doth it rob people of their chiefest good acceptance with God when I look at the general depravity and dissipation I am led to think of what was said of old to Ephraim let Ephraim alone he hath joined himself to idols<note resp="transcr">Hosea 4:17</note>: How many in these days worship the works of their own Hands that which their own fingers have made<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 2:8</note></p>
<p>See William Law's words, page 32: The true way of turning to Gods he says that is pure and unmixed idolatry that lives wholly to self if so what abundance of idolatry there is in these days: although if anyone should say his goods or his gold was his god he would be counted an heretic but does not the language of conduct of very many say to the gold thou art my hope and confidence compass sea and land to obtain it: and I think he says in another place the heresy of all heresies an earthly mind. Page 33, he says: For self love is the greatest of all thieves: hath it not robbed and cheated millions out of their greatest riches and best treasure: peace of mind, acceptance with God, the Kingdom of Heaven.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-02-13"><dateline><date when="1823-02-13">13 of the Second Month, 1823.</date></dateline><p> Was Fifth Day. At our meeting Thomas Evans and son of William and Mary Matlack daughter of George were married Elizabeth Hunt from Indiana had given general invitation and the meeting was very large and she had a great deal to say and it was no doubt to general satisfaction: our friends say in early days they had meetings wherein there was scarcely a dry eye but now it is rare to see a wet one it easier to find ten a sleeping than to find one a weeping even under the most powerful pertinent ministry powerful preachers and dull hearers the love of the world and friendships of it operated like opium stupefy and besot.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_052"/>
<div type="entry" when="1823-02-14"><dateline><date when="1823-02-14">14.</date></dateline><p> I went to the burial of Job Cole's wife, aged about seventy. Had been lingering and declining a long time. A violent, stormy, cold snow and hail. There was a large number of people, and conducted orderly and well, but such was the poverty and leanness I was ready to wish myself at home. There was a great mixture of sorts and sects. My old acquaintance Mary Allen, formerly Roberts, was buried the same day at Woodbury; about seventy, has suffered much of later time.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-02-16"><dateline><date when="1823-02-16">16.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. Very cold sharp freezing weather but I did get to our meeting and had no cause to repent being there it was an open owning favored satisfactory time to me once more</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-02-21"><dateline><date when="1823-02-21">21.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. Went to Evesham meeting, which was small, but I believe there were some stirrings of life and ownings of truth if I am not mistaken, as very many thousands and millions are it is to be feared who seem satisfied and contented with the performance of a round of religious duties with a sort of peace that if they would examine it they would find it was a counterfeit peace that never came from the Royal Mint: However upon the most mature deliberation I find no condemnation and the apostle says if our heart condemn us not then have we confidence toward God<note resp="transcr">1 John 3:21</note> – I have often feared of late there are abundance of people who are contenting themselves with a hope that is like a spider's web and what a dreadful thing to be deceived in a matter of such vast importance.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-02-24"><dateline><date when="1823-02-24">24 First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting and not to much satisfaction a violent snowy day snowed all day and all night and next day the greatest snow we have had this winter but not very cold this was the time of Burlington Quarterly Meeting when we used to say winter mostly broke up: a spirit of ease prevails.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-02-27"><dateline><date when="1823-02-27">27 Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting E.R. and H.W. had savory service.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-02-28"><dateline><date when="1823-02-28">28 was our select meeting</date></dateline><p> some life and savor as I thought although dryness and leanness attends answering our queries they seem to become like an old lesson dry and formal this has been for several days the most severe cold winter weather we have had all winter sleighs fly about more than all winter.</p></div>
{1823-03}
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-02"><dateline><date when="1823-03-02">2nd Third Month, First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting rather smaller than common and very poor all shut up quite silent: dissolution threatens us.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-07"><dateline><date when="1823-03-07">7: of the Third Month</date></dateline><p> a great rain swept away the snow which has lain near two weeks and very cold.</p>
<p>[marginal note] 13. I went to see Margaret Peacock in a deep decline.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_053"/>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-06"><dateline><date when="1823-03-06">6th of the Third Month, 1823.</date></dateline><p> At our Monthly Meeting a violent storm a very great rain the meeting on the whole was in a good degree satisfactory but not quite all together so.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-07"><dateline><date when="1823-03-07">7.</date></dateline><p> Abigail and I went to Evesham Monthly Meeting the first meeting was pretty well: and savory Elizabeth Balderston was there and I thought it end very well but I thought the meeting for discipline was old fashioned answering queries poor, dull, dry formal work yet there was room for some clost, plain, pertinent remarks to profit I hope: How we can smooth things along in investigating our state with respect to our conduct at marriage and other occasions and conclude moderation is kept to: whilst I really question whither there is greater profusion amongst any sort of people: see the equipage in carriages at these times I do not know whither a spirit of libertinism has a more full swing amongst any: and a greater departure from moderation divers young couples have given this as a reason why they went out in their marriage because our way was so expensive – a sorrowful reflection on the society that the rich travel so fast the poor cannot keep up with them as a worthy minister remarked in a select meeting.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-09"><dateline><date when="1823-03-09">9.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting some little satisfaction waters low.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-12"><dateline><date when="1823-03-12">12.</date></dateline><p> Went to select meeting at Haddonfield (Abbe and me) forepart seemed low and poor, old fashioned but I had a little lesson worthy of a place in the minds in all the people in the world and that was look unto me all ye ends of the earth and be ye saved<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 45:22</note>: saved from every wrong thought and wrong way and I looked it over and over: when we came to read the queries I ventured to say something on that great and most important matter of the training up children and it seemed to kindle a zeal <persName key="w6hj799d">Elizabeth Collins</persName> and Sarah Cresson took it up and after them I had something more and that subject and then <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> took it up and expressed his full unity with the exercise of us that had spoken on the subject and then he went on in a very high degree I was ready to say I never heard the Like he told us there had been more concern to gather money than manna it was an evidently owning highly favored time to sweet satisfaction: and feeling nearness at last.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_054"/>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-13"><dateline><date when="1823-03-13">13 of the Third Month.</date></dateline><p> Was our quarterly meeting. John Warring from Long Island a great and worthy minister had very pointed, pertinent service respecting the dull, drowsy, lifeless state of society after him stood up <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> the old standard and almost king of America and he did make all shake and ring again there was another stranger from the Province of Maine. Townsend Hawksworth had good service in the afternoon these appear to be great ministers and I thought in the afternoon these appear to be great ministers and I thought their countenances were marked with seriousness gravity humility and meekness: do we not read there was an inscription of Holiness on all the vessels of the Lord's house [Exodus 39:30]: their faces did not look like the faces of the drunkards: dismal as some have said: some of us thought it was an highly-favored meeting throughout: a concern appeared on account of the loss state of religion by reason of the many deviations amongst old and young.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-16"><dateline><date when="1823-03-16">16.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting not so bad but it might have been a great deal worse and not so well but it might have been a great deal better if we had not been wanting on our part I hope it ended reputably if it was not crowned as it might have been and some have been.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-20"><dateline><date when="1823-03-20">20.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. A great snow storm I did not get out to meeting although the children went: I was reading a little in a little geography a school book it seems beyond conception to think of the extent of our continent and the numerous states, towns, islands, and rivers and the numerous inhabitants and it is likely all of them have a religion of some sort and it is to be feared that saying in Scripture yet remains to be true strait is the gate and narrow the way that leads to life and peace and few there be that find it<note resp="transcr">Matthew 7:14</note>: as the primitive Christians and our worthy progenitors did and the faithful yet do who do experience the promise of Christ to meet with them and that his words are spirit and life and to say with one of old I sat under his shadow with great delight and his fruit was sweet to my taste<note resp="transcr">Song of Solomon 2:3</note> I sit not to be feared that hundreds of thousands professing religion never come to experience this: yet content with a hope and a peace of some sort: and what is all the profession of religion and the Scripture good for with without acceptance with the Lord is not like feeding on wind as some of old.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_055"/>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-23"><dateline><date when="1823-03-23">23 of the Third Month 1823 First Day</date></dateline><p> fine weather again swept away the snow Joseph Justice and Hannah Warrington appeared and I thought it raised the life a little but oh the dissolation that abounds and want of life and ownings of truth: Notwithstanding all the abundant labor bestowed upon us what will be the end of this prevailing loathsome lukewarmness and ingratitude.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-24"><dateline><date when="1823-03-24">24.</date></dateline><p> on Second Day. At 4 o'clock Townsend Hawksworth of Long Island appointed a meeting at our meeting House it was as large as could be expected. The stranger had a good deal to say but in a complaining way he expressed he found it hard to say any thing amongst us and spoke of the easeful state of many who go and come to meeting in an easy way like the door on the hinges.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-26"><dateline><date when="1823-03-26">26.</date></dateline><p> A very great northeast storm of snow and rain and cold.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-27"><dateline><date when="1823-03-27">27.</date></dateline><p> Was our preparative meeting the most lively and strengthening to me of any I have seen of latter time with desires I might be favored and preserved so as to have such favors continued.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-28"><dateline><date when="1823-03-28">28.</date></dateline><p> Christopher Healy of Bucks County Pennsylvania appointed a meeting at our meeting House at the usual hour and I believe preached an hour or more and I thought an heavenly quiet attended at last and I fear few consider the excellency of it the work of righteousness is peace and the effects thereof quietness and assurance forever: but how many thousand there are of whom it may be said the way of peace they know not.<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 59:8</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-30"><dateline><date when="1823-03-30">30th of the Third Month, First Day.</date></dateline><p> A very great storm of rain and snow and high wind I was not well enough to go through the storm to meeting.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1823-03-31"><dateline><date when="1823-03-31">Second Day Morning</date></dateline><p> a considerable snow no doubt it has been a suffering trying to many especially those whose business is on the waters but it was but a light trifling storm compared to some we have accounts of when people found but a precarious shelter in their houses yea many houses blowed down and buried the people in the ruins and rubbish and thousands of pounds lost in damages done to mills and other things: a wind from the wilderness smote upon the four corners of the house and it fell upon the young man and they are dead so we read of the children of Job thou shalt be visited with a storm.</p>
<p>[marginal note] abundance of rain this month.</p>
<pb n="A0011534_056"/>
<p>[31] 30 of the Third Month, 1823. Second Day. Clears up fine and moderate but the snow is not yet gone. See a pamphlet called the <emph rend="italic">Reformer</emph> Ninth Month 1st 1821, volume 2nd page 282 an extract. Whoever rebels against the laws of his duty and plainly affronts the dictates of his conscience, does that moment bid adieu to all true repose and quiet and exposes himself to the severest resentments of a self-tormenting mind. And though by secret acts of wickedness he may be able possibly to drown the voice of it for a while, yet every little affliction or petty accident, will be apt to awaken it into horror and let in terror like an armed man upon him. A torment infinitely beyond what the most – ingenious tyrants could ever contrive. Nothing so effectually invades our ease as the reproach of our own minds. The wrath of man may be endured, but the eruptions of conscience are irresistible. The Scriptures say a wounded conscience who can bear – some have compared or called it unquenchable fire and some of the martyrs chose rather to be burnt at the stake than bear that unquenchable fire: the Scriptures say it is not by us to be conceived the good things the Lord hath in store for the – righteous and Addison says it is not in the power of imagination to conceive the direfull state of a wounded conscience to that effect.</p></div>
{1823-04}
<div type="entry" when="1823-04-03"><dateline><date when="1823-04-03">Third of the Fourth Month, Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> I have been so bad with my old cough and poorly I did not get to meeting heard of the death of Jeremiah Matlack seven or ten years younger than me. He has seen much unpleasant things in his day. His wife many years confined to her bed and himself many years confined to his room. I knew his father and mother from early life so we see how soon one generation passes away after another. This day received another letter from my son Joseph.</p>
<p>One of my friends brought me Samuel Scott's diary to read I had seen it before but it was very acceptable: This week he says has passed pretty comfortably not much cause for condemnation having attended: nevertheless I have fallen short in respect to unnecessary words and thoughts: When we neither act speak or think anything inconsistent with the divine will: this says one is perfect satisfaction: and this is the mark of our high and Holy calling in Christ Jesus who himself was holy harmless, undefiled, and separate from sinners.</p>
<p>[marginal note] I have been poorly with a bad cough and kept house chiefly of Late 19th Fourth Month.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011534_057"/>
<div type="entry" when="1823-04-10"><dateline><date when="1823-04-10">10th of the Fourth Month, 1823.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day I ventured out to meeting though hardly able it was our Monthly Meeting – Sarah Cresson was there and shewed her zeal for the Lord had extensive acceptable service. Humility she said was the true Christian's everyday dress. My mind was impressed at the same time with the same in substance I was viewing the vast importance of true vital religion and the blessed fruits and effects and on the other side the direful fruits and effect where it was suffered to go to decay where people cast off all religious restraint and pursue lying vanities and forsake their own mercies<note resp="transcr">Jonah 2:8</note> and the grievous humbling things sorrow of heart and remorse of conscience destruction and dissolation that often overtake poor mortals not only individuals but even whole nation: that which I have planted will I pluck up even this whole nation oh to think of the blessed safe happy glorious state of the primitive Christians but did any either individuals or whole societies of people ever come to experience the precious fruits and effects of true religion without – humility the humble the Lord teaches of his ways and dwells with them but beholds the proud afar off. In the afternoon I thought there was some life and savor to good satisfaction – I dined with Sarah Cresson at Joseph Matlack's – seen an account in the news of the great storm about two weeks ago. I said it would be a terrible time with people on the water and so it is said abundance of vessels on all our coasts great and small and many lives were lost but the destruction amongst the vessels was such as is very seldom heard of the vast number great and small being lost away and wrecked.</p>
<p>[I have?] seen a vast large account of what they call a work of grace amongst the Baptists, Methodists and Presbyterians. I fear they will fill the world (as Stephen Crisp says) with a sort of Christians that want acceptance with God. And then what is all the profession of religion in the world good for without his acceptance and S. Crisp says their doings has been the downfall of Christianity in the present: it is surprising to think of their great inventions – I believe the Devil does not care how much religion people have if they keep clear of humility and the cross.</p></div>
</body></text>
</TEI>