<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader></teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="A0011529_001"/>
{1817-07}
<div type="entry" when="1817-07-18"><dateline><date when="1817-07-18">1817, 18 of Seventh Month.</date></dateline><p> Harvest two or three weeks later than formerly. Reaping – had eleven hands, and with very hard scrabbling they cut it all down about fourteen acres and on the whole very good.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-07-19"><dateline><date when="1817-07-19">19.</date></dateline><p> We got about two-thirds of it in. A smart shower catched some.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-07-20"><dateline><date when="1817-07-20">20. First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. A very poor, low shut up time. Almost completely overwhelmed with ease, dullness, and indifferency. Hardly deserved the name of a meeting. I pitied the sincere seekers. Getting in our harvest and hay. Weather showery, but we scrabbled and got along very well. Our barn never better filled with grain and choice, good hay.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-07-24"><dateline><date when="1817-07-24">24. Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Very small, people very busy getting in grain and hay. Weather rainy, but yet I believe harvest is generally got in. Our meeting, though low and poor, I thought not destitute of some savor of life and ownings of truth. Came off without condemnation. I have read an account that the persecutors of our first Friends said of them that they would keep up their meetings if their corn dropped in the ground, but they lived and attended their meetings so as to make it answer a good purpose. They pleased the Lord and obtained his favor, and that was enough and far transcended all this world could afford. But they did not tend their meetings in a poor, dry, formal way, nor were they overwhelmed with a spirit of ease and dullness.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-07-28"><dateline><date when="1817-07-28">28. First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. I thought it a very poor, low time, but I don't know, for I was so unwell I could hardly sit meeting. William Ashby of Philadelphia came to see me Seventh Day night and will at meeting and had acceptable service and Ebenezer Roberts, also <persName key="w6wx87x7">my wife</persName> and children, and William Ashby went to a meeting at four at the schoolhouse near the Green Tree Tavern and they say they had a very open, good meeting. Hinchman Hain appointed it and was very large among a people who seldom tend any sort of meeting. I have been twelve months trying to open a door amongst them, and now I hope it will be occupied. This is the 2nd meeting with them. Very busy getting hay and favored to get along, though it goes very hard with me.</p>
<p>[marginal note] I so poorly I could not go with them.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-07-31"><dateline><date when="1817-07-31">Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting I thought to me more lively, open and satisfactory than common. By thee, said David, have I run through a troop and leaped over a wall.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 18:29</note> We have many troops to encounter and walls of opposition.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_002"/>
{1817-08}
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-03"><dateline><date when="1817-08-03">3 of the Eighth Month, 1817. First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Edward Hicks of Newtown, Pennsylvania, was there (the meeting large) and Edward had very great deal to say. Stood, I reckon, more than an hour. A great and powerful preacher, but, oh, the dullness of many hearers! Not as it was at the preaching of Peter, where several thousands were converted at one time and as it was in the days of George Fox, when great numbers were convinced at one meeting and when tenderness and brokenness of heart prevailed so that the tears often trickled down their cheeks and sometime, it is said, the floor was sprinkled with tears like to a sprinkling of rain. However, I thought I seen a tear, which is a great rarity now a days – under the greatest and most powerful preachers we have many frequently sit nodding.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-04"><dateline><date when="1817-08-04">4.</date></dateline><p> On Second Day Edward Hicks had a meeting at Lower Evesham and had a great deal to say. Stood, I suppose, more than a hour.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-05"><dateline><date when="1817-08-05">5. Third Day.</date></dateline><p></date></dateline><p> I went to see an old man and his wife several miles beyond Upper Evesham, found her in a very afflicted condition with the rheumatism. Then down to Upper Evesham meeting. Edward Hicks had a great deal to say, and I thought it ended sweet and savory. Then I went to see Job Chambers, who a few days ago had a loaded wagon with hay run over him – and his life has been much despaired of – but is getting better and to see Susannah Balinger, in a very languishing condition and very low and poor. Then called to see William Glover, afflicted greatly with a rheumatic complaint, a young man with a family.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-06"><dateline><date when="1817-08-06">6.</date></dateline><p> Fourth Day I was at Cropwell with Edward Hicks. He generally stands more than an hour and is very searching. This afternoon at 4th hour we had a meeting at a schoolhouse near the green tree tavern. Edward was very large there also. Then he and his companion Steven Comfort came home with me to lodge.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-07"><dateline><date when="1817-08-07">7.</date></dateline><p> On Fifth Day we were at our Monthly Meeting and I think it was a favored, good meeting and ended savory and well. Edward Hicks and a great deal to say and very searching and pertinent. But alas, poor creatures we are. A little matter
<pb n="A0011529_003"/>
disturbs still water, and as Thomas Ross says, how hard it is to keep right when we are so!<note resp="transcr">in Thomas Wagstaffe, <emph rend="italic">Piety Promoted</emph></note> Trials does come and will come and oh, how a little matter disturbs a quiet mind.</p>
<p>[marginal note] 5. Our son Joseph was here to see us.</p>
<p>[marginal note] S. Dudley died in a short time after.</p>
<p>About a horse at I. C. Lent. We had a sweet time in the company of our friends Edward Hicks and Steven Comfort. I was ready to call him sterling, staunch, steady, standard Steven Comfort. After our Monthly Meeting they went home. A very great rain after some weeks dry weather.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-10"><dateline><date when="1817-08-10">10 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Ann Edwards got home after six weeks, perhaps, out in Pennsylvania. She said a little, and at last the weight fell on me, and I don't know whether I ever stood up in a meeting in more diffidence and fear of myself but through mercy come off with satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-11"><dateline><date when="1817-08-11">11th. Second Day.</date></dateline><p> Very rainy and a very watery aspect at present.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-12"><dateline><date when="1817-08-12">12.</date></dateline><p> Rained all day and all night. A great storm.</p>
<p>John Parrish, my dear old intimate friend, said he sometimes had thoughts in the night which he thought was too good to be lost and used to rise up and get his pocket book and pencil and write in the dark so that he might not forget the subject. How precious are thy thoughts unto me, oh God, and how great are the sum of them. If I should count them, they are more than the sands of the sea. When I awake I am still with thee, said the prophet David.<note resp="transcr">Psalms 139: 118-119</note> Thoughts: third Day morning very rainy. We read of the good remembrancer that was promised should come and would bring all things needful into remembrance. And he said, my sheep hear my voice and follow me.<note resp="transcr">John 10:26-7</note> and the voice of a stranger they will not follow. And again we read in the Old Testament: they shall know how to refuse the evil and choose the good<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 7:16</note> There is a spirit in man and it is the inspiration of the Almighty that giveth them an understanding.<note resp="transcr">Job 32:8</note> Said Elihu, is not this the great thing in religion - to learn, to understand, and distinguish between the voice of the stranger and true teacher and to know how to refuse the evil and choose the good? It seems as if people in common believe these things. See Thomas Chalkley's account: an old woman found him crying and asked what was the matter. He said he did not know without it was because he was a naughty boy. She said, it's the devil tells you so, for you are the best boy in all our street.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_004"/>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-12"><dateline><date when="1817-08-12">12.</date></dateline><p> Eighth Month, 1817. Third day morning very rainy. William Shewen?<note resp="transcr"><emph rend="italic">Counsel to the Christian Traveler</emph></note> says vain thoughts are great troublers of the world and the language of the prophet Jeremiah was: wash thy heart from wickedness that thou mayest be saved. How long shall thy vain thoughts [be] lodged within thee<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 14:4</note> Only observe how that when any alarming calamity approaches, how vain thoughts are turned out and willingness wrought in them to make room for their betters. In the time of the plague in London, it is said, the people were all in tears, and I heard N.S. say when the yellow fever raged in Philadelphia that they might stop and talk with a neighbor in the streets at that time and frequently see the tears run down their cheeks. There, says he, was silent worship. So we read the law of the Lord is sure, enlightening the eyes, the law of the Lord is perfect, converting the soul and making wise the simple.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 19:7</note> Although people are generally so taken up with the crowding cares and [encumbering concerns of this world, very many find no time to consider of nor care nor to prepare for the world to come. Only see how it is, how all worldly concerns sink into an equal nothingness – hardly a name little enough to call them by! Then, as <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says, the cry is a world of gold and of pearl for a little more time when as they had given up all their precious time for a little of this transitory world. Vanity of vanities, all is vanity and vexation of spirit,<note resp="transcr">Ecclesiastes 1:2</note> Solomon.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-14"><dateline><date when="1817-08-14">14.</date></dateline><p> My daughter Abigail and I went to Woodbury Quarterly Meeting with our neighbor, Samuel Church, and Abigail Matlack. It was a very large meeting and divers worthy, able ministers – <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName>, Edward Hicks, Simon Gilum, <persName key="w6gq882n">R. J.</persName>, and E. Hicks – were much shut up, and the labor in the ministry seemed to fall on some of rather smaller gifts – on Simon Gilum, myself and some others. I thought there was something of a solemn, quieting, heavenly nature and it ended savory and well and that thought for business was an open, good time.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_005"/>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-15"><dateline><date when="1817-08-15">15.</date></dateline><p> Were at Youth's meeting at the Woodbury. Service in the ministry fell to the lot of Simon Gilum and myself and some others. Edward Hicks did appear in supplication, and I believe it ended well and to general satisfaction. We dined at John Tathame, Jr., where there was a house full, some aged, middle aged, and youth. My mind was arrested with some thoughts which seemed to me was not altogether for myself. I mentioned it to Simon Gilum, and we had sitting with them and a lively, owning time I believe it was. We lodged at James Cooper's where was a house pretty well filled with Friends, but none appeared concerned to bring back the King. Does not the King of Kings stand still knocking at the door of our hearts? Oh, how seldom we do as well as we might do! I thought the minds of the people wanted to be raised from lower sublunary enjoyments to something more divine and sublime. I thought the ancient language was applicable to us, viz.: lift up your heads, ye doors, and be ye lifted up, ye everlasting gates, and the king of glory shall come in. Who is his King of glory? The Lord of Host, he is King of glory,<note resp="transcr">Psalm 24:7-9</note> and as Azariah testified to the people of Judah and Benjamin and told them the Lord would be with them whilst they were with him and if they sought him he would be found of them, etc..<note resp="transcr">2 Chronicles 15:2</note> Oh, to think of the great offers held out to our acceptance! How shall we escape if we neglect so great salvation?</p>
<p>At this meeting I seen many of my old acquaintances of Salem and between here and there who expressed great gladness and love and respect for me. I thought I never seen the like before; it was affecting almost to tears, the feeling nearness and uniting regard, the expressions of kindness and inviting language, I having been weakly and sickly and confined at home very much for seven years past.</p>
<p>Whilst I was at Woodbury I heard of several remarkable, sorrowful scenes. A few days ago a woman was so frightened with the thunder she went into convulsion fits and died in a very short time and left young children near Woodbury. And in the time of these late great rains and high winds that at Baltimore the floods of water swept off some horses with the families in them and that the arches of the bridge became choked up with rubbish that the flood raised so high as to come up to the second floor of some houses, and some lives were lost. And at Little York the like dreadful accounts and some say fifty drowned and found in Delaware since the storm.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_006"/>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-17"><dateline><date when="1817-08-17">17 of the Eighth Month, 1817, was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Very poor and low forepart, and no wonder! A state of ease and indolence seems to have gained the ascendancy over very many. I thought it would overwhelm all, but at last I ventured and was helped beyond expectation and came off without condemnation, although the waters were very low. The scarcity of bread is for want of labor and the scarcity of water for want of digging. Ann Edwards appeared in prayer, and I thought the meeting ended savory and well at last.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-21"><dateline><date when="1817-08-21">21. Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. The words of the prophet sweetly accompanied my mind; see Psalms 87 and 3rd: glorious things are spoken of thee, oh City of God, and of the apostles. Expressions of the fruit and effects of true religion and the blessed and great attainment of that church and people to whom he wrote his epistle. He tells them they had come to the new and heavenly Jerusalem, to the city of the saints' solemnity, to the church of the firstborn whose names were written in Heaven.<note resp="transcr">Hebrews 12:22-23</note> And are we endured with rational understandings, capacitates, gifts, and talents capable, if rightly improved, to attain to the like blessed experience in some good degree. And how shall we escape if we neglect so great salvation, etc., etc.?<note resp="transcr">Hebrews 2:3</note> The meeting was very small, and in answering the queries there was so much dryness and formality, so much of the creaturely man's part, I had hardly patience enough to bear it, and I fear scraped rather harder than some could well bear. But on the whole, feel pretty well satisfied.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-22"><dateline><date when="1817-08-22">22.</date></dateline><p> This morning I picked up a piece of newspaper dated 15 of August, 1817, <emph rend="italic">Relf's Philadelphia Gazette</emph>, giving accounts of the dreadful distress and destruction of the great floods and inundations of waters occasioned by the late great rains at Washington City, August 13, and at Baltimore and places adjacent - of the destruction of their mills of all sorts and manufactories of all sorts and at Little York. At some places the flood swept away many houses of diver sorts and people in them were crying for help as they floated down the stream on the tops of the houses, and none could help them, but some were taken into boats out of the windows. The damage in mills and manufacture, dams, bridges, etc., can hardly be recovered or estimated.
<pb n="A0011529_007"/>
An account of a dreadful storm in New England and eastward we had a few years ago wherein many lives were lost as at this, and as great destruction in mills and stores. As at this time they say the streets near the scene of this dreadful misfortune are covered with ruins and that this was a terrible visitation of providence and will be too many unfortunate people irretrievable in its consequences. This flood is said to have risen from four to six feet higher than the memorable flood of ‘86. This imperfect sketch is – rely on it – is by no means exaggerated but in truth comes short of a full picture of the distress. So we read, fear ye him who can terribly shake the Earth<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 2:19</note> and whom the clouds, winds, [and] waves of the sea obey. But, alas, what little lasting impression they make and how soon forgotten. Even the destruction of the world by Noah's flood and the destruction of Sodom and the great and mighty acts of the Lord by sword, pestilence, famine, etc., etc., etc., and earthquakes! What vast countries and cities and multitudes of people; many thousand sunk into ruin in a few minutes!</p>
<p>[marginal note] An account also eastward of dreadful destruction by floods of rain. One man, it is said, lost  acres of famous wheat.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-24"><dateline><date when="1817-08-24">24. First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting, pretty large. John Hallock of Egg Harbor (a native of New York government married a poor girl, Lydia, brought up with us) he had very acceptable service and Ann Edwards also, and it was a satisfactory, open time to me. I thought an unusual quiet, stillness, and solemnity attended the meeting.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-28"><dateline><date when="1817-08-28">28. Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. I had a choice to be silent but was not and have no cause to repent it. I believe it was for some one or more I stayed there and lodged at Joseph Matlack's and visited divers of my old acquaintance in the town to satisfaction – some very ancient and some under great affliction, Doctor Stokes and others.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-29"><dateline><date when="1817-08-29">29.</date></dateline><p> Was our select meeting. Although I thought there was a great want of life and power and of the overshadowing of truth, yet on the whole not destitute of it. Something owning and sweetly, uniting and healing, comforting and strengthening to me. My friends owned me.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-30"><dateline><date when="1817-08-30">30. Seventh Day.</date></dateline><p> I went to my son John's to get a plow fitted up in my every dirty dress, not knowing it was their select meeting. But I sat with them, or stood with them, and had good satisfaction. Although I thought the waters were low as to the life and power of truth, there was sweetness and feeling nearness at last.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_008"/>
<div type="entry" when="1817-08-31"><dateline><date when="1817-08-31">31st of the Eighth Month 1817. First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting a very poor, low, dry time – a shut up time like all around, no savor or life. And no wonder idleness so much prevails. As to the outward, with many the scarcity of bread is for want of labor and the scarcity of water for want of digging. Like some we read of who said, I cannot dig and to beg I am ashamed.<note resp="transcr">Luke 16:3</note> To dig too idle and to beg too proud. Yet under in my hearing name of stewards feign would shroud.</p>
<p>As William Hunt once asked the people: children, have you any bread? And told them they were too idle to labor for daily bread and that they looked to him. To be a lazy, idle pack – we may consider how far this is applicable to us.</p></div>
{1817-09}
<div type="entry" when="1817-09-04"><dateline><date when="1817-09-04">4 of the Ninth Month.</date></dateline><p> At our Monthly Meeting, and a precious, sweet one it was to me. Sarah Cressen and Deborah Stuart of Haddonfield were there. Sarah had very open, extensive, acceptable service. She is a sweet singer in Israel<note resp="transcr">2 Samuel 23:1</note> and it seemed to sing some to sleep, but she had very pertinent service. Deborah appeared in prayer and it ended savory and well. The meeting for business also more lively than common and many thought it was a favored good meeting. It was a satisfactory one to me once more.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-09-07"><dateline><date when="1817-09-07">7 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> Asa Matlack and his wife and our daughter Abigail and I went to Cropwell meeting and had no cause to repent it. To me it was as open, owning a time as I remember to have had there, openness and feeling nearness was felt. After meeting we dined at Joseph Evans and sweetly enjoyed one another's company, but into light and trifling a way. We had need to be always on our watch to do as well as we might do, which I think is but seldom.</p>
<p>[marginal note] at Cropwell meeting Jose Coles, an old drunkard, was there, who has took to coming to meeting since we have had these meetings at the Green Tree Tavern and another old confirmed drunkard, they say, often comes.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-09-10"><dateline><date when="1817-09-10">10.</date></dateline><p> At our select meeting at Haddonfield, <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> and others had very lively, acceptable service on the whole. It was a searching, open time. I had some share in the labor to good satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-09-11"><dateline><date when="1817-09-11">11.</date></dateline><p> Was our quarterly meeting. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> was raised in a great eminence. Edwin Atley of Philadelphia and Nathan Yarnall and others had lively service and answering the queries. Life and savor attended and covered us; I had satisfaction and some share in the labor.
<pb n="A0011529_009"/>
1817 What a mercy it is we are thus favored with a living Gospel ministry. There was signs and tokens of the marks of the word of a right spirit. I think evident to and I think they must acknowledge with the Egyptians of [indecipherable] that the finger of God is in it. Very different from [indecipherable] and effects of that spirit amongst the people met together for [indecipherable] learn the arts of war for the defense of the country, when, a few years ago, in their rioting, drinking, and reveling some were killed and some wounded. Like them we read of whose thoughts are thoughts of iniquity; wasting and destruction are in their paths, their feet run to do evil and they make haste to shed blood. But the way of peace they know not.<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 59:7-8</note> Oh, what a mercy it is that our lot is cast among them that know the way of peace and walk in it! Now in these days of great depravity and dissipation among many, oh, how very great is the difference between the company of those skilled in the art of spiritual warfare and those of the carnal murdering spirit! Oh, that we might improve the many precious opportunities and means offered for our help! Or surely will they not militate against us if we do not.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Weather very hot. I was almost exhausted and overcome with the long meeting and hot, dry weather.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-09-14"><dateline><date when="1817-09-14">14th of the Ninth Month was First Day.</date></dateline><p> <persName key="w6wx87x7">My wife</persName>, daughter Hannah, and granddaughter, little Mary, went over Ancocas Creek to see our ancient sister, Hannah Buzby, and cousins at Joseph Wills and were at Ancocas meeting, which forepart seemed poor and low but through unmerited mercy at last was the most open, owning time I ever had there. Oh, how open, sweet, kind, and inviting friends were when we broke up! More so than ever, we enjoyed one another's company amongst our relations in very pleasant conversation in too light a way about worldly matters that did not tend to much profit. None appeared concerned to bring back in the King, who said; Behold I stand at the door.<note resp="transcr">Revelation 3:20</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-09-18"><dateline><date when="1817-09-18">18. Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting (small), Abigail Barker and Margaret Allinson of Burlington were there and had very sweet, acceptable service as I though. Although things seemed low and formal, they, as we, seemed to think, and spoke very prettily on that subject.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_010"/>
<div type="entry" when="1817-09-21"><dateline><date when="1817-09-21">21 of the Ninth Month, 1817, was First Day.</date></dateline><p> I wanted to go to Westfield but was so poorly I thought of giving out going to any meeting, but did get to ours. I poorly. Things felt so poor and low and so much ease and indifferency I feared for a time we should be all overwhelmed in a spirit of ease and dry formality. But after a time ventured to stand up in great weakness and was mercifully helped beyond all expectation and came off with good satisfaction. I thought I had not seen so open a time there latterly. May it humble me.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-09-25"><dateline><date when="1817-09-25">25.</date></dateline><p> Fifth. Instead of going to our meeting, I went to the burial of a black girl about twenty years of age whose parents had lived in this neighborhood and among my relations. She died at Camden at the ferry and they brought her up to Evesham to bury her. It is said she had joined the Roman Catholics in Philadelphia; however, there were a number of women, perhaps a dozen or fifteen, who, when the coffin was let down into the grave, all fell to saying something I could not understand but in a very serious, solemn manner and continued their ceremony near fifteen minutes. There was, I thought, something very serious, savory, solemn, and weighty in it, affecting and trusting. They tell me they were French Negroes of the Roman Catholic religion. At last I had something to say to them and came off pretty well.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-09-28"><dateline><date when="1817-09-28">28. First Day.</date></dateline><p> <persName key="w6wx87x7">My wife</persName> and children went with John Hallock of Egg Harbor and his wife – who was brought up with us and lodged with us – Seventh Day night to Cropwell meeting. The waters seemed low, but through mercy we both had a pretty open time to satisfaction, and I believe it ended savory, lively, and well.</p></div>
{1817-10}
<div type="entry" when="1817-10-01"><dateline><date when="1817-10-01">1 of the Tenth Month, 1817.</date></dateline><p> Having a minute of our Monthly Meeting to visit some meeting in Salem Quarter, I left home. William Evans of Westfield my companion, we traveled near twenty miles this afternoon to his son Enoch and lodged in the evening. A neighbor came there, and we had a very satisfactory time with young people.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-10-02"><dateline><date when="1817-10-02">2nd on Fifth day.</date></dateline><p> [We] were at Upper Greenwich meeting, which was pretty open and satisfactory considering thing are low at that place, as at many other places these days.</p>
<pb n="A0011529_011"/>
<p>We went towards Woolwich or Mullica Hill. Lodged at [missing] Snowdens where Phebe Brown lives, upwards of eighty years, [indecipherable] my old schoolmate under great affliction with something [indecipherable] cancer. They were our old neighbors and exceeding kind. We had [indecipherable] sweet, owning time at parting then went to their meeting [indecipherable] appointed meeting and the house pretty well fill and an open [indecipherable] time it was to general satisfaction, I believe. Dined at Enoch [indecipherable] then went to Woods Town. Lodged at David Davis, whose wife is my near kinswoman and received us with great kindness.</p>
<p>[We] had an appointed meeting there which was to me a time hard getting along, a sort of mortifying labor, as John Woolman expresses it. But several sweet little ministers helped out and it ended pretty well, I believe. This afternoon, Thomas Davis, Sarah Scull and Rebeck Hubbs (my cousin) went with us to visit the county poorhouse, where was a number of most distressed, miserable objects. Some lost their reason and were chained, and some lost their limbs, and some silly, not [no?] common sense, and some lost their reason by fits. We had a meeting with them. T.D., S.S., and R.H. had pertinent matter for the poor distressed creatures, and tenderness even to tears appeared in some that were blind, and I hope it was for the better. I forgot in its place we had with some young people at David Davis' at parting, a very sweet, tendering time. We left them pretty plentifully bathed in tears. Elizabeth Lippincott, a very hopefully young minister, and Sarah Scull and Rebeckah Hubbs had very sweet service. From the poorhouse we went home with Joseph Bassit, who had come up to Woodstown on purpose to take us to his house to lodge, where were very kindly received.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-10-05"><dateline><date when="1817-10-05">5th was First Day.</date></dateline><p> We went to Salem meeting, a very large house and well filled, where I had an open, owning time for more than an hour, like a full flowing tide. We dined at Jonas Freesland's, a friend in good esteem, where at parting we had a sweet, owning time with his children. Then [we] called to see a widow and her daughter Phebe Miller, an old acquaintance, a native of our parts. There we had a very satisfactory time at parting, the widow being very weakly and not able to get out to meeting. Then we went to Jame Den's (to lodge at Alloways Creek), whose wife is a sweet minister and an old acquaintance. We were at their meeting, an appointed one, which my companions think was a very good meeting, but I thought it not so open as some others were.</p>
<pb n="A0011529_012"/>
<p>[indecipherable] came home with Joseph Bassit to lodge, who very [indecipherable] accompanied us to Alloway Creek in the morning. At parting Joseph proposed calling his children together and we had a satisfactory [indecipherable] parting. Then we came up to Asa Kerby's. At Penn's next day, were at an appointed meeting, there where I was much disappointed. Having been there some years ago and found things so very poor and low, I went there with reluctance. But my mind was now replenished with a hope and some apprehensions of a revival of life, that I had and open, owning, satisfactory time to general satisfaction, I believe. At parting at Asa Kerby's we had a very tendering time with a young woman. Several women friends about Piles Grove and Salem told me the tendering impression they had received when they were children in opportunities or sittings in their fathers' houses 30 or more years ago, when I used to attend Salem Quarterly Meeting, and the words that I had expressed had made lasting impression on their minds. And now several of them become grandmothers and useful members of society and one of them a minister in good esteem. But in some families where our lots were cast, there seemed to be no room for any such thing as a religious opportunity. But I observed that if the discourse turned on worldly affairs – fatting of cattle, telling how many bushels of wheat they had raised on an acre, and other grain, and how many hundred pounds of flax they had on an acre – then I found they were in their element, very wise and knowing about worldly business. And the world had opened her mouth and swallowed them up like the briars and thorns choked the good seed<note resp="transcr">Matthew 13:22</note> and as to religion they were become as dwarfs, mopes, and cripples besotted. We came from Asa Hirbey's up to Woodbury, lodged at Samuel Micles.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Doctor Stokes was buried while I was at Salem, aged 5 [indecipherable] died of the dropsy. Supported a good character as a doctor [indecipherable].</p>
<p>Fifth day, 9th of the Tenth Month. We were at Woodbury Monthly Meeting, at which, through mercy, I was helped and strengthened beyond expectation, having been so unwell I could eat neither breakfast nor dinner. So we got through fully according to prospect and I believe parted with our friends with an evidence of the ownings of truth and feeling nearness and uniting regard, and got well home to my house after meeting and found all well, all of which mercies call for humble gratitude and dedication of heart. At Penn's Neck and Piles Grove there is a dreadful alarm with mad dogs, which have bit many creatures and some people.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_013"/>
<div><dateline><date when="1817-10-12">12th of the Tenth Month, 1817.</date></dateline><p> First day at our meeting which I thought was attacked with an easeful lukewarm spirit so [indecipherable] if it would overwhelm and swallow up all. I felt the attack [indecipherable] with the feeling infirmities of old age, but as I endeavor [indecipherable] to struggle and labor against it, was mercifully helped at [indecipherable] and had an open, owning, strengthening time to good satisfaction. This day we heard of three burials: Deborah Stuart of Haddonfield, a worthy, sweet minister of an unblemished character about seventy; and Esther Venable of Moorestown, a widow upwards of eighty; and William Rowlands of Vincentown, a most miserable drunkard [who] left a wife and family of children. And a young man came up from Philadelphia to Moorestown, went with others in a party of pleasuring, got to diverting themselves with a large swing in the time of meeting when that worthy able minister Joseph Hoag from New England was at Moorestown. The young man got a fall and, it is said, cracked his skull so that he lay some days speechless and his life yet despaired of. And at or near the same time a man and woman was drowned at Philadelphia and several more narrowly escaped drowning through some mismanagement getting on the steamboat.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-10-16"><dateline><date when="1817-10-16">16. Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. I went with a hope and willingness to have a silent meeting. There were divers strangers, young doctors. I felt an exercise and knew not for who it was. One of these young doctors, a comely young man, had give way to excess in drink, and – as I was told after – somewhat alarmed with the sudden death of the youth killed with the swing, who we now hear is dead. I had something for them, but not (as I thought) with that strength and ability as I have been favored with latterly. However, not much cause of complaint. The young doctors, though several quite strangers, got round me and seemed very respectful. I am told that they think Deborah Stuart's death was occasioned by a fall in the street near her own door. She fell with her breast on the root of a tree and hurt her very much. One would think her situation as much out of danger as any, but strange to think how accidents happen which no care or precaution of ours can prevent, and the many ways that bring people to their end.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_014"/>
<div type="entry" when="1817-10-19"><dateline><date when="1817-10-19">[indecipherable] Tenth Month, 1817. Was First Day.</date></dateline><p> Mary Witchel of Frankfort, Pennsylvania, (a native of England) was there and had very acceptable service, and I thought a savor of truth attended, and which them that knew not what it was, must have had a sense of. </p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-10-23"><dateline><date when="1817-10-23">23. Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Though small, was a lively, strengthening one to me, tending to unite to the wise in heart. Although in general, as far as I can hear, it is and has been a very healthy season, yet we almost daily hear the language of mortality sounded in our ears. We now hear of the very sudden death of James Wood, middle-aged, a wealthy man near Haddonfield. It is thought he died with an apoplectic fit. And of the death of Samuel Key, near Haddonfield, a very hard drinker in the midst of his days – left a widow and children. And at the same time of the death of a black young woman at Moorestown. Thus the ancient decree, almost as old as the creation – dust thou art and unto dust shalt thou return<note resp="transcr">Genesis 3:19</note> – we see an almost daily fulfilling. And to take a view of the bulk of mankind as a family at large, it is said that many are dropping into eternity every minute. And as Daniel Stanton said on hearing of the death of a friend, our time is a coming. And Thomas Ross once said, when he heard of the death of Mordecai Yarnall, a worthy minister, well, says he, repeating it over and over, Mordecai is gone; by and by we shall be gone. And as Sarah Gissum once said, if we can but get to a better place when we are done with this world it will do. But, oh, how prone we are to be too careless about that.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-10-26"><dateline><date when="1817-10-26">26. First Day. </date></dateline><p>At our meeting open, but not all together as satisfactory as some. Something wanting, somewhere, somehow. A great thing to keep clear of self gathering corn and so forth.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-10-30"><dateline><date when="1817-10-30">30.</date></dateline><p> Was Fifth. Silent as to me, but E.R. and Ann E. had lively service. A very great rain, the greatest fresh we have had a considerable time.</p></div>
{1817-11}
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-02"><dateline><date when="1817-11-02">2.</date></dateline><p> Eleventh Month, First Day. At our meeting. Very large, full, crowded. Daniel Haviland from Nine Partners, State of New York was there and was very large in testimony and to general satisfaction, I believe. He was here with us and at our house about 18 years ago, aged about 71 now.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_015"/>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-06"><dateline><date when="1817-11-06">6 of the Eleventh Month. Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting. Something of a heavenly quiet, as I thought. On the whole it was a satisfactory time to me throughout, although there was two cases concerning worldly interest, which I thought hurt the life and savor, which I think money matters always do when they get into our meeting. All very wise and knowing in their things and they can gabble about them as if they were at market or vendue if they can say nothing about things of a more spiritual nature.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-13"><dateline><date when="1817-11-13">13. Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> We went to the burial of Thomas Bishop, a relation to <persName key="w6wx87x7">My wife</persName>. He lay about one week very ill with the gravel, an innocent, orderly, inoffensive man. The people conducted very orderly, and it was cordial and comfortable to see so much of a Christian like spirit in attending him in his illness and at the burial. But yet it seemed to me it was too much in the spirit of Martha of old, to whom Christ said, Martha, Martha thou art careful about many things; one thing is needful.<note resp="transcr">Luke 10:41-2</note>]  . And the mind not enough turned towards the better part which Mary had choice, of which should never be taken from her that so we might know more of the evidence and ownings of truth and the savor of life and the great Master's presence amongst us at these solemn seasons. In thy presence, said David, is fullness of joy, etc.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 16:11</note> I came off middling well, well satisfied.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-16"><dateline><date when="1817-11-16">16. Was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting and had no cause to repent being there, but sweetly satisfactory to think of it on my pillow. We went to see two sick neighbors. At the last, something owning and uniting and satisfactory, but all the day was not as I could wish. Oh, how great a thing it is to keep clear of every spot or stain, wrinkle or any such thing! The subject was concerning honesty, seriousness, and sincerity. And it remains to be true there is that scattereth and yet increaseth, etc..<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 11:24</note></p>
<p>Fourth Day. 19. Amos Peasley of New England (who was with us some month ago) appointed a meeting at Moorestown which was pretty large, and I thought he did famously and worthily. A large door of utterance, but I thought a door of entrance was much wanting. Powerful preachers and dull hearers, not like it was when three thousand was converted at the preaching of Peter and when hundreds were convinced at one meeting in the days of George Fox and <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> when there was often much tenderness and contrition, but now more frequently dullness and drowsiness and sleeping instead of weeping under the most powerful ministers. A great rarity to see a tear or tokens of tenderness.</p>
<p>[marginal note] But they seem to think nothing of going any further.</p>
<pb n="A0011529_016"/>
<p>Plenty makes dainty and the full stomach loathes the honeycomb.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 27:7</note> As Daniel Stanton said when he was told how the people at Moorestown was pleased with his preaching and wished he lived there to be there every First Day – how glad they should be to go to hear him - ah, said he, I reckoned it would soon be like an old song. And as George Fox said when the people of New England was so taken with his preaching they began to consult together to hire him to stay with them to preach to them, he said it was time for him to be gone. But when he seen people at their meetings settled down in solemn silence with their minds turned towards the Lord, then he said they were finally settled in the truth.</p>
<p>This morning we heard of a dismal accident or scene of sorrow. A lad about 18 years of age lived with our neighbor Joseph Hugg, got up about 2 o'clock at night to help his master get ready to go to market. His master got up about fifteen minutes after him and found him on the fire, burnt to death. He carried him to the pump to put out the fire on his clothes but could perceive little or no signs of life. He was subject to fits and had fell in the fire once before, but they pulled him out so that he received no hurt, only singed his hair.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-20"><dateline><date when="1817-11-20">20.</date></dateline><p> I went to the burial of this young man that was burnt to death. The family in which he lived were not members of our society nor the people gathered, but they conducted soberly, orderly, and well, and I had an open time with them with which one of the near relations of the deceased expressed satisfaction. At the grave I had a few sentences to good satisfaction. We heard of two burials this day at Moorestown, a man and a young woman. Although it is counted a very healthy season in general, both in city and country, yet we hear of deaths almost daily or very frequently.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-23"><dateline><date when="1817-11-23">23. First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting Lidia Lippincott and Ann Edwards appeared lively and savory, yet I thought it a low time, however. Too low for me to venture, though am doubtful I missed it and am not alone, for one expressed a secret sense of the same thing.</p>
<p>Fourth Day. Went to see our kinsfolks William Hooton and went to see John Hollen, a poor man who has a cancer lately increased to an alarming degree.</p>
<p>Fifth Day. At our meeting. </p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-06"><dateline><date when="1817-11-06">6.</date></dateline><p> At our select [meeting]. Pretty well.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-30"><dateline><date when="1817-11-30">30. First Day.</date></dateline><p> I went to Cropwell meeting a time of low water and scarcity. For want of labor I found it hard getting along, yet it felt pleasant to look over the day. I took a young doctor lately come amongst us or he took me, and we went to see the man with the cancer, and I took him some little things.</p>
<p>Twelfth Month, Third Day. <persName key="w6hj799d">Elizabeth Collins</persName>, my old fellow traveler in visiting families, came to see us with <persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Collins</persName> and others and we did not talk ourselves poor – a rarity and satisfactory.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_017"/>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-04"><dateline><date when="1817-11-04">4th of the Twelfth Month, 1817.</date></dateline><p> See [Robert Proud's] <emph rend="italic">History of Pennsylvania</emph>, volume 2, <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn's</persName> letter, page 4th, expressing a desire to glorify God in our bodies, souls and spirits, in temporal or eternal affairs, being indeed none of our own. For as much as we are our own, we are none of the Lords. A great mystery, but a great truth, and of absolute necessity to witness. To be of the number of the chosen nation, the peculiar people and royal priesthood of Christ and his glorious Kingdom. Oh my friends, let all below this keep on the left hand and wait to feel those blessings or blessed things to inherit right hand, etc., etc.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-05"><dateline><date when="1817-11-05">5.</date></dateline><p> I went to their select meeting at Cropwell. Although the waters seemed low, yet there is a precious remnant, a little seed and I believe we were somewhat comforted and strengthened together. John Haines and wife, elders came here and lodged with us, and we went Sixth Day to our Monthly Meeting, which I think was an open, owning, lively time, especially forepart something savory.</p>
<p>Seventh Day. I went to Evesham Monthly Meeting, where I found Daniel Lukens and wife of Pennsylvania, Chester County. His wife is a lively minister and had good service and also Ann Edwards, both had very acceptable service. An owning, solemn time. Mary Lukins was my companion when I visited the families of their meeting. They went to Upper Evesham Monthly Meeting.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Very cold freezing weather.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-07"><dateline><date when="1817-11-07">7 of the Month First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Ann Edwards had an open favored time.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-10"><dateline><date when="1817-11-10">10 of the Month.</date></dateline><p> At our select meeting, there was a number of strangers, many lively ministers who had open. Lively service. </p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-11"><dateline><date when="1817-11-11"><dateline><date when="1817-11-11">11</date></dateline><p> was our quarterly meeting at Evesham.</date></dateline> There were many worthy, lively young ministers who had very open, lively service. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> concluded with a very solemn, powerful prayer, and it was thought these meetings were crowned with the evidence of the owners of truth. Betsey Purington of New England, Samuel Rhodes of Darby, Simon Gillum and divers others of Pennsylvania and Philadelphia. The largest meeting ever seen there, perhaps, and as solemn and orderly as I ever seen there.</p>
<p>There was a solemnity, savor, and sweetness in the silent part that strengthened a hope that we were advancing towards that state which is better and beyond words, which is the end of all good words or gospel ministry: the superior excellency of the Christian religion, which is a communion with Christ.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-13"><dateline><date when="1817-11-13"><dateline><date when="1817-11-13">Seventh Day.</date></dateline><p> 13.</date></dateline> Killed our hogs, about 1,000 wt.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_018"/>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-14"><dateline><date when="1817-11-14">14th of the Twelfth Month, 1817, was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Sarah King and E. Collins and Lydia Lippincott and several others appeared lively and savory. A satisfactory meeting to me, although I was so unwell in the morning I thought I could not go out. But concluded it was better to wear away than to rust away, so wearied along and went this afternoon at 3 hour to a meeting at the schoolhouse near the Green Tree Tavern, among a people that seldom ever attend any place of worship, for whom I have some time past been thinking of and have endeavored to stir up others to think of them and have opened the door for laborers and divers strangers. A little back Edward Hicks, Joseph Hoag of New England, and Betsey Purinton, and Mary Witchell, and others. Ann Edwards appointed this meeting and desired me to go with her, which I did and had no cause to repent it, for this day's work afforded me satisfaction on my pillow. Ann Edwards has now got liberty to visit this people in their families, forty or fifty families, perhaps, in that neighborhood in the compass of two or three miles.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-16"><dateline><date when="1817-11-16">16.</date></dateline><p> I was invited to the burial of an old Negro woman but did not go. Weather cold and I not very well.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-18"><dateline><date when="1817-11-18">18. Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting strengthening. As <persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Collins</persName> used to say, if we are but favored, we fear no colors, and as Thomas Gawthrop said, you may think this strange doctrine, but, Tom, don't mind that as long as his master stands by. I felt as if I was not afraid of being had up.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-21"><dateline><date when="1817-11-21">21. First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Most extreme cold freezing weather and through mercy I believe it ended savory and well. About two weeks ago it was so cold and freezing it set the boys a skating, but it growed warmer and broke up all the ice till now. It as cold and freezing as is commonly known here. It has, till now, been a very fine, moderate Fall. We have foddered our cattle but very little till now within a few a few days. About three or four days before what is called Christmas.
<pb n="A0011529_019"/>
Twelfth Month 28. Was First Day. At our meeting. John Hallock and <persName key="w6hj799d">Elizabeth Collins</persName>, both of Egg Harbor, were there and had savory acceptable service. Last First Day was a very remarkable cold freezing time; the river was froze up and lay fast some days. But it has been now several days past very fine and moderate. We have not had any snow yet to cover the ground more than a common white frost.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1817-11-29"><dateline><date when="1817-11-29">29.</date></dateline><p> Very fine, warm moderate weather [for] several days.</p></div>
{1818-01}
<div type="entry" when="1818-01-01"><dateline><date when="1818-01-01">1st of the First Month 1818 and Fifth of the week.</date></dateline><p> at our meeting, which was and open, strengthening one to me. Weather very fine and moderate. I hear that several have got their feet badly frozen [during] last cold spell and in divers places a great alarm of mad dogs. About Moorestown and divers other places, it is said, divers people have been bit by mad dogs and other creatures, hogs and other creatures. Our neighbor S.C. lost two hogs [to] mad dogs.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-01-04"><dateline><date when="1818-01-04">4. First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting pretty full and through unmerited mercy it ended lively, savory and well. Sweetness and feeling nearness appeared after it broke up. I went to a meeting at the schoolhouse near the Green Tree Tavern at 3 hour appointed by Ann Edwards (who is now engaged in visiting families there away). Ann sent word she wished me to meet her there, and I hope the meeting was for the better and ended savory and well. Very moderate, fine weather.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-01-07"><dateline><date when="1818-01-07">7.</date></dateline><p> On Fourth day Betsey Purrington from New England appointed a meeting at Moorestown, which I thought forepart was very poor and low, but it grew better, and she had acceptable, savory service, and it ended solid and well.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-01-08"><dateline><date when="1818-01-08">8.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting, and it was a downright lively, open, favored time throughout. It made me think of an account of Friends in early times; it is said friends met at a meeting for discipline and there was so much of the stirrings of life that one stood up after another till they were forced to adjourn the meeting. It seem they were not ruled by form, nor did they limit the spirit.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-01-11"><dateline><date when="1818-01-11">11. First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Rebecka Burr of Mount Holly had lively, acceptable service and Joseph Justice also, so I thought it ended pretty savory.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-01-14"><dateline><date when="1818-01-14">14.</date></dateline><p> Now is the first snow so as to cover the ground so as to track a fox, and seven men on horseback rode through our place and hunting hounds with them. I think it is a great pity they were not better disposed and employed.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_020"/>
<div type="entry" when="1818-01-15"><dateline><date when="1818-01-15">15 of the First Month, 1818. Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Small. There was great plenty of words among us, but I thought a want of savor and life which only and alone can give satisfaction and true consolation. It is an easy matter for us to tend meeting and not for the better – but, oh, how deep in guilt, how ignominious the fault! A teacher throned in pomp of words. Dr. [Edward] Young [resignation] in deeds beneath the taught – again unto the wicked the Lord saith: what hast thou to do to declare my word or that thou shouldst take my covenant in thy mouth seeing thou hatest instruction and casts it behind thee.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 50:16-17</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-01-17"><dateline><date when="1818-01-17">17.</date></dateline><p> I went to see John Hollen, a poor man with a dismal cancer on his temple and eye. Divers others have now dreadful cancers. Simeon Ellis and Benjamin Bispham and divers round about have of latter years died with cancers. And what is worse, if possible, several have lost their reason. Nathan Yarnal of Philadelphia – a well approved young minister, I hear – they talk of taking him to the asylum newly erected for such who lose their reason, and James Frinch's wife also quite crazy. See the scenes of sorrow and humbling circumstances and solemn calls.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-01-18"><dateline><date when="1818-01-18">18. First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. I thought it was a good, favored, open, owning time, I believe to general satisfaction. Oh, what a mercy! Winter-like: stormy, cold, freezing, some rain, hail, and a little snow.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-01-22"><dateline><date when="1818-01-22">22. Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Several were pretty open, but not me.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-01-25"><dateline><date when="1818-01-25">25.</date></dateline><p> First Day we went to Evesham – an open, highly favored time. Spent the afternoon with our son John and choice grandchildren. There was openness, sweetness, and feeling nearness when we came out.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-01-27"><dateline><date when="1818-01-27">27.</date></dateline><p> A very great rain; stormy weather, but not cold.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-01-29"><dateline><date when="1818-01-29">29.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting, which was sweet and satisfactory to me some clothing. Several days [of] very severe cold weather.</p></div>
{1818-02}
<div type="entry" when="1818-02-01"><dateline><date when="1818-02-01">1st of the Second Month. First Day.</date></dateline><p> Very cold. I was at a stand about going to meeting, but did get there and had no cause to repent it. Such an open, owning time I [have] seldom, if ever, seen there. When we got home, the query was: what made you stay so long, what kept you so late? Evidently helped and strengthened. meeting pretty full. This was the first snow to set sleighs a running.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_021"/>
<div type="entry" when="1818-02-05"><dateline><date when="1818-02-05">5 of the Second Month, 1818.</date></dateline><p> Weather more moderate. Was [at] our Monthly Meeting, which I thought was pretty open and lively, although it was not so satisfactory as some to me. I was poorly with a heavy cold, but I thought there was not much cause of complaint and that both sittings ended sweet, savory, solid, and well.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-02-08"><dateline><date when="1818-02-08">8 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. It was a mortifying time to me, and perhaps good and needful for me. Thy rod and thy staff hath sustained, said the prophet David.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 23:4</note> Humbling. We have had now several days very severe cold weather, none more so this winter.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-02-12"><dateline><date when="1818-02-12">12. Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Weather more moderate. Some life, some salt, some cloathing [clothing], some satisfaction. We are informed that John Braddock and Levi Lippincott, both of Evesham, were lately struck with the palsy and several others very much wounded by accidents. Joshua Lippincott with a very bad cut and Joseph Coles with a bad fall – broke his thigh. Very cold again. We heard about this time of the death of Abigail Stokes at Burlington. She was struck with the palsy and died very suddenly. [She] was once an overseer of our meeting, a daughter of William and Hannah Foster. Had a mortifying humbling pilgrimage. Oh, the scenes of sorrow all round us! James Frinch: his wife very crazy, kept chained, and a number others in her condition.</p>
<p>Fifth Day. At our preparative meeting. Lively words enough and some pertinent remarks, yet need of improvement in solidity, depth, and weight. Snow storm and cold.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-02-22"><dateline><date when="1818-02-22">22. First Day.</date></dateline><p> Abraham Hibbern of Goshen in Pennsylvania there and had very savory, acceptable service. Savor and solidity attended to general satisfaction, I believe. What a mercy continued.</p>
<p>Fifth Day. At our meeting: Learn not the way of the heathen.<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 10:2</note> Satisfactory.</p>
<p>Sixth Day our select meeting. Our daughter Abigail went with me for the first time. Some thought it a favored, lively time to select meeting. Not fully so to me; rough work not the pleasantest, but sometimes necessary. We hear that an ancient woman went to warm her cape and it catched fire and set her clothes on fire and burnt so that she soon died (Sarah King's mother at Slabtown, 4 miles above [Mount] Holley).</p>
<p>[marginal note] I think four old women have been burnt to death now within a few years.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_022"/>
{1818-03}
<div type="entry" when="1818-03-01"><dateline><date when="1818-03-01">1 of the Third Month, 1818. First day.</date></dateline><p> Quite warm, road very [indecipherable]. At our meeting and to me I thought it was an owning, favored time; something that cast out fear. This afternoon we went to the burial of our neighbor, Benjamin Williamson's wife (died sudden with a stroke of palsy). They had their Baptist minister there and high doings preaching, and singing of psalms, prayers, etc. Some thought there was some salt, savor, and life, but if it was so, it was all hid from me. Yet I thought it was an instructing time to me, under a feeling sense of the difference between ability which truth gives and the want of it. Our meeting last First Day did not leave a comfortless, mortifying remembrance, but quite otherwise. A very great storm of rain and at last considerable snow and cold weather. Very changeable from warm to cold.</p>
<p>Fifth Day. At our Monthly Meeting and I think I [have] seldom, if ever, seen a more lively, evidently owning a time. From first to last answering queries there was great openness for labor, and very many very pertinent remarks were made and savor and life attended. Is it not a wonder, every thing considered, that we should be thus followed and favored in the first part? I had an evident, owning, favored time. Oh, how it calls for humility!</p>
<p>Fourth Day last, that violent stormy day, Solomon Sanders near Cropwell was buried. [He was] in the midst of his days [and] left a family, wife and children. Few, if any, have exceeded him in the improvements of worldly affairs. As the partridge sitteth on eggs and hatcheth them not, so he that getteth rich and not by right shall leave them in the midst of his days and in the end become a fool.<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 17:11</note> He was a very industrious, moral man.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-03-09"><dateline><date when="1818-03-09">9 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> We went to Evesham meeting. My sins are ever before me, said David.<note resp="transcr">Psalms 51:3</note> It was a mortifying time forepart, and I was very desirous do right, either to suffer in silence or otherwise. But at last was evidently helped and an open, owning time it was. The meeting was large and some there that seldom come, who showed very pleasant and very respectful.</p>
<p>Went to see our daughter-in-law, Ann, brought to bed with a daughter.</p>
<p>[marginal note] I told one of our elders he looked pleasant. I believed I had not displeased him this time; he said, not one bit.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_023"/>
<div type="entry" when="1818-03-11"><dateline><date when="1818-03-11">11 of the Third Month, 1818.</date></dateline><p> My daughter Abigail went with me to our select quarterly meeting at Haddonfield (for the first time), which was smaller than common. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> was favored to speak most excellently and Thomas Kite, a young minister of Philadelphia. But it proved to be a very mortifying, stripping time to me, but perhaps needful and profitable. It is a great thing to bear prosperity unhurt, either temporal or spiritual.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-03-12"><dateline><date when="1818-03-12">12.</date></dateline><p> We went – that is, all the family (except our black hired man) – to quarterly meeting, which was very large. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> was raised again in great eminence to preach very powerful, and in the last meeting it was an healing, satisfactory time to me. So here I experienced the difference between peace of mind and the want of it. Restore me to the joy of thy salvation and uphold me by thy free spirit, said the prophet,<note resp="transcr">Psalms 51:12</note> none else can. Heard of the death of Cornwell Sevenson, an elder of Burlington Quarter, a choice, innocent friend. [He] left a widow and family of children middle aged. Short illness, something like the typhus fever, of which there seems to be divers instances creeping about of late.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-03-15"><dateline><date when="1818-03-15">15. Was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. An open, owning time, I believe. To general satisfaction as far as I could see. If our hearts condemn us not, then have we confidence towards God, etc. But if our hearts condemn us, he is greater.<note resp="transcr">1 John 3:20-21</note> A wounded conscience who can bear,<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 18:14</note> bear? If we can keep a conscience void offence towards God and man<note resp="transcr">Acts 24:16</note> the whole world cannot condemns us.<note resp="transcr">Stephen Crisp</note> But if our conscience condemn us, the whole world cannot justify us; so great is that judge. And as Habakkuk says, though the fields should yield no meat, yet will I rejoice in the Lord.<note resp="transcr">Habakkuk 3:17</note> And as [John] Hoiland say, the righteous fear not the crush of worlds and as Seneca says, if the earth should open her mouth and show them all the secrets of the infernal pit, they would look down upon them without dismay. Abraham Gibbens said in my hearing he had seen a state wherein death was no more terror than to put of one suit of clothes and put on another, or to go out of one room [and] into another. And William Hunt said when the mind had passed through the necessary baptism, there was not much for the fear of death to lay hold of. Oh blessed and glorious experience, how far it transcends all this world can afford! Remember Mary Dyer and thousands of martyrs.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Daniel in the lion's den, Shadrack in the furnace.<note resp="transcr">Daniel 6 and 3</note></p>
<pb n="A0011529_024"/>
<p>William Law says conscience is God's (vice-regent for judge). When we do right and do well, we find acceptance and justification. Our conscience justifies us when we do well; when we do not do well, it condemns.
<l>Conscience unpleasant truths may tell</l>
<l>But mark her sacred lessons well:</l>
<l>They that live with her at strife,</l>
<l>Parts with their better friend for life.</l></p>

<p>Will it not be our greatest friend or greatest enemy? A wounded conscience who can bear? As to a clear conscience, one says it is the best estate, and again:
<l>The music and the mirth of Kings</l>
<l>Is out of tune unless she sings.</l>
<l>Then close thine eyes and sleep secure:</l>
<l>No peace like thine, non left so sure.</l>
<l>A quiet Conscience is the best,</l>
<l>Has only peace, has only rest.</l>
<l>The music and the mirth of kings</l>
<l>Is out of tune unless she sings.</l>
<l>Then close thine eyes and sleep secure:</l>
<l>No rest like thine, no sleep so sure.</l>
<note resp="transcr">From a popular poem called “A Quiet Conscience,” sometimes (most likely erroneously) attributed to King Charles I</note></p>

<p>But how is it, on the other hand, when we miss it and do not do well? Then I know how it is with me; I remember the command of the angel was curse ye (or condemn). Meroz, said the angel of the Lord, curse ye bitterly the inhabitants thereof because they come not up to the help of the Lord, to the help of the Lord against the mighty.<note resp="transcr">Judges 5:23</note> This I have often to do through the abounding frailties and infirmities.
<l>He is more a prince that rules himself</l>
<l>Than he who nations keeps in awe.</l>
<l>Who yields to that which doth their souls convince</l>
<l>Shall never need another law.</l>
<note resp="transcr">From the poem “The Soul” by Katherine Philips (1632-1664), first published in 1667</note>
He that ruleth his spirit is stronger than he thought taketh a city, says Solomon.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 16:32</note>
<l>Long have I sought the wish</l>
<l>Of all true happiness to find,</l>
<l>Which some will wealth and some will pleasures call</l>
<l>And some a virtuous mind.</l>
<l>What cannot resignation do?</l>
<l>It wonders can perform;</l>
<l>That powerful charm, “thy will be done,”</l>
<l>Can lay the loudest storm.</l>
<note resp="transcr">Edward Young, “Resignation”</note></p>

<p>I do solemnly declare that after seeking happiness for years in the schools of the learned, in the philosophy of ages, and in the pleasures of the worlds, I found her not till I became acquainted with this pure and vital principal. Dillwyn last page.</p>
<p>[marginal note] He that makes conscience his counselor will find it his comforter when all of them stand aloof or fail, yea, everlasting life.</p>
<p>[marginal note] He that would have the comforter must receive the reprover, says Isaac Pennington</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_025"/>
<div type="entry" when="1818-03-14"><dateline><date when="1818-03-14">14 Third Month, 1818. Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Not satisfactory but rather a mortifying time, yet I thought deeply instructing. All fair weather is not best; pruning and purging necessary.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-03-22"><dateline><date when="1818-03-22">22. First Day.</date></dateline><p> My daughter Hannah went with me to Easton meeting, which is but a small, little, poor meeting and great indifferency, ease, and indolence prevailing there (as is most other places). I was desirous to do right there – if it should be best to suffer in silence with the seed under oppression – but at last was helped and had a very open, satisfactory time. A few days ago Joseph Moor's House in Evesham (which was large) was burnt down from a spark of the chimney and some goods burnt in it. And near the same time, we hear that the Powder House at Wilmington caught fire and blowed up a great quantity of power in it. It is said thirty persons were killed in it. The sounds of the explosion was heard by divers here in Jersey.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Stormy</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-03-23"><dateline><date when="1818-03-23">23.</date></dateline><p> We hear of the death of Hannah Fish, wife of John Fish, a few years ago our nearest neighbor, died at [indecipherable]. A distant relation to <persName key="w6wx87x7">my wife</persName> [and] left a number of children: two sons, almost men, grown and silly, no common sense, and a young child a few weeks old. A very innocent, industrious couple. She was very much out of her senses several weeks before she died. Now to think of and see the scenes of heart piercing sorrow, the heavy strokes on families and individuals almost daily all round us, these solemn awful calls. One would think, if we seriously considered, if our hearts were not as hard as the nether millstone or the adamant stone, they would serve as serious calls to a devout and holy life. Call after call, after divers ways and divers manners as in days of old.</p>
<p>Heard of the death of Joseph Hoag of New England, a worthy minister. [He] was here whilst I was down at Salem, so I did not see him. His wife and several children, ministers low in circumstances, but very cheerful and seemed to have a sense of his end being near. Died soon after he got home.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_026"/>
<div type="entry" when="1818-03-26"><dateline><date when="1818-03-26">26 of the Third Month, 1818 was Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our preparative meeting. Small, [though] not altogether destitute of some savor and life. But, oh, how very little of that to what it might be if we were not wanting on our part! It seems to have come to this: to be considered a high degree of religion and piety, to keep clear of gross enormities and to lead a moral life, even although they know no more of the life of God in the soul than a sheep. Be ye not as the horse or the mule that hath no understanding, said the prophet David.<note resp="transcr">Psalms 32:9</note> And see Memorials [1787], Sarah Morris's words: if they can but live in prosperity and keep clear of gross evils they sit down at ease and conclude all is well, but, oh, that they may find out their mistake before it is too late. Some snow.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-03-29"><dateline><date when="1818-03-29">29. Was First Day.</date></dateline><p> My neighbor same church went with me to Westfield meeting, which was the most evidently owning, open time I ever seen there, I believe. Oh, how pleasant all seemed when we came out! Inviting kindness, sweetness, openness, and feeling nearness. But, Oh, how great a thing it is to keep right!
<l>If I am right thy grace impart</l>
<l>Still in the right to stay.</l>
<l>If I am wrong, Oh, teach my heart</l>
<l>To find the better way.</l><note resp="transcr">From the poem “Universal Prayer” by Alexander Pope</note></p>
<p>When we are so, let me remember the mortifying time I had just before this meeting.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-03-28"><dateline><date when="1818-03-28">28.</date></dateline><p> Hannah and I went to the burial of John Hollen, 72. He died with a cancer on his temple, which spread over one side of his face [and] got into his mouth and throat, and it was some weeks difficult for him to eat, and it is likely he starved to death at last, as I believe many have done with that disorder. The people behaved very still, sober, and well, and I had satisfaction with them, especially at the grave. They owned me, and I believe there was something of an evidence of the ownings of truth, and I came off with right good satisfaction. At Cole's Church, as it is called.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_027"/>
{1818-04}
<div type="entry" when="1818-04-02"><dateline><date when="1818-04-02">2nd of the Fourth Month, 1818, was Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Came off pretty well satisfied, but great room and need for improvement. I have my trials, the wormwood and the gall to partake of. No longer watch, no longer safe, nor then neither; except the Lord keep the city the watchman waketh but in vain.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 127:1</note> We now hear of latter time a great many instances of people breaking or falling greatly in debt, bankruptcies of one breaking in debt and breaking and plunging others and their families in difficulty and poverty and divers who made a very great show. Diverse who were thought and thought themselves prospered of a great deal of worldly wealth, riches, and earthly treasure and who had pursued earthly treasure in a very large, extensive manner. Yet things have turned out so that divers of these will not have enough to pay their debts. Some forced to go to gaol who had made a very great show in the circle of very high life. And we hear very straight and clear of divers murders committed about Allentown; a black man stabbed a white man with his knife so that he died quickly and a malicious black boy for revenge throwed a white child into a well. What a sink of depravity is this world without religion, without attention to that preserving, right-ordering, regulating principle placed in every heart.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-04-05"><dateline><date when="1818-04-05">5 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. I went with almost a determined conclusion to have a silent meeting but yet very desirous to do right, for I know nothing else will do. But so it was I put off out of season and if right seasons are mixed right services are lost. So it seemed as if did not get through with my lesson. After meeting I found some from a great distance and I believe stood in need of what was given to me. Yet I had satisfaction as far as I went. A burial was spoke of which seemed hurt the meeting – it being, as I thought, spoke of too early – or I believe I should have tried to have go through. I had concluded to go this day to Ancocas meeting, but, it being so very stormy, I gave out going.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_028"/>
<div type="entry" when="1818-04-06"><dateline><date when="1818-04-06">6th of the Fourth Month, 1818.</date></dateline><p> Went to the burial of Mary Gibbs, an old acquaintance from our youth, the daughter of Robert Finch, a minister in good esteem. She [was] near my age. The company [was] not very large but very still and quiet; the practice of talking at burials as formerly is nearly dropt and done with, but yet great need of a more lively inward traveled. [There was a] want of life and savor. I had but hardish work getting along, though came off middling at the grave. I felt nothing to say till the very last, [when] a few sentences sprung up and it did right well and afforded satisfaction. The people seemed pleased, sweet and pleasant, very kind and inviting. I could but notice that one poor old drunkard (and even then a little fuddled) should have such a sense and feeling when and where there was a little life and ownings of truth stirring, for he followed me and was very pressing and inviting me to come and see him. And also one other neighbor was very pressing and inviting.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-04-09"><dateline><date when="1818-04-09">9 was Monthly Meeting.</date></dateline><p> Some did think it was an open, lively, favored time throughout, and I don't know but it was so.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-04-12"><dateline><date when="1818-04-12">12. Was First Day.</date></dateline><p> We went to see our old sister Hannah Busby, lately moved to Henry Warrington's. My cousin Benne Warrington took me over to Ancocas meeting and through unmerited mercy it was the most open, evidently owning time I ever had there, for near about one hour and a half. Never did there appear more sweetness, feeling nearness, and uniting, inviting kindness. But we came directly home.</p>
<p>A few weeks ago Joseph Bispham's store was broke open and robbed of 150 dollars. The thief is now detected by his leaving a gimlet where he broke open the window, which some could say (by a knot in the handle) they had seen a carpenter use. Which, when he was taxed with the crime, he could not deny. A smart young man of a reputable family eastward. I have often sympathized and felt for the youth in their temptation.</p>
<p>This day heard of the death of William Wilkins. He died sudden with the gravel this day three weeks ago. He was well several years younger than me. His first wife, Sarah, [was] a worthy minister, but he married lately and not reputably. See the dangers.
<pb n="A0011529_029"/>
Last Seventh day night I had a remarkable dream at cousin Henry Warrington's. I thought I was in a room with a number of people and that there was an unusual solemnity, and I thought my voice was lifted up beyond what I ever experienced, seemingly beyond its natural power. But the consoling, comfortable feeling that attended it was far the most remarkable, for it seemed to do me good to the heart and made me think of John Rutty's words in his diary: soliloquy a song in the night. In the morning I went to Ancocas meeting, where was something a little or a good deal like it. But, oh, how hard it is to keep right when we are so! For so we read the heavens are not clean in his sight.<note resp="transcr">Job 15:15</note> and he chargeth his angels with folly<note resp="transcr">Job 4:18</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-04-16"><dateline><date when="1818-04-16">16 was Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Exceedingly attacked with a spirit of ease, indolence, and lukewarmness, which seemed to me almost ready to overwhelm and swallow up all. Yet several had something today and in that complaining way. <persName key="w6wx87x7">My wife</persName>e thinks I did very well, but I thought it a very poor time (but I was unwell; was not fit to be out).</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-04-22"><dateline><date when="1818-04-22">22 of the Fourth Month.</date></dateline><p> My daughter Abigail and I went to the select meeting at Philadelphia, where I think there was something of a heavenly nature felt. We attended the several sittings of this yearly meeting, except I missed one. It concluded Sixth Day about noon. Some sittings were very trying and rather afflicting, but some were very solemn, favored, instructing seasons where my lot was cast. We had at divers times sweet, uniting, satisfactory opportunities in families. The love and near unity many of my old friends and acquaintances expressed of seeing me once more was beyond what I can readily describe, and was very humbling and very tendering and affecting. Very many were like mirrors or looking glass to me. Some were so weak as to express great gladness in hearing a few sentences, which I thought they had better be very sparing of however. It is a great mercy to be so far preserved and kept from sinking.</p></div>
<pb n="A0011529_030"/>
<div type="entry" when="1818-04-26"><dateline><date when="1818-04-26">26 of the Fourth Month, 1818.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting John Hects and Horton Howard from the state of Ohio was there and had a very great deal to say in both meetings (for they had one in the afternoon) and preached good sound doctrine. But I could see but little animation. I believe the people take too much opium, anodyne, sleepy drops. Powerful preachers and dull hearers; it is like a pleasant song now, as we read it was in the days of the Prophet.<note resp="transcr">Ezekiel 33:32</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-04-27"><dateline><date when="1818-04-27">27.</date></dateline><p> Elisha Hunt, my brother Joshua's son of Redstone, and his wife and mother and several neighbors paid us a very acceptable visit.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-04-28"><dateline><date when="1818-04-28">28.</date></dateline><p> <persName key="w6wx87x7">My wife</persName> and I went to Evesham appointed by John Heald and Horton Howard. They both had a very open time and spoke very well, and I hope it will be as bread cast upon the waters and found after many days, as I find it is in some instances.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-04-29"><dateline><date when="1818-04-29">29.</date></dateline><p> A very sick man desired to see me and Ann Edwards at Moorestown. I went and we went to see Samuel Laning and wife, [an] old acquaintance, quite blind [for] many years. Then I went to see the sick man in deep consumption and came off with pretty good satisfaction, although at some places it seem hard work to come at anything savory or lively. This day's work wearied down.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-04-30"><dateline><date when="1818-04-30">Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> I did not go to our meeting. Rested to recruit.</p></div>
{1818-05}
<div type="entry" when="1818-04-30"><dateline><date when="1818-04-30">Sixth Day.</date></dateline><p> Hannah and I went to Cropwell meeting appointed by John Heald and Horton Howard. Came off about as well as is common nowadays. This afternoon we had a meeting at the school house near the Green Tree Tavern, which I thought ended savory and pretty well, considering all things. The people chiefly such who never make no pretenses to any religion. I expected the strangers home with me, but they stole them from me till next morning they came and Abigail and I went with them to Haddonfield meeting. Horton preached till one o'clock. It ended to my pretty good satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-05-03"><dateline><date when="1818-05-03">3 of the Fourth [illegible] Month, 1818. First Day.</date></dateline><p> I went to the burial of William Cowperthwaite, an old school mate and fellow prentice about six weeks older than myself. [He] died suddenly in a fit of the apoplexy at the Mount Holly and came off with satisfaction in this day's work.</p>
<pb n="A0011529_031"/>
<p>Although the fatigue was almost more than I was able to bear, so that at the meeting the forepart the infirmities of old age and the very great want of a more living concern, I felt as if I must pass the meeting in silence. Yet through mercy was helped and strengthened with an evidence of the ownings of truth. At last, however, they were very open, kind, and inviting, especially a great man, a magistrate, a man of a good disposition and natural abilities. I called to see Jacob Hollinshed – aged about 84, a very constant attender of our meetings till a few months past to satisfaction. Got well home, well satisfied, although I did not seem to get quite clear of Mount Holly meeting, which I have been thinking of some weeks. Their language was over and over, one after another, come and see us again come and see us again, etc.</p>
<p>A few sentiments of Benjamin Lay: Money the love of money – the destruction of nations – the foundation of evil. Again he admires Numa Pamplilias [Pompilius] when he refused the Kingdom. Oh, wise Numa, famous virtue! Again he admires the wisdom of Lucurgus in preventing foreign wares and merchandise. He says, I admire the wisdom of that man. Again he notes William Edmondson's words: Mammon – cursed love of Mammon. Mammon surfeits and corrupts the mind and darkens the understanding. Oh, the blessed doctrine and practice of the first Christians, which kept out luxury, pride, and cursed covetousness. Again, the joy at selfish spirit is Satan's spirit. Again, a few things serve a right mind; find the world's glory hath destroyed many.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-05-07"><dateline><date when="1818-05-07">7.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Month, 1818. At our Monthly Meeting William Williams from Indiana western territory and was large in testimony. [He is] a work man that need not be ashamed, yet some speak lightly of such as he. See the impudence of the present generation. I thought it was an open, favored time to my satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-05-08"><dateline><date when="1818-05-08">8th.</date></dateline><p> I went to see a poor sick woman who seemed much in the innocency to satisfaction, then went to Evesham Monthly Meeting. William Williams was there but silent and left the meeting, he being taken very sick. I left him at Isaac Haines's; they got the doctor to him. I came off without condemnation, although rough work. Weakness prevails there.
<pb n="A0011529_032"/>
We have had a very severe, cold winter and but little snow, so that the winter grain is very much killed on heavy land. Many field[s] look as if they would not produce the seed again; many say they never seen the like. How many ways are the fruits of the field destroyed! And a very cold backward spring, but very few warm days, which makes it seem more admirable that there was on the 6 of the Fifth Month, 1818, a very heavy thunder shower here with us and in other places. It is said the thunder and lightning was most tremendous towards or at Lancaster and in order parts of Pennsylvania. I am told several barns were burnt with the lightning and some creature[s] (horses, etc.) were burnt in them, and others very narrowly escaped being burnt. Oh, to think of the many solemn calls and warnings after divers ways and divers manners. But oh, how blind, how deaf and stupid we! We don't consider and we will not see!</p></div>
<div type="entry" when="1818-05-10"><dateline><date when="1818-05-10">10th of the Fifth Month. First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting, and a precious, open, owning time. Some besides myself thought it was scarcely if ever seen the like there. William Ashby of Philadelphia told me he thought I had gotten a new lease, etc., etc. But, oh, the different sentiments concerning ministry! However it need not trouble us, if we can but have [the] peace that fortifies and crowns all.</p>
<p>William Ashby went with me to see D. Stokes's widow of large family of children and we had an open, owning time then, so he thought it a favored day, well spent.</p></div>
</body></text>
</TEI>