<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
			<title></title>
		</titleStmt>
		<publicationStmt></publicationStmt>
		<sourceDesc></sourceDesc>
	</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text><body>
<div type="entry" n="1796-10-04">
<pb n="001"/>
<dateline><date when="1796-10-04">4 the 10 month 1796</date></dateline><p> This morning took my leave of all that was near and dear to me as wife and children, houses and land, to run the ways of the Lord’s commands, believing that He did require me to pay a religious visit to the southern governments, to the which I now freely am given up, though feel very insufficient for such a work, being poor in spirit, but an inward sweet calm. Blessed be the Lord for his goodness that he has never suffered my head to sink below hope. I crossed the river at Cooper’s Ferry. They would take no pay. Landed at Philadelphia, having a son in that town who bore me company that afternoon as far as Wilmington, where he left me and returned home. I was comfortably entertained at Joseph Tatnel’s that night and next morning had a solid opportunity with his daughter, she being gay dressed. She appeared solid and so we parted in a very friendly manner.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-10-05"><dateline><date when="1796-10-05">5 the 10 month 1796</date></dateline><p> In company with William Canby, traveled near forty miles towards Baltimore intending for that yearly meeting. A sweet inward calm attending my mind being overtaken by a stranger, who kindly invited us home and kindly entertained us.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-10-06"><dateline><date when="1796-10-06">6 the 10 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Pursued our journey. Crossed the River Susquehanna after paying the owner for our passage, being set over by two black slaves. Was most easy to pay them for their labor over and above the owner’s charge, which I did, and then seeing an ancient, well-looking black man staking corn tops, asked if they was his own or did they belong to his master. Said they was his own. He had bought that piece of land. I asked if he would sell me some. He answered yes. He handed me two [single?] sheaves of blades. I asked his charge. He said what I pleased. So I paid him well and passed on.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-10-07"><dateline><date when="1796-10-07">7 the 10 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Arrived at Baltimore town. Took our lodging at David Broun’s.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-10-08"><dateline><date when="1796-10-08">8 the 10 month 1796</date></dateline><p> This day began the yearly select meeting. Here I had to mention [?] the prevailing fashion of using wine at yearly and quarterly meetings so freely a fashion. Hard for some that had tender scruples to refrain when handed about in glasses on servers. As also the fashion of smoking tobacco, much of which might be spared amongst country friends when attending yearly and quarterly meetings. This was well received by some.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-10-09/1796-10-15"><dateline><date from="1796-10-09" to="1796-10-15">9 the 10 month 1796 to the 15th</date></dateline><p> Yearly meeting at Baltimore continues. To me it was exercising, though I believed some fared better than I did, but I must not murmur, for I believe I had brethren and sisters in suffering, and I believe it was all in wisdom if I can but have bread to eat, and water to drink, and run the ways of the Lord’s commands, and do the work he has for me to do, and that not deceitfully but according to His word. That is enough. I think I see with some degree of clearness the yearly meeting of North Carolina, and perhaps that is far enough at this time. Purpose setting out that way tomorrow morning if consistent with the divine will, whose counsel and holy aid I hope always to wait for. Let my lot be as it may, and my sufferings ever so great. Be pleased, O Lord, to be with, and keep my head above water when the most tried seasons may overtake, then leave me not nor forsake me, Oh Lord, but be pleased to renew my faith in thee, that so I may stand for thy cause and truth on earth, come what may come. For I have none to look to or trust in but thee alone at this time, when I have left all for thy name and the gospel, such as houses and land, wife and children, yea, all that is near and dear to me, and to be come as a sojourner and pilgrim here, as one that has none inheritance, for I believe the time is come that was spake of, that those who has wives as though they had none, yet my soul can bless, magnify, and praise thy great and glorious name, Oh Lord God almighty.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-10-16">
<pb n="002"/>
<dateline><date when="1796-10-16">16 the 10 month 1796</date></dateline><p> This morning left Baltimore. It being very stormy, went to [illegible] Elk Ridge a meeting. It was a poor, little meeting. After, we went fifteen miles.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-10-17"><dateline><date when="1796-10-17">17 the 10 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Went towards Caroline to Alexandria, where we had an evening meeting, large and favored. I thought truth was over all.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-10-19"><dateline><date when="1796-10-19">19 the 10 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had some meetings till the twenty-third on our way for Carolina, and had a meeting at Roneoack on first day. At this meeting was a large number of Black people who appeared very solid. I had conversation with a many of them who appeared to fare hard as to food and clothing, having but a very scant allowance, such as a peck of Indian Corn for a week, and sometimes a few herrings or a pound of beef, and some only a peck of corn and one suit of clothes of the poorest kind, so it had but the name of clothes for a year, being so ornery that they was soon almost naked, and in this naked condition and their lodging. But like the day on the floor, men, women, and children without distinction to age or sex as in some places i was an eyewitness and also in labor where i have seen men and women in the fields carrying rails and fencing. five men and ten women as also at other like labor, such as clearing ground about the like in number as it may suit their overseer, who drives them hard. woe, woe will be the lot of such hard taskmasters unless they repent of their wickedness.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-10-25"><dateline><date when="1796-10-25">25 the 10 month 1796</date></dateline><p> we had a meeting at Burleigh this was a solid good meeting. so far I had the company of <persName key="w6f1984q">Charity Cook</persName> and Susannah Hollingsworth and a man friend that drove the carriage to my comfort.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-10-26"><dateline><date when="1796-10-26">26 the 10 month 1796</date></dateline><p> this morning parted with the above said friends, and my companion stayed to visit some meeting, one of which we had at Black Water, large and solid.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-10-28"><dateline><date when="1796-10-28">28 the 10 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Seacock to our comfort.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-10-29"><dateline><date when="1796-10-29">29 the 10 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at the West Branch, a close searching time. It was it was said to have such an effect on two young men that had never been at a Friend’s meeting before that they followed us to the next meeting, near seventy miles into North Carolina. This took us till the thirtieth, where we attended the meeting at Little River, Carolina.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-10-31"><dateline><date when="1796-10-31">31 the 10 month 1796</date></dateline><p> This day began the yearly meeting of business at the tenth hour, and a poor low time it was. Then adjourned till next day.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-01"><dateline><date when="1796-11-01">1 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> About the time adjourned to the meeting assembled. Things went better, and, in the course of their business, there was much condescension. In the evening, attended the committee on the revisal of their discipline that was short and to my satisfaction. I gave many close hints that seemed well received, although in the main but a poor, low, week time as a yearly meeting.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-03"><dateline><date when="1796-11-03">3 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> About the tenth hour the meeting assembled again, having but one adjournment in a day. At this was revived the state of society, and that of dised spirist [missing]me before friends. They, being in the frequent practice of distilling and use of such [missing] appeared and many objections, but no further advanced [missing]
<pb n="003"/>
Then, with some difficulty, it was so far moved as that they should send accounts next year of their proceeding. This was thought as far as they could go at this time, I was, because of the free use thereof, their hands hang down, for they held it needful because of the badness of the water in them parts, but I thought it was more of custom then of real necessity, for I thought some had a love, therefore yet here is some honest hearted ones that had the cause of truth at heart. I was led to encourage such. The meeting ended with a select meeting.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-04"><dateline><date when="1796-11-04">4 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at New-begun in Pasquotank, North Carolina. This was large so that all could not get in to the house. By many there was near as many blacks as whites, if not more, and I thought was the solidest part of the meeting. It was a favoured season. The blacks in these parts are much the longest lived and most healthy, for the whites mostly die young, and but here and there one lives to an advanced age. It is said a sickly place. But it is not so with the blacks, who fair hard with nakedness, hunger, and cold, lodge as doth the dogs. These live to old age, mostly lust and stout, their children seldom sickly or die young. I believe it is owing to the manner of living, for the white people live luxuriously and lazy, for the most part, depend on the labor of the blacks, for there is scarce a house but has, some more and some less, from five to fifty and so on to a hundred. Here is poor management as to husbandry, desolation appears, look which way we will: pale faced men, women, and children, and small of size. The country looks poor, barren and desolate—here, round those hard taskmaster[s] who fare sumptuously every day, and waste that which might be a comfort to those poor, oppressed slaves, with which any soul has had a near feeling sympathy. Many of those have their allowance weekly, a number of whom have but one fourth of a bushel per week, and nothing else, neither meat, salt, nor fat, but they may cook it as they please, for when that is gone they have no more till the next week. Their clothing is one suit of any of the poorest and cheapest stuff they can get, this for one year and when gone, then go in rags, and some naked. These things I was informed by both blacks and whites, and some of which I was an eye witness myself, to the tendering of heart.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-05"><dateline><date when="1796-11-05">5 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at the narrows of Paspetanque. This was long a gathering, yet ended well. It was large, mostly not friends, but appeared solid.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-06"><dateline><date when="1796-11-06">6 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Was at Symond’s Creek First Day meeting, very large. It was thought one-third part was black folks. It was the largest that has been at this place, a number that had never been at a Friend’s meeting before. It was a solid, good meeting and ended well and, I believe, to general satisfaction, after which we visited one of the members of the house of assembly, and had a solid opportunity on the state of the oppressed slaves, and those set free by conscientious person who, by wicked persons, taken up and sold by public sale, and a law to support such conduct besides. This gave me comfort that he said he would use his influence to have it repealed, and he was in hopes to have it done, for it was a wicked law and could not be justified to encourage such evil doers.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-07"><dateline><date when="1796-11-07">7 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Sutlon’s Creek, a large solid good meeting. In these I had some close service that was well received, although from meeting to meeting great poverty of spirit, but not left with our hope in the Lord, my holy helper that puteth not his forth but he goeth before and prepareth the way for his faithful servants and messengers to do the work he has for them to do. Blessed be his great and glorious name.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-08"><dateline><date when="1796-11-08">8 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> This day had two meeting, one at a place called Welses and another at Beach Spring in Paspetanck County, North Carolina. These large so that the houses could not hold the people by far.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-09">
<pb n="004"/>
<dateline><date when="1796-11-09">9 the 11 month [1796]</date></dateline><p> Was at Piney Woods meeting, large and exercising. These meetings was attended by many blacks who sat very solid in these parts is abundance of the sort.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-10"><dateline><date when="1796-11-10">10 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Turned back thirty-six miles to Jessy Copland’s in Virginia, and, in our way, we beheld many poor blacks almost naked, eight or nine of which was little children under ten years old. Some of these as naked as they was born, and the rest nearly so, with their arms full of wood to carry to their master’s, about a mile. Here was a black man chopping, and the children carrying. He said there was nine or ten more nearly of that size at home. “Well,” said I, “How many is there in all?” He said, “I cannot tell, the sight was afflicting to me.” And, a little further on our way, came out of their quarters a large number more blacks, both men, women, and children, some of whom was almost naked, and others covered with rags. The very prospect was enough to tender the most hardest heart, but custom and wickedness hardens the hearts of these cruel, hard taskmasters and fore oppressors when they come before the Judge of all the earth who will do right, and reward every one according to their works. Oh what must be the lot of these poor oppressors if they repent not!</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-11"><dateline><date when="1796-11-11">11 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Was at Sumerton Meeting. It was large. One-third blacks as has been almost all the meetings for some time back, to my wonder. They sat very solid as power, to labor for Truth’s course, though in a close line of doctrine which seemed well taken as far as appeared.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-12"><dateline><date when="1796-11-12">12 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Was at the select meeting at the West Branch Quarter in [Virginia?], a poor low time it was, there was a want of living zeal. They had the form without the life and power. They had but little business, and that poorly managed.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-13"><dateline><date when="1796-11-13">13 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting in Suffolk Courthouse, very large. A great many, both black and white, more than the house did hold. A very solid time it was, and to general satisfaction. In this town was but one family of Friends. After, returned to Ann Scott’s, a widow near the West Branch, who is building a new meeting house at her own expense and cost, she being very rich and has no children. She is a solid Friend that is a station that needs great care as any, that they be not too tight and so forget the holy leader, and dishonor the truth, and choose thereof and wound themselves.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-14"><dateline><date when="1796-11-14">14 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> This is the meeting for business. An exercising time it was. There was much dryness and barrenness. I had close labor with men and women that I believe had some good effect on the minds of the youth and others, but little life was to be felt. In the evening of this day had a meeting in a schoolhouse. Near the widow seats for the black people, which was very large, and a solid favoured time. It was, though, the first that was ever in these parts, but there attended one justice of the peace and some other masters of Negroes. These spoke well of the meeting, and some of them said they should be glad their Negroes should attend such meetings, and was glad they was there themselves, for what was said they united with, and wished I might be observed by all that was there.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-15"><dateline><date when="1796-11-15">15 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Traveled from Ann seats to Bennett’s Creek near the sea, where is a little meeting held where I lodged at one Joseph Ricks.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-16"><dateline><date when="1796-11-16">16 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Bennett’s Creek, large and favoured. Also another in the afternoon at the Widow Buskins in like manor. Large for the place, and a solid good meeting. We parted with the people very lovingly. They seemed rejoiced. They not have many such opportunities of friends meetings.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-17">
<pb n="005"/>
<dateline><date when="1796-11-17">17 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had meeting at South Branch, very exercising. There was so much who [lenes?] that there was no room for labor, though their cry is all peace, but I believe there is no peace, for pride and oppression aboundeth. The slaves bear the burden, for they are naked and starving. They are sorely oppressed with nakedness and hunger, many under hard taskmasters. Their religion is in talking. The country is poor, barren as is the people, and poorly cultivated. Their crops have failed and, to me no marvel, so that bread corn is hard to be come at by the poor. Then the slaves share but lightly, though the rich are very wasteful and luxurious, who live on the sweat of the faces of their slaves, for the white people oppress the slaves and labor but little themselves, for that is become a reproach, for a young man that has no slaves is but little thought of, as also a young woman. It has been a trying circumstance to see their poor naked bodies in cold weather, when the sons of their oppressors and their haughty daughters walking with their stretched forth necks and wanton looks with their long tailed gowns trailing on the ground some near half appeared which might cover many of their poor naked bodies, and what these waste and lavish away in luxuriousness at the tables of the proud and haughty might feed many of the hungry, needy blacks who they sorely oppress. Would it be any marvel if the Lord should withhold the increase of the earth from those hard taskmasters? My heart has been pained within me from the sight of mine eyes to see the poor naked bodies of men, women, and children, some in part and some wholly so, not having a single rag on more than they was born with, when I thought it cold enough to wear a greatcoat, and some of the blacks wholly naked, yet those wicked oppressors are pretending to draw near the Lord and confess him with the lip and tongue of their heart, far from him being seared as with an hot iron. I have been afraid and yet some of those will have children by those they oppressing.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-18"><dateline><date when="1796-11-18">18 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a small meeting near the great bridge at Robert Poole’s to satisfaction, after which I had a solid opportunity with some women of the gay sort respecting their way of dressing, and whether some part of the tails of their gowns that was trailing on the ground near half a yard and the superfluous ribbons might not be spared, and the expense clothe the naked bodies of the poor little blacks. This was a solid opportunity, such as they had never heard before, yet seemed well taken, and parted very friendly. At this house we was kindly entertained. They appeared religious, but I was afraid they wanted depth of root. These was not acquainted with friends nor their principles, yet was kind and parted very friendly. Then traveled fifteen miles to Edward Doughties with whom we had a solid time this evening. He said he was born in the Jerseys at Egg Harbor.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-22">
<pb n="007"/>
<dateline><date when="1796-11-22">22 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at the Widow Britts. This was large and solid. It was at a place where never had been a Friends meeting held before. Few ever had been at such a meeting. This was in Camden County, Carolina.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-23"><dateline><date when="1796-11-23">23 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at the Widow Richison’s, same county, large and favored, and many hearts tendered. Though unacquainted with Friends, these people sat very solid to my comfort. The people very kind. I believe not a time to be forgot by some of them.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-24"><dateline><date when="1796-11-24">24 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Was at a preparative meeting at Piney Woods. Here I had some close labor which seemed well received. Things are at a low ebb amongst friends as to religion. I labored to stir them up to a more lively zeal for the cause and testimony of Truth.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-25"><dateline><date when="1796-11-25">25 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Began the quarter the select part this day at Piney Woods. It was thought a favored season. I was laboring to stir up the pure part in the bringing up children and families in plainness and being good examples themselves in houses and furniture.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-26"><dateline><date when="1796-11-26">26 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> This is quarterly meeting of business at Piney Woods, a very poor low time. Life and power was much wanting. I labored in the small ability that Truth gave amongst men and women. It ended to some profit at last through hard labor.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-27"><dateline><date when="1796-11-27">27 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Was at Little River a second time at First Day meeting. Not very large but ended well and in the afternoon had a meeting in the court house in the Pasquotank County, Carolina. This was large, both of blacks and whites. It seemed to general satisfaction. Many in great tenderness signified their unity with me and my service, and would fain have had me stay all night in their town. Their hearts seemed sincere, but I felt most easy to leave them as I, though in the hand of the Lord.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-28"><dateline><date when="1796-11-28">28 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at the Old Neck, Prequimans County, North Carolina, small yet somewhat favoured and still.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-29"><dateline><date when="1796-11-29">29 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Was preparing and amending my wagon at Elias Abborson’s.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-11-30"><dateline><date when="1796-11-30">30 the 11 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Left Piney Woods and traveled to Rich Square.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-01"><dateline><date when="1796-12-01">1 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Rich Square, not large and exercising.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-02"><dateline><date when="1796-12-02">2 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting in a Baptist house at their request, larger than I expected. The notice was small and the morning rainy. It was satisfactory and I believe ended well.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-03"><dateline><date when="1796-12-03">3 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Was at Jack Swamp Monthly Meeting it was small, yet some tender friends here. I had a solid time and they signified their unity with my service. They appeared in a weak state and stood in need of help many ways.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-04"><dateline><date when="1796-12-04">4 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Stayed their first day meeting. This was large and favoured. Then went to Holefax.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-05"><dateline><date when="1796-12-05">5 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> This day rode fifty miles towards Raleigh, a little town in North Carolina.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-06"><dateline><date when="1796-12-06">6 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> This day reached the town of Raleigh where the assembly sat. Here was several friends attending on the account of the cruel laws of this government against the black people. Many ways not suffering them to be manumitted, there being a law for any persons to take up such free blacks and sell them for slaves at public sale, and also if any of the black was found off their master’s land, they may be taken up and receive sixteen lashes, so cruel is North Carolina laws. We was trying to have those laws repealed and others more favorable. Made but little prospect, for the peoples’ hearts seemed hard, and a pretended fear of their rising and murdering of them, and not without a cause, as they are used so cruelly and kept in slavery.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-07">
<pb n="008"/>
<dateline><date when="1796-12-07">7 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Attended the house of Common and Counsel and had many private opportunities. Those received us friendly, but seemed mostly opposed to setting them free. I had many solid opportunities with many of the members who invited me into their rooms, who treated me with respect, such as their most leading men, as they was mostly quartered with us. This gave me a fool opportunity to relieve my oppressed mind.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-08"><dateline><date when="1796-12-08">8 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Friends propose to hand in their portisans and bills, though the prospect appeareth gloomy, and not but little, I believe, can be done for the blacks, but I would not have friends be discouraged, for I am clear the cause is good, and that way will be made for their liberation, but how soon or what way must be left to the Lord. I have purposed to have a public meeting this afternoon. This seems united with by most of those great ones, but a suitable place is not concluded on, but am to have an answer in a few hours whether the house may be where the assembly sits. Several thinks they will so well approve of such an opportunity that they will give way, but, being engaged, way does not open, so I took several private opportunities with the members to my and their satisfaction. Here being a large gathering of the first rank of gentry, being most of them men in some office in government or in the meliskey, but the respect they showed to me was marvelous, for my way, though singular, as I was they could but confess to them was deep instruction, and that they clearly saw that much might be spared, and that their way of living was luxuriously, for I looked as they did, though they had a great variety of roast, baked and boiled, and mine was about half a pint of milk, and as much water, morning, noon, and night, breakfast, dinner, and supper, all of us sitting at one table. They looked at first astonished, and many of them confessed, though they had never seen the like before, they believed it was the right way of living, but it would be hard for them to come at such a way of living, as they had private rooms. They kindly invited me, if at any time was wary with the noise, as it was a tavern, and at this time near fifty borders, and all men of note in the government where I would be more retired, come and sit with them. They should be pleased if I would make so free, for I should be very welcome. This gave me great opportunity of easing of my mind respecting the cruel laws of that government, North Carolina, concerning the black people, which was that if any set his negro free, anybody might take up such negro and by an order of court sell them for term of life, or if any slave was found off his masters place without an order, they might be taken and whipped sixteen lashes. This engaged my mind, for to lay before many of them the cruelty of such treatment and why it should be more severe in North Carolina than any other government on the continent, for I had been through all them to the eastward and found none like those. Now pray tell me why it is so, for all those speak well of their laws. They said they had not so many and, if free, they feared they the blacks would rise and murder them. I told them they had need fear as they did so sorely oppress them. I had much close labor, which seemed well received. I told them that those governments, Maryland and Virginia, had as many if not more, and I had never heard no such complaint, nor any such fears, but rather was in enlarging their liberty. This my labor was so well taken that many of them gave me kind invitations if ever I came in the parts where they lived to come and see them, for it would give them pleasure to entertain me, as also the tavern where we boarded when my companion
<pb n="009"/>
settled with him, would not take pay for my board he was so well satisfied with my visit when he charged the others ten shilling per day.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-09"><dateline><date when="1796-12-09">9 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> I parted with them in great friendship. They, many of them in their way, gave me their blessings, wished my success and safe return home. This was a time that was no dishonor to the cause of truth, but had a tendency to spread our principles. Blessed be the great name of the Lord our God, to whom be all glory, honor, and praise, now and forever and ever.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-09"><dateline><date when="1796-12-09">9 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> This morning left Raleigh. My companion bought him a new horse, and at first starting the horse run away and threw him. The ground being frozen and the rode stumpy I thought it a mercy he was not killed. I in a strange place and knew not where to go, but, through favor, in a little time he returned, having been thrown and somewhat hurt, but not so. But that we traveled forty miles that day and two days following, so far as to make up one hundred and fifty miles to Core Sound in North Carolina.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-13"><dateline><date when="1796-12-13">13 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Met the ministers and elders to confer on a religious visit to the families of friends at Core Sound meeting, which was united with, and, two friends joining me, we concluded to refer the beginning till after forth day meeting.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-14"><dateline><date when="1796-12-14">14 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> This day was at Core Sound Meeting and visited four families.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-15"><dateline><date when="1796-12-15">15 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Visited nine families, mostly to my satisfaction.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-16"><dateline><date when="1796-12-16">16 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Visited one family and returned to where I left my horse and carriage.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-17"><dateline><date when="1796-12-17">17 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a solid good meeting at Core Sound near the seacoast, North Carolina, with friends by themselves.  I think we was favoured with the divine presence. Here is a hopeful parcel of youth, both male and female. They are more in the simplicity in dress and other ways than is common, young women’s bonnets of linen instead of silk, their gowns of home spun, and made in a plain way, and their countenances modest, and becoming our profession. This was to my comfort. We parted in near feeling love, then, on our way, visited families and so on to Horton Howard’s, whose wife lay bad with the consumption, who I thought so innocent as near perhaps fit for to leave this world. She laid much the quiet. I had some solid conversation with her about her close, at which she seemed not [afraid?]</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-18"><dateline><date when="1796-12-18">18 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a solid meeting at Clubfoot Meeting in North Carolina. I thought near half of them was blacks who sat solid as many as could get in, but the house would not hold them a near all. I thought the meeting ended well, then visited one family that afternoon.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-19"><dateline><date when="1796-12-19">19 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> This day had a meeting with Friends after visiting near all the families belonging to this meeting. It was a solid good meeting and we parted in near love, especially Horton Howard’s wife, who appeared near her end and in a good frame of mind, and, as I thought nothing in her way but to die in a state of innocency, and going where to see now no more sorrow in that kingdom of rest and peace where the righteous are to magnify and praise that God who giveth forever and ever.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-20"><dateline><date when="1796-12-20">20 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Rode thirty eight miles to Lower Trent this day. Very poor in spirit, though I kept it to myself, for it is nothing uncommon for me to go from meeting as an empty vessel, which is all in wisdom, that may I be in a depending state, and wait for holy aid to prepare the way and go before. Blessed be his holy name, who has never failed his depending children.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-21"><dateline><date when="1796-12-21">21 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Was at Lower Trent meeting, very large and an humbling tender season it was. I believe there was some whose hearts was truly contrited at the close. Friends was requested to stay a little. I laid before them a prospect of a visit to the families of friends within the compass of this meeting, which was fully united with, and in the afternoon in company with two other began the visit.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-22">
<pb n="010"/>
<dateline><date when="1796-12-22">22 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Proceeded on to visit five families, and returned after night, having spent the day diligently. These being remote, so that we had to go on foot from house to house.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-23"><dateline><date when="1796-12-23">23 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Continues the visit to the remaining part, being six more, and so ended our visit to our comfort, and the visited also as many of them expressed. This day I met with a loss. One of my horses died, having two very good ones to my carriage. Finding it too heavy for one to go without oppression, this was some trial, as a Friend had lent it to me till I got home and then, if it lived, to sell and pay the money to a school master at Wilmontown that had his children to teach. This made it more trying than if it had been my own. Though I was much unsuited now, but felt a quiet mind. I think it was hurt by eating peas in the field not gathered.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-24"><dateline><date when="1796-12-24">24 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Parted with friends in Lower Trent in near love and rode twenty miles to Upper Trent and, in our way, visited two families.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-25"><dateline><date when="1796-12-25">25 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Was at a meeting at Upper Trent large and exercising. In the afternoon visited four families. It was but a low time in these parts. The life and power is wanting. Things looks poor within and without. I had some close labor in these parts, which seemed well taken. This is a poor, bare country, and I believe a blast attends, because of the oppression of the black people, and I believe Friends’ hands not clear enough to plead their cause, and the people see they are not clean handed, but will have them some way in their families because they can be had at lower rate to do the drudgery than the whites, this the world saith. This is a just reflection, I fear, for mine eyes in North Carolina hath seen that which made mine heart ache within me, and that in Friends’ houses.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-26"><dateline><date when="1796-12-26">26 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Visited one family, which was the last, at Upper Trent, and then spent the other part of this day in writing and some other matters needed.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-27"><dateline><date when="1796-12-27">27 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Set out early towards Contentnea. This evening reached Bear Creek near forty miles. Had a poor low time in so much that I was ready to conclude that I had spent my time to no purpose, but I believe it must be the tempter to try me with despair, but I remembered the Lord had not been wanting in the most trying seasons I had ever known, so that my faith was renewed and my hope in my God that he would not leave me nor forsake me in a time of trouble, but that I might do his work faithfully.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-28"><dateline><date when="1796-12-28">28 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Bear Creek. This was large and favored, and my strength renewed in the Lord to whom be all the praise now and forever.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-29"><dateline><date when="1796-12-29">29 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Was at Turner’s Swamp week day meeting. It was small, no notice being given. A few old friends and but few others. A poor low time it was.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-30"><dateline><date when="1796-12-30">30 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> I am now at Benjamin Arnold’s writhing, having not taken a day to rest since I left home, nor laid by for want of health. This, at times, causes deep humble thankfulness to the God and father of all our mercies.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1796-12-31"><dateline><date when="1796-12-31">31 the 12 month 1796</date></dateline><p> Visited several families in the neighborhood of Turner’s Swamp.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-01"><dateline><date when="1797-01-01">1 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Contentnea. First Day meeting very large. Was long a gathering and very exercising. The people’s state resembled the face of the country, poor and barren but little sense of good. I had some close labor, but not to the relief of my mind, for to me it was a day of mourning and heaviness, for the people’s hearts remain hard, and a cloud of darkness covered the meeting, to my grief. Though there was a few tender spirited little ones, but the living was not able to bear the dead.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-02">
<pb n="011"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-01-02">2 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Nawhuntor, very large and favoured, at which many hearts was tendered. I thought that some made covenant with the Lord to amend their ways and their doings if he would spare them a little longer. After, I went to the Widow Eginton’s.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-03"><dateline><date when="1797-01-03">3 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is a very stormy day, rather uncommon for this country, North Carolina. The trees are loaded with ice, and the ground of a sleet. The weather has been colder than common for near two months, but I hold as well as is common for me, thanks be to the Lord for his many fold mercies, saith my soul.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-04"><dateline><date when="1797-01-04">4 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Great Contentnea Preparative Meeting, a very poor low time, business managed poorly. They answered the queries in a very formal way, almost crying all is well, but, if so, I had not a true sense of feeling, for I thought all was not well, for death and darkness was felt to prevail. A world spirit had crept and was creeping in, and did blind the eyes of the foremost rank.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-05"><dateline><date when="1797-01-05">5 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Neuse Preparative Meeting. Here was disorder upon disorder, and in answering queries held up fair colors so that I feared they think all is well, but I was afraid the queries would be a snare to them. I told them how things appeared to me, and labored in the ability received, though close, yet well received, and I believe will not be all forgot, but be by some as bread cast on the water.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-06"><dateline><date when="1797-01-06">6 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Am waiting for company to go on to Holly Spring, upwards of thirty miles. After waiting till noon and Friends not coming, came one Winslow, a stranger to me, who offered to pilot me to Joshua Hasting’s. This I excelled of but had not gone far before I found my guide at a loss and several other things as not keeping to truth, and the company of an ornery looking man. This gave me some doubts, respecting the honesty of my guide and that he and his companion might have some ill design, as night was coming on and I where I knew not, nor where they would lead me, for I was altogether a stranger. But I had two good horses to my carriage and thought I would put on whilst I had day light and pay but little regard to my guide, thinking I should come to some house before dark, and soon, but little. Came where I had been before, and so got to my friend Hastings by dark safe. This was some comfort to me. This evening came Thomas saint, wife, son and wife and two little children going one hundred and fifty miles to a new country to settle. They looked very poor this was followed by a cold, snowy day in the winter and followed by extreme cold. This made my heart ache to see the women and children in so suffering a condition. This I write to warn them that can get bread to eat and rainment to put on: be content and not move, for in it there as much suffering for to the pain of my heart. I have of late seen much of these poor travelers going to new countries when perhaps no better than where they was, many much wasted.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-07"><dateline><date when="1797-01-07">7 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Here I was waiting for my company who was appointed to go to Tar River, but they not coming up as I expected. Came one Willis Bryant, who offered to pilot me to Thomas Horn’s near Holly Spring Meeting. Having no better expected of him as a pilot. This was a cold stormy day, and snowed fast. We traveled about three miles. He then wanted to alight and warm himself, and then again about three more, where was to be held a Baptist meeting. Here he would alight again, this whole I sat in my carriage. Those people now was gathering. These would fain have had me get down and, as they said preach to them, they wished to hear me. I told them I had no mind to stop and would be glad. They would tell the man I should be glad to go on, which they did, and soon out he came, much intoxicated with strong drink. However, he mounted his horse but had not rode but a little way before I found him too drunk to be a pilot, and not able to sit on his horse, nor knew the way. I was forced to go back with my drunken guide. A friendly man said if I would stay the meeting, he would go with me. So I was forced to stay. These people used me, I believe, better than I should have done them in like condition, for they gave me the preference of preaching if I would. I told them I had nothing to say, and I would have them go on in their own way. And so they did. And I sat and warmed myself. I thought in the quiet, and then two of them went where I wanted to go and behaved well.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-08">
<pb n="012"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-01-08">8 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Holly Spring meeting it being First Day not very big it being cold snowy day yet we had a favored meeting and parted to our comfort.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-09"><dateline><date when="1797-01-09">9 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Traveled to Tar River twenty five miles. It is uncommonly cold for this country, North Carolina, but we got well on, though very icy, but I left not my home for outward pleasure.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-10"><dateline><date when="1797-01-10">10 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Tar River, where is but a few friends, who had dropped their meeting, though it had been a preparative meeting. This was sorrowful. The meeting was not very large, but I thought a solid good meeting well. At the close I requested that the few that was members would stay so that I might have a little opportunity with them, which they did. With them I labored closely to keep up their meetings, for to have them taken away would be a loss to them, their children, and grandchildren, but all seemed but very low. There was no zeal for the cause of truth, to my grief, though the people sat solid who was not members, and I thought our visit ended well.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-11"><dateline><date when="1797-01-11">11 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This morning left Tar River and retuned towards Contentnea month [?].</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-12"><dateline><date when="1797-01-12">12 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day had a meeting at Joseph Hall’s which was so large that we was forced to hold it out of doors, though the house was large, yet half the people could not get in. This was but exercising. They was mostly waiting for to hear words. After meeting I had some close conversation concerning the oppressed blacks that seemed well taken. For of all the people under heaven these poor things suffer the most nakedness, hunger, and want besides, sorely oppressed with labor and whipping, with hard usage every way. Their houses to live in is no better than dog kennels, and their lodging on the bare ground as I have seen when I have looked in to their quarters (as they call them), where they the black live round their oppressors who fare sumptuously, and that in great waste, both of food and raiment, while the oppressed blacks are in a perishing condition and the fruits of their labor withheld from them, besides the cruelty used to them by their hard taskmasters. This was so trying that I in some places could hardly live through when I saw their poor naked bodies in cold frost and snow, as it was in North Carolina when I was there in 1796 and 97.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-13"><dateline><date when="1797-01-13">13 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at a select month meeting at the great house Contentnea and next day at the monthly meeting of business where I believe I had some profitable labor that friends united with. These meeting ended well, as I thought, to the advancement of the cause of truth. Blessed be the great name of the Lord and that forever.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-15"><dateline><date when="1797-01-15">15 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at the first day meeting, same place, that was said to be the largest that was ever seen at that place. The people sat very solid, though it was silent for near two hours. Then I stood up, as I thought, with a small opening not expecting to say but a few words, but he that is mouth and wisdom, tongue and utterance was not wanting, for words flowed as fast as I Could speak for I believe more than an hour, to the which the people of all sorts appeared attentive and sat very solid, and I believe the meeting ended to general satisfaction, for many of other societies came in a friendly manner and gave me the hand.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-16"><dateline><date when="1797-01-16">16 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Am writing at Benjamin’s Arnolds in North Carolina. Pretty well. This afternoon visited four families to good satisfaction and returned to my lodging at Benjamin Arnold's.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-17"><dateline><date when="1797-01-17">17 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Visited several families in the same meeting this day.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-18"><dateline><date when="1797-01-18">18 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Contentnea forth day meeting, small but solid. Visited several families, and in the evening had a solid time with some friends respecting the extensive trading in foreign goods on which a large duty is laid in order to defray the expense of war, and that with a little moderate labor in this plentiful Country, all things needful may be had to support nature as to food and raiment, and then we need not be at a loss for time to go to week day meetings and other religious duties.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-19">
<pb n="013"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-01-19">19 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Turner’s Swamp week day meeting, this was large and solid. I had, before meeting, a solid favoured time in a Friends families, and after in the evening at Benjamin Arnold's. Had a satisfactory time with some solid Friends respecting the management of the discipline and the presentations of marriages, which is as follows, according to my sense as given me at this time to recommend and leave in writing for friends of Contentnea Monthly Meeting, as their custom would admit of some improvement. My labor in these parts seemed well received though uncommon.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-20"><dateline><date when="1797-01-20">20 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was detained by reason of the wetness of the weather, and was writing as followeth. [note: written in another hand:] To his Wife, Children, and friends. See copy of letter pinned on the Cover of this book to the left hand.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-21">
<pb n="014"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-01-21">21 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This was the select quarterly meeting at Contentny. A poor low exercising time in which I labored for truth's cause, which was owned by friends. Blessed be the Lord for his gracious goodness to me.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-22"><dateline><date when="1797-01-22">22 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is first day meeting at the same place, very large, dull, and heavy. The life and power was wanting, and the ministry low and poor.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-23"><dateline><date when="1797-01-23">23 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> The quarter for business. This was a time not to be forgot, and made up for all the labor that was bestowed before. It was a parting meeting, for I was now to take my farewell of Contentney and friends of this place, which was done in much love and sweetness, when many tears was shed and tender feelings toward each other that will be remembered, as also my labor both in men’s and women’s parts and {went to Joshua Hastings}.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-24"><dateline><date when="1797-01-24">24 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Set forward towards Charleston, South Carolina. Reached Gum Swamp the 27. Had a favorable journey of four days, in which time I met with some thoughtful people, one of which expressed himself on this wise concerning discipline, both in the church and in families: that people who are wanting and let fall Discipline are in danger of going to decay, be it in families or in the church. This I thought a just remark and worth notice, especially in families. I thought I unite with him in sentiment and wish it may be of advantage to all.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-29"><dateline><date when="1797-01-29">29 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a large favoured meeting at Gum Swamp on first day, and visited four families. In one of them was a poor afflicted woman. And then to my lodging.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-30"><dateline><date when="1797-01-30">30 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Visited four families, and the aforesaid afflicted woman. All to satisfaction to me and them, as far as appeared. This was at Gum Swamp meeting.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-01-31"><dateline><date when="1797-01-31">31 the 1 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Traveled to Pedee in company with several friends.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-01"><dateline><date when="1797-02-01">1 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a small meeting, there being but a few friends, though there came in some others that sat solid, and it was a tender time and some tears shed. Then the owner of a ferry gave orders (it being near) that we should be set over without charge. We then went about three miles to where we was kindly entertained, Lewes Thomas.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-02"><dateline><date when="1797-02-02">2 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day traveled on for Charleston and lodged at Charles Evens, who appeared hard with his black folks, some of whom had not clothes to hide their naked bodies. This I mentioned to the woman, but her heart was hard and no impression could be made, and also a young man that had rode with us some miles that was some thoughtful, but the custom of the country has a powerful affect as to these people, but he did unite that at least they should be fed and clothed well when toiling all day and the most part of the night under hard cruel task masters. Had but a pint of broken rice for a working man for twenty four hours, and had it to provide when they should sleep, that they had but a little time to rest before called to labor, and if not at a word ready—then comes the lash. This is the lot of the blacks. This was a very sore trial to me.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-03"><dateline><date when="1797-02-03">3 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day passed through Camden in South Carolina, to Mallciah Murfey's who was very kind. They appeared an orderly family who had an afflicted daughter, that by reason of a rheumatic pain that had confined her for ten years, seven of which she had not sat up. I had a solid opportunity to her great comfort and my satisfaction.
<pb n="015"/>
She said her trials had been so great that she feared she had not borne her affliction with patience enough, for her limbs was all out of proper shape. With this poor thing I had a near sympathy and thought it a sufficient reward for all my trouble in coming. We parted very friendly, and they wished to have some Friends' books, which I am very desirous to send if way should open, for they wanted more knowledge of Friends.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-05"><dateline><date when="1797-02-05">5 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day crossed the river at Nelsons Ferry after traveling fifteen miles of as bad rode as ever I did in a level country. Two black men set us across, one of them very pleasantly said, "Now master, give us biscuit and we soon push you over." I said yes, I give him biscuit if they soon set over, <add>which they did</add> very cheerfully, which gave me to believe was they to receive a reward sufficient for their labor, it would be far better than such cruel whipping and starving and no encouragement to labor. We then traveled till evening came on, and had to put up at a Negro driver’s. This was almost too hard for me. I indeed was ready to say, "Lord, this is more than I can bear," what I see of the abuse of this people in passing this dark wicked land of North and South Carolinas. We tarried all night; they used us kindly and would not receive any pay, so I gave the Negroes some vittles and so we parted. I was afraid if I should reprove them, it might fare harder with the blacks, and so I thought it might be best to leave the Lord to plead their cause.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-06"><dateline><date when="1797-02-06">6 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Spent this day in a solid way and manner and in writing, with some peace of mind which I attribute to the dear Lord and master in whose service I believe myself in at this time and in this place.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-08"><dateline><date when="1797-02-08">8 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day was at their week day meeting, which was small and exercising, yet ended well and, I hope, to the honor of truth.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-09"><dateline><date when="1797-02-09">9 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day my friend Caleb Morris left me at Charleston. The weather is so warm that they are gardening, and I saw a peach tree in blossom and the gardens green, and some of them said they frequently had green peas all winter. This is near the middle of the second month in 97, when I was in Charleston on a religious visit, where I saw the great ruins of a fire last summer that had consumed as supposed five hundred houses and outhouses. It appeared as it had been a dreadful fire in my view. It was supposed to be set on fire by somebody, and another that did consume sixty more within a short time and many other fires of a lesser kind to the great alarm of the inhabitants. Supposed they were in danger of being burned every night, and to me it is no wonder, when I think of the oppression of the poor blacks. I visited an aged woman who had been long afflicted with the rheumatism, her daughter being present. It was a solid time.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-10"><dateline><date when="1797-02-10">10 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This night has been a heavy rain. Went and visited a honest inquiring woman to my satisfaction and her comfort, after which I had and solid time in the family of Daniel Latham.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-11"><dateline><date when="1797-02-11">11 the 2 month 1797.</date></dateline><p> {A Negro} As I walked out to water my horses, sat a Negro girl [add: the door]. "Well," said I, "hast thou sat here all night?" She answered yes. I was informed she had a hard master. Oh, the sufferings of this people! Will it not be accounted for someday? I believe it will, and that before him who is judge of all the Earth and will do that which is right. Oh, then what will be the portion of those hard cruel taskmasters? I believe they must have their portion in that place of torment that burneth with fire and brimstone where the wicked are.</p>
<p>Some expressions of a poor negro after the last night’s rain, said, “Me glad it rain. It raise the water in Congove River. Boats come down bring corn. Corn very scarce, very dear, then more plenty.” These poor things in time of scarcity suffer much with hunger and want of all things that is comfortable, whilst the white {people live in great [missing]}.
<pb n="016"/>
people live in pride and luxury and in lust, I think the most so that I did ever see. In Charleston, there has several things happen to this town that I believe has been from the hand of the Lord such as sword, fire, and pestilence, but all has not humbled the inhabitants, but they grow worse and worse. It is supposed that more than half are black, and mulattos, for in these parts, [add: it is] thought no crime to commit whoredom with their slaves, some of whom have virtuous wives. This evening had a meeting with the blacks, and solid favoured time, and ended well.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-12"><dateline><date when="1797-02-12">12 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> I am very poor, but my faith and hope is not lessened in him that has never failed me in every time of need, nor I hope never will, and more especially when the honor of thy most holy cause lyeth at stake, so that none may be able to reproach the cause of truth, nor thy servants and messengers. This is first day. Was at two meetings, the first small and low, the Last favoured and large. This evening, a fire broke out and consumed one house in the thick part of the town and did not much further damage. This was in Charleston, here is but a few Friends, and meeting but small and (I think) like to drop.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-13"><dateline><date when="1797-02-13">13 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This morning left Charleston after a stay of near a week, and had five meetings and visited several families and was kindly entertained.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-14"><dateline><date when="1797-02-14">14 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day had a meeting at a place called Edisto, where is a few Friends in a remote place. They do but hardly hold a meeting to the credit of the Society. Their meeting house is a few logs with holes cut for doors and windows but all stands open without shutters. I told them it was a dishonor to them and the cause, they are but weak and poor.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-15"><dateline><date when="1797-02-15">15 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting in a Methodist meeting house at their request, which was a solid good meeting and I believe ended to the honor of truth.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-16"><dateline><date when="1797-02-16">16 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day traveled fifty-five miles towards Augusta in Georgia, and had but a poor night’s entertainment. The company not agreeable.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-17"><dateline><date when="1797-02-17">17 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day reached Augusta and lodged at the Widow Fox's in the town near the market house, a good place of entertainment. She was friendly to us, but here is a wicked set of inhabitants.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-18"><dateline><date when="1797-02-18">18 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day, was sorely tried for want of the knowledge of where Friends lived, as we was both strangers and for some time could not find by inquiry where or how to find any of our Society, and the roads bad and hard traveling, and some said we had missed our way and that there was no Friends anywhere here. This I hope will make Friends careful in those or any other part to let strangers have a pilot that is acquainted with the ways and where Friends lives, but we found Friends, to our Comfort.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-19"><dateline><date when="1797-02-19">19 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a solid good meeting in Columbia County, in the government of Georgia, where is a settlement of solid friends thirty miles from Augusta, near a west Corse up the Savannah River. One of them is William Farmer, where is good entertainment and kind friends. In the afternoon began a family visit which ended well.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-20"><dateline><date when="1797-02-20">20 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Continues the visit to eleven families, and had another meeting at William Farmer's this Evening.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-21">
<pb n="017"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-02-21">21 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting a third time at William Farmer’s. Here was a number of friends from Wrightsborough who met by an appointment to consider the propriety of holding a meeting at this place under the care of the monthly meeting, as this had not been the case before. This was a favoured time. The Committee met at the close of the meeting, and I was desired to sit with them. It seemed to be united best to grant their request, and that a meeting should be held twice in a week at William Farmer's in Columbia County, Georgia. After this I went with Friends to Wrightsborough and lodged at David Mots.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-22"><dateline><date when="1797-02-22">22 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Wrightsborough forth day meeting, which was large and exercising. At <add>this</add> was many idlers and lukewarm.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-23"><dateline><date when="1797-02-23">23 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at a week day meeting at Williams Creek, ten miles from Friends settlement near Wrightsborough in Georgia (this was large and favored), and then visited four families. I believe the oppression of the black people causeth a cloud of darkness to hang over this land, yet the Lord has a little remnant that cryeth against this crying sin of slavery and are favoured to stand clear.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-02-24"><dateline><date when="1797-02-24">24 the 2 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Entered on a further visit to the families of friends of Wrightsborough Meeting, and continues till the twenty eighth, and was at their first day meeting, which was very large and power given to labor for truth’s cause and ended well. Here was many negro masters some of whom it was said shed tears.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-01"><dateline><date when="1797-03-01">1 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at their preparative meeting, which was a poor low exercising time. In the afternoon visited two families.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-02"><dateline><date when="1797-03-02">2 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is a stormy day and the <del>creeks high</del> water so high. I returned to Daniel William’s near the meeting house.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-03"><dateline><date when="1797-03-03">3 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Finished my visit and the names as follows begineth at Georgia Columbia County:</p>

John Sorrels; William Farmer jr; Ephram Owens; Jessy Hurst; John Connor; William Farmer; Samuel Owens; John Sandors; Prudence Cooper; Benjamin Oens; John Jones; Nathan Jones; Miller Hust; Benjamin Farmer;

then Williamses Creek in Maddocks settlement:

Richard Bottom; John Sibole; Hugh Bradshaw; Soloman Dickson; Joseph Evans

Wrightsborough meeting:

Joel Cloud; Isaac Stubs; John Stubs; John Stubs jr; Samuel Jones; Richard Jones; Franses Jones; Nathan Stubs; Samuel Maddock; Thomas Faling; Daniel Williams; Margret Davis
Nathaniel Vearnem; William Tod; Isaac Vearnem; Thomas Adkinson; Henry Williams; William Thomas; Joseph Stubs (over);
<pb n="018"/>
Joseph Jones; Joel Sandors; Masor Brown;  Richard Brown; John Mote; Joel Gilbort; David Mote; Jeremiah Mote; James Parham; Samuel Stubs

These families are in Georgia which I visited in 1797.

Where friends lived in Charleston South Carolina 12th 2 month 1797.
Thomas Sykes in Hasel Street Number 3
John Kirk East Bay
Rowland Hazard Crafts warf
John Hopkins Broad street
Daniel Latham Hasel street number 3

This is so that Friends going there may not be at a loss as I was where to go.</div>

	<div type="entry" n="1797-03-04"><dateline><date when="1797-03-04">4 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Wrightsborough Month Meeting. It was large for that place, it being in Georgia, beyond South Carolina. Their business was but small and but poorly done. The prospect of things is very gloomy as to religion, for the land groweth under oppression and tyranny towards the blacks who they murder as it was inch by inch, by whipping some to death, and some with hunger and nakedness and an over proportion of labor and hard driving. But of this Friends stand clear, for they have none of this color amongst them as slaves. But there seems a cloud of thick darkness to hang over the land, I think it doth in some measure affect our Society in these southern lands. But I thought in the fore and latter part of this meeting I was favoured with power, as well in men’s and women’s part, to clear myself of the trust that I did believe the Lord had reposed in me, and felt my mind much relieved, for I was hardly able to hold up my head since I came into Georgia until now when I feel relief. It seemed an affecting time. Many was much tendered, both men and women; I thought it seemed to be a farewell season. I told them I hoped they would gather up every fragment and let nothing be lost, for I did believe a trying time was coming that would try the foundations of every one of them, and happy for them whose foundation was on the one sure rock Christ Jesus when the wind should blow and beat vehemently, and that they might know where the sheltering place is, for some would be ready to wish they had died before these days had come. These things I believed right to leave with them and felt clear of the burden that had lain on my spirit for many day. These things had this tendency to unite in near and dear feeling love to the shedding of many tears that I believe will not be soon forgot by them nor me we parted in near love. </p></div>
<note type='structure'>[written delicately at bottom of page: "Richard" next two words illegible]</note>


<div type="entry" n="1797-03-05">
<pb n="019"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-03-05">5 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is their first day meeting at Wrightsborough, Georgia. I thought I felt easy to stay that meeting, which was uncommon large, so that not half the people could get in the house, but it was silent, for I thought I had cleared myself and had no more to do in that place, and at the close a large number of men, women, and Children came to take their farewell of me in feeling nearness and love. This was done with the dropping of many tears, and so we parted not expecting (as some of them said) never to see one another anymore. This at the end of near two weeks' labor amongst them, and then in Company with several Friends I came to William Farmer's about ten miles, who is a solid friend and worthy notice.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-06"><dateline><date when="1797-03-06">6 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at William Farmer's writing, and in the afternoon went to Benjamin Owen's and tarried all night. He and wife are sober people. At this place is a kind settlement of Friends in Columbia County, Georgia, and a meeting held.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-07"><dateline><date when="1797-03-07">7 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is the first meeting that was held under the care of the month meeting; now it is granted to be held first and third days at farmers settlement. This was large and favoured. It was the last that I was at in Georgia government. I had twelve meetings in Georgia and visited the most of Friends' families to my satisfaction, though I have seldom felt my spirits so oppressed as in Georgia. For I believe there is a cloud of darkness hangeth over the inhabitants, because of oppression and the blood of many cryeth from the ground and reacheth to heaven against those murderers that kill the poor blacks, as it were inch by inch with cruel whipping, hunger, and nakedness. I believe is the ground cause of these blastings and the reason why the earth bringeth not forth its increase. And no marvel to me, when those poor blacks that does the labor and beareth the burden and heat, and that in a cruel manner, so that they have but little time to rest. For I have heard the hand mill going all times of night, as they take it by turns to grind their morsel, that is in some places. Not more than a pint of broken rice for twenty four hours, or Indian corn without salt, or fat, or any other thing, and they have their tasks given them both by night and by day, and if not done—then comes the whip, so that these poor creatures have hardly time to dress their morsel before comes the driver with the whip and calls to labor and there is no excuse. No, not if they have not ate their morsel nor had any rest or sleep, for they receive the most cruel usage of all the creation, I do believe, insomuch that I could hardly live in passing through those southern governments, but was fain to keep it out of my mind as much as I could and leave their cause to the Lord to plead, which I do believe he will sooner or later. For the abomination that many are guilty of with these poor creatures is that some of their cruel hard taskmasters will be guilty of fornication and adultery with those they use so cruelly, when many of those poor <del>things</del> <add>black women, however modest</add> dare not say nay, for some of them have received a hundred stripes <add>for so doing</add>, and yet at another <add>time</add> to gratify their lustful desires will make so free with those they <del>are</del> <add>have</add> so cruelly oppressing, and in so devilish a manner as to leave a virtuous <add>wife</add> and commit adultery <del>in so heinous a manner</del> with those that they so cruelly oppress.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-08">
<pb n="020"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-03-08">8 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This morning I left Georgia, and after riding twenty miles crossed the River Savannah into South Carolina and went to Nathaniel Henderson’s.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-09"><dateline><date when="1797-03-09">9 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Henderson’s settlement, and an exercising time it was. Yet power was given to labor for truth’s cause, and the meeting ended well.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-10"><dateline><date when="1797-03-10">10 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day rode to Bush River in South Carolina, very low spirited.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-11"><dateline><date when="1797-03-11">11 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was writing this day. Continues poor.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-12"><dateline><date when="1797-03-12">12 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Bush River first day meeting. Very large and an exercising time. It was a silent meeting and a suffering season. I thought the sins of many was of a scarlet dye and the Lord had no more for them.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-13"><dateline><date when="1797-03-13">13 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day rode to <del>Tiger River</del> Pagets Creek, where I was informed of a negro master who and his cruel wife had so whipped one of their slaves that next day he was found dead in the woods, and the cruel wicked oppressors would not suffer the body of the negro that they had so murdered to be buried, but said he would sue any man that should bury him, and so his body was eaten by the beasts and fouls. Are not these the devil’s children? and, unless they do repent, must go where their master is and will be in torment, it being the just reward of their works? I have hardly been able to live through these accounts.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-14"><dateline><date when="1797-03-14">14 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Padgetts Creek meeting, large and satisfactory and ended well. I returned to the same place to lodge, it being rainy.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-15"><dateline><date when="1797-03-15">15 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was preparing to cross the Allegheny Mountains in a few days.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-16"><dateline><date when="1797-03-16">16 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Tiger Cane Creek Preparative Meeting. It was a solid good meeting. They had to answer the queries, which I thought was not done with so much life as I could have wished, as is too much the case in many places, but are looking outward for some easy way, which I believe is not safe, lest we get into a form and they become a snare to us, and the good design lost of stirring up the pure part and quickening the mind, so that the state of society may be sent up to the superior meetings in a plain clear and explicit manner.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-17"><dateline><date when="1797-03-17">17 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Wrote a letter to my dear wife and some other writing.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-18"><dateline><date when="1797-03-18">18 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is Cane Creek Month Meeting. I had much clost labor for truth’s cause, for things are very low both amongst men and women, and in both parts I did labor against many deficiencies that was creeping in, and Friends giving way to and mixed with the spirit of this world that woundeth the good part and hinders the growth of truth and the advancement and increase of friends, and keepeth them dwarfs in religion. The number of the faithful are but few. The answering of the queries are done in a light and formal way, to my grief; the life and power is wanting in transacting business.</p></div>9

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-19"><dateline><date when="1797-03-19">19 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is the first day meeting at Cane Creek. It was very large, more than the house could hold, as is the most of the meetings that I have been at. This was a solid good meeting to the tendering of many and ended well to the honor of truth.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-20"><dateline><date when="1797-03-20">20 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Returned back to Rocky Spring in order to attend their preparative meeting, in which the queries are to be read and answered. Their month meeting is near, that is preceding the quarter which I propose to attend if consistent with the divine will.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-21"><dateline><date when="1797-03-21">21 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was writing.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-22"><dateline><date when="1797-03-22">22 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Rocky Spring preparative meeting, it was a solid good meeting, though in answering the queries had the answers prepared beforehand, which makes light work and is not the best way.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-23">
<pb n="021"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-03-23">23 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Bush River preparative meeting. It was an exercising time. There is much danger of formality and of concluding all is well. They answered the queries very poorly and in a light way.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-24"><dateline><date when="1797-03-24">24 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Isaac Hollingsworth's (Susannah's husband), and was preparing to cross the Allegheny Mountains into Tennessee.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-25"><dateline><date when="1797-03-25">25 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Bush River Monthly Meeting, where I had much gospel labor, both in men’s and women’s part. To general satisfaction and comfort, this ended well, and so I took my farewell of these parts and proceeded to cross the mountain and to took Mud Lick in my way and Rabon Creek meetings.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-26"><dateline><date when="1797-03-26">26</date></dateline><p> Was at their first day meeting, it was large and solid and ended well.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-27"><dateline><date when="1797-03-27">27 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Mud Lick meeting, it was large and solid.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-28"><dateline><date when="1797-03-28">28 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Traveled thirty-five miles, got to Rabon Creek.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-29"><dateline><date when="1797-03-29">29 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a favoured large meeting at Rabon Creek. The house held not half the people it was thought. It seemed to general satisfaction.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-30"><dateline><date when="1797-03-30">30 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Set out in order to cross the Allegheny mountains into the Tennessee government at a place thought very difficult. And some said I could not cross, for the mountains was of such a towering height and so steep that one told me that he thought that six horses could not go with an empty wagon, and some places so steep to go down that it was almost impossible, and those that had crossed was forced to cut trees and tie behind, and wished they had never attempted to cross that place; and that there was a swamp called Laurel Swamp, for five miles in length, where was no other way but by passing in a large creek, and so stony for a great way that it was in danger of one’s life, and he thought I had best not go that way. But on a solid thought I could not see no other way but to attend to the opening and trust myself in the hand of the Lord that had never failed me. The first day we traveled upwards of fifty miles, and camped in the woods that night <add>near the head of Saluda River</add>. We had not yet come to the mountains by some few miles. In the morning it rained. That made the traveling much more difficult for my horses, especially when we came to the mountains, which was wet and mirey.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-03-31"><dateline><date when="1797-03-31">31 the 3 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day about the tenth hour, we entered the blue mountains, it being the first. These was very hard for my horses by reason of the rain that made them slippery, but we passed them very well and camped again in the woods. This night, the wind blew up cold for the season (it being in the third month), but I felt inward comfort and something as a stay and a staff to lean to. My hope nor faith had not fail<del>ed</del>, but thought I saw as yet the way clear. Told my friends I believed we should get through, though it might be with some difficulty, as there was four from Bush River quarter that had given up to bear me company through this wilderness. In the morning, being all well, and our horses, though but little <add>to</add> eat besides corn, seemed in good heart, as I was favoured with two very good ones. As I traveled in a small carriage, I thought I felt him near who putteth not his own forth but prepares the way before them. We set forward <del><gap/></del> early.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-01"><dateline><date when="1797-04-01">1 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> The mountains being seventy miles across, we got on very <del>well</del> this day. Came to a house in the evening; was kindly entertained. This was very refreshing to my body, as I now am turned of sixty five years old and not used {not} to camp in the woods, but had no cause to murmur as I did believe we had the company of my dear Lord and master.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-02"><dateline><date when="1797-04-02">2 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This morning traveled about fourteen miles, and came to the Allegheny mountains about two in the afternoon, which was far the most difficult to pass, they being sixteen miles and no house. Here was a counsel held: whether to tarry here, or go on as far as we could. I gave it as my sense to go on as far as we could. This was united with, for we seemed much united
<pb n="022"/>
in doing the best we could. So the first we ascended was very high, and one after another for about two miles, when we came (as was said) to one of the worst to go down. It was the steepest that I had ever seen passed {here}. The{m} few that had passed that way had cut down trees and fastened to their carriages. Here we was at a stand what was best to do, but at last was united that the horses could not go down before the carriage, it was so steep, but best to lock all the wheels, and as there was five of us we would try ourselves without the horses, and it answered well—we got down safe. After this, we traveled on till night, up and down such mountains for towering height as I had never seen passed before with a carriage, but all went well till night came on, and then we camped in the woods again. We had not come as yet to the Laurel Swamp as we had so bad an account of. Here we could get nothing but corn that we had in our bags for the horses, yet they held out well. Early in the morning we set forward, looking for worse times than what we had passed.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-03"><dateline><date when="1797-04-03">3 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> We had many towering mountains to pass, I thought as any there was for height, till at length came to the aforesaid Laurel Swamp. Here we had many logs to drive over, some not less than two feet thick, and the laurel roots was indeed very trying, and sometimes for half a mile up the creek that was full of rocks, some of them so large the carriage could hardly pass. Some places we had to take off the carriage wheels so as to get under very large trees, and many we cut out of the way so that we made it much better for the next that came that way. The sudden ups and downs over the logs, and in and out the creek, the rock and stones broke the carriage tongue in the midst of this Laurel desert howling wilderness. But as I looked that somethings of this kind might <add>be</add>, I provided tools to repair, and as some of our company was handy men, we soon put in another that lasted through our journey, which we obtained that day to the praise of him, the God and father of all our mercies. For I believe to him alone it is due, for which favor I did feel all <del>that</del> is living within me bow and reverence his great and glorious name, and can say with an heartfelt sense, thanks, thanks, this night being got over the Allegheny mountains and this howling wilderness for sixteen miles, which took us about seventeen hours traveling—we entered the mountains the fourth <add>at two in the afternoon</add> and got through the fifth about sunset 4 month.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-04"><dateline><date when="1797-04-04">4 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day traveled thirty miles to New Hope in the Tennessee government.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-05"><dateline><date when="1797-04-05">5 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at their fourth day meeting at New Hope. It was an hard meeting. Here was a marriage accomplished.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-06"><dateline><date when="1797-04-06">6 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This and the seventh, we traveled sixty miles to Lost Creek. Here the roads was bad and {our}<add>my</add> carriage axletree failed, but we was near a friend before it failed that I thought a favor, for here we could have repaired one.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-08"><dateline><date when="1797-04-08">8 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day was spent in repairing the carriage at John Mitses, a valuable friend. I found great need of patience, feeling myself as a poor pilgrim, but have not cause to murmur for the Lord has been kind.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-09"><dateline><date when="1797-04-09">9 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day had two meetings at Lost Creek. The forenoon was a laborious time but ended well. That in the afternoon was a favoured meeting and was (I believe) to the honor of the cause of truth and tendering of many hearts.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-10"><dateline><date when="1797-04-10">10 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Traveled eighteen miles and had a meeting at Grassy Valley ten miles beyond Holston in the Tennessee government. It was an instructing time, and in the evening the same day had another solid opportunity with Friends by themselves to good satisfaction, it being a farewell season, and then we parted in feeling nearness and love.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-11"><dateline><date when="1797-04-11">11 the 4 month 1797.</date></dateline><p>Returned back to Lost Creek with the reward of peace, having now been to the farthest part of my journey in the southern governments: Carolina, Georgia, and the Tennessee.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-12"><pb n="023"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-04-12">12 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a favoured meeting at Lost Creek (it was the third that I had at that place) and went to Abraham Wodarts in order to return back to New Hope, believing myself clear of these parts.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-13"><dateline><date when="1797-04-13">13 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This and the next day traveled sixty miles to New Hope.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-15"><dateline><date when="1797-04-15">15 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> It being seventh day and rainy, I was writing at Ellis Ellis in Tennessee government.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-16"><dateline><date when="1797-04-16">16 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at New Hope first day meeting, it was very large and solid but this is a poor place for Friends. Here is so much of the spirit of this world. Was grieved at the low state of religion. Alas, they are content with the form without the substance.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-17"><dateline><date when="1797-04-17">17 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at a meeting called Limestone in the Tennessee government. This was a comfortable meeting and ended well.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-18"><dateline><date when="1797-04-18">18 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> From this to the twenty {second}<add>first</add> we was traveling to Little Reed Island, which was one hundred and fifty miles, and the roads very bad. In this my way I was tried almost as much as I could bear in seeing so large a number of men, women, and children, as also a large number of slaves, in a miserable suffering condition. This to behold was <del>almost more than I could bear</del><add>enough to tender the hardest heart</add>. To think where those dear little children was going—to strengthen the hands of men destroying the Indians, and take from them their lands by the hands of wicked cruel men that sticketh not to murder these poor natives. This was trying to behold, that Friends did not stand clear but was following on after and settling the land thus obtained {[illegible] after}, <add>Indians being</add> violently forced off their lands then to hide there, cruelly would give them just as much as they pleased, which the Indians are forced to take that or nothing, and then cry a fair purchase. This was so far from doing as we would be done unto that I could but bear my testimony faithfully against all their conduct, let whose may plead for it, and was a further grief to see the poor dear innocent children carrying into this distant land. We met at least a thousand people moving to those back lands of all descriptions, some to Cumberland, some to Caintuck, <add>some</add> into the Spanish Dominions. This increased my grief, for I believe some day there will be an overturning, and a terrible day it will be, for it appeareth to me the land is stained with the blood of the Negroes and Indians, and the cry of the slain no doubt hath reached the holy ear. If we could put ourselves in their conditions, and the power put into their hands for one man to chasse a thousand and two put ten thousand to flight, and they to do to us as we have and are doing to them, we should cry out against them as a cruel barbarous wicked people ,no doubt with me, and they to come in to the bowels of the country, and cut in pieces our wives and children, and destroy all our living, and take our land, we should hardly bid them good speed as now is too common. And I fear our Society stands not clear but feels a kind of gladness to hear of more land being obtained from the poor natives, so that we may have our borders enlarged if they the Indians should starve for want of bread.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-22">
<pb n="024"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-04-22">22 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> We rode to Chesnut, a small meeting at that place, it is on the mountains or Blue Ridge. <del>Here we had a good meeting</del> </p></div>

	<div type="entry" n="1797-04-23"><dateline><date when="1797-04-23">23th 4 1797</date></dateline><p> Here we had a good meeting this day at Chesnut, and then turned back fifteen miles with an heavy heart, for this seemeth to be the general cry, "more land, more land," but content with less religion {seemeth to serve}, though they would hold by the skirts of the garments in order only to take away their reproach. This is the state of Friends on the mountains in the upper parts of Virginia. It's low times, and but little done as to the nature and ground work of religion.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-24"><dateline><date when="1797-04-24">24 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Big Reed Island meeting. Low times for Friends. Here a little religion service.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-25"><dateline><date when="1797-04-25">25 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Little Reed Island to my satisfaction, and went to the top of the mountain near Wards Gap and tarried this night. This is the Blue Ridge.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-26"><dateline><date when="1797-04-26">26 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day had a meeting in a private house on the top of the mountain to my comfort, after which we came down off the mountain at a place called Wards Gap, and two young men bearing us company that proved great help, so that we got down safely. On the top of this mountain the woods appeared almost like winter, but before we had got four miles to the bottom of the hill, the leaves of the trees was more than half grown. On this mountain it is more than a cote colder than what it is below; it seem like another climate, I thought. I felt cause of humble thankfulness to the God and father of all our mercies, in that he had so prepared the way before me and had done all that could be done. Then traveled this afternoon twenty two miles, where we had a meeting next day. This is in North Carolina and Virginia.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-27"><dateline><date when="1797-04-27">27 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Boyers Summers. It was a solid good meeting, ended well. And then traveled to Westfield, where we had another meeting this day, the third hour, large and very exercising; the people was gathering till near the close of the meeting. This ended near silent, which {was} seemed a great disappointment, so that I was told that some reflected hard to think I should call people from their work in so busy a time and then say nothing, and some thought {hard and that} it could <add>not</add> be right.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-28"><dateline><date when="1797-04-28">28 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day traveled to Deep Creek about thirty miles.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-29"><dateline><date when="1797-04-29">29 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Deep Creek, large and favoured. We traveled to Hunting Creek. The roads in these parts is bad traveling.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-04-30"><dateline><date when="1797-04-30">30 the 4 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Here we had a good meeting at Hunting Creek in a barn. It was large and solid; they could not all get in. I thought some interrupted by rain.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-01"><dateline><date when="1797-05-01">1 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day traveled forty five miles, where we crossed the Yadkin River at a place called the Shallow Ford; {the water f<gap/>d} it was quarter of a mile in width. This we did very pleasantly, though sometimes it ran into the wagon body.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-02"><dateline><date when="1797-05-02">2 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day had a meeting at Muddy Creek in North Carolina.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-03"><dateline><date when="1797-05-03">3 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Center Meeting, not very large.</p></div>

	<div type="entry" n="1797-05-04"><dateline><date when="1797-05-04">4 the 5 month</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Providence, large and solid.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-05">
<pb n="025"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-05-05">5 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Cane Creek month meeting. This was long a gathering, and but few of the youth. I had a solid time and was favoured to labor for truth’s cause amongst men and women; that was well received. I had to lay in pressing terms the necessity of a reformation, and to refrain the use of those imported goods, as there is so large a duty on <add>them</add> and the money arising therefrom is to hire men to go out to war and maintain them while destroying the poor Indians to make room for us. This would not be doing as we would they should do to us, to send armies of men into the bowels of our country, and destroy our living, and burn our towns, kill our wives and children, as we do theirs. What should we think then? Could we bid good speed to them, or could we think well of those that found them<supplied>selves</supplied> money (as we now do) by the use of those foreign articles, on which is a duty of two and half percent, which they say is fifty shillings to every hundred pounds so imported. This, I was told by one of the Congressmen, was for no other purpose but to support the war against the Indians. Now my dear friends, who can say "I" am clear of the blood of those poor innocent ones", no doubt a number of whom <add>would</add> be glad to live as peaceable as any of us and enjoy their wives and children? We do know that money is the very sinews of war—how can <add>we</add> be easy to strengthen those hands that are shedding blood? To me it appeareth a weighty matter, and more especially since I have been in these southern lands to see and behold <add>how</add> anxious the people are to follow the armies, such as want to get where they can live a lazy life and that by hunting yea before the poor natives are drove so far as that those lazy ones are <add>not</add> in danger of their lives as also their dear children. This <add>I saw</add> when in these parts, Georgia and Tennessee, that now lies bordering on the Indians' land, driving them further and further. Now friends, where are we? Are not <add>we</add> following on after those wicked men, whose hands we are strengthening by using those foreign goods, when we have aplenty in a less compass of land <del>as also</del> <add>to have</add> food and raiment in a more innocent way, and avoid those just reflections cast on us that none <add>are</add> more anxious <add>for</add> land than Friends are. Yea, may it not justly be said that <add>we</add> are pushing them forward who are cruelly destroying the Indians.</p><p>I have believed the cry of their blood doth reach the holy ear, and one day will be called for at {the} our hands, though now it is a time of peace and luxurious living,</p><p>when those poor things, the natives, say they have nowhere for their wives and children to lay down, and we are craving more land, more land, when in a very little time our length and breadth will be enough for us—alas! alas!</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-06">
<pb n="026"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-05-06">6 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Cane Creek first day meeting. It was dull and laborious.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-07"><dateline><date when="1797-05-07">7 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Spring month meeting, large and a favoured time. Here I had more faithful labor in the meeting of business for truth’s cause, which was well received. Things in these parts is much out of order by reason of a worldly spirit and the love of many things, and help is much wanting; the work is great, and the faithful laborers are but few. I have often prayed the Lord would be pleased to send forth more faithful laborers in to the harvest, for the harvest is great.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-08"><dateline><date when="1797-05-08">8 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Eno meeting, which was a favoured little meeting.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-09"><dateline><date when="1797-05-09">9 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Rocky River. This meeting was large and interrupted for want of more room in the house, for the meetings have been large and the houses small, so that in many places hardly half the people could get in.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-10"><dateline><date when="1797-05-10">10 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Tysons meeting, this was a solid good meeting and large.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-11"><dateline><date when="1797-05-11">11 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at the Rig meeting. This was large and a favoured time.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-12"><dateline><date when="1797-05-12">12 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Holly Spring meeting. It was very exercising to me.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-13"><dateline><date when="1797-05-13">13 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Back Creek. This day the quarter began called Cane Creek quarter in North Carolina. The select members being gathered, things was opened in a plain clost manner respecting many deficiencies that had crept in and was creeping in, and so it ended well though in clost labor, yet it was what truth owned, and I <add>believed</add> sealed on the minds of some of the ministers and elders.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-14"><dateline><date when="1797-05-14">14 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is first day meeting at Back Creek. It was so large that it was thought that one half the people could not have room in the house. It was a dull heavy season, and but little sense of good. And another meeting in the afternoon, which was but little better, though very large.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-15"><dateline><date when="1797-05-15">15 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This <add>day</add>, the business transacted in which I had but little to do <add>in the fore part</add>, for the feet of my mind seemed turned another way in a clost labor, both in men’s and women’s part, in reviving ancient advice that seemed almost lost and much departed from, amongst other thing, the <add>free</add> use of rum, tea, and tobacco, as also coffee. This is a testimony that a number of our worthies <add>(Friends William Edmonson and others)</add> bore to their last days, and I believe will never be lost but will be kept alive and revived by here one and there another, whom the Lord will raise up and qualify for that work and service. These things had more <add>place</add> when revived than I could have expected, and I believe will not be all forgot but will be as bread cast on the waters found after many days.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-16"><dateline><date when="1797-05-16">16 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Hugh Worrey, large and favoured, then had a solid time in a family where was several young people at my lodging, where I was kindly entertained.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-17"><dateline><date when="1797-05-17">17 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Marlboro. This was large and solid good meeting.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-18"><dateline><date when="1797-05-18">18 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Hover's <add>(a Dutchman)</add> at a private house, where was the largest gathering by more than half than was ever seen at this place before, I believe one cause is of my different appearance. This was a favoured time, the people sat solid and very quiet to the end.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-19"><dateline><date when="1797-05-19">19 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> No remark.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-20"><dateline><date when="1797-05-20">20 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day was at Center month meeting. It was very large here. I had much clost labor for truth’s cause, both in men’s and women’s part, to my comfort and their satisfaction, as it was a parting time with us. Many tears was shed, we parted in much love.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-21">
<pb n="027"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-05-21">21 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at New Garden first day meeting, this was large and solid good meeting and ended well, after which I visited an ancient friend to comfort.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-22"><dateline><date when="1797-05-22">22 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Hopewell meeting. To my comfort, large as they are in general, such as have never been seen for numbers and solidness, they are of all sorts and societies. My service in these parts has been accepted as far as appears, for there is sweet harmony felt amongst us and my labors well taken amongst them; this is to my comfort.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-23"><dateline><date when="1797-05-23">23 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Dover meeting, large and solid, after which I had a solid time in the family where we dined, as there was several youth there that expressed their satisfaction and comfort.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-24"><dateline><date when="1797-05-24">24 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at New Garden preparative meeting. Here I had more clost labor for the Lord and his cause. Here they read and answered the queries, I thought in too formal a way, and went not deep enough into their state, having the answers prepared beforehand by the overseers. This is in danger of leading into a form and making them becoming a snare and we crying all is well. But I proposed their being read a second time, which was done, and I felt ability to speak to the queries and answers, which was well taken, and as there was room for improvement, they hoped to take it into consideration.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-25"><dateline><date when="1797-05-25">25 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Dover preparative meeting. This was very large, and an exercising time it was. Things appeared very low.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-26"><dateline><date when="1797-05-26">26 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Came back to New Garden again.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-27"><dateline><date when="1797-05-27">27 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at New Garden month meeting. Here business was transacted the best of any that I have been at with in this yearly meeting, for I found the cause of truth handled very poorly, and its advocates too formal and not deep enough, but on a sandy foundation that will not stand against storms nor the current of the spirit of this world, so that the cause suffereth and many of the youth mourn, but the old folks cries more of this world as they grow nearer the grave. This prevaileth in these southern governments very much</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-28"><dateline><date when="1797-05-28">28 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is first day meeting at New Garden. It was a silent meeting as to my part; there was a few words spoken by a young woman. The people sat solid and it ended well. This afternoon was their monthly conference, as they call it, with the ministers and elders here. I had some clost labor, for I thought I saw great danger of formality creeping amongst this class of people. For when they began the answering the queries, they had a form prepared by somebody that was in a language "a[ll] is well". This was trying, for I thought it was not, so I told them if they was as good as their represented, there was not so many more as good upon the continent as they was, but I had my fears that it was not so, and their way of answering queries was in danger of making them a snare, and a departing from the intention, and the elders not filling their station in watching over those young in the ministry for good, advising against tones and that which would hurt their service. For I did believe the service of some was hurt by so much of a tone in their ministry, and this perhaps for want of early care of faithful elder to advise against tones.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-29">
<pb n="028"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-05-29">29 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Rode to Bluse Creek, and next day had a little good favoured meeting at this place where is some tender spirited Friends.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-05-31"><dateline><date when="1797-05-31">31 the 5 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day was at Springfield preparative meeting where they read and answered the queries, having the answers prepared before by somebody as is the general Custom in those parts—I believe to their hurt and a danger of leading into formality, and the queries becoming a snare wherever it is practiced, and the good intended by them lost, which is to quicken the mind and lead into a deep inquiry individually—how we square our conduct answerable to those weighty queries—and not just give them a reading and so pass them over and think all is well, as some do.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-01"><dateline><date when="1797-06-01">1 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Deep River preparative meeting. Here was a large gathering of people and in the fore part was favoured, but when they entered on reading their queries and answers in that formal way, I thought instead of ministering life, it ministered death, and so it will (I believe) always do where this is practised. For I <add>believe</add> it was intended the queries should be answered in the meeting and nowhere else, for we may as well prepare our sermons before the gathering of the people as to prepare answers to these weighty queries before the gathering of the meeting. For I believe there needs the same qualification to answer them as to preach the gospel, or else we had better not have held them lest they become a snare to us instead of our profiting thereby.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-02"><dateline><date when="1797-06-02">2 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Piney Woods in North Carolina, not large but favoured, though in passing felt very poor and low. Went to see Isaac Hunt's wife and children, he being from home on a religious visit. I had some deep thoughts on those that filled the stations of Elders in our Society and who did fill them with propriety as they ought to do, for we find they were to be such as fear God and hate covetousness, not given to wine, no strikers, but given to hospitality, and a number of other qualifications as may be seen mentioned in the first chapter of Timothy in the New Testament.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-03"><dateline><date when="1797-06-03">3 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Springfield month meeting. This was large and, although exercising, yet power was given from on high to labor for truth’s cause, though in a clost way yet seemed well received. Here in these parts. Friends was in a hurtful practice of standing round the meeting house both before and after meeting in conversation, which is a disorder and a bad example to the youth, and I believe hurtful to the minds of many—as also the custom of the overseers preparing answers to the queries before the preparative meeting, where they ought to be read and answered in the meeting by the overseers or some other solid Friend, first reading the query and then taking a solid pause, and then if any friend feel anything arise in the life and not else, which if faithfulness is abode in will not be wanting, though it should be, but to speak to part of a query, if that is observed, it will have a tendency perhaps to open the way for some other friend to say something further, and I believe this will spread the concern over the meeting and enable the clerk to form an answer agreeable to the sense of friends and the intensity of these queries answered, which is to quicken and stir up the minds of friends to a deep search. How they pass the time that in mercy is lengthened out from day to day in order to prepare for future happiness, that so we may do the work of our day in the day time, and lay down our heads in peace, and favour with the Lord, and be forever at rest where to know no more sorrow with the heavenly host.
Joshua</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-04">
<pb n="029"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-06-04">4 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Springfield first day meeting. This was a favoured meeting, and very large, as few of the houses are sufficient to hold anear all the people. At the close was a select conference to read and answer the queries for ministers and Elders. This was done in the most solid manner that had ever been and most to satisfaction, as several expressed. This was done in their meeting without having answers prepared beforehand, which I believe doth lay waste the service and intention of having queries and answers in our meetings, which is in best wisdom and might be a blessing, but there is a danger lest they become a snare to us if we look out for some easy way and go not deep, they will become a form only. This day is eight months since I left home on this visit.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-05"><dateline><date when="1797-06-05">5 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This morning was at another select conference at Deep River that was by adjournment held {at} this morning at my request instead of first day afternoon. This was a very trying time to me; I thought all was over and I now forced to turn my back in the day of battle, for I seemed to stand alone. But he who never did fail nor (I believe) never will was not far away at this season. When I saw there was none in heaven nor all the earth to trust in but the Lord alone, he then gave me power to plead his most holy cause and stand by his power. Trying as it was, I found him near and as at my right hand, and my bow renewed and strength given to use the same, whose arrows wound that lionlike nature which was brought down, that did too much appear. But I was so favoured both in this and the succeeding part of the day that it was cause of deep humble thanks to the God and father of all our mercies. In this meeting I had much service, both in men's and women's parts, though very clost yet it seemed well received, and a minute was made that my Gospel labors and service was to them truly acceptable {to them}. I believe we parted in nearer love than before for it was clearly felt my labors brought into greater nearness than we had experienced, and in this we parted, that {brought near} which bringeth nearer and nearer to each other.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-06"><dateline><date when="1797-06-06">6 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day had two favoured meetings with a people called Nicholites, having taken their names from one Joseph Nichols, who was the first of this Society. These <add>meetings</add> was very large, more especially the first of them that was for General notice for all sorts of people. But at the close of the first meeting I informed them that I should be glad to sit a little while with the Nicholites (all of them, and their children) by themselves, and that others would withdraw. This was complied with readily, and so in half an hour after the first meeting ended they came together again, and a solid favoured time it was. These are a very plain people in their dressing, being all of one plain color and that the natural. They are said to be very honest in their dealings and a sober people, and bear a good Character, but I thought I saw that Satan wanted to have them, that he might sift them as wheat is sifted in a sieve. I {thought}<add>would</add> they might be found as the weighty wheat and not as the chafe, for I could say I loved the<supplied>m</supplied>. One of their elders said they and we had a query against the excessive use of strong drink, but not against the excessive eating, which he thought was needed, for our tables was in danger of becoming a snare to us.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-07"><dateline><date when="1797-06-07">7 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Visited some sober friends, and in the evening had the company of an afflicted woman and her husband, to my comfort. We had some solid conversation concerning Friends' using goods imported on which was much money raised that went to defray all the expense of war, and that one not of our Society had this day told him that Friends must drop part of their principles or leave the use of those goods so imported while those monies defrayed all the expense of war.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-08">
<pb n="030"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-06-08">8 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day visited some widows and fatherless children, to my and their Comfort, as also a poor afflicted woman who needs the sympathy of friends.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-09"><dateline><date when="1797-06-09">9 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day began the quarterly meeting at New Garden, the select part. It was a poor low time but ended with some more life and power to labor for the cause of truth and the stirring up of Friends out of a state of ease and lukewarmness.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-10"><dateline><date when="1797-06-10">10 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Today transacted the business of the quarterly meeting of New Garden, in which I had much clost labor both in men's and women's part <add>Here I had to mention some hurtful customs, that of the youth and others getting together at cotton picking and quilting</add>, which was well received, and I hope will be as bread cast on the waters—not be soon forgot, but found after many day by the youth as well as others. I had to revive a custom in these parts: at the time of marriage of the young people signing the certificate before it was read, which I did believe was not safe to sign any instrument of writing before they knew what it was or heard it read. This seemed united with by some, but others seemed hard to move from their old customs as it is in all cases when of long, though bad and deep rooted. This meeting ended to general satisfaction and thought to profit, though held till near night in those long days. It seemed not tedious to me, being in master's work and service who richly rewardeth all his faithful laborers with peace of mind such as the world cannot give, neither can it take away. Blessed be his great and glorious name, and that for ever and ever.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-11"><dateline><date when="1797-06-11">11 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is First Day at the same place. Had two meetings today, as large as ever was known in this house—in the forenoon at large, for all sorts both young and old, which was almost silent, but that in the afternoon was appointed for the youth of all societies, selected from the aged such as parents and heads of families, but the young people only. This was the largest that was ever in this place, and a solid favoured time. It was a very humbling season to many of the youth. I stood on my feet, an usual time for me I suppose, near two hours all which time, though very crowded and weather warm, the people sat very quiet and solid. This meeting ended to edification and comfort, and a very large number of the youth came with tears in their eyes to take their leave of me, as it was thought it <add>was like to be</add> a farewell time, in which to part with such feeling nearness and love was cause of humble thankfulness to the Lord. May those favours never be forgot by his poor servants.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-12"><dateline><date when="1797-06-12">12 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting this day with the Nicholites again, as I had had two some time before this. Was held in a barn, large and solid to good satisfaction. Those are a plain people in dress and furniture, having all of the natural color, for they believe it not consistent with truth to paint or color anything either for clothing or furniture. These people avoid very much all superfluity. To me <add>they</add> appeared much in the moderation. They use the plain language, and are very honest in their dealings, and are in good esteem amongst their neighbors.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-13"><dateline><date when="1797-06-13">13 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day visited Naomi Whites school to good satisfaction.</p></div>

<div><del><p>14 and 15 the 6 month 1797. Traveled ninety miles to Bannister Meeting Virginia.</p></del></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-14"><dateline><date when="1797-06-14">14 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had two meetings at New Garden, it being their week day meeting, then at the close requested that parents and heads of families would stop, which they did, of all societies. This was a highly favored time, and ended to general comfort, and had this tendency to bring us nearer in feeling love to each other, as it is a time of parting for I have been some time in these parts, which made it hard to part with each other. This caused many of my dear friends of New Garden to shed tears as they came to bid me farewell, for a large number came to take their leave in feeling nearness and love this though hard yet a comfort.
<pb n="031"/>
For in the afternoon of this day came many, both young and old and some of other societies. Several of them signified in writing their unity with my service in these parts, as I had visited the most of their preparative, monthly, and quarterly meetings at Cane Creek and New Garden, and all the particular meeting within these two quarters, and visited a many families during this time. I made Timothy Russel’s my home, and the kindness of him and his wife as also a many other friends will not be soon forgot, for I wanted nothing to make me comfortable as to the outward, but I had much clost labor in a way that was much united with, though hard to comply with, for old deep rooted customs are not very easily broke off from when we behold the evil thereof, which is the case here in these parts as well as in others—that of a too free running to the stores for foreign things, and neglect the produce and plenty that this country affords with a little moderate labor would supply us with all that nature calls for, and that without this extensive trading which is carried on in so corrupt a way that I do not see how a conscientious person can meddle with, and especially those that do not hold with wars and fighting, as there is so large a duty now on goods thus imported and that money going to defray all war expenses, and those that consume those goods are those that pay the duties, and so aiding and assisting in ways which is directly inconsistent with all Christianity and that of doing as we would be done unto.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-15"><dateline><date when="1797-06-15">15 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This morning parted with Timothy Russell and dear wife and little daughter Sarey, aged about five years—she wept as though it was her father or mother. It affected my heart to see the love she had, as well as a number of dear young women who came to see me set off, as I had to travel near one hundred miles where was no Friends. These dear women friends came with such things as they thought I could be free to use, for as I was led in a way different from my dear brethren (though I could say I did dearly love them), yet I had a tender feeling towards taking life, which I believed most safe to attend to, as also the use of imported goods whilst it commanded so large a supply of that which was the sinews and strength of wars. These things, for conscience sake and in obedience to the teachings of grace, I thought safest for me to refrain from. This gave me more peace than all this world could do, and I wanted for no good thing. Blessed be God and that forever, who alone has provided for me and has made hard things easy, and bitter sweet, rough smooth, and crooked straight, whose ways are all ways of pleasantness, and all his path are peace. There is I find liberty enough in the truth and have no desire to look back.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-16"><dateline><date when="1797-06-16">16 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This and the foregoing day traveled from New Garden to Bannister 90 miles.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-17"><dateline><date when="1797-06-17">17 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Am waiting till first day so that they may spread notices, for here is but few Friends and they lie very scattering—I want to see them all.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-18"><dateline><date when="1797-06-18">18 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day was at Bannister first day meeting. This was so large, the house held not more than one third part of the people. This was a solid good meeting. As some expressed, the truth had <add>been</add> spoken this day. The people {at most of the} seem to come from all quarters, though some came perhaps out of curiosity. Yet the solid sitting of this meeting gives me cause to believe that it has had some good effect on many minds, which has been cause of humble thankfulness to the author of all good. For I clearly saw that the best of us are but as the saw in the hand of him that shaketh it, and nothing due to man, who is but
<pb n="032"/>
dust and can do nothing without divine help and holy aid.  This morning came a black man and requested that I would have a meeting with the black folks this afternoon. I told him I was free to grant his request at the fourth hour, and he might spread as much notice as he pleased. This was largely done, as there was a formal sermon preached (as is the custom in these parts, sometimes a week and sometimes months after the death of a person, and they are laid in the ground, and the grave part filled up, this gathering to preach as they say a funeral sermon, and fill up the grave, and perhaps is sometimes some months after the body is laid in the ground), the gathering this day (as it was a black person) gave opportunity to spread notice of this afternoon meeting, to which came a very large number of blacks and some whites. This was a favored time with these poor things.</p>
<p>I could say I was thankful my lot was to be with those poor things, both black and white, for here was a remarkable instance at Bannister Meeting—it being dropped for many years, perhaps more than twenty, and the house almost rotten down—that a religious young woman between eighteen and twenty, by name Elizabeth Hendrick, believed it her duty to go by herself, and sat down in that alone, nobody knowing where she went for some time, till at length she told a friend of hers and her sister that she could not be easy any other way, though it was alone when this was spread, some laughed and mocked. Yea her parents thought strange, but she continued steady. Her sister and one more came and sat with her, and so from so small a beginning, it is now become a considerable meeting held to good satisfaction, and I do believe had a right beginning, and that there is a number of innocent little ones, and the young woman is a worthy friend and in good esteem, and I believe has been an instrument in the hand of the Lord in doing much good. Let this be an encouragement for us all to be faithful to our duty, though it be but ever so much in the cross and in the littleness. I believe the Lord has blessed her labors. I write this for the encouragement of all the poor little ones.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-19"><dateline><date when="1797-06-19">19 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Traveled to Hills Creek where I met with the aforesaid Elizabeth Hendrick to my satisfaction, she being now at Micaiah Davises at school, where was one kept by his daughter in the meeting house, whose school I visited to my comfort, as here was some hopeful youth with whom I had a solid opportunity.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-20"><dateline><date when="1797-06-20">20 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a solid good meeting at Hills Creek. This was large. It is not common for the meeting houses to hold a near all the people, and many times not half.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-21"><dateline><date when="1797-06-21">21 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Seneca, rather low and not so large. Here met me several friends from South River where I went this afternoon.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-22"><dateline><date when="1797-06-22">22 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at South River in Virginia. This was large and favored. There was a many blacks, some of whom came with tears trickling down their faces, who in a solid manner took their leave of me some with feeling expressions.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-23"><dateline><date when="1797-06-23">23 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Went to Goose Creek and next day to Upper Goose Creek.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-25"><dateline><date when="1797-06-25">25 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Upper Goose Creek First Day meeting. This was a solid good meeting.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-26"><dateline><date when="1797-06-26">26 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at James Jonson’s, about ten miles above Goose Creek, up in the mountains, the upper part of Virginia. Here had never been a meeting held before, so that the people were strangers to Friends. Here I had my certificate read, at which they expressed satisfaction and wished the Lord would bless me and my labors. Here I had satisfaction as well, in the family as in the meeting, for they had a large family of hopeful children, for whom I was concerned at their remote situation, believing it is not best for Friends to move so remote with such a flock of children, who will be in danger of sociating with company not suitable. That outward interest should not be a sufficient inducement to run the risk of the ruin of our children for the sake of more land and <damage><gap/></damage> the better part.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-27">
<pb n="033"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-06-27">27 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Came back to Samuel Davises. Had some close labor respecting raising tobacco, as they could not make one shirt, coat, or any clothing for their families, or feed them with bread; therefore, their time might be better spent, and ground put to better use, to raise that which would feed and clothe their families without this extensive trade. These things is an exercise to my mind.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-28"><dateline><date when="1797-06-28">28 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was again at Upper Goose Creek weekday meeting, not very large yet a solid favored time here. They read and answered the queries to some degree of satisfaction, though a little meeting and but few friends.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-29"><dateline><date when="1797-06-29">29 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Lower Goose Creek Preparative Meeting. Here I had some very clost labor on the account (as I thought) of many deficiencies in raising fields of tobacco and the free use thereof, as I told them I thought raising tobacco and distilling spirits was so near <add>a sin</add> that I believed them best for Friends not to touch with, as they neither fed nor clothed the body, but was both a strong poison, but be content with the natural produce of our country, and <add>not</add> to be concerned in this extensive trade and dealing that is now carried on in so a corrupt a channel that the world see it not consistent with our principles to deal in and use those imported goods, on which so large a duty is now laid to raise money to defray all war expenses. Is not this, our hiring men to go to war as Soloman built the temple? This is the light that I see the consuming of those foreign goods in—the raising of money for all the purposes of war.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-06-30"><dateline><date when="1797-06-30">30 the 6 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day somewhat at leisure as their month meeting is tomorrow. I am willing to stay so as to attend the meeting.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-01"><dateline><date when="1797-07-01">1 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> The select conference adjourned til this morning. Here I had power given from on high to labor for truth’s cause to the comfort of friends, though in a clost way, as also in the other part for business, all which ended well. I was in the women's part also.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-02"><dateline><date when="1797-07-02">2 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is First Day. General notice was given of my being here this day, which caused the largest gathering of people that was ever seen at this place, but it was my lot to sit silent. As one informed me after meeting, some had said they had never known the Quakers sat silent when they had appointed a meeting, though they might at home. He thought it a favour and believed it would be of great service. I, not finding myself clear, proposed another meeting the fourth hour this afternoon. The people being desirous to hear me preach (as they called it), many stayed at the house till the fourth hour. These was most of them not Friends. The meeting was again very large, and a highly favoured season it was said to be by many who said they begrudged not their time in staying. I stood on my feet perhaps two hours or more, I believe to good satisfaction as was by several expressed. This was a parting season from Goose Creeks, as here in these parts are two of that name which constitutes this month meeting. We parted in feeling nearness and love such as will I believe not soon be forgot by some.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-03"><dateline><date when="1797-07-03">3 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day went a second time to Hills Creek, it being thirty m<supplied>iles</supplied>.</p></div>

	<div type="entry" n="1797-07-04"><dateline><date when="1797-07-04">4 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This morning went a second time to visit Susannah Davis's school, where was the greatest improvement that I had ever seen in two weeks, and the most beautiful order, she being a young woman of a steady behavior. <gap><supplied>The</supplied></gap> school consisted of nine scholars. This did more fully convince me of the <gap><supplied>adv</supplied></gap>antage of small numbers both to scholars and employers, from spelling <gap><supplied>to r</supplied></gap>eading and writing, and that to my astonishment, and that in two weeks, for some <gap><supplied>of th</supplied></gap>em read distinctly and wrote a plain hand that was in their spelling books when <gap><supplied>I vi</supplied></gap>sited that school two weeks before this. I write for the encouragement of <gap><supplied>yo</supplied></gap>ung friends both male and female, not to be discouraged nor want too many scholars, but be content with small gain and live low.</p></div>

<div><pb n="034"/>
<head>The Negro's Prayer</head>
<p>The following prayer was penned by a black man a slave in the lower parts of Virgina, and was presented by him to his master, which struck him with admiration and surprise as he acknowledged to a friend written in 1790.</p>

<lg>
<l>Lord if thou dost with Equal Eyes</l>
<l>see all the <add>sons</add> of Adam rise</l>
<l>Why dost thou hide thy face from slaves </l>
<l>Confin{e}'d by fate to serve such knaves</l>
<l>stolen and sold in africa</l>
<l>Transported to America</l>
<l>like hogs and sheep in market sold </l>
<l>to stand the heat and bear the cold</l>
<l>to work all day and half the night</l>
<l>and rise before the morning light</l>
<l>sustain the lash endure the pain</l>
<l>Exposed to storms of snow and rain</l>
<l>Pinch{e}'d both with Hunger and with cold</l>
<l>If we complain we meet a scold</l>
<l>and after all the tedious round</l>
<l>at night like Beasts lie on the ground</l>
<l>Hath Heaven decreed that Negroes must </l>
<l>By cruel men be ever crush{e}'d</l>
<l>forever drag the Galling chain</l>
<l>And ne{v}'er enjoy themselves again</l>
<l>When will Jehovah hear our cries</l>
<l>When will the son of freedom rise</l>
<l>When will a Moses for us stand</l>
<l>And free us all from Pharaoh's hand</l>
<l>What tho' our skin be black as Jet</l>
<l>Our hair be curl{e}'d, our Noses flat</l>
<l>Must we for this no freedom have</l>
<l>until we find it in the grave</l>
<pb n="035"/>
<l>yet while I thus my fate condole</l>
<l>Jesus my Lord possess my soul </l>
<l>that when my slavery here shall end</l>
<l>I may ascend to thee my friend</l>
<l>Tho' here is none to plead my cause</l>
<l>My soul appeals to thy Just Laws</l>
<l>Who will bring all things to the light</l>
<l>I know thy Judgments Lord are right</l>
<l>for all the comforts that I have</l>
<l>Whilst I am here confin{e}'d a slave</l>
<l>Is that strong hope that I{ a}'m made free</l>
<l>By thy rich Blood once shed for me</l>
<l>My soul is free it can{no}'t be sold</l>
<l>for all the Gold that can be told</l>
<l>and when my body drops in Dust</l>
<l>My spirit in thy hand I trust</l>
<l>and tho no coffin I shall have</l>
<l>Nor yet be Laid in a<add>ny</add> grave</l>
<l>The Lord shall watch it from the skies</l>
<l>Til the great Trumpet bids it rise</l>
<l>Contentment Lord on me bestow</l>
<l>While I remain a slave below</l>
<l>And while I suffer grief and wrong</l>
<l>May thy salvation be my song</l>
</lg>
<p>a true copy transcribed 30th 6 month 1797.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-05">
<pb n="036"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-07-05">5 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Seneca, weekday meeting there. They had the liberty of reading the queries and answering them. Though the meeting was small, yet they was favoured in their answers to go deep into things, to my comfort.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-06"><dateline><date when="1797-07-06">6 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day traveled to South River a second time.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-07"><dateline><date when="1797-07-07">7 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is South River preparative meeting. It was exercising, though power was given to labor for truth’s cause to good satisfaction here. As is much the custom in these parts for the overseers to prepare the answers beforehand so as to have them ready and make the work easy, and so it does, for it's common to read both queries and answers, and {not} perhaps not a word said to the business, for the work is done. This I do believe will be in danger of making the queries becoming a snare, and making members which might become useful as dead weights, and instead <add>of</add> their ministering life, they will minister death. For I do believe the queries ought to be read and considered in the meeting, where they ought to be spoken to by the overseers or any other solid Friend, and then and there the Clerk, having gathered the solid sense of Friends, ought to prepare answers—and not till then, as I do believe it requireth the help of the spirit to enable in this work as in that of preaching the gospel, without which neither can be done to profit. In the afternoon it was purposed holding the select conference, but I thought it might be better to adjourn that till tomorrow morning preceding the monthly meeting. This was united with.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-08"><dateline><date when="1797-07-08">8 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This morning the select members met. It was but a low time. Then {a solid time was held} at the {opening}<add>transacting</add> of the business, which was a favoured season both in mens and womans part. I <add>had</add> much clost labor which held till near sunset, all to good satisfaction as far as appeared.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-09"><dateline><date when="1797-07-09">9 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is First Day meeting at South River in the forenoon as common, and in the afternoon at the third hour with the Blacks, and at the close of that with the Blacks, another meeting with the slave holders. These were all large, and a most solid day it was to many minds, and all ended to good satisfaction with all sorts. Blessed, magnified, and forever praised be the Lord our God, who hath from time to time been pleased to renew my bow in my hand and give ability to draw the same in the lamb's warfare.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-10"><dateline><date when="1797-07-10">10 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This and the next day I spent in visiting the Black free people, as there is near or quite twenty families. This visit was much to my and their satisfaction. There appeared great tenderness in some of them, but the low degraded and neglected way of their bringing up is most lamentable, even amongst Friends. This was cause of mourning to me; this I laid clost to some, but not to the relief of my mind, for custom has a powerful influence. They have always been held to do the drudgery and to be set below their children, and some of them half naked, hardly clothes to cover their nakedness, and perhaps not washed for weeks till as black as their skins, when their children is fine and gay {and needlessly dressed}<add>with costly clothing</add> that which would be a blessing to those poor sufferers who must stand at the laboring ore.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-12">
<pb n="037"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-07-12">12 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day had a meeting at a little town on James River called Lynchburg, with the blacks of this town in the morning, and then at the eleventh hour a public one, which was very large and favoured. There was a many of those of high life, fine and gay dressed. I had much clost labor for truth’s cause and the good of souls, all which ended well and for the honor of the Lord and his most holy cause. Those high life people sat solid and very commendably for the most part though not acquainted with Friends.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-13"><dateline><date when="1797-07-13">13 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is their week day meeting at South River. It was a solid time.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-14"><dateline><date when="1797-07-14">14 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day visited a sick woman whose husband was a negro driver. Here I was again tried: came out of their poor little houses, a number of poor naked Black children as naked as ever they was born, girls and boys to all appearance, ten or twelve years of age. I said, <q>have women no shame? If the devil has hardened the hearts of men so as to have no shame, can women not blush to see their nakedness?</q> Then <add>as I</add> rode <add>on my way</add>, here was ten Negroes hoeing tobacco and seven of them women and came out of these houses where they lie and live like or worse than dogs; a large number more poor distressed Black children much like the before mentioned. This is the most of all things wicked: the usage of those poor black people.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-15"><dateline><date when="1797-07-15">15 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day began the quarterly meeting at South River, the select part, which was a solid time, and power given to labor in the good cause.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-16"><dateline><date when="1797-07-16">16 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is first day meeting at South River. It was the largest gathering by half than was ever seen at this place. The house held not more then half the people. It was a highly favoured season and to general satisfaction. I suppose I stood on my feet near if not quite two hours, which is not common for me to do. Although there was of all sorts, black and white, and some of them of high life, yet truth was in dominion over all. Considering the crowded situation, it was remarked for stillness and the solemnity that attended during the whole setting, and many hearts tendered. Blessed be the great name of Israel's God who has never nor never will fail his truly depending children in the most trying time of all.</p></div>


<div type="entry" n="1797-07-17"><dateline><date when="1797-07-17">17 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is the day of transacting the business of the quarter, and in which the queries was read and answered. Here I had much labor to promote the cause of truth and in reviving some ancient testimonies with respect to plainness of speech, behaviour, and apparel, as also house furniture, which is much departed from in calling our children Betsey, Polly, Peggy, and Nancy, and Tom, Jack, and Harry, when Elizabeth, Mary, Margaret, and Ana, Thomas, John, and Henry is their names given them. I thought <add>it was</add> as far from plainness as <q>you</q> to a single person, and came in at the same door and sprang from the old corrupt root of pride, and the many new fashionings in house furniture that has crept in at the back door. In the night season while people slept the Enemy sowed the evil seed, which, when it sprang up, it bore fruit of this kind: dram drinking, smoking, and chewing tobacco, as also the use of foreign teas, and coffee [inserted: curious vessels of China and silver and [inserted: curious] beds and bedding, sumptuous tables as also of charable <gap/>]. All which our ancient worthies had to bear testimony against to their dying day, which though they are dead yet their testimony liveth, and I believe will live forever, and that the Lord will raise up those who will have to sound them as on the Lord's holy mountain, as with a trumpet set to their mouths. For I do believe these things are departing from the truth, however custom may have reconciled them at this time, for plainness becometh us as a people and there is liberty enough in the truth for young and old.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-18">
<pb n="038"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-07-18">18 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day parted with Friends in near and dear feeling love. Many came in great tenderness to take leave of me, both black and white, to where I lodged at Christopher Johnson's. Also, yesterday at the close of the meeting, it seemed a tender time I believe. Although in these parts I had much clost labor for the master's cause and good of souls, yet I believe I left a good savor for truth and Friends, some of which will not soon be forgot by some, but be as bread cast on the water found after many day. In these meetings, both amongst men and women, the dreadful desolation of wars and destroying the poor Indians and taking their land, first by the point of the sword and then under a pretense in order to cover their wickedness—give them some trifle and then say they have bought their land, when at first and by force they drove them by burning their towns and cutting in pieces their wives and children, and that without mercy. And we are contributing towards hiring those men and maintaining them whilst in this barbarity, by the use of those imported goods on which money is raised by duties to defray all war expenses. And it is unitedly agreed that those who consume those goods indirectly pay those duties, and so cannot stand clear of doing to others as they would not be done unto. Therefore, what shall we say in the day of account, when all things are brought to the true light, and before Him whose Judgments are true and will do right, the Lord of hosts, who will not condemn the Just, nor acquit the guilty, nor spare the wicked, nor let them go free, but give them the reward of their works.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-19"><dateline><date when="1797-07-19">19 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Traveled to Bannister a second time in company with several Friends, not apprehending myself clear of that place. It seemed to be a poor low time of great strippedness and poverty with me, but I believe all for my good and in wisdom, so that no man should exult nor glory in anything but in the Cross and humbly submitting to the divine will, for self hath nothing to do in the Lord's work.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-20"><dateline><date when="1797-07-20">20 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Bannister a second time. It was very large and solid. In this appeared much tenderness, and at our parting came many of all ranks to take leave of me with tears, expressing their love, saying they should love me as long as they lived, if they should never see me no more. I thought I had a belief that the cause of truth would gain ground in this place, for it was revived in a manner uncommon by a young woman from a concern to go and sit by her self for some time, till at length her sister and one more came and sat with her, till now it is a meeting granted, and they have the privilege of reading and answering the queries and are united in proposing to build a new house as the old one is far too small. This was fully agreed on at the close of this meeting, as the old one this day contained not half the people. These, though few in number, subscribed near what was thought to be the expense; some of the young women subscribed ten pounds. This was a favoured time.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-21"><dateline><date when="1797-07-21">21 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day traveled fifty-five miles to the Widow Durham's.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-22"><dateline><date when="1797-07-22">22 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at {Henry Stanford's, where was never a Friends' meeting held before nor any of them that was acquainted with Friends, nor was at any of their meetings} <add>the Widow Durham's</add>. This was to general satisfaction. These was a people of very high life, but to my admiration they appeared much humbled and for the most part sat very solid, and when we parted many came and bid me farewell in a tender frame of mind and gave me their blessing in their way yet in a solid manner, and, I believe, from an heartfelt sense.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-23">
<pb n="039"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-07-23">23 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Henry Stanford's. This was very large, of all sorts both black and white being for the most part never at Friends' meeting before, and seemed at first to appear very dearingly, but the man of the house and his wife appeared very friendly and desired we might use freedom, for they was not acquainted with Friends' custom of meetings. This was a highly favoured time, truth was over all, and power given to labor for the glory of God and the good of souls. The loftiness of the lofty was brought down. I suppose I stood on my feet near two hours. It was an humbling season, and I believe to good satisfaction, for when I came away at our parting, many came and bid me farewell in a very friendly way and manner, and these was gay dressed with large hankerchiefs pinned over their heads in this hot season—why so? Because it's fashionable, and that must be complied with however grievous it may be to the poor body—if it should even take life itself, as I do believe it doth shorten the days of many.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-24"><dateline><date when="1797-07-24">24 the 7 month</date></dateline><p> This day had a meeting at Jared Ladd's, large and solid, I trust. Ended well, but here is in these parts much dearth and darkness as ever I remember, I believe by reason of slavery. They train up their children to domineer and in a manner to tyrannize over the poor black and to use as a disdainful a language as they use to their days which is <q>be gone.</q> This language I could say I did hate to hear used to the poor black.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-25"><dateline><date when="1797-07-25">25 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Featherston Sadler's, this large and an highly favoured time, and many appeared tendered, and some said they had never heard the truth so spoken in all their lives before. Another said he thought so too. <q>I wish,</q> said he, <q>he had continued an hour longer.</q> Many of these people came in much tenderness to take leave of me with wishes that I might prosper. This was a comfort, to believe I had left a good savor for the cause of truth. This crowns all and is all that I want is God's glory and the good of souls.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-26"><dateline><date when="1797-07-26">26 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Traveled thirty-five miles from Featherston Sadler's to Gravelly Run.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-27"><dateline><date when="1797-07-27">27 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Gravelly Run fifth day meeting. It was said to be the largest that was ever seen in that place. Here I had clost labor for the good master's cause, which appeared well received, after which I felt very low and much stripped <gap/>at I often think I shall never preach no more. Yet the Lord is so kind <gap/> few silent meetings since I left home, though some and them has <gap/> of the largest where has been great expectations, whereas I was told afterwards that some people had a belief the Quakers never appointed meetings when traveling, but what they did say something, though when at home might be silent. And some poor things had on first day when first gathered broke up this meeting to come and hear me preach, and when came to our meeting, I had nothing to say. This was another great disappointment, but no marvel to me for if it was right for them to come to gather on so solemn occasion as to perform divine service, I believe it was not right for them to leave their meetings for the sake of hearing me preach, and I believe it was the good master's will to give me nothing to say. This I believe was all in wisdom and quite right not to feed that spirit.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-28"><dateline><date when="1797-07-28">28 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Petersburg in Virginia on James River, it is a little town. We held it in the Courthouse. This was not large, thought by rea<gap><supplied>son</supplied></gap> of neglect of notice being spread, yet there was a very considerable number came (as I believe) of the most unthinking sort as to any good. This I had to revive in their hearing, as also their unfitness to die and leave the world, if they had any desire to go to rest and peace, or to be where the righteous are. For their thoughts, I did believe,  was almost continually evil, and their words not better, (for I did believe they stuck not at profane language, no, not to take God's name in vain) whose deeds was also evil and th<gap/> amongst the leaders of the people and such as should be a terror to evil-doers and a praise to that do well. This kind of doctrine seemed to draw their attention, and I believe was well taken, and tendered some of their hearts bad as they was. I do believe ended well.</p></div>

<div>
<pb n="040"/>
<note type="structure">On the page numbered 40, the journal entries are interrupted by “a true Coppey of the Nicholites Queries” as recorded by Joshua Evans in 1797. The  version of Evans’ journal published in <title>Friends Miscellany</title>, pages 173-174, contains the following statement: “When I was among those called Nicholites, in North Carolina, I observed they had nine queries, which in substance were much like ours: these they read at times in their meetings….” Friends Miscellany does not include the text of the queries.  For a discussion of the Nicholite queries, see  Kenneth Carroll, <title>Joseph Nichols and the Nicholites</title> (Easton, Maryland: Easton Publishing Company, 1962), 38-42.</note>
<list>
<item>21 are all friends that hath a reasonable opportunity Diligent to attend their meetings duly and timely both for worship and discipline and are friends striving against sleeping or Needlessly moving about or any other unbecoming behaviour therein</item>

<item>22 are friends Careful to maintain Love and unity amongst them is tale bearing backbiting and evil reports discouraged and when any difference arise is speedy Endeavors used to End them</item>

<item>23 are friends Careful to bring up them who are under their Care and direction to the due attendance of meetings to plainness of speech behaviour and apparel to frequent reading the scriptures and other useful books and from reading pernicious Books and from needlessly frequenting the Company of those of a Disorderly behavior and from the Corrupt Conversation of the world</item>

<item>24 are friends Careful to be Just in all their dealings to giving good weight and Measure and avoid that Evil practice of Multiplying words to set their stuff to sale</item>

<item>25 are friends Careful to settle their accounts yearly or as oft as may require and in a way so as to give their Creditors no Just Cause to blame them are the Necessities of the poor the faithless and the widows attended too and they assisted ageable to their Circumstance</item>

<item>26 Are friends Careful not to make any wrong use of spirituous Liquors and when their business takes them out amongst other people are they Careful to avoid light and Needless discourse and not to be drawn away with the Errors of the wicked</item>

	<item>27 are friends Carefully guarding against superfluity and Excess in all its various branches Endeavoring a temperate use <gap/> so as to beare A steady <gap/> the prevailing sin of Luxury and pride</item>

<item>28 is Care taken to deal regular with offenders in the spirit of meekness and wisdom without partiality or unnecessary delay </item>

<item>29 are friends Careful to bear a steady testimony against slavery and oppression in all its defining branches and Endeavour in Every thing to do to others as we in the like Case would have others to do to us</item>
</list>
<closer>This is a true Copy of the Nicholites Queries by Joshua Evans in 1797 copied.</closer>
</div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-29">
<pb n="041"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-07-29">29 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> We poor travelers, pilgrims, and sojourners have many proving seasons, I believe all for our good and safety, that we may be kept humble and have no confidence in the flesh nor what we can do without holy aid and assistance. This I have often been made in my experience to confess, and to acknowledge God's goodness and mercies to me in preparing the way before me and being a present helper in every time of need. Blessed, magnified, and forever praised be his great and glorious name, saith all that is within me and at this time doth humbly bow under a sense of his gracious goodness, loving kindness, and mercy to me, a poor pilgrim engaged in, as I hope his word and service, having left all for Christ’s sake and the gospel with desire to do his work faithfully, come what may come.</p>
<p>I was informed about this time of some things that I thought very remarkable. It was told me by a Friend who said it might be depended to be true. Several people playing at cards, came on a thunder storm so severe that some of them thought best to leave off for the present and lay down and go to sleep, which they did. One of them was killed with the lightning, and the others much hurt but was like to recover. As also another alarming instance, a young man and a young woman was riding the rode in a gust when it thundered hard. The young man was rather alarmed, said he thought they was too rude at such a time. The young woman laughed at the young man, and so laughing was struck dead <add>with lightning</add> and so continued—they could never alter the form of her mouth, but when dead appeared as one laughing. I thought best to note these circumstances that it might serve for a warning for others {as a warning}, so that none may be taken so unprepared as those poor things seems to have been, not considering the uncertainty of time, and that we stand no more but as the monuments of God's mercies, and should be always ready and sin not least the thread of our life be Cut at a time, when we was not looking for such a Change from time to Eternity.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-30"><dateline><date when="1797-07-30">30 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Curls first day meeting, which was very large, the most that was ever seen at this place, and I thought it might be said a solid favoured time. Many appeared tendered. It ended well and to comfort.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-07-31"><dateline><date when="1797-07-31">31 the 7 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Wine Oak. This was a poor low season and small.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-01"><dateline><date when="1797-08-01">1 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Skimino. This was large and to edification and comfort. Here I had some clost labor for the cause of the Lord in pleading with the people against the prevailing customs of the world in all its various sinful ways—in ornamenting these bodies, that they was more concerned about adorning their heads than their hearts, and their bodies than than [sic] their souls, with many other remarks with respect to making a right and a suitable preparation against a dying hour, that none may be found unprepared and so miss of eternal happiness and have their portion in that place of torment, which we read of. These things I laid very pressingly to them, which seemed all well received. This meeting ended well, and I believed the cause of truth gained ground in the hearts of some, and we parted friendly.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-02"><dateline><date when="1797-08-02">2 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This being their meeting day and preparative, in which they was to read and answer their queries, as I had purposed to be at a meeting one hundred miles off in two days, if they would meet in the morning at the eighth hour, I should be free to sit with them, to which they readily agreed. They being but a few in number met according to appointment. It was, as they said, an edifying time and much to their satisfaction. After this meeting, we crossed James River at Jamestown in Virginia, and travel forty miles that day. Had a favorable passage over the river. Though gusty season, yet I did believe the Lord did provide for and prosper our way to home. I have cause to ascribe, all blessed be his great name.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-03">
<pb n="042"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-08-03">3 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> The third and fourth traveled to Jack Swamp in order to attend that month meeting. In my passing on my way, had a firm belief that I was where I ought to be, and in the great good master's service whose work I desire to do faithfully, and I believe I left my home and all that is near and dear to me in the right time. For many said there had not been so favourable a season (since their memory) for traveling as this has been many ways, for which I have been often humbly bowed before the God and father of all sure Mercies, who has Marvelously prepared the way before me so, as no man could have done. I feel myself wholly devoted to the Lord, to do as he may please with me till he should think best to take me from time, and then all I ask is to be in favour at the reckoning day, to receive a penny at last. Oh, that I may die in God's favor and go where to know no more sorrow. I, at this time, feel all that is with in me bow in awful reverence with this language: Great and marvelous are thy works, O Lord God almighty; just and true are all thy ways, thou king of kings, hallelujah; and praise is in my soul at this time. This day makes ten months since I left home.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-05"><dateline><date when="1797-08-05">5 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day was at Jack Swamp month meeting in North Carolina. This is a poor weak meeting. I had much clost labor, but there is some formalist old Friends that was hard to bend or move out of their dens and helds, but there was some others that was tender spirited, but that number is but small. My labors was well received according to a minute that was made by the clerk and they united with, that my service had been very acceptable. We parted very friendly, both men and women. One Friend at the close of the meeting stood up and said he did not want to multiply words, but thought he had thus much to say: that if what had been said was not regarded but forgot, it would lay heavy against them in a day of trial, for they had been sound gospel truths and what they stood in much need of; so that I believe all ended well, and for the honor of truth, and I often say that is enough and all I want. Many, both men and women, came to where I lodged, where we had a comfortable opportunity and parted in feeling nearness and love.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-06"><dateline><date when="1797-08-06">6 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is first day meeting at Jack Swamp, it was very large. I had much clost labor for truth’s cause and the good of souls, for here was a many of the bad folks. I also had an invitation to a burial of a Friend whose body had been laid in the ground two or three weeks, as is and has been a custom in these parts—not only with them of other societies, but Friends had fell in with that custom of burying their dead. The custom is lay the corpse in the ground and fill the grave near the top, and so leave the other part till a priest could attend, and then fill the remaining part and have a sermon, and so powerful is custom that Friends have fell in with the same. I told them I had such a Testimony to bear against such a practice as that I could not go. They say they are somewhat coming out of that way and custom.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-07">
<pb n="043"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-08-07">7 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day we traveled twenty-seven miles towards Vicks's.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-08"><dateline><date when="1797-08-08">8 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day had a meeting at Vicks's, this not large, thought by reason of short notice and a stormy day, though the house was full. The people sat solid, and I believe ended well.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-09"><dateline><date when="1797-08-09">9 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day had a meeting at Black Creek, this was large, both black and whites. A very tendering time it was, and more particularly amongst the blacks, some of whom wept almost aloud. This was a favoured season I believe to many.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-10"><dateline><date when="1797-08-10">10 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Stanton's. This was so large that it was, though<supplied>t</supplied> that not more then half the people could not get in the house; they had made seats for them without as is common, for there is but few houses that can hold all the people. The wearing of my beard has been of great use, for it is thought that I have seen thousands more than I should have seen if not on this account, and for the most part it has been remarked the most tender seasons that was ever known. Some who had never been seen at a Friends' meeting was a number of the gay sort who was seen weeping and appeared in a tender frame of mind, one of which came after meeting and spoke to me, and said, <q>You have this day spoke the truth for I witnesed it to be so.</q> This man was seen to weep in the meeting. He had but seldom been at a meeting before.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-11"><dateline><date when="1797-08-11">11 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Johnsons', not large. It was a poor low time. In those parts is a large number of wicked people, I had a belief, occasioned from the oppression of the blacks, which has been a hurt to both young and old.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-12"><dateline><date when="1797-08-12">12 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is the select quarter at Black Water. It was an heart searching time. I had some clost labor all, which was well taken I believe.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-13"><dateline><date when="1797-08-13">13 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is first day. This was the largest meeting that was ever seen at this place, but very unsettled for want of more room in the house—though large, but it was thought half the people could not get in. I was nearly silent. This seemed a disappointment, for many come to hear a man that bore such a character as I did preach, but I had a desire not to move without ability from on high.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-14"><dateline><date when="1797-08-14">14 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is the meeting for business. It is their custom not to open the partition between men and women. This is agreeable to my mind, that at such times as meetings for discipline to be no public times for worship, but the women gather in their part and men in their part with the shutters closed and, after a solid pause, enter on the business without any stirring, or breaking up, or going out, or unsettlement of mind. This was a laborious time, and more especially in the women's part, respecting the prevailing fashions and customs of the world we as a people are running into and following of. Feeling near the close not clear respecting people of other societies (there not being room for the them in the house the days before) to have a meeting on third day with them only and not Friends.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-15">
<pb n="044"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-08-15">15 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> About the time appointed the meeting gathered at Black Water the day following the quarter, and a large meeting of both black and white, all not of our society except a few solid Friends. This was believed to be a favoured solid good meeting and ended to the honor of truth, as many expressed their satisfaction, both black and white. I was ready to say the last one is the best, and good is the Lord, let none despair of his mercies, for they are great and has been my shield and buckler this day in overcoming all the Golia<supplied>t</supplied>h-like spirits, for it was an humbling season and very solid.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-16"><dateline><date when="1797-08-16">16 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting a second time at Burley, as I stopped last fall at this place. This was a poor low time. The life and power was wanting. It was their preparative meeting, but it was a poor lifeless time throughout, I but little encouragement to labor; but as I found them, so I left them.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-17"><dateline><date when="1797-08-17">17 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a second meeting at Petersburg in the courthouse. It was the largest and the most solid that was ever seen in that town, where is no Friends. This ended to the honor of the cause of truth. I was thankful that I was there. We crossed James River second time.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-18"><dateline><date when="1797-08-18">18 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at the monthly meeting at White Oak being held by an adjournment on my account so that I might attend, as I could not without such an adjournment. This was when their queries and answers was read, and the conference of the select members here is too much form, the substance wanting; as to religion things, was at a low ebb, and but little prospect of a revival.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-19"><dateline><date when="1797-08-19">19 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Black Creek on the east side of James River. It was rather exercising, but thought ended well. In passing along, I had many solid seasons in families to good satisfaction. Here is a few hopeful youth.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-20"><dateline><date when="1797-08-20">20 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting in the town of Richmond, in a small house Friends had prepared for that purpose. This was held in the morning, and solid favoured time it was, and ended comfortably. And in the afternoon had another in the state house in a large room, when I believe the most part of the inhabitants came. It was thought there had never been so many at a meeting at that place before. A great many appeared very solid, but not all. It was thought a profitable time. There appeared a many tender spirited ones; they came very tenderly to take their leave of me, great and small. I {yet} feel myself not clear of this town as yet; the people take great liberty many ways.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-21"><dateline><date when="1797-08-21">21 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a third meeting at Richmond in the state house, not so large as yesterday, yet a large number it was—now a working day, the other was first day afternoon. Those meetings all ended well as was believed.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-22"><dateline><date when="1797-08-22">22 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day traveled towards Genito. I had in my passing along many poor, low, baptizing seasons by reason of the abounding of sin and iniquity, which I believe more prevails in these southern governments than anywhere I have traveled before, for slave-keeping has had a tendency to harden the hearts of both young and old, for tyranny and oppression {have}<add>doth</add> prevailed.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-23"><dateline><date when="1797-08-23">23 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Genito meeting when they answered the queries and did the business of their preparative meeting. It was a solid good time and ended well. I had some clost labor in those parts for truth’s cause that will be as bread cast on the waters found after many days, and to some as a nail fixed in a sure place will be retained fresh in the minds of many.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-24"><dateline><date when="1797-08-24">24 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at a meeting that was adjourned on my account. It was a preparative, in which the queries was read and answered here. I had some clost labor for truth’s cause, for I saw many wrong things getting in among Friends and none to gainsay them by life and practice, though the advices from the yearly meeting was read and appointments made.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-25">
<pb n="045"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-08-25">25 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This morning their school committee met at the eighth hour, for Friends had a school under the care of this meeting. But it was a poor one, though (as I had seen in some such schools) when the trustees met all things made a fine appearance as though children was the finest readers and writers that I had ever seen. But I went and sat by the teacher, asked <add>him</add> if he would please to give me those scholar's books. {They came and read a little more} Then I opened a place where they had not got by heart; here they could read but poorly. Then they was called on to say some passage they had got by heart, which was by way of argument, as though in the House of Assembly, {some one thing and then another}<add>or as though pleading law one against the other</add>, then was called on to tell where and how such countries laid, some of which I knew was very erroneous where I had traveled. These things—with reading very pernicious books, such as related to wars and fighting—these things to fill the minds of children with, gave me pain and deep exercise, which I did freely signify before I left them, believing these things not fit for Friends' schools. But for Friends' children to learn to read English well, and write well, and as many figures as to keep their accounts was learning enough in general for Friends to handle the tools of any common trademan or husbandman—which I would recommend that Friends bring up their children, in a course of industry, not in high life, so that they may live by {the trust of other men's}<add>their own</add> labor and that their own hands should minister to their own necessities. And if Friends should want a clerk knowing how to write well and read writing of any kind, this would (if other ways qualified) fit them for usefulness in Society. This is my sense and judgment, and I feel most easy to leave it, that it may be seen when I am dead and gone as my testimony. Filling the dear little children's minds with things so hurtful, as early impressions take the deepest root. Oh, how much guarded care ought we to have in the education of children, so that they may walk in the way of holiness and end in peace with the Lord?</p>
<p>This afternoon, the select meeting of conference before the month meeting at Cedar Creek. This was a laborious time, and many clost hints was given that seemed well received. I believe the meeting ended well.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-26"><dateline><date when="1797-08-26">26 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is their month meeting at Cedar Creek. Here was another clost day's work, both with men and women, which ended well.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-27"><dateline><date when="1797-08-27">27 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is first day meeting, the largest by far that was ever seen at this place, and the most rude behavior that I ever saw. It was more like a fair time than a place for worship, but they say it is common. So at this season they had watermelons and spirits for sale during the meeting time, and almost all unbecoming behavior, but a few appeared solid. I informed them it was not becoming the occasion for which we were met, and that I was desirous to have another meeting this afternoon, and hoped they would behave better than what they had done at this time, for I was afraid the sin which was committed outdoors was more than all the good done by coming together, for the negro masters would send them here to market. But what I said had a good effect, for we had in the afternoon a solid good meeting and ended well. This morning the select members met. It was (I thought) not a suitable time, but, the meeting gathering, I proposed adjourning til second day morning, which was agreed to. I also proposed their thinking on a more suitable time for holding their select meeting than first day morning.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-28">
<pb n="046"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-08-28">28 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This morning, the select members met about time adjourned to. It was a solid time and much clost labor for truth’s cause, which was well received, for I thought the world and the love of wrong things was prevailing, and that amongst ministers and elders. This I had clostly to lay before them, and what would be the consequence if those gave way, and not to tell others to do that we would not do ourselves. For to preach one thing and practice another would be hurting the cause and render such as the salt that had lost its savor, henceforth good for nothing, for nothing more so than an old formalist Quaker. These things was well taken though clost.</p>
<p>This day the business. It was but a poor low time, both with men and women.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-29"><dateline><date when="1797-08-29">29 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day went towards Caroline meeting.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-30"><dateline><date when="1797-08-30">30 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Caroline large and I think favoured.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-08-31"><dateline><date when="1797-08-31">31 the 8 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Then went to Stafford this day.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-01"><dateline><date when="1797-09-01">1 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Stafford, solid good meeting rather long agathering.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-02"><dateline><date when="1797-09-02">2 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a good meeting at South Land in Virginia and traveled 55, and in the morning visited that school held in the meeting house to my comfort.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-03"><dateline><date when="1797-09-03">3 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Culpeper. It was a solid meeting. As one said, it was the plainest doctrine that he had ever heard preached, and expressed his satisfaction, and wished me well - that the main thing was to be right good, and not by the halves - that would not do, as I had told them that they had tried all things but that of being right good. I said I would have them come and try that, and it would no doubt bring comfort to their souls. This, and the like, was the doctrine that I had to preach that he spoke w[missing].</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-04"><dateline><date when="1797-09-04">4 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Traveled to Crooked Run in Virginia, with thoughts respecting the scattered situation of Friends, with this belief: they are too much so for the honour of truth and good of their children. But I believe if Friends had been content with less of the honors of this world, and sought the honour of God and the good of their own souls, less would have done. And we lived more as one family and as in the land of Goshen, where the Lord would not have suffered his judgments to have reached, no more new than he did in the land of Egypt when they would not let Israel go, neither famine, sword, nor pestilence, which threateneth this our land at this time. And in some places it has fallen heavy, and we have had a share in the oppression of the Indians and Negroes, which if the blood of Able cried from the earth that had opened her mouth to receive his blood and had reached the holy ear, what must the blood of so many thousand of poor Indians and Negroes that has been slain in this land - and our hands not clear of contributing to the shedding so much innocent blood, and coveting their land, and so nearly following the armies who cut in pieces men, women, and children without mercy - is this doing to others as we would they should do to us? No, no, far from that, but I believe has been the cause why the Lord is thus threatening this land and manifesting his displeasure, because of sin and inequity which doth much abound at this time.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-05">
<pb n="047"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-09-05">5 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had two meetings, one at Crooked Run, another at Mount Pleasant, the first large, in which I had much clost labor for the good master’s cause that was well received as far as appeared, and ended well. That in the afternoon, small but a comfortable season. Truth’s cause lies low, the general customs of the are vain, which makes it hard for the little few to stem the rapid force of the current of the spirit of this world. I said what will become of the little ones, whose delight is in the Lord; they must endeavor to take their refuge under the divine wing, which is a safe heading place for all the righteous. In every time of trouble, Jerusalem is a quiet habitation and a place of refuge and a sheltering place for all the little ones that are babes in Christ.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-06"><dateline><date when="1797-09-06">6 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Sento near Winchester in Virginia. This was long agathering and laborious time. Their did appear some tenderness. After which we rode twenty five miles towards Redstone, lodged at a tavern where we was entertained, though in these parts, the people much inclined to music. They began to play on the fiddle. I told them it would be more agreeable to me if they would lay by the fiddle, which they readily did and excused themselves by saying it was the Negroes.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-07/1797-09-08"><dateline><date from="1797-09-07" to="1797-09-08">7 and 8th 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Got over the Allegheny mountains to a meeting called the plaids, or Sandy Creek. In this journey we travelled hard, but I held well my ride. At this place we had a meeting, the 9 day small and poor, then travelled to Benson Town, being now over the mountains.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-10"><dateline><date when="1797-09-10">10 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at union: the life of religion was wanting as I thought, though some tenderness appeared and some solid Countenances.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-11"><dateline><date when="1797-09-11">11 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Redstone, very large, but a hard laborious time it was. I thought I clearly saw the people going from Jerusalem to Jericho, and as I told them from better to worse. I had much close labor, which was solidly attended to. And as some said, I had spoke so plainly to the state of some that they was afraid it would be thought I had been informed of the state of that meeting, but I had not.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-12"><dateline><date when="1797-09-12">12 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Traveled to Sewickley, being the furthest meeting from Redstone.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-13"><dateline><date when="1797-09-13">13 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Sewickley, large for that place exercising.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-14"><dateline><date when="1797-09-14">14 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Providence, and very trying time it was, for in these parts the love of the world and the free Conversation is a great hurt to the promotion of truth’s cause. This I had mention in this meeting, for so much of such worldly discourse became as burdensome to me as profane language and swearing. This and much more close work I had for the good master. Though it was hard for me as for Jonah to preach the preaching the Lord bid him. Yet it was what my safety depended on was to do the Lord's work faithfully, and leave the event to master to set it home to the hearts of the people as he may see meet. This seemed to beget tenderness, and I hope will not all be lost but prove as bread Cast on the waters found after many days.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-15">
<pb n="048"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-09-15">15 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was a center meeting, large and trying, poor low time.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-16"><dateline><date when="1797-09-16">16 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a general meeting for the members of that month meeting selected by themselves. This was very large and favoured for these parts, for they Came over the mountains for sake of the treasures of this world, and that is what the most of them have got and are in the eager pursuit of, and their minds over Charged with, this to the wounding the better part. Both in parents and Children, or a great part of their Conversation is about more land, new Countries, and the things of this world. This was what I labored to turn their minds from, and to often Consider their latter end, and to make a right and a suitable preparation for a death bed and a dying hour. These and much more I laid close for their Consideration before it was too late, and not to put of a work of such importance till the going down of the sun or the evening of the day, lest they be found unprepared when it is too late.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-17"><dateline><date when="1797-09-17">17 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Fallowfield meeting, and in the afternoon at Pike Creek. These was large, in which I had more close labor for truth’s cause, for in these parts is but few faithful laborers, for they are worshiping the works of their own hands, and that which their fingers have made. They have lords many and Gods many that is made of wood and stone, no better than the roman Catholics worshiped. This was the language of their Conduct. This is the Situation of Redstone settlement, according to my sense when I visited that part. How ever it might have been favoured in times past, here is much Care about the things of this world, which is a hindrance to the growth of the better part and drowneth or Choketh the good seed soon in the heart. This I have seen to my grief, where the indians has been forced off their land by the white people, and that by the sword, Contrary to a Contract and agreement yearly made between the indians and the white people, that the Blue Mountain should be a boundary line forever as long as water run and the sun shined. But Contrary to this solemn Covenant, the white people would trespass and settle over the bounds to the uneasiness of the indians, which they frequently signified, but instead of giving them relief, held forth the sword by sending powerful armies in to the bowels of their Countries, burning their towns, destroying their Crops, Cutting in pieces their wives and Children. This is the way they have been forced off the land over the Mountains, though after they have made some pretence of a purchase such as they pleased, for they had got the land first by the sword and determined to hold it now. Whether this land so obtained is clear enough from war and blood shed, for friends to be and live on, I say I see it not so and believe better friends had never gone over the Blue Ridge but had made less do, and maintained the Credit of that most noble of all testimonies against war and blood shed, and maintain that royal law of doing to another as they in the like would be done unto. Had been this the Case our principles would have sure clear as a morning with out Clouds, and the nature and ground of our principles would have spread more than they have done and not been so mixed with the world and the spirit thereof.</p>
<pb n="049"/>
<p>I had some solid Conversation with several friends that had lately been paying a visit to the indians. One of them signified that he had traveled much amongst them, and that he had received great kindness from them. For it was Commonly practiced by them, he believed that in less than a quarter of an hour that they had some thing brought by way of refreshment, who was strangers and travelers. Another said he had also been in the indian Country, and that they was very friendly and received him with great openness and manifested friendship. I told him I feared that Could not last long, for we the whites had been always trespassing on them and taking their lands, and I thought it would be so again as soon as we wanted more land. As we had done, we should do again and that would make them uneasy, and we should be at war again so that we might get more land, and so till we had got it all. He said he believed this would be a lasting and an established line. I said why, more so then what has been for the Blue Mountains was to be forever as long while the sun shined and water run, but now where are we? Got far beyond the Blue Mountains and have drove them poor things farther and further, and why not again? He then gave this as his reason for our not further encroaching on them, for we had got almost all the land that was worth having. There was but a little strip that was good good [sic] for any thing. It then may be we shall be at rest if that be the Case, but now let us look how inconsistent our Conduct is. When we have got all the land that is good for anything, then let us learn then to be farmers. I have seen this to be the Case in the Jersey's, the sand that is allotted them is the most of it, so poor that a good farmer Could hardly live. These things to me is unpleasant and savors not well.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-18"><dateline><date when="1797-09-18">18 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Westland purposed for all the members of that month meeting on that side the River Monongahela, west of Redstone. This was very large and silent, yet solid and profitable. This was the last meeting I had on that side the Allegheny mountain Called Redstone, where I had labored about ten days in the Lord's cause. I believe to good satisfaction and take my leave of them at this meeting. I believe I may say in near feeling love one to the other.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-19"><dateline><date when="1797-09-19">19 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This morning set out in order to return back over the mountains again from William Dicson's, where my dear friend <persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Hunt</persName> came to take her leave of me. Having been formerly acquainted before, she Came to these parts. I felt myself very low in body and mind, having been much fatigued, but thought best to set forward, and that and the next day traveled through very rough and mountainous, one hundred miles. I felt so poor and stripped that I thought I should never preach any more, but when I got over the mountains, my bow was renewed in my hand, and strength renewed, and I believe power given to preach the gospel to the praise of my dear Lord and master, blessed be his great name.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-20"><dateline><date when="1797-09-20">20 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Bear Garden, it was small yet some Comfort. They had not much notice, it was their week day meeting.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-22"><dateline><date when="1797-09-22">22 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Back Creek not large by solid.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-23"><dateline><date when="1797-09-23">23 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at the Ridge so-called, not large. These are uncommon but little meetings. There was some tenderness appeared in each of them. That was some satisfaction to see in those remote parts.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-24">
<pb n="050"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-09-24">24 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was a center near Winchester first day meeting with out notice, being had it was a laborious time, though power was given to labor for truth’s cause. And then I went in the afternoon to Hopewell in order to attend their month meeting next day.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-25"><dateline><date when="1797-09-25">25 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Hopewell month meeting. This was poorly Conducted, almost every way. They was for hurrying the business right or wrong, but I told them that business once well done was better than twice ill done, but there was a stiff set of which the clerk was not the least. He would make minutes as I thought agreeable to his one sense before the meeting had given theirs. This I hinted to him, I told them I Could not tell how the clerk Could Come at the sense of the meeting before they give it, as it was a time when they read, and the queries and answers. I had an opportunity to labor in close plain terms, which was well received by some as they expressed in the meeting and also after. The clerk said he wanted they might get through the business, for they had sat a long time, which I never love to hear, for I think it has a tendency to unsettle the minds of the young people. I told them that we was not often tired attending in a mark when we was getting money fast.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-26"><dateline><date when="1797-09-26">26 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at their select meeting at Hopewell. I had a close time of labor, respecting many wrong things that had Crept in amongst this Class, such as was Chose as the fore rank, who giving way was the ground cause of so great a degeneracy prevailing amongst the lower Class. And that I believed here the reformation ought to begin, for we was the first in the trespass as in old times.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-27"><dateline><date when="1797-09-27">27 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Middle Creek meeting. This day, I am sixty six years old.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-28"><dateline><date when="1797-09-28">28 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Bullskin so-called.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-29"><dateline><date when="1797-09-29">29 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at the gap of the mountains, these three last but low seasons, though some tenderness appeared in the youth to Comfort.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-09-30"><dateline><date when="1797-09-30">30 the 9 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Fairfax select quarterly meeting. Here I had some close labor, though I believe it went down hard with some, for there was need of stirring up some of them that was settled at ease. For there was but little of the life and power of truth to be felt to my grief, but they did not return but used me friendly for they knew it was their due.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-01"><dateline><date when="1797-10-01">1 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day had two meetings: one at Goose Creek and another at South Park, one in the forenoon and the other in the afternoon, the first small the last very large and silent to the great disappointment of many who was very desirous to hear a man preach that wore his beard.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-02"><dateline><date when="1797-10-02">2 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is the day business is transacted. The harvest is great and faithful laborers very few. Here is much to do and but little done; I was led to admire how so many solid looking friends Could let business go on so poorly, and so few put a hand to the work but as though all was well, but I had to stir things to the bottom amongst men and women with the help of but a few that said any thing in meeting but after spoke well of my labor, said they was well pleased with what was said, for they had never seen things in so clear a light before as they now did respecting war, as also some other things.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-03">
<pb n="051"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-10-03">3 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day held a youths meeting; in this, I was silent. It was large, for many, as is common, came to hear and see me. At the close, the select members stopped, at which time, it being a parting time, taking our farewell, I had some clost hints with regard to superfluous dress, believing that we of that class, ministers and elders, stood not clear and was harder to reform then the young people of needless things - as neckcloths on men and two handkerchiefs in warm weather - that was for ornament only, that for these things there could be no plea but do errath.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-04"><dateline><date when="1797-10-04">4 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day makes twelve month since I left my home on this visit to the southern governments, and am now on my way to Indian spring in Maryland very low in mind, as often is my lot, and I believe in wisdom and all for my good.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-05"><dateline><date when="1797-10-05">5 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Indian Spring in Maryland, to my Comfort.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-06"><dateline><date when="1797-10-06">6 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Sandy Spring, somewhat favoured and large.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-07"><dateline><date when="1797-10-07">7 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Bush Creek, large and exercising. Yet in those two last appeared some tenderness, more especially amongst the youth, for the old folks seemed turned to the love of the world. This spirit prevaileth in this land, for prosperity hath opened her door. The people have got and getting rich building fine houses and much fine furniture and forget the giver but think all Came by their own industry and, as they Call it, good management. This Chokes the good seed where ever it Comes or in whom it prevails, which is very prevalent in these southern governments.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-08"><dateline><date when="1797-10-08">8 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Pine Creek, first day meeting large and solid, many young people whose Countenances appeared sober. Had some suitable service for truth’s cause, such as I believe will not all be lost at this time. An aged, worthy handmaid of the Lord expresed her sense with regeard to the tender Constitutions of many young women, when very delicately brought up that they often had weak nerves, thought they needed much medicine. But she gave it as her sense, as also some others, that if those girls would not sit up late and unseasonable, but go timely to bed and rise early in the morning and make their own beds and stir about buisness, it would be the best remedy for weak nerves. She believed such girls would need less doctrine, be more healthy, and have fewer Complaints of weakness. Also, an inhabitant of Maryland gave his sense of the bad effects of slavery and raising tobacco. It had almost ruined a good country, for by those two things, much good land had been worn out and many slaves most cruelly abused. For the cry of cruel whipping, hunger, and needness for which the land mourns and muck lies at their doors, and I believe some day will be required at their hands. For if the blood of one man did cry from the ground and reached the holy ear, what must the blood of so many thousand of negroes and Indians slain by the white people in so most cruel a manner as they have been, and now are, and by us winked at I say us, for who has washed his hands in innocence and now doing to them as we would they should do to us?</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-09"><dateline><date when="1797-10-09">9 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Traveled thirty miles to Menallen meeting or near.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-10"><dateline><date when="1797-10-10">10 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Menallen- large in this though in the fore part but low, yet ended well and solid.</p></div>

<pb n="052"/>
	<div type="entry" n="1797-10-11"><dateline><date when="1797-10-11">11 the 10 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Huntington- solid, favoured time, and ended well.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-12"><dateline><date when="1797-10-12">12 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Warrington large and solid, but in my passing from meeting to meeting I feel so striped low and poor that I think it is hardly worth while to put friends to so much trouble as to spread notice of my being in these parts. For I say of my self, I am a worm and no man and fear some times lest I should bring some reproach on the cause of truth which I love more than all; but friends often signify their unity with my labors, but they know not the bitterness of my soul. But at times I feel my dear master near, blessed be his great name, saith all that is living with in me for his tender Care and heavenly regard over me in keeping my head above water and preparing the way before me. For to him the Lord alone do I ascribe all, for I clearly see there is nothing due to man nor the sons of men. For It is said there has never been such a time to travel these southern Countries has has [sic] been since I left my home many ways. This I believe has been the Lords doing, and it has been cause of humble thankfulness to the God and father of all our mearces.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-13"><dateline><date when="1797-10-13">13 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Newberry. There was a burial that occasioned it to be larger than Common and very tender time it was.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-14"><dateline><date when="1797-10-14">14 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at little York on or near the south side the River Susquehanna. This was small few but friends attended. It is a little town where is many youth so that I felt my self not clear of that place, though we had a Comfortable meeting and I saw no other way at that time but to go forward to the next meeting, which I did - twelve miles at one Thomas More's, which I believe was right, for their was a burial the next day that caused a large gathering of people of all sorts and solid favoured time. It was to the tendering many hearts.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-15"><dateline><date when="1797-10-15">15 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is first day when I attended the aforesaid burial at Thomas More's and had a solid meeting. And then in the afternoon returned to York again and had another meeting in the town at the fourth hour - very large in which I had much close labor that was well received, for the people sat very solid the most of them till the meeting which held till near dark. I believe it ended well.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-16"><dateline><date when="1797-10-16">16 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day traveled from York to Fawn meeting. Before I left York this morning, came in to take leave of me several friends, inhabitors of this town, with whom I had a solid opportunity respecting the reformation and living more Consistent with our principles in eating, drinking, and putting on of apparel, so as to revive ancient testimonies that should not be lost that was born by our ancient worthies against rum, tea, and tobacco that is so much use made of, as also this extensive trading in, so Corrupt a way and manner Contrary to the purity of our principles. That gives it cause to be reproached by evil doers and lessens the Credit of that testimony. We ought to maintain against all war and shedding of blood, either directly or indirectly, by paying any demands that should aid or assist in hiring men for that purpose or maintain them while so employed.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-17">
<pb n="053"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-10-17">17 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Am now waiting this day, as tomorrow is preparative meeting at Fawn. It hath been rather a pleasant day, though time seems tedious when not employed in masters cause, for I have been more than twelve months from home in the southern governments on this visit.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-18"><dateline><date when="1797-10-18">18 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Fawn preparative meeting. Here, men and women sat together for want of better conveniency. They read and answered the queries in but a very formal way, as is too frequent the Custom for in those southern parts as to religion thing is very low. The old folks are in the world and the youth in the air for, as one said, the Country is ruined with raising tobacco and keeping slaves. They make so free a use of the pipe, laughing and Chewing, that I am weary therewith and have to revive ancient testimony against the use of tobacco.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-19"><dateline><date when="1797-10-19">19 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Deer Creek preparative meeting here was Zachariah Ferris and <persName key="w68m543d">John Simpson</persName>. Zachariah had in the Business good service here they read and answered the queries much in the easy way that I Could not unite with my friends they having prepared answers before hand that I have ever believed to be wrong this I did fully express and told them that I believed there was but one right way and that was not it but to read the query and then take a solid pause and then the overseers or any other solid friend feeling a right qualification to speak one after another the overseers nor any friend being excluded nor looked to more than another for an answer for I did believe it required the same ability to answer queries as to preach the gospel and to be waited for and to be spoke from before the clerk Could or should attempt to prepare an answer or any other person or persons either in or out of meeting in this I differed from my two friends but It made them all silent</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-20"><dateline><date when="1797-10-20">20 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Little Falls this small and a poor low time</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-21"><dateline><date when="1797-10-21">21 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Traveled twenty miles to Gunpowder</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-22"><dateline><date when="1797-10-22">22 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Gunpowder small but favoured this evening had a solid time with Moses Dilwin valuable friend who had lately been over the Ohio River on the new purchased land where seeing the uneasiness of the indians and the wrong done as he thought in obtaining that land and running the line some miles further than they intended or expected with which they was not satisfied therefore believed best not to have any thing to do with such lands but Came back and settled in Maryland for which he said he was thankful</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-23"><dateline><date when="1797-10-23">23 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Came down to Bush meeting place</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-24"><dateline><date when="1797-10-24">24 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Bush though small as all those are yet this favoured</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-25"><dateline><date when="1797-10-25">25 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Went to Deer Creek in order to be at that month meeting</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-26"><dateline><date when="1797-10-26">26 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at that month meeting at Deer Creek supposed to be a favoured season both with men and women it had this tendency to bring us near to each other though I had some close labor for truth’s cause which was well received this meeting ended well</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-27">
<pb n="054"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-10-27">27 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at a select Conference of ministers and elders at Deer Creek this was a poor low time as I have found religion and the cause there of but very weak amongst the Professors there of and in the afternoon attempted to Cross the River Susquehanna but the wind blowing so hard we was forced to stay till next morning</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-28"><dateline><date when="1797-10-28">28 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Earley this morning between day break and sun rise with my friend G. C. we Crossed the River Susquehanna and proceeded to East Nottingham month meeting a poor low exercising time and ended not with almost any degree of Life or power to labor for the great and good master death and barrenness over spread this meeting</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-29"><dateline><date when="1797-10-29">29 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Stayed their first day meeting at East Nottingham this was very large but laborious for the poor servants</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-30"><dateline><date when="1797-10-30">30 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Little Britain large and laborious</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-10-31"><dateline><date when="1797-10-31">31 the 10 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Eastland meeting this was very large and a more favoured season here appeared many tender little ones this seemed a little Comforting to my poor drooping soul for I thought many times it was not worth while to appoint meetings for such a poor thing as I was but found no way but to look to the Lord and keep on trying as it was for he the Lord was not wanting on his part for the most part strength was given for me to do his work and so to leave the effect with him to set it home if he please and where</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-01"><dateline><date when="1797-11-01">1 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at West Nottingham very large and solid and I believe ended well and then they held a select Conference this was a close searching time I was favoured to lay things close which was well received and requested not to be forgot by none for said one of them it well suited them they said my Company was to them satisfactory</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-02"><dateline><date when="1797-11-02">2 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was again the third time at East Nottingham and it was a solid favoured meeting this being the last I purpose in these parts now proceed towards the Eastern shore of Maryland in these parts had some solid private labor I believe to some good purpose that will be like bread Cast on the water found after many days we now parted in feeling nearness and Love</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-03"><dateline><date when="1797-11-03">3 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Traveled to Sassafras near thirty miles</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-04"><dateline><date when="1797-11-04">4 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Sassafras but small though solid good meeting after I visited George Michael and wife Susanah with whom I had a satisfactory opportunity she being one that was brought up and had a right amongst friends but as she said had taken too much delight in gay dress and frequented such Company but she always did and yet doth love that
<pb n="055"/>
which good better than every thing and good people and friends in a particular manner and she was clear that if she never made a good quaker she should never make a good any thing else for she had never been but twice at any other meetings in her life but friends and then she felt nothing but death and did not intend to go again though the most of her time she had lived thirty miles from friends meeting and near the meetings of Church people of whom her husband was one as also the presbyterians meetings and Methodist meeting but now they had moved nearer and she now did intend to be diligent in going to friends meeting and to my admiration she had through all persevered the plain language so much as she had done though as she said not altogther yet in her dress she appeared not like a friend this I wondered at for she was of a tender spirit but as she said not so much so as she ought to be or else this dress must Come off if once the inside was Clean but Custom had such a powerful influence she was Captivated thereby she had such an influence with her husband that though a Church man by profession and a man in high life he always used as he said the plain language to her they seemed to live in much love and harmony he seemed a good spirited man and wished for more of friends Company and also his wife said it was her delight to do for friends and would fain have had me stayed all night and if I Could make it in my way Call again which I should have gladly have done for I believe a use might have arose to them to have had more of friends Company they live at Georgetown at the river Called Sassafras on the Eastern shore of Maryland she and her husband was at meeting this day appeared solid</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-05"><dateline><date when="1797-11-05">5 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Cecilton meeting I was at this day it was small and dull</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-06"><dateline><date when="1797-11-06">6 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Chester meeting large in this I had some labor for master</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-07"><dateline><date when="1797-11-07">7 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Appointed a meeting this day at Cecilton in order to be with them to read and answer the queries this was a close laborious time for in those parts truth’s cause is at a low ebb seems to be rather on the decline</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-08"><dateline><date when="1797-11-08">8 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at the head of Chester so Called this large of other societies for friends number is in those parts but small to what I expected and very weak at this time was their preparative and the queries read in this meeting was an heart searching time I believe my labors was well received and I hope will be as bread Cast on the waters found after many days for some in most places appeared tendered</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-09"><dateline><date when="1797-11-09">9 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Choptank meeting here they read and answered the queries in as poor a weak way as I ever seed them done the number but few lifeless as to religion yet Could say much and to but little purpose for as I told them in speaking to business to be short and to the matter as much as may be was the way to preserve life in a meeting this is sorrowful that many friends thinketh to Carry their point by multiplying words without life this is hurtful in meetings of business and woundeth the cause of truth</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-10">
<pb n="056"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-11-10">10 the 11 month 1797.</date></dateline><p>had a meeting amongst the Nicholites small and low for I thought this people in this place was looking back and going into the vain Customs of the world and so departing from that which the Lord had once favoured them with this was a grief to me for I had heard a good account of this people and had seen some in North Carolina that I thought was the plainest that I had seen and these was Nicholites but these in Maryland are gone in to superfluities equal to the worlds people in dress and houses and house furniture and they now request to Come as a body and Join friends this I told friends was with a view that they might have more liberty I thought friends had need take Care for I was doubtful whether it would be for the better</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-11"><dateline><date when="1797-11-11">11 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had another meeting amongst that people small and a poor low time</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-12"><dateline><date when="1797-11-12">12 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Coldspring very small it was a stormy day here is but little appearance of religion and the cause of truth much gone out of fashion and the world and the spirit taken the place thereof for the most part meetings are the smallest that I have met with in my travels and they have so many blacks in their families that is a very great hurt to the white Children it makes them proud and lazy for the blacks are first to stand as drudges and kept at a distance and in the kitchen where is most miserable doings in general while parents and Children appear very diligent in the parlor this I see is the cause why friends in these parts are falling away and meetings grow small and much neglected and pride increases</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-13"><dateline><date when="1797-11-13">13 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Milford this was a little better and some what favoured here was many of this number not friends amongst whom I have often the most favoured times the cause I must leave but that there seems more openness amongst those than amongst friends that have had so much labor bestowed and to so little profit</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-14"><dateline><date when="1797-11-14">14 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Mispillion month meeting here I had much close labor that appeared well received amongst men and women <persName key="w6cz4d1t">Warner Mifflin</persName> signified his unity with my labors amongst them though heard sayings yet worthy their notice as he was with me in the womens part as well as mens</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-15"><dateline><date when="1797-11-15">15 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Traveled to Third Haven this day</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-16"><dateline><date when="1797-11-16">16 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Third Haven month meeting here I had some close labor in the meeting for business I believe well received this afternoon had a satisfactory opportunity with some young people</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-17"><dateline><date when="1797-11-17">17 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Marshy Creek meeting this was a stormy day and the meeting small</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-18"><dateline><date when="1797-11-18">18 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Choptank meeting not large after meeting where we lodged lived an aged friend who informed me that within twenty miles distance was but one white man of his age being upwards of sixty and in that distance was more then twenty black men of that age this he thought was occasioned by luxurious living that shortened the days of the whites and so it is in many of these southern parts the blacks are much the longest lived and I believed it is not because they have got a black skin but owing to their way and manner of living for the black
<pb n="057"/>
fare hard and live on Coarse food and that but scanty many or most of them have no more than one peck of indian Corn for a week allowance without salt or fat or any other thing therewith they may eat it any way they please if ground it must be in a hard mill or if they Choose any other way it is mostly in the night to provide next days provision and that very Commonly between eleven and four in the morning when they are Called to work so Cruel are those hard task masters that keep slaves</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-19"><dateline><date when="1797-11-19">19 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Third Haven first day meeting this was large and favoured</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-20"><dateline><date when="1797-11-20">20 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Bayside this was large meeting and many of the youth appeared tendered though they were fine gay dressed people not friends yet the solid seating was satisfactory to me and encouraging though here aways in many places meetings small and truth’s cause in a suffering state though people both parents and Children had a thurst after high life and worldly preferment this woundeth the better part and hinders the growth of truth</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-21"><dateline><date when="1797-11-21">21 the 11 month</date></dateline><p> Was at a select meeting at Third Haven this was a stormy day and things very low as to religion here was some hints dropped that friends should guard against laying out work to do on meeting day mornings such as womens baking and washing or any other business but that parents and heads of families should make way for families to get out to meeting in a Calm quiet state of mind not Coveting the last moment of time and then being full of the world unfit for divine service</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-22"><dateline><date when="1797-11-22">22 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Tuckahoe meeting not large the storm Continues</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-23"><dateline><date when="1797-11-23">23 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at Choptank meeting a second time</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-24"><dateline><date when="1797-11-24">24 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at a select meeting at Motherkill [modern Murderkill] this is a poor little meeting</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-25"><dateline><date when="1797-11-25">25 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at the quarterly at Little Creek select meeting not large and low</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-26"><dateline><date when="1797-11-26">26 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This first day meeting at Little Creek and in the afternoon with the black people here was a large meeting of the blacks but I often think it needs Care least we should feed that people with too many words for I have thought they wanted to be taught true stillness and that at such times a few pertinent hints was best</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-27"><dateline><date when="1797-11-27">27 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is the day for the business of the quarterly meeting held at Little Creek here I had much close labor both in mens and womens part with respect to those poor Children both black and white under friends Care this was so far united with that it was proposed to appoint a Committee to visit friends families and to inspect into the Condition of those under their Care as to Clothing lodging and other ways and getting them out to meeting and to have Clothes fitting and not to make so much difference in Clothing bedding and going to meetings between those and their own Children for they are the Children of somebody and have souls to save or lose as well as our own Children but some friends found it would Come so close that they strove to avoid such search being made though the Clerk had prepared a minute for that purpose and Called for names to be appointed but some plead that it might only be recommended for the representatives to Carry to the month meeting which was done but many said they had rather the appointment should go forward and would have them come to their houses first for they believed there was need of such an inspection</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-28/1797-11-29">
<pb n="058"/>
<dateline><date from="1797-11-28" to="1797-11-29">28 and 29th 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Having now performed a visit to all the southern governments I believe my self clear to go towards home taking two meetings in my way</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-11-30"><dateline><date when="1797-11-30">30 the 11 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Am on my way home stopped at Whiteley Creek meeting which is the last that I have in prospect the meetings in these parts are generally small the blacks are too many and that in friends families which is a hurt to friends Children the blacks must stand at the laboring oar and the whites be indulged in pride and idleness but I told friends that it would be good for their Children to take their turns in the kitchen to learn to wash dishes turn to wash tub and kneading trough and learn how to manage their household business and not to Call so often on bets and Nance but learn to wait on themselves and let the black girls Come in to the parlor and learn to spin knit and sew by turns with their own Children so that they may all both black and white know how to make a good use of freedom when of suitable age for I have seen some fine parlors and poor kitchens and bad Conduct therein</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-01"><dateline><date when="1797-12-01">1 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day traveled thirty miles and upwards to my one home after being gone to the southward fourteen month wanting two days and having visited all the meeting but for one in Maryland two in Virginia one in North Carolina and not one in South Carolina Georgia nor Tennessee in the Course of this visit I traveled between five and six thousand miles and now through Divine mercy am at my one habitation found my dear wife Children all well this is Cause of humble thankfulness to the God and father of all our mercies who has prepared my way before me having passed through many baptising seasons in so much that I thought it was hardly worth while for me to appoint meetings and Call people from their work to attend them but be it spoken to the praise of the great shepherd who putteth not his forth but he goeth before and prepareth their way before whom I now feel all within me bow and reverence his great and glorious name Oh what shall I return to thee for thy manifold blessings mercies and favours</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-02"><dateline><date when="1797-12-02">2 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was this day with my dear friends at our select meeting at Haddonfield which was a time not be forgot by me for we was glad to see each others faces once more in this world but I feel my self no more but like a sojourner and one that hath no Continuing City here but at times like a poor pilgrim that hath no where to lay his head but if this be Consistent with the Divine will I Can say the will of the Lord be done and am willing he may dispose of me whether so ever he may see meet to send me to do his work and service Oh that I may be through Divine aid enabled to do it to the glory of his great name to whom be all praise now and forever.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-03">
<pb n="059"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-12-03">3 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at our meeting Newtown it was large and solid a favoured good meeting my friends was glad of my return once more to sit with them for we Could say we did love each other</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-04"><dateline><date when="1797-12-04">4 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This day the business of the quarter is transacted it was thought well Conducted I gave some account of my Journey to the southward which was satisfactory I believe in general and I had cause of humble thankfulness to the Lord for his gracious goodness lovingkindness and mercy in bringing me once more to see my native land and feel the reward of peace which is enough for all my labors in his work and service</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-05"><dateline><date when="1797-12-05">5 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> The following five days I spent much at home received many Comfortable visits from my friends in this time</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-11"><dateline><date when="1797-12-11">11 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is our month meeting at Haddonfield when I returned the Certificate had from this meeting and many more from monthly and quarterly meetings where I had been which gave General satisfaction as many expressed themselves</p></div>

	<div type="entry" n="1797-12-12/1797-12-13"><dateline><date from="1797-12-12" to="1797-12-13">12 and 13th 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> These two days to me poor low baptising seasons I had enough to do to keep the anchor hold of faith and hope but I believe all in wisdom that no man might glory in anything but in the Lord whose lovingkindness has been great and his ways in the deeps and past finding out by all human wisdom I had many time to say good is the word of the Lord</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-14"><dateline><date when="1797-12-14">14 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was our week day meeting received some favour from the great mastor and bishop of souls to our Comfort</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-15"><dateline><date when="1797-12-15">15 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Returned from a visit to Joseph Kaighn's family</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-16"><dateline><date when="1797-12-16">16 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at home under an humbling sense of the Lords goodness</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-17"><dateline><date when="1797-12-17">17 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This was our first day meeting at Newtown it was a favoured meeting I believe many of the youth was tendered and led to Consider their latter end with great seriousness which to see was a Comfort to my mind</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-18"><dateline><date when="1797-12-18">18 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Spent this day I believe to Gods glory and to the Edification of some honest inquirers with whom I spent much of this day</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-19"><dateline><date when="1797-12-19">19 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Went to visit <persName key="w6zk9cxf">Benjamin Swett</persName> who was and had been Confined by sickness for some time his wife being gone to England this was a great trial though he seemed freely to give her up to do the great masters work</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-20"><dateline><date when="1797-12-20">20 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Was at a meeting appointed for a distant friend in this meeting was much preaching but I thought the dead was not raised I was afraid of long and tedious testimonies and life not felt to be raised</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-21"><dateline><date when="1797-12-21">21 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This was our week day meeting here was two friends from a distant meeting their testimonies was very large but as to life and power I must leave to others for to me it was an exercising time I have sometimes thought where there was two much eloquence it lessened the weight and service of such testimonies though a flow of words might be uttered and that very Correctly yet the life and power wanting</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-22/1797-12-23"><dateline><date from="1797-12-22" to="1797-12-23">22 and 23th 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> These days I spent very industriously the first in looking over the most of my writing and the last is visiting the sick and those in affliction as is the way I spend much of my time in this way</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-24">
<pb n="060"/>
<dateline><date when="1797-12-24">24 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This is our first day meeting which was a solid good meeting</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-25/1797-12-28"><dateline><date from="1797-12-25" to="1797-12-28">25 to the 28</date></dateline><p> I spent in many deep Contemplations on the state of things and of what would be Come of our society the old folks seem buried in the Earth and their Children flying in the air the day increase in Excess fine houses rich furniture with abundance of gay and fashionable Clothing with great Excess in eating and drinking and this is growing amongst our society in too general a way though warning after warning and by dearth striping after striping seasons but the people and friends too much so grow worse and worse though the sound of mortality is so loudly heard in our borders at this time and in our land so many widows and fatherless Children what Can be done for this people but to stretch forth the rod of Chastisement and thin the inhabitance by Judgment following Judgment til the inhabitance learn righteousness and forsake the Evils of their ways if so no doubt with me but the Lord would show mercy again and spare the people as he did Nineva</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-29"><dateline><date when="1797-12-29">29 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> This morning Can hardly keep my head above water beholding the abominations of the times and who shall stand for the Lords cause</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1797-12-31"><dateline><date when="1797-12-31">31 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> For Eight days I have been visiting the widows and fatherless Children who I thought was like the turtle mourning for her mate under a deep sense of their loss with these I had a near sympathy believing some of their trials would be great I also visited several neighbouring meetings in which had some close labor well received as far as appeared I saw their wanted more faithful laborers in our society to stand as up right pillars in the Church of Christ</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-01-08"><dateline><date when="1798-01-08">8 the 1 month 1798</date></dateline><p> A Concern that had lived with me for more than twenty years to Cross the sea in truth’s service but though I saw in the true light that I must first visit friends in America which having accomplished believe the time fully Come to lay the Case before my friends for their Concurrence which I did this day and many friends Expressed their unity yet it being a weighty matter the meeting thought best to refer the further Consideration thereof to next meeting it not interfering with its being laid before the next quarterly meeting with this I was well satisfied for Crossing the seas has been a sore exercise to my mind having had some small trial on the water part of which was on the seas but when I had laid the Concern before the meeting Oh the peace I felt I Cannot set it forth my tongue is too short it is such as I never felt but once before and that was when I first opened my mouth in public testimony Then and now felt as one translated into another world and this lasted me all the ensuing night of the sweet peace that is felt for faithfully giving up to serve the Lord who is worthy to be served honoured and obeyed I mention this for the encourage of all to faithfulness how ever it may be in the Cross the reward is sufficient equal to the Cross is the Crown no doubt with me I have always found it so for we Cannot serve the Lord but as we become more and more Crucified to the world and self reduced and laid in the dirt Oh that it may be my one experience for none have more need than I of such a reducement so that I may be favoured with holy aid and assistance</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-01-09">
<pb n="061"/>
<dateline><date when="1798-01-09">9 the 1 month 1798</date></dateline><p> I attended Woodbury month meeting had some close labor revived some matters that I feared was going out of their sight one was the new addition to the meeting house that had given me a sorrowful sensation many a time and though of some time standing grows no better but rather worse to my my mind as I believe the lord is angry with us be cause of our back sliding and gradually going into the worlds spirit of which this new part being made so different from the old speaks that Language and ever will so long as it standeth and show that we are not the people we profess to be but are falling away and degenerating from our first principals and in danger of going to decay I also had to mention the growth of superfluity and pride in building riding Carriages since the first which was a great Conveniency many ways but now had paintings of many Colors with Carvings this made them more Costly and less useful this spoke the same language of worldliness and in this spirit things grew worse and worse with great Confusions and Commotions and thirsting after honour with their parties each striving for victory this Tendoreth and ends too frequently in blood shed this I advised friends to guard against and keep out of and have not hand in that of a peaty spirit all though they should suffer in their intrust</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-01-10"><dateline><date when="1798-01-10">10 the 1 month 1798</date></dateline><p> From this to the twentieth I was in my usual way going up and down amongst the afflicted with whom I have a near feeling wishing friends would oftener go and sit with them in their trials some who are loath to make Complaint in their deep baptisms remember but blessed are those who Consider the poor the Lord will deliver in a time of trouble psalms 41 first verse</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-01-14"><dateline><date when="1798-01-14">The fourteenth of this month</date></dateline><p> We had the company of our beloved friend <persName key="w6rj4s40">Elias Hicks</persName> from Long Island whose company and Gospel labors was truly acceptable and edifying and I believe has made impressions on some of our minds that will be of lasting advantage</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-01-21"><dateline><date when="1798-01-21">21 the 1 month 1798</date></dateline><p> To the thirtieth of the same was much at home looking over my writings and visiting meetings some of which was trying and sorrowful to me because of the people giving in to the Customs of the world yet trying to hold up the form with out the substance</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-02-01"><dateline><date when="1798-02-01">1 the 2 month 1798</date></dateline><p> For three days I have thought much respecting that text in Matthew 17 Chapter and 25 verse<note type="editorial">Actually begins Matthew 17:24</note> in an old translation before they were in Chapter and verse stands thus and when thee were Come to the City of Capernaum they that use to receive tribute money Came to Peter and said Doth your master pay tribute he saith yea and when he was Come into the house Jesus prevented him saying what thinkest thou Simon of whom do the kings of the earth take tribute or toll of their Children or of strangers Peter saith unto him of strangers Jesus saith unto him then are the Children free notwithstanding lest we should offend them go thou to the sea and Cast an angle and take the fish that first Cometh up and when thou hast opened his mouth thou shall find a piece of twenty pence that take and give it unto them for me and thee</p>

<p>The words and spelling [modernized] is as it stands here I have taken this hour of an old bible printed before they was put in Chapters and verse I have it now in my hand and do admire the simplicity and plainness </p>

<pb n="062"/>
<label>Exodus XXX Chapter and 13</label>
<quote>
<l>13 and thus much shall every man give and that goeth into the number half a cycle after the cycle of the sanctuary a cycle is twenty half pence an half an half cycle shall be the heavy offering of the Lord</l>
<l>15 the rich shall not pass and the poor shall not diminish under half a cycle</l>
<l>16 and thou shall take the reconciling money of the Children of Israel and shalt put it unto the use of the tabernacle of witness</l>
</quote>

<p>It doth not appear to me that money raised as recorded in this old translation was ever intended for the purpose of war neither that paid by Peter with the money taken out of the fishes mouth I write this is for them of my Children that may be favoured to out live me to look on and to Consider the propriety of paying money for the purposes of shedding of blood lest they stand not clear this has been the cause of my refusing all taxes and duties or any monies raised in any or being Called by any name if for the purpose of war I have refused for more than forty years for the encouragement of others I Can say the reward has been enough the which I would not have missed for all the kingdoms of this world and the glory thereof the late or translation though not in the same words with the old yet hath the substance yet not quite so clear to my understanding</p></div>

<div>
<pb n="063"/>
<p>from the 1th 2 month 1798 to the fifth visited some neighbouring meetings to but little satisfaction had some low times</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-02-05"><dateline><date when="1798-02-05">5 the 2 month 1798</date></dateline><p> And 6 attended Philadelphia quarterly meeting I had some close labor and there was I believe much need for I think truth’s cause was very poorly handled for I thought they spoke not so much to forward the work as who should be the most Cute in words and make the most wise speeches as men</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-02-06/1798-02-10"><dateline><date from="1798-02-06" to="1798-02-10">from the 6 to the 10th 2 month</date></dateline><p> Was so poor and striped of divine favour that I was ready to Call all in question but as I was going to meeting a man who was a practicer of physick passed by me and at that time I had this to open to me with some degree of Clearness that human study was not sufficient to qualify any man for a doctor but that it was a divine gift this I give as my feeling at that time and am more and more Confirmed of the truth of its being so</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-02-12"><dateline><date when="1798-02-12">12 the 2 month 1798</date></dateline><p> This is our month meeting my prospect was now revived again of Crossing the sea on truth's account this was again almost united with by the meeting in general three or four excepted this seemed not to feel so easy as Could be wished those that made their objections Could not say they was in the Clearness as those that was for setting me liberty to attend to my prospect but yet friends thought it would be the most safe to let the matter rest for this time and so it was dropped off the minutes this caused a deep feeling of mind to me with desire to know the cause as I had  great an assurance that I had done well in laying it before my friends if the answer of peace was to be depended upon as an evidence well doing for a greater portion of sweet peace I had never felt that I remember in all my life before for any dedication of my self to service in the Lord's work how I Could reconcile my feeling with that of my friends I was at a loss but believed if I Could be favoured to keep in the quiet I should not be left in the dark but the cause would appear and so it has within these four following days with some degree of clearness fully to my satisfaction and Comfort and Can say good is the Lord whose ways are out of the reach of human wisdom and past our finding out therefore needs divine wisdom to give us an understanding in things of a divine nature now I believe the cause is thus having had a prospect of a visit to England for more than twenty years it became so weighty that many times last summer I was afraid it would be more than I Could bear and attend to the visit before me in the Carolinas and so perhaps Cut that work too short and Came home hoping I might be clear but I believe it was the goodness of the Lord to me and all in wisdom that I should have no more laid on me than I Could bear suffered me to return and lay my Concern before my friends and be relieved of that burden that so I might perform the remainder of the work the Lord has for me yet to do in my one land when this opened as I believed in the true light shining out of darkness and the darkness Comprehended it not Oh the sweet flowings of the Lords goodness my tongue is too short to set it forth by the one half glory glory to the Oh my God saith my soul for thy mercies great

<pb n="064"/>
from the twelfth to the seventeenth [2m. 1798] nothing more than Common attending meetings and visiting the poor and the afflicted attended our first day meeting it was a solid good meeting there was many from the hedges and highways some I believe was almost ready to be invited to Come in to the marriage feast I believe those are them to whom I am sent to tell them all is ready Come to the marriage</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-02-19"><dateline><date when="1798-02-19">19 the 2 month 1798</date></dateline><p> I was at a quarterly meeting at Woodbury here was a number of solid friends not belonging to that meeting this made me feel my self but very trifling yet master works not always by those that are the most wise I thought every one ought to stand in their proper allotments though it was but only to Clean the gutters as one once told me was my work I said if so I am Content master is good pay however I had at this time to drop some close hints I suppose as much as they Could bear respecting a part spirit that doth now prevail almost through out the land my desire is that friends may take Care how they are Concerned in making or gaining with any party spirit though it should interfere with their interest for it hath so great a tendency to break the unity not only in kingdoms and nations but in neighbourhoods and amongst us as a people to our shame and reproach and lessening the dignity of the profession we make which is peace on earth and good will to men Oh that friends did but live up to their principles then I believe before this time we should have had no suffering Cases to bring in they Could not have exacted nor Could on friends for any military service this is not my sense only but the warriors them selves as I have heard them say if we lived up to our principles we need not fear them we should have been set above their heads and out of their reach this to me has appeared a clear Case but while our society is so full of the world and the spirit of it it is hard to live at peace in our own minds with all men and this puts us in to the hands of unreasonable men to do as seems good to them Oh poor Quakers alas alas they take our property and we suffer patiently however wrong in them I believe it may be good forces if it should have this affect to wean us more from the love of this world and turn our mind to heaven and heavenly things that durable riches that fadeth not away</p></div>

	<div type="entry" n="1798-02-19/1798-03-23"><dateline><date from="1798-02-19" to="1798-03-23">From the 19 2 month to the 23 the 3 month [1798]</date></dateline><p> Has been for the most part a poor low suffering time with me and as yet feel no better for yesterday I think we had as poor a hard lifeless meeting as I was ever at of the select sort I have been at several monthly meetings within this last month and a many others some I did believe favoured ones if I may be able to keep my head above water It will be a favour indeed from God for I have thought my service has been to disturb the resting place of them that are at rest short of the true rest had I to mention some indulgences that was Creeping in amongst us of the foremost rank such as we had too much given way to and was now by some applauded but to me was no better than at first that of having the benches spread with Cushions this is such an indulgence that I have never seen but in friends meeting houses
<pb n="065"/>
also new fashion bonnets black silk silk gowns those things are got in families the foremost rank and spoke well of though to me are now no better than at first but now a many of them who at the first appearance bore testimony against all those things are now silent when they had more need be as when they was repairing the wall of Jerusalem so that the Lord would raise up more such as Nehemiah to stand for his cause and not put off their Clothes but for washing neither night nor day for there was never more need than now</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-03-31"><dateline><date when="1798-03-31">31 the 3 month 1798</date></dateline><p> It has been to me a time of mourning and deep wading in sorrow for some days past when I look which way I will for if I look towards the Lord I think our ways doth displease him and if I look at this world there is little else but envying and hatred one towards each other I have been striving to take my refuge under the divine wing believing it to be the only safe hiding place where all the righteous flee and then they are safe from all storms and tempests though the drums may beat and Cannons roar and many garments rolled in blood for it doth appear to me and has done for some time that we are threatened with the Judgment of the Lord and that if we do not repent I have believed we shall be tried with sword famine and pestilence now if our ways were such as did please the Lord he would make our enemies at peace with us for I firmly believe that Carnal weapons are not necessary to defend a Christian Country as Gods power is over all and his word spoken in so it is out of all the powers of death and darkness to Changing one title thereof for he Can say go so far and no farther this I firmly believe that his name which is his power is as the shade of a mighty rock in a weary land and none Can make such afraid I believe the time loudly Calls for us to wash our hands in innocency</p></div>

[Page 66 blank]

<div><pb n="067"/>
[The following pages include a list in two columns of the places to which Evans traveled and their distances, and with whom he stayed. Unfortunately the information in the two columns often do not correspond in the original manuscript. For the ease of the reader, efforts have been made to match the information in both columns. It is likely that many mistakes were made, but the following represents an attempt at an accurate breakdown of who Evans stayed with and where]

4 the 10 month 1797. Left home to pay a religious visit to the southern governments
from Philadelphia to Baltimore miles 102	lodged at Joseph Tatnalls
from thence to North Carolina - 400	then at Charles Johnsons
by going a little out of from the post rode	then at Samuel Paxsons
we lodged but one night at a tavern but	then at Samuel Snowden
passed through the settlement of friends	then at a tavern
from Philadelphia to the yearly meeting
of North Carolina we was very kindly
entertained by them and piloted on our way
passed through the federal City then through
Colchester and Dumfries Crossed Rappahannock	then passed Rappahannock River
at Fredericksburg	at Fredericksburg
	lodge at George Rogers not
	a friend he was very kind
	then at Thomas Harriss
	then at Nathan Bells on Chickahominy River
	then at Samuel Lads
	James Hardgrove
	Crossed James River at Westover
	ferry lodged at White Honeycutts
	then at Thomas Pretlows
	then at Joshua Barless
	then at Thomas Pretlows a second time
	then at Robert Jordans at Suffolk
from thence to Newberg meeting - 4	then at John Winslows in Carolina
from thence to Pasquotank narrows -10	then at Joseph Wilsons
	at Pasquotank County North Carolina
from thence to Symonds Creek on - 10	then at Joshua Truebloods
from thence to Sutton Creek - 11	then at Joseph Wilsons during the
	yearly meeting of North Carolina
from thence to Welses - 7	then at Nathan Morris
from thence to Beach Springs - 3	then at Benjamin Albertsons
from thence to Piney Wood - 5	then at Elias Albertsons
these are all within the Compass of Symonds Creek
Quarter North Carolina
from thence to Somerton - 40	then at Jesse Coplands
from thence to West Branch 20	then at the Widows Ann Seats
	here is many friends during
	the quarterly meeting
	at West Branch Virginia
from thence to Suffolk and back 18	then at Joseph Ricks
quarterly meeting and back - 6
thence to the Widow Bufskins - 24	then at the Widow Bufskins
from thence to South Branch - 10	then at Robert Pools
from thence to the long bridge 10	then at Edward Doughlies
from thence to Pasquotank narrow	then at Abel Truebloods
a second time ---- 30	at the Narrows of Pasquotank
	then at Josiah Truebloods
from thence to Camden
Courthouse where we had a meeting 6	then at Christopher Whittuses
from thence to great swamp 16	then at the Widow Brights
	Camden County Carolina
from thence to Widow Richesons 8	then at John Cornwells

from thence to Piney Woods	then returned to Elias Albertsons
a second time to quarterly meeting 20	at Piney Woods
from thence to Benjamin
Albertsons a second time - 12	then at Benjamin Albertsons
from thence to little River second time 4
from thence Nixonton where
we had a meeting in the house
Courthouse in Pasquotank Court - 4	Nathan Moreses
from thence back to Piney wood
a third time -------- 20	and back to Elias Albertsons
from thence to Rich Square - 60	then to William Coplands
	then at Mary Lawrence
	then at Lawrence Smiths
from thence to Jack Swamp - 30	then at John Pattersons at Jack Swamp
the sum on this page is [illegible prob. 890]
<pb n="068"/>
miles
	then at Halifax at a tavern
	then at one Perreys
from thence to Raleigh a little town in
North Carolina where the assembly sits - 100	then at Raleigh at one Atkinses at Raleigh
	then at one Crawfords then at one Words
from Raleigh to Corsesound month
meeting in North Carolina - 170	then at Benjamin Stanton at Corse Sound
	North Carolina
in visiting the families of Corse Sound 30	then at Owen Stantons
from thence to Clubfoot meeting - 10	then at Horton Howards
from thence to Trent - 38	then at Joseph Dews North Carolina
	then at Benjamin Stantons at Coventry
from thence to upper Trent - 20	then at Malachi Jolley's at upper Trent
from thence to Bear Creek meeting - 40	then at Thomas Outlands at Bear Creek
from thence to Turner Swamp meet 20
at Contentnea North Carolina	then at Thomas Hallowell North Carolina
in visiting families at Upper and Lower Trent - 30	then at Benjamin Arnold
from thence to Contentnea where the month meeting is held --- 4	then at Joshua Hastings
from thence to Nahunta - 18
from thence to Sarah Edgingtons - 2	then at Sarah Edgingtons
from thence to great Contentnea - 12	then at Robert Felles
from thence to Neuse meeting - 20	then at James Edgentons
then back to Contentnea - 20	then at Joshua Hastings
from thence to Holly Spring - 12	then at Thomas Horns
from thence to Tar River - 38	then at Joseph Hall
	then at Nathan Vicks this in North Carolina
then back to Contentnea large house 38	then at Joshua Hastings five nights
then to in visiting families
at this place and meetings - 50	then at Silas Holloway
	then at Isaac Dearken
	then again at Benjamin Arnold five nights
	then at James Edgentons
from thence to Gum Swamp	then lodged two nights on the way
the way we went is 178	towards Gum Swamp
	then at Jonathan Merine
from thence to Pee Dee - 22	then at John Thomas
from thence to Charleston - 200	then at Thomas Moreman
	then at Lewis Thomas
	then at Charles Evens
	then at Mallachiah Murphy
	then at John James
the 7th 2 month 1797. This day arrived at	then at Daniel Latham
Charleston in good health and had cause to	in Charleston South Carolina
bles magnify and praise the Lord who prepared
the way for me through a dark land of
deep oppression and Cruel treatment to the blacks
with nakedness hunger and Cruel whipping
from Charleston to Edisto meeting - 50	then at tavern where was many Negroes
from thence to Martha Lewis - 4	then at Martha Lewis at Edisto near
	the road leading from Charlestown to Georgia
from thence to Augusta in Georgia - 100
from thence to friends settlement in
Georgia Columbia County - 30	then at William Farmer several nights
from thence to Wrightsborough - 10	then at David Mote
from thence to Williames - 10	then at Joseph Evans at Williams
	in Georgia
in visiting families within
Wrightsborough month meeting 60
on this page is 1222 [not accurate]

<pb n="069"/>
from Wrightsborough in Georgia to	then at Francis Joneses
Allwoods meeting in South Carolina - 60	then at Daniel Williams
	then at James Ges
	then at several places where I had lodged
from thence to Bush River - 40 	then at Nathanial Hendersons	 	then at Henry Stidhams
	then at Thomas Wilsons
from thence to Padgetts Creek - 40	then at Ralph Hunts
	then at Seth Wilsons
from thence to Tiger River - 15	then at Eli Coocks
	then at Isaac Hollingsworth
to and from Tiger River on Cane Creek - 14	then at Joseph Thomsons
from thence back to Bush River - 39	then at Isaac Cooks
in South Carolina in this place bad rods	then at William Grigory
from thence to Mud lick - 20
from thence to Rabons Creek as we went 35
though but twenty the nearest way	then at one Hustans
towards the Allegheny mountains and so to Tennessee
the first day lodged in the woods near the head
of Saluda River in South Carolina 53
then over the Blue Mountains and lodged
in the woods a second night - 35
then amongst the mountains had good
entertainment at William Rises - 40	then at William Rises
then in the Allegheny mountains that
was of a towering height and lodged in the wood 22
then over the mountains to George Husts 12	then at George Howards
then to New Hope meeting in the Tennessee - 30	then at Cornal Rodors
then to Lost Creek meeting - 60	then at John Millses
	these are in the Tennessee government
then to Grassy Valley beyond	then at Thomas Marshalls
Holston River ten miles to a small settlement	at Grassy Valley ten miles beyond
of friends where I had a meeting in Tennessee 18	Holston in the Tennessee government
then back to Lost Creek - 18	then at Abraham Woodard
then back to New Hope - 60	then at William Parkses
	then at Ellis Ellises
then to Limestone - 14	then at Thomas Emeries
then to across Holston ferrey near
the mouth of Autauga Tennessee -30	then at Abraham Smith
then to Little Reed Island - 120	then at taverns
	then at Isaac Greens
then to Chestnut and back - 32	then at David Ballards
then to Great Reed Island and back 24	then at Thomas Jessups
then to the top of Allegheny mountain 12	then at Jacob Talberts
then to Westfield meeting - 30	then at Bowtor Sumner
then to Deep Creek - 32	then at John Burcham
then to Hunting Creek - 13	then at Simon Healey
then to the shallow ford - 22	then at James Burnsides
then to Muddy Creek - 33	then at Samuel Welch
then to Center - 30	then at Joseph Mendenhall
then to Providence - 6	then at Enoch Macy
then to Cane Creek monthly meeting 18	then at Jessey Wilson
	then at John Davis
then to spring monthly meeting - 9	then at Jonathan Lindley
then to Eno meeting - 23	then at Joseph Thomson
then back to Thomas Lindlies 28	then at Thomas Lindley
then to Rocky River - 8
then to Tisons meeting - 27	then at Sabra Gilbert
North Carolina	deep River North Carolina

<pb n="070"/>
miles	lodging is in these places
then back to the Ridge meeting 8	then at Hugh Morford
then to Holly Spring - 22	then at David Kinworthy
then to Back Creek quarter meeting 17	then at Thomas Winslow
then to Heugh worrey meeting
and to back Creek again - 20
then to Mobra meeting - 12	then at Fenias Nixons
then to Jewors a meeting in a print house 9	then at Enoch Macys
then to Center month meeting - 14	then at Jessey Hendleys
then to New Garden first day meeting 10	then at Timothy Russel
then to Hopewell and back 12
then to Sherborne - 14	then at Selvenas Gardner
then to Dover and back - 15
then to Belews Creek - 17
then to Springfield - 22	then at Seth Cofings
then to Deep River and back - 16
then to Piney Woods and back - 18
then to Deep River again - 8
then to the Nicholite meeting - 4
then to New Garden - 9	then at Matthews Cofings
	here I lodged several nights at New Garden
	in North Carolina in the 5 month 1797.
	then at John Talberts
so two and from thence and back in these	then at Obediah Herrises
parts ---- 50	then at Timothy Russels several nights
then to Bannister meeting - 90	then at Valentine Peggs
	then at John Barnets
	then at the Widow Hendrick
then to Hills Creek - 40	then at Micaiah Smith
then to Seneca - 12	then at Stevan Butler
then to South River - 18	then at John Coffee
then to Goose Creek - 27	then at Steven Morelin
then to upper Goose Creek in Virginia 7
then to James Johnsons and back - 20	then at James Johnsons
	then at Joseph Wright
then back to lower Goose Creek - 7	then at Samuel Davis
then to Hills Creek again - 30	then at William Pidgeon
	as I am a second time at Hills Creek
then a second time at Seneca -
to Seneca from Hills Creek - 12	I lodged a Daniel Strattons in Virginia
then a second time 	then at Robert Hannows
then to South River a second time the way we came 25	then at William Stantons
in visiting the meetings and the
Negroes about South River - 68	then at John Timborlak
	then at Ekellas Douglas
	then at John Linch
then to Bannister a second time 60	then at Cristopher Johnson
	then at the Widow Hendricks a second time
then to the Widow Derhams - 65	then at the Widow Derhams
then to Jared Ladds - 35	then at Richard Hanford
	then at Jared Ladds
then to Sadlors - 15	then at Sadlers
then to grarley Run - 35	then at Joseph Butler
then to Petersburgh a little town
where we had a meeting in the Courthouse 12	then at Robert Pleasants
then to Curls on James River - 18	then at James Ladds
then to Wine Oak - 16	then at Benjamin Bates
then to Skimino - 32	then at Joshua Bailey
then to Stanton - 50 	then at Samson Stantons
then to Jack swamp - 50	David Marmson

<pb n="071"/>
then to James Jurkines - 27	at James Jurkinses
then to Vise meeting - 17	then at Jorden Densons
then to Black Creek - 22	then at Samson Stantons
then to Stanton meeting - 17	then at Joseph Joneses
then to Johnsons - 30	then at Joshua Raley
then to Black Water - 24	then at Thomas Pretlows
then to meeting and back and forward 20	these are a second time in Virginia
then to Burley a second time 26	then at John Honeycut
then to Petersburgh a second time 19	then at Robert Pleasants
then to Black Creek on the East side
of James River - 32	then at Gideon Ellenson
then to Richmond - 30	then at Nathan Bells
	then at George Winstons near Richmond
then to Jeneto the way I went 34	then at Thomas Pleasants
then to Cedar Creek - 20	then at Micajah Crew
then back again - 10	then at Thomas Standley
then to Caroline meeting - 32	then at Widow Harrises
	then at Thomas Harris
	then at Pleasants Terrels
then to Stafford - 45	then at one Rogers a second time
then to Southland - 25	then at Robert Painters
then to Culpeper the way we Came 35	then at Jacob Pickering
then to Crooked Run - 26	then at Cousin John Garwood
then to Mount Pleasant - 12	then at Isaac Painters
number of miles since I left home 4761
this is in Virginia Winchester
then to Bear Garden - 20	then at Isaac Perkinses
	near Winchester in Virginia
then to the glades or Sandy Creek 100	then at two taverns in Crossing the
	Allegany mountains towards Redstone
	then at John Willits
then to Union meeting - 27	then at William Cammels
then to Redstone - 12	then at Jonas Cattels
then to <persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Hunts</persName> - 6	then at <persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Hunts</persName>
then to sweetly meeting - 22	then at Finley Megrews
then to Providence - 16	then at Allen Forquer
then to Center the way we went - 9	then at <persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Hunts</persName>
then to Providence a second time - 7	then at Margaret Brown
these are on the western waters
in the settlement of Redstone
then to Fallowfield - 6
then to pick run - 8	then at Mary Englands
then to Westland - 8	then at David Graves
these are on the westside the
the Monongahela River
then to William Dicksons - 11	then at William Dicksons
then to Thomlinsons - 50	then at Thomlinsons
then to Thomas Claytons - 50	then at Thomas Claytons in the mountain
then to Bear Garden in the
mountains --- 15	then at Richard Sidwell
	then at Isaac Perkinses
then to Beak Creek meeting 10	then at Joseph Bond
	then at Richard Ridgaway
then to the Ridge meeting - 7	then at Isaac Haines
then to Winchester again - 5	then at Edward Conard
this is on my return from Redstone	these are on the other side of
	the mountains called Blue Ridge
	near Winchester

<pb n="072"/>
miles
then to Hopewell meeting - 8	then at Mahlon Jenney
then to Middle Creek - 14	then at
then to Bulskin meeting - 17	then at Evan Thomas
then to the gap meeting - 19	then at John Thomas
then to Fairfax - 8	then Widow Ballinger
then to Goose Creek - 8
then to South Fork and back to Fairfax 28
then to Indian spring - 64	then at George Rewseys
then to Sandy Spring - 20	then at Joseph Elgors
then to Bush Creek - 25	then at Isaac Hendrick
then to Pine Creek - 20	then at Nicolas Wireman
then to Menallen - 30	then at Benjamin Walker
then to Huntington - 10	then at James Bean
then to Worington - 12	then at William Willits
then to Neberrey - 12
then to York --- 13
then to Thomas Mores and back 24	then at Thomas Mors near
	the River Susquehanna on the
	south side
	then at Joseph Updegraff
then to fawn meeting - 26	then at Richard Webb
to this place is miles since I left
home in these southern governments 5526
then to Deer Creek - 18	then at Asif
then to fawls - 20	then at Joshua Hursbands
then to Gunpowder - 20	then at Joshua Staplor
	then at Moses Dilwin
then to Bush - 32	then at Daniel Robinson
	then at William Coles
then to Deer Creek again - 13	then at Hugh Elye
	then at Isaac Wilsons
	then at George Churchmans
then to East Nottingham - 20	then at Benjamin Masons
then to Little Britain - 13	then at Jean Runels
then to Eastland - 4	then at [add: Isaac] [del: Nathan] Haines
then to West Nottingham - 8	then at Thomas Rogers
then to East Nottingham - 7	then at Oliver Cork
then to the head of scefras - 36	then at John Corse
then to Chester - 30	then at the Widow Brown
then to the head of Chester - 28	then at David Lambs
then to Choptank bridge - 30	then at Joseph Turner
then to center a Nicholite meeting - 10	then at James Harrises a Nicholite
then to Westfork another Nicholite - 12
then to Cold Spring - 40	then at Jacob Rights
then to Malford - 20	then at Sarah Rolands
then to Mother Cil - 17	then at Isaac Rolands
then to third Haven - 50	then at John Regorstors
	then at Howel Powel
then to Massey Creek and back - 21	then at [del: Sarah] Rebecca Bartlet
then to Choptank and back - 21
then to Bayside and back - 40
then to Choptank bridge again 25	then at Bacholer Chans
	these are in the Lower Counties between
	Chesapeake bay and Delaware river

<pb n="073"/>
[on this page the column on the left includes the distances traveled and the column on the right includes the persons with whom Evans lodged]

then at <persName key="w6cz4d1t">Warner Maflin</persName> 	then to Motherkill [modern Murderkil] - 24
then at Clayton Cougel	then to Little Creek - 15
	then to and from meetings - 12
then at Sarah Hanson	then to Whitley Creek 12
	then to Appequimeny - 12
then at Daniel Williams	then to Wilmington - 23
then at Joseph Tatnalls a second time	then to Philadelphia - 27</div>




<div type="entry" n="1797-12-01"><dateline><date when="1797-12-01">1 the 12 month 1797</date></dateline><p> Returned home from a visit to all the southern governments on the west side Susquehanna as far as Georgia not missing but four meetings in all that way it took me fourteen months wanting two days when I Came home found my wife and Children all well but many of my friends number to the silent grave both aged middle aged and youth so that we see no age is Exempted from the stroke of that undeniable mace death ready or not ready Oh that we all may often Consider our latter end and be wise so that none may be found in a state unprepared to leave this world not having their accounts in readiness and so not be worthy to receive the answer of well done good and faithful servant</p></div>

<floatingText>
<pb n="074"/>
[This page is written in handwriting different from that of the author of the rest of the manuscript and describes the last days of Evans's life, although the journal continues for several pages after this in the original handwriting]

On getting into New Jersey again he appeared at first unusually cheerful saying he felt easy in his mind and clear of America, but soon after had to pass through a scene of sore conflicts on account of some near connections who were chargeable with misconduct and with whom it is believed he labored in measure successfully within the short space of his life after returning home as he lived but six days. On the day of his decease being the 7th of the 7th mo 1798 he rose early in the morning (as was his practice) and went into the field near his house to work among the sweet potatoes. About sunrise he was observed to lean on his hoe, which is supposed to be the time he began to feel himself unwell, soon after he hasted to the house, his wife being yet in bed, casting himself on the bed by his wife, he told her he had a pain in his breast. As soon as he lay down, his wife hearing an unusual noise, rose up and asked what is the matter but to her great surprise she perceived his breath was gone having instantly expired in a few minutes after he left the field. The weather being very warm he was entered in the grave yard belonging to friends at Haddonfield the next day, his corpse being accompanied by a large concourse of his friends and neighbours. After his interment a solemn silence ensued and in the efficacy of divine power testimony was born to the gracious dealings of our Heavenly Father who had led this our valuable friend, through various unusual trials and exercises in the course of his pilgrimage through life and at the solemn close had granted that in an unusual manner he should be exempt from bodily pain except for a few minutes and thus be taken as a shock of corn gathered in due season.
</floatingText>

<div type="entry" n="1798-04-01/1798-04-09"><pb n="075"/>
[Original writing resumes]
<p><date from="1798-04-01" to="1798-04-09">From the first to the ninth of the 4 month 1798</date> I visited several monthly meetings although several of them was but poor low seasons yet I thought I had some acceptable service have no cause to murmur I had to mention that of giving children three names in order as they say to keep in remembrance some of their kindred as also some single letter between the two names this the rich and great have a plea for to distinguish where there is two of one name but I have seen it seldom done amongst the poor folks as in like manner some words gathered from the top of the high tree of knowledge and wisdom of this world which is foolishness with God and ever will be</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-04-09/1798-04-17"><p><date from="1798-04-09" to="1798-04-17">From this to the 17 of the 4 month 1798</date> have had much close labor in dealing with some of my neighbors who has been likely to spend much in the law which always giveth me pain to hear of money spent that way believing all matters might be settled much better by Crossing men themselves and save much Cost this several days of my time has taken up in with a favorable prospect the 9 of this month I laid before a desire I had to be at Baltimore quarter and Virginia yearly meeting and to take some meeting that I had passed by last summer friends granted me liberty to proceed as we should open but am yet defined in truth’s service</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-04-20"><p>Till <date when="1798-04-20">the twentieth of the same month 1798</date> I am detained by some indisposition in some part of family but now believe the time come for me to leave them to proceed on the service before me took my leave of my friends at our meeting</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-04-21"><dateline><date when="1798-04-21">21 the 4 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Parted with my dear wife in near feeling love and sympathy, she having so often to part with me on truth’s account yet saith she has her reward this this I hope will be encouragement to both husbands and wives to submit to the divine appointment be that what it may and then I believe all will be well both at home and abroad though it may some times in suffering for season yet I have not doubt but the reward will be enough. I now crossed the river to Philadelphia where I stayed the sitting of the Indian Committee. Here I met with some things not so pleasant as I could have wished. Friends had lent the Indians money to build some mills that government had agreed to do for some services in the time of war and for some money to replace that which they had borrowed of friends government was this the going to the war office for money to pay us what we had lent them to build these mills which government had promised for services in war and other losses at such a time which to me did not look clear enough consistent with our principles and that of faithfulness against all wars and fightings I then went to Darby and lodged at John Hunt’s where I had I believe good service in his family.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-04-22"><dateline><date when="1798-04-22">22 the 4 month 1798</date></dateline><p> This is first day had two meetings very large the last most favoured the one at Darby the other at Springfield.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-04-23"><dateline><date when="1798-04-23">23 the 4 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had two meetings, the first at Chester, that in the afternoon at Providence these large in so much that I thought I now saw with great clearness how the Lord had been preparing me for his work and service in pointing out so narrow a path for me to walk in and also that of wearing of my beard for from the largeness of meetings where I have travelled it being almost over the continent that I had seen thousands of people that if it had not been for my different appearance I should not have ever seen which has been a comfort to many <gap/> for it was the people that I wanted to see and that for their good every way.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-04-24">
<pb n="076"/>
<dateline><date when="1798-04-24">24 the 4 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Chichester not very large yet a solid good meeting 25 at Concord, 26 at Birmingham 27, at Kennet,  28 at Center,  29 at Wilmington-- two meetings fore and after noon, this being first day these were all large and some of them favored ones though some more trying dull and heavy by reason of a worldly spirit which so much prevails in the general as also amongst us as a people to our great shame professing as we do to be lead by truth is it anything less than giving our principles the lie and so proving a stumbling block to many of the honest hearted inquirer I found it is hard work for the faithful laborer to discharge the trust reposed in him but let none be discouraged nor let their hearts fail them for master is good and will reward everyone according to their labor.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-04-30"><dateline><date when="1798-04-30">30 the 4 month 1798</date></dateline><p> This day set forward towards Baltimore took Whitley Creek in my way and traveled upwards of thirty miles had in my journey so far have had many solid opportunities in families in laboring against wrong things I which seemed well received I hope not all lost.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-05-01"><dateline><date when="1798-05-01">1 the 5 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Crossed the River Susquehanna traveled about 20 miles to Bush</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-05-02"><dateline><date when="1798-05-02">2 the 5 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a favored good meeting at Bush meeting house large</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-05-03"><dateline><date when="1798-05-03">3 the 5 month 1798</date></dateline><p> This morning rose an hour before day in order to be at Baltimore week day and preparative meeting. This is a poor low time it was very sensibly felt the life and power was wanting. Truth’s course is at a low ebb. There wants more faithful laborer I see the harvest is g<supplied>reat</supplied></p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-05-04"><dateline><date when="1798-05-04"><supplied>4</supplied> the 5 month 1798</date></dateline><p> This morning I believe I had some profitable labor for the great and good master where I now am in Baltimore a place that aboundeth in sin and iniquity. I have been ready to believe the cup is almost full I also had some solid labor in several families in pointing out some things which truth did not own neither was they Consistent with the profession we do make this they had to grant though it seemed as I thought they was in a spirit to confess and continue for I could not see much prospect for the better gives me pain I likewise had a solid time with some friends going on a religious visit to the southward I did believe one of them was well qualified to do the Lord’s work and had a large share assigned her I told her I felt a desire that nothing might retard the work but their precept and example might keep pace with each other and not to preach one thing and practice another I also informed them I was afraid the carriage they proposed to ride in was too fine and savored too much of fashion and the customs of the world which perhaps they might have to speak against. I was afraid as I told them it might hurt their service where they was going and wound the little ones and strengthen the hands of those who was standing ready to catch at everything to vindicate their evil conduct. Oh how guarded ought preachers to be and more especially those who travel in truth’s service</p></div>

<div><pb n="077"/>
[Another section containing columns with distances traveled and persons stayed with. Again, efforts have been made to match the two columns appropriately]

twelve miles to Darby - 12				first at John Hunts
then to the next meeting - 5
then to Chester - 7					then at Roger Dicks
then to Providence - 7
then to Chichester - 8					then at Daniel Sharpless
then to Concord -5					Thomas Pierce’s
then to Birmingham - 8
then to Kennet - 6					Caleb Pierce’s
then to Center - 5
then to Wilmington - 8
then to Baltimore - 79					then at William Harvey
							then at Joseph Crosly
then to Alexandria - 50				then at Caleb Seels
							then at Enen Williams
then to Fredericksburg - 55				then at William Hartshorn
							then at Joseph Cristey
then to Caroline meeting - 40				then at Pleasant Terels
then to Cedar Creek - 25				then at Thomas Standley
then to Richmond - 26				then at George Winstons
							then at Robert Pleasants
then to Curles in Virginia - 16				then at Samuel Hargroves
then to Wine Oak - 17 				then at John Crues
then to Blackwater - 45				then at Joshua Baleys
then to and from the yearly				then at Thomas Pretlows
meeting at Blackwater - 50				during the yearly meeting
							at Blackwater in Virginia
then back to Richmond on
my return from blackwater 68			then back to Robert Pleasants
							then a second time at George Winstons
							near Richmond
then back to Fredericksburg - 85			then at cleark Moremans
							then at Matthew Tenets
then to Elecuts mill - 39				then at Ellecuts Mills
then to Baltimore on my				then to Philip Wontors
way back from Blackwater - 52			then at Samuel Snowdens
							then at David Browns
							in Baltimore on my
							return from Blackwater
then to Susquehanna ferry - 40			then at Joseph Inglands
then to West Grove - 30				then at <persName key="w6xf1s5t">Jacob Lindlies</persName>
then to Newgarden - 4
then to Hockessin -4
then back to London grove - 16			then at John Wilsons
then to Fallowfield - 8
then to East Caln - 7					then at Isaac Jacksons
then to West Caln - 6
then to Lampeter - 16					then at George Welches
then to Lancaster - 8
then to Sadsbury - 18					then at Isaac Coatses
then to Bradford - 16					then at Gayas Dickasons
then to Newtown - 17					then at William Webbs
thent to Wrightstown 7				then at Robart Mores

<pb n="078"/>
then to Willistown
then to Goshen					then at George Welches a second
then to Upland 					then at Isaac Thomases
then to Nantmeal					then at Agnes Minshens
then to Pikeland					then at Jonathon Cormott
then to Valley						then at William Milhous
then to Radnor
then to Hartford					then at John Lewis
then to Merion

<pb n="079"/>
27th 5th month 1798. Was at Richmond first day meeting very large and solid after traveled <gap/></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-05-28"><dateline><date when="1798-05-28">28 the 5 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a solid good favored meeting at Caroline in Virginia.</p></div>
 
<div type="entry" n="1798-05-29/1798-05-30"><dateline><date from="1798-05-29" to="1798-05-30">29 and 30th 5 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Traveled to Alexandria and in the afternoon had a meeting in the town though but a poor prospect of much growth in the truth. As I have passed through those southern countries I thought it would be no marvel if it should come to pass that a turn of times should take place when the masters and mistresses with their children should be out at work amongst the tobacco in nakedness and hunger as the poor oppressed slaves now do and that the same measure be measure to them as they have done to the poor Negroes. For I should not marvel if the Black should have the rule and treat the men and women as they are now treated, that a man should marry a wife and another should lay with her. This would be as the whites serve the poor oppressed Black. This would be a great turn from what it now is and I did believe the time was coming when it would fall harder on the women than any other of the inhabitants, that they would not only suffer nakedness, hunger, and cold, but the Black men would ravish the white women and that with severe whipping because of their chastity, and no man shall be able to deliver his own wife, neither shall there be any to plead their case of the women, though now so delicate. The sun that is a blessing from heaven and comfort to the Earth must [add: not] be suffered to shine on {you} [add: those] miserable barbarous wretches when the poor oppressed blacks and their children must without complaint suffer all, both heat and cold, when you their oppressors can’t adventure to set your feet on the ground for delicateness, who live in such shameful waste of that which would be a comfort to those your poor slaves who bear the burden and heat of the day in nakedness, hunger, and want, and that without mercy or pity but have I believed that there will be a mighty overturning in this land so that the oppressed will go free and the oppressor will be the oppressed both them and their wives and children this will be by the mighty power of God and no man shall be able to deliver those when he will arise to shake terribly the Earth and the resting places of the wicked slave holders. Oh that they may repent so that the Lord may show mercy before this overflowing surge overtakes the inhabitants of those southern countries where there is so much innocent blood been shed and tearing parents from children and children from parents and selling them like the beasts. What think you? Hath not the cry of those reached his holy care? Who will be able to stand before him in the day of his judgments? Thus has been the feelings of my mind as I have passed through those lands and I believe that time is coming to pass and unless by sincere repentance and an amendment of life and to do justly so far as is in their powers it over take the inhabitants of those southern countries where there is so much of those poor oppressed Blacks.  Joshua Evans</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-05-31">
<pb n="080"/>
<dateline><date when="1798-05-31">31 the 5 month 1798</date></dateline><p> This and two following days traveled towards home to East Nottingham under an humbling sense of the divine goodness and mercy of God.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-03"><dateline><date when="1798-06-03">3 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Was at West Grove First Day meeting large and favored.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-04"><dateline><date when="1798-06-04">4 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at New Garden, a large solid good favored time</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-05"><dateline><date when="1798-06-05">5 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Hockessin an exercising time</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-06"><dateline><date when="1798-06-06">6 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Was at London Grove week day meeting, very large and highly favored and power given from the Lord to do his work faithfully.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-07"><dateline><date when="1798-06-07">7 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Fallowfield not large.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-08"><dateline><date when="1798-06-08">8 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had this day two meetings in the forenoon at East Caln and in the afternoon at West Caln. These dull and small.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-09"><dateline><date when="1798-06-09">9 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Lampeter large and favored in those parts the young people are the best of the flock they are the foremost in religion though too much in the aire the old ones are grappling in the Earth in so much that I was ready to say I was afraid truth could not grow unless the Lord would remove the old folks not of the young ones I had much close labor in those parts which I think is much wanting all which seemed well received they to me was very kind I had much private labor in families some of which was to my Comfort and I believe to theirs also as many of them expressed both young and old we parted in much love and tenderness that seemed to Crown all for that sweetens labor when the divine presence is felt to accompany that is enough</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-10"><dateline><date when="1798-06-10">10 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Lancaster in the town small here is but a few friends it is a poor pace for Quakers I at this time thought truth was over all before meeting I had a solid time with one who was much in the spirit of war and a very great party and was pleading much for self defence as at this time their is great Commotions making and learning the use of carnal weapons which he seemed much to applaud and the necessity for our defence against our enemies I told him I did believe carnal weapons was not necessary to defend to a truly Christian Country but that if our ways did please the Lord he would make all our enemies at peace with us. He seemed to think strange I told him it was scripture doctrine which I did believe he pretended to Call in question the possibility of such a thing I asked him if he did believe the power lessened that preserved the three servants of the Lord when cast in to the furnace and not an hair of their heads singed nor the smell of fire on them and this not by carnal weapons but by the mighty power of God and that power was not lessened nor his hand shortened that he could not save now in this our day. He did was forced to confess to the truth of the sufficiency of that power and that it would be far the best but the coming at it was much wanting to have our ways please the Lord then he confessed he believed all wars would be to an end.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-11">
<pb n="081"/>
<dateline><date when="1798-06-11">11 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Sadsbury, large, a solid good meeting.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-12"><dateline><date when="1798-06-12">12 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Bradford it was a favoured time and large</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-13"><dateline><date when="1798-06-13">13 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Newtown, a large good season.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-14"><dateline><date when="1798-06-14">14 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had two meetings this day the first at Wrightstown and that in the afternoon at Willistown these both large and exercising in general the love of the world and the cares thereof chokes the good seed this is mournfully the case in this highly favored place as to the good things of this world and the dew of heaven and yet forgetting too much God the giver.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-15"><dateline><date when="1798-06-15">15 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Goshen, large and comfortable and in the afternoon had a solid setting in the family where I lodged.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-16"><dateline><date when="1798-06-16">16 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Uwchlan, large and laborious but in all though often trying in so much that I think sometimes it is poorly worth my while to call people from their work to Come to meeting when they are so busy about their worldly Concerns and I like an empty vessel</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-17"><dateline><date when="1798-06-17">17 the 6 month</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Nantmeal small and laborious but power over all was given to do the Lord work and that faithfully and that to the tendering of many and that of the youth for in these parts the old seem in withring state to my grief they have too much of this worlds goods</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-18"><dateline><date when="1798-06-18">18 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Pikeland small but ended well</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-19"><dateline><date when="1798-06-19">19 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> A poor little meeting at the valley in the forenoon Radnor a poor low exercising meeting the same in the afternoon</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-20"><dateline><date when="1798-06-20">20 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Hartford and Me Merion [sic] appears almost discouraging to me for as we drew near to the City of Philadelphia the hearts of the people was more worldly and less religious this makes hard work for the faithful servants of the Lord to discharge their trust faithfully</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-21"><dateline><date when="1798-06-21">21 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Here the people seemed much in the traffic of this world here is such poor meetings I was ready to say vain is the labor of thy servants Oh Lord yet I think I had some profitable labor in some families amongst the youth for in these parts they are best as I thought though too much are pastimes of the world but the old folks is in the Earth in so much that however poor ground and hard work may be best for Quakers I must leave but I think I clearly see that rich ground and prosperity Cannot be borne by us as a people in these parts here they build large teams but little meeting houses and a complaint of small meetings though thick inhabited and good farmers and fine fine things about</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-22"><dateline><date when="1798-06-22">22 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Germantown this was a poor little meeting the people taken up with the cares of this world and but little time to provide for the next. I thought truth was at a low ebb. I had some private labor that gave me some relief but hard work for the honest laborer, but their minds but labor faithfully and leave the event to the great author of all good who is able to prosper his one cause in the Earth</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-23"><dateline><date when="1798-06-23">23 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Was at Providence this meeting small but favoured [missing] the ownings of the masto [missing] this was [missing]</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-24">
<pb n="082"/>
<dateline><date when="1798-06-24">24 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Was at Plymouth first day meeting very large and favoured the youth in these parts the most lively to me it has been comfortable though riches I believe has been hurtful to some of them.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-25"><dateline><date when="1798-06-25">25 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Was at Abington Month Meeting. I thought they was likely to do business pretty well but some began to make long speeches and others to preach it out this began to flatter the work as it always doth and will do I never know it to increase life but the fewer words so as to convey our sentiments and ideas of matters before the meeting is best but some friends value themselves upon their eloquence.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-26"><dateline><date when="1798-06-26">26 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Was at Gwynedd month meeting here I had some close labor which was more than one old friend could well bear because it touched the spot that needed but many spoke well of my labor that day before and after the meeting ended requested that I might not be discouraged for they had good unity with the hints given though close.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-27"><dateline><date when="1798-06-27">27 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Was at Horsham month meeting this was a favoured time and ended well as I thought.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-28"><dateline><date when="1798-06-28">28 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Byberry something favoured with ability to labor for the good cause which I esteem a favor.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1798-06-29"><dateline><date when="1798-06-29">29 the 6 month 1798</date></dateline><p> Had a meeting at Bristol this was large and openness felt to plead truth’s cause which seemed well received. This was the last in this my visit after which I crossed the River Delaware and met my dear wife at my son and daughter Warrington’s to my great comfort being humblingly thankful to the God and Father of all our mercies who has in so a marvelous a way provided for me through all my visit to all the friends meetings on this continent that I have heard of but four which is in North Carolina Mattamuskeet and in Virginia Smiths Creek and in Maryland the Cliffs and in Pennsylvania the Half Moon Valley these four are all that I have not been at that I have heard of the thirtieth of this month. I am returned to my home again and found all well as to health though as to myself as is common with me to return as an empty vessel as I thought if I had known any good I had lost it all behind yet I can in sincerity and from a feeling heart say great and marvelous are thy works Oh Lord God, almighty and just and true has been all thy ways towards me in preparing the way before me in so much that I have wanted for nothing to make me comfortable as to the outward neither hast thou been wanting in every time of need Oh Lord I feel whole. I am now writing everything bow and reverence thy great name who are worthy of all praise adoration and praise now and forever and ever saith my soul and all that is within me.</p></div>

[The last words are in a different handwriting, the same as that in which the account of Evans's death is written]

An account of his last illness and death 4 leaves back
</body></text>
</TEI>
