<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
 <fileDesc>
 <titleStmt>
 <title></title>
 </titleStmt>
 <publicationStmt></publicationStmt>
 <sourceDesc></sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
 <front>
 <pb n="001"/>
<docTitle><titlePart>Journal of Joshua Evans</titlePart></docTitle>
 </front>
 <body>
<div type="part" xml:id="autobio">
<div type="year" n="1731">
<head>1731</head>
<p>I was born in the year 1731. My parents were Thomas and Rebekah Evans from whom I received a religious education, but was <del>more</del><add>much</add> under the care of my mother, being the eldest by her. And my father had several children by his former marriage, yet I doubt not his prayers were in secret for me, for I was full of my pranks for which my mother often corrected me, which I justly deserved. She kept me to wait on her till nine or ten years old, during which time I often rode on the same horse with <del>my mother</del><add>her</add> to Evesham Meeting, of which meeting we were members. Some of these meetings were favored seasons <del>to</del> never to be forgotten. The solid sittings of some friends reached me to the tendering of my heart many times as also by some powerful testimonies, for within the first ten years of my life weighty considerations impressed my mind respecting the tenderness of the thread of life and the uncertainty of our stay here and the length of eternity which must never end. These thoughts of times brought me very low in my mind, inasmuch that I loved to be alone and very early believed there was a state of happiness for that part of the righteous that must never likewise a place of woe and misery for the wicked.</p>
<p>Let me never forget the many favors bestowed on one in tender life, one of which was when fetching my father’s flock, the glory of the Lord shone round about me far exceeding the sun at noon day (it was no eternal light). I stood still beholding the light, now tears flowing from my eyes, saying in my heart this exceeded any thing I ever saw, matchless mercies to me a poor sinner. This no <add>human</add> eye beheld, I being alone. I have had to marvel many times at the early visitations of divine kindness to me and many times had to reflect on the little lads and lasses summoned from time to endless eternity. Oh! The awfulness of these considerations. Am I ready for a change like this? Can I be happy if I go in the state I am now in? I had these considerations before I was ten years old. </p>
<p>Notwithstanding these favors and many more marvelous to think of, forgetfulness and disobedience to God prevailed, although I hated sin and loved truth in my heart. I wrote these things to warn boys and girls against the first 
<pb n="002"/>
appearance of evil, to cleave to that which is good and you will find peace. Light not the day of small things, for the tender impressions of divine grace in early life takes the deepest root. Delays are dangerous, dear children. The Lord calls for the whole heart, and may not spare you a more convenient season. Life is too slender a thread to trust your eternal happiness upon, and thoughts of repenting leisurely on in later life cost you dear, and your time be too late and the day of Mercy over, and you left to yourselves. So let the seed of the good seedsman in your hearts be precious in your eyes that fruits may be brought forth to the praise of the great husbandman. 
And parents though you cannot give your children grace, you through the holy help may prepare the ground of their hearts to receive the good seed of grace, which by their occupying may increase until the final close or day of account wherein they may enter into the joys of their Lord and be forever happy among the saints and spirits of just men made <del>happy</del><add>perfect</add> and join the heavenly host singing praises unto God who lives forever and ever, so be it saith my soul.</p>
</div>
<div type="year" n="1741">
<head>1741</head>
<p>From the eleventh to the fourteenth years of my age (notwithstanding the many favors of a gracious God) I grew in a libertine spirit. An inclination for company prevailed, and the free use of my tongue, when out of my parents sight, in using the plural language of you to a single person. Likewise jest and joke and sometimes lie and swear (to help out as its called). These practices grew upon me until they grew very familiar. Astonishingly Oh! God when thy mercies are remembered who cut me not off in rebellion, my spirit groaned within me by reason of my sinful state. Let it be a 
<pb n="003"/>
warning to everyone who may read these lines that they may cease to do evil and barn to do well. And you whose state is like unto mine beware. Oh! How the first nature doth grow in the hearts of the disobedient.</p>
</div>
<div type="year" n="1745">
<head>1745</head>
<p>In the fourteenth year of my age my father put me apprentice, which was no small trial to me to leave my father’s house. But, as my custom was, I put on a cheerful countenance. In my way an aged man enquiring who I was and whither I was going, advised me thus “be sure be kind to your mistress and keep in favor with the women.” I took his advice, though I knew him not, which was an advantage to me. I do not remember ever refusing to go at the biding of my mistress by night or day which gained me <del>the</del> favor <add>in</add><del>of</del> the <del>whole</del> family. I often feel for apprentice boys whose trade exposes them to ramble through the country as mine did, being bricklaying. My inclination increased for company and more liberty, which my master indulged me in as I was faithful in his business. I then lay open to a wide world, threw off my education in dress and address, had my coat altered and cross pockets put in, and you instead of thee to one, and so ready with my tongue as to suit almost any company. Oh! God! been merciful unto me, and, instead of cutting me off in this state, following me with judgment for treading under foot my education, for which I had lashes of conscience as an arrow piercing my very heart. Many sorrowful walk alone in the woods had I to bemoan my state and pour out my cries and prayers to a gracious God with great abhorrence to my ways, insomuch that life was a burthen to me, loathsome in my own eyes. And how much more so in thine Oh God! was often my 
<pb n="004"/>
cries. Many are thy mercies. I love thy everlasting Truth.</p>
<p>Notwithstanding all these favors and many more, and I hated the Devil and all his works at times, yet my sins were increased. So captivated was my mind with <del>the</del> my large acquaintance, it seemed not for me to be alone unless I took to the wood, which I often did. In many of these times the Lord beheld me as a <del>weary</del><add>poor</add> pilgrim in a weary <add>land,</add> seeking a place of retreat, that could find none, for I could not say I had one hour’s true comfort in these ten years of my life; yet mercy was mixed with judgment in that I was not cut off in this time. Oh! Company, company, how captivating, although with what the world calls clever folks and in favor with men, for such as those in their folly make light of everything, however sad their hearts may be, as mine often was even unto death. Marvelous are God’s mercies unto poor captive sinners almost abandoned in a far country among as Satan’s instrument, wasting their blessed portion of grace, lavishing away precious time, when the fathers house mount Zion is beautiful, for situation and abounds in plenty and is the joy of the whole earth. I cannot forget the kindness of my heavenly father who, from time to time, spread the canopy of his love over me and plucked me as a brand out of the burning to blow a trumpet and sound an alarm in the cause of Truth on Earth. I was carried away captive and had by the rivers of Babylon, hanged my harp on the willows, there I wept as I sat down, and those who wasted me required of me a song. I often said in my soul, how can I sing one of the songs of Zion in a strange land. Oh, Let my right hand forget its cunning and my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth if I prefer not Jerusalem to my chiefest joy. I was still touched at the pleasure of a fluctuating world not obeying God who was still following me. Oh! That the youth 
<pb n="005"/>
may be warned and keep the fear of God before their eyes which would preserve from the snares of death.</p></div>
<div type="year" n="1751">
<head>1751</head> 
<p>My master leaving his trade I bought my time and still wrought <del>with my</del><add>for my</add> master to pay him, fearing to go in debt, in which time I took the usual or more liberty than before.</p>
<p>When I went for myself, the first day I worked was a sorrowful day to me. I thought I would gladly have stayed longer. My clothes, while paying for my time, was much worn. I thought no man’s case was like mine. My mother, being old, I chose for her ease to make my home with my brother Jacob. </p>
</div>
<div type="year" n="1752">
<head>1752</head>
<p>I had many sorrowful hours which none knew but the Lord, for I kept my condition much to myself.</p>
<p>25th of the 12th Month. I was taken at Philadelphia with the pleurisy. I had done <add>but</add> little work <add>for my skill</add> and was scant of money and too unwell to be moved home. I was taken to John Collings’s, where I lay six weeks not expected to recover. On the seventh week I was moved to my father’s, where I was some time before I recovered my health again, which was no small trial, but nothing to my inward exercises, for I thought <del>it</del><add>what</add> would become of my poor soul if I should now leave the world. My prayers were for mercy night and day, which was so far granted that I felt willing to die a favor never to be forgot by me while life remains. I made many covenants to amend my ways if my life was granted, but as too too many do as health increases, I went into my old liberties or worse, shocking to think of strolling hither and thither full and empty, joyful and sorrowful as things went well or ill with me, as one of none inheritance in heaven or Earth. The weight of my sins increased until my life seemed a burthen, having forsaken the fountain of living water. I found no rest or peace to my soul insomuch (as the wicked man) in the evening wished for morning and in the morning for evening. The anguish of my soul seemed deeper than the sea, finding no rest for soul or body. Let this be a warning to those who may be tempted to break their solemn covenants with God, for as double sin it will cause deep sorrows sooner or later in this world or the next, I often said “Lord let mine be here, 
<pb n="006"/>
be they of what kind they may, if it be thy will, that my suffering may end with time, and the body brought in subjection to thy government by judgment passing on the transgressing nature that would not that thou might reign whose right it is in time and eternity.” After having passed away or squandered much of my precious time in that which profited not either Body or soul, as many of our Youth do, in passing from one young woman to another in a thoughtless manner, endeavoring to draw out their Affections improperly not considering the consequence, but the Lord who followed me with his mercies and was near me than I was aware, and dealt not with me according to my deserts but, as it were, held me in his hand. For about this time I gained the affections of a virtuous young woman and was nearly attached to her before I was aware, which alarmed me, having no expectations of marrying at this time, but believe it a mercy from God to stop my career, and make the matter of marriage a serious thing, I told her I feared I was too unsettled for so great an undertaking as marriage was, and she would be running too great a risk thro marry<add>ing</add> me in my present condition. She answered so discreetly that it brought a solemn weight over us, and the matter became more serious with us. I was tried to a hairs breadth as my affections was to the young woman and it was below the dignity of a man to leave her, and <del>how</del> to undertake so weighty a matter at this time seemed difficult, however bad as I was. I thought right to consult my father and at a convenient time laid the matter before him, and after a solid pause he gave his consent, and her parents approved of addresses to their daughter. But a fear I couldn’t break off from my old associates was my great concern, and to continue this after marriage as many did I had a great abhorrence, and thought I had better never marry than do so. I also had inclination to travel by sea and land but the Lord in mercy chained me down and made 
<pb n="007"/>
made <add>me</add> willing to quit all company and join in marriage with Priscilla Collins, Daughter of John and Elizabeth Collins in the year 1753 and, to my great astonishment, I became weaned from my old associates and cleaved to my wife, but I found I had a great work to do <del>to</del> in return to God <del>who</del> for his manifest mercies to me, a poor unworthy creature.
I settled near Mount Holly on a poor farm and had many discouraging prospects, and feared I should not pay my rent, and thought I must labour hard, and by taking up any trowel I made out, but was under some inward exercise as no mortal knew. I often sought retirement by night and by day in lonely places, frequently in the woods, and sometimes my wife sat with me in silence, and we shed many tears together when neither of us spoke one word, but poured forth our prayers to God <add>in secret</add>. I had many deep rooted customs and habits which I could not overcome but thro divine aid, for my own resolutions were soon frustrated; a wounded Conscience is hard to endure. My natural rest was much broken by reason of the Judgment of God on my Transgressing nature, insomuch I saw nothing would procure me peace with God short of a surrender to his will, and my sins which were as a scarlet or crimson dye must be cleansed by the fire of his word and the transgressing nature in me must yield to the flame as dry stubble to natural fire, for I saw by the true light that newness of life was called for at my hands, viz. I must speak the truth from my heart. I must say thee and Thou to a single person even in <add>the</add> company of my old companions, this was a trial like parting with a right hand or eye, but the Lord must have the government. I had a hard struggle with my old taskmaster (the Devil) whom I had long served against my judgment. Oh! Lord cause this to be a warning that others may escape the snares of the fowler and serve the in the flower and prime of life.</p> 

<p>I saw there was a rest to the righteous in <del>serving</del> God, amen forever, who will be as a mighty rock in a weary land, but weary of sin we must be before we shelter here.</p>

<pb n="008"/>
<p>My cries were to the Lord to be as walls and bulwarks round about me, without whose aid I could not stand temptations, but through his aid I believed I could stand the strongest assault of Satan, and know the Lord to sway his scepter and have the government of me in all things, I began to be more and more conformable to <del>that Divine</del> <add>God’s <del>w</del></add> will and his yoke became more easy and his burthen light, his ways pleasantness, and his paths peace. My love to God increased, and the glory of the world became stained in my viens. My love to God so overbalanced lower enjoyment I seemed as a pilgrim who had none inheritance. Here I thought no time lost in attending religious meetings to wait on God. It seemed long between meetings, for I had many deep baptisms within, and combats without for my old taskmaster whom I had too long served was loath to let me go.</p>


<p>I must attend meetings on first and other days of the week and go the common road to weekday meetings (for I had gone byways to weekday meetings for shame) and bear the cross in all things where truth’s honor lay at stake, which in time became easy to me and the Lord, by his life-giving presence, refreshed my soul, and increased my faith.</p>

<p>After being two years a tenant through many trials my father gave me a house and lot in Mount Holly to which I moved. Here were several babes in Christ and some fathers, viz. <persName key="w6wr0v4m">John Woolman</persName>, <persName key="w64r0gvn">Josiah White</persName>, and <persName key="w6sk2b2m">William Jones</persName>. These were men of experience. And several others spoke a few words in meetings, of which I was one of the hindermost. It was like death to me to give up (as the old inhabitants were rooted out before Israel possessed the Promised Land: so naughtiness must be rooted from the heart before God will tabernacle therein. I had a foresight of an untrodden path <add>or lonely way in these times of Prosperity</add> for me to walk in.</p>
</div>
<div type="year" n="1757">
<pb n="009"/>
<head>1757</head>
<p>I removed to a house and lot I bought near <persName key="w6wr0v4m">John Woolman’s</persName>. I had as much as I could do to keep my head above <del>water</del> the current of Wickedness which seemed strong, and I, as a small ship easily tossed when the Anchorhold of faith failed, yet some of us, at seasons, as children of our heavenly fathers flock and family, could speak feelingly by me to another of his goodness, in plucking us as brands from the burning, being as the offscouring of all things which was much my case. I wanted to be what the Lord would have me to be, and be conformable in all things in order to which however hard to flesh and blood I found my own honor <del>in all things</del> must be laid low, and God’s honor over all, and the creaturely will which would plead for a little liberty subdued, for I saw to love God and the world was <add>as</add> impossible as a Cable to go thru a needles’ eye, this excludes busy self from <del>having</del> acting in the things of God. It would not do to be of believing parents—no more than of Abraham’s seed, formerly without doing the works of Abraham. I found I must serve God for myself, and that by the immediate influence of the spirit in my own self, and that neither Education nor tradition would avail in God’s sight, all things <del>must</del> become new and <add>be</add> of God. Though I had embarked for the land of promise, my trials seemed as the Red Sea before and the Egyptian Army behind. My Enemies, within and without, made me fear I should someday bring a reproach on the truth, and perhaps had better never set out, for I seemed for some Years as in the Wilderness of this world, but at times partook of the hidden Manna which kept my soul Alive to God, and believed he was often nearer me than I was aware in the hour of temptation, and preserved me from those who waited for my halting, some impatiently, for the Instruments of Satan are one in Nature with 

<pb n="010"/>
himself, and are striving to turn the righteous form the right way, which was trying to me who was newly embarked in God’s cause. I could not tell how to reconcile being a minister, it seemed to me, from my element (like poor Jonah) and plunge me into the deeps. To preach to those I had rioted with seemed like death to me, and I feared the consequence of giving out, lest God in displeasure would cause a final separation from him, which would be terrible in the day of account, which made me Willing to stand to his cause thro’ his holy aid, however discouraging things might appear to me a poor shortsighted creature, without whose Assistance I knew I could do nothing to advance his cause or procure peace of mind.</p>
</div>
<div type="year" n="1759">
<head>1759</head>
<p>This year 1759 I removed within the compass of Haddonfield meeting with the full unity of friends of Mount Holly and was favored to keep on my zionward, for <add>when</add> the Lord putteth <del>not</del> forth, he goeth before and fights our battles for his honor and our good. I was recommended as a minister though I thought myself very unequal to the <del>task</del> work, and feared I should some day drop off, but the Lord dealt with me in a way much hid from me in putting a trumpet like a ram’s horn to my lips and, as it were, compelled me to blow the same though at the loss of all my worldly honor, yet he has rewarded me an hundredfold. So let all be encouraged to serve him who is eternally worthy for abundant unmerited mercies, saith my soul and that forever I ever.</p>
</div>
<div type="year" n="1761">
<head>1761</head>
<p>This year bought a farm and moved within the <del>compass</del><add>Township</add> of Newtown. I met with many discouragements within and without, being a recommended minister but not be enticing words. But the demonstration of the spirit led me to plain dealing and, with some other exercised brethren, to plead for the liberty of the Black people, and to visit those who held them, and that from house to house. This went hard with some who thought it would make uneasiness between them and their Blacks, and would scarcely suffer us to perform the visit, but I saw it was the Lord’s 
<pb n="011"/>
work, yet we need be as wise as serpents and harmless as doves. Truth opened our way to proceed, to sit down in silence with the whole family, and our communications gave the Blacks no knowledge of our business with their master, but when the other parts of the family withdrew, we pleaded with the master and mistress, and truth <del>so</del> favored us to do it in a way as gave general satisfaction. And I never felt a greater reward than in pleading the cause of those captive people. Another trial came on, it seemed as though the cries of the slaves in the West Indies reached my ears day and night for some months and in a special manner when partaking of their labor, and did believe it was required of me to use the fruits of their labor no longer. Many thought this going too far, and thought we might use what we bought and paid for, and cast many reflections on me for my conduct herein, but being convinced my peace lay at stake I bore all with patience, till many of my opposers saw it and the testimony spread to my admiration. Though in times of weakness my faith was strengthened to believe it would spread through all opposition of men, for the Lord was strongest of all this bore me up in times of great weakness.</p>

<p>I was little in the ministry and led in such a rough manner it was hard for me to open my mouth, and as hard for some to bear. I made as little do as I could, and sometimes too little, for my peace but an ancient worthy friend feelingly dropped some hints which strengthened me, but my trials were so uncommon I had to look to the Lord for help and counsel, having to testify against many things which were generally approved of, even by [friends], which made my way exceedingly difficult, for some could not bear my testimony. Though I was thus led by precept and example, I was much reproached for my testimony against war because I could not pay my money to defray the expense of shedding blood. This exercise came on me in the year 1756 being a bloody war between France and England and a number of our youth drafted but <del>government</del> the inhabitants concluded to open a subscription
<pb n="012"/>
to hire volunteers, which seemed so plausible many friends were much taken with it. But, when it was demanded of me, I felt a scruple and told them if I could pay my money for such a purpose, I would consider it and bring the money. But it opened very clear to me when from home, and had none to confer with on the occasion, that to hire men to do what I could not for conscience sake do myself was very inconsistent. This led in the deeps for wisdom, and refused demands to defray war expences (though <add>my part might appear</add> as a drop in the ocean yet it is made up of drops) for which I went thro a great deal of reproach for fighting under his banner whose kingdom he declared was not of this world, else could his servants, yea, and the angels too fight for him. When my goods were taken and sold for half value some would pity me, saying I should be ruined, others would call it stubbornness, and say it was contrary to the doctrine of Christ in rendering Caesar his due, but I saw thro their groundless arguments, for there was nothing in the text about war, and I have been willing to pay my money for the use of government, though not to pay for killing men, women and children and laying waste countries and towns. Thro all my wife encouraged me, saying if we suffer in right spirit, we shall have that peace the world cannot give, neither can it take away. And when my goods have been taken it has seemed as though I had never possessed them and could in my heart love my opposers and magnify God, so let all be encouraged to hold on their way. No weapon formed against you <del>shall</del><add>can</add> hurt you if you are faithful. Some of my great opposers came to own my testimony and great was my peace. I passed thru many baptizing seasons, but the gog and magog arise. The foundation cannot be shaken, I cannot reconcile war with Christianity nor the devouring spirit with the Lamb’s nature, No more than murder and theft with the royal law of <add>doing to</add> others as we would <del>be done</del><add><del>they should</del></add>
<pb n="013"/>
they should do unto us. I endeavored to keep close to the gift within while those storms blew over, believing if I was faithful I should not want bread and so it proved, for in time they said I gave myself to Truth’s service and should not be troubled with such Demands, so took my name off the list. My tongue is too short to set forth thy goodness to the full O God. <add>Let</add> thanks <del>thanks thanks</del> and living praises for ever be given and everything in me bow low <del>low</del> <del>low</del>.</p>
</div>
<div type="year" n="1762">
<head>1762</head>
<p>The Lord was pleased to give me to see the vanity <del>of</del> and loss of time in dying our garments many colors, some of which is very injurious to the cloth, but the heart and mind so set thereon the pattern must be followed be the damage what it may, and by this means good pieces of cloth are much damaged, and this <del>excess</del> <add>pleaded for</add> only to hide dirt, which seems to me no part of cleanliness, for hiding faults is not <add>a</add> cleansing from sin; so hiding dirt doth not remove the filth thereof, for I should suppose the same quantity of dirt would gather on the dyed as the undyed garment with the same wear. Then surely, if the expense and injury of dying was laid out in washing, we should be more cleanly. To dye garments staineth pure innocency, for outward gratification feedeth the lust and pride of life, and weareth off the pure inward sensations which in the language of the spirit to the soul. 
The cross in wearing white clothes was more than I could bear. I pleaded my insufficiency for such a singular work, fearing I should not bear the reproach thereof, but my pained soul could not get ease until I submitted <del>to wear</del> and was made willing to wear white clothes, but I kept my exercise to myself in a great degree.
The Lord was pleased to deal with me as a tender father, and lay no more on me than I could bear. To get a white hat and stockings was as far as I could see at that time, and after wearing old one till it was not fit to be seen,
<pb n="014"/>
I <del>endeavored in</del><add>went to</add> Philadelphia <add>with intent</add> to get a white hat, but returned home without letting my exercise be known, but not announcing the Lord’s requiring I made another trial, and then thro weakness got a black one, this brought such trouble on me I verily thought I felt the terrors of Hell by night and by day, until I became willing to be a reproach among men, and to confess my fault to the man I got the black one of, and offer to pay for the damage done if he would take the hat again and inform me where I could get a white one, which he did. My mind was much bowed but not low enough, for I returned home without buying one. My supplications was to the Lord for mercy on me, a poor weak creature, but was chastised by the Lord until deeply in the cross I went to the place informed of and got a white hat and returned in sweet peace and Joy as though translated into another world. And having got white stockings likewise I believed it was all the Lord required at that time. Though in my dress was an inconsistency, the Lord dealt gently with me and, as I kept to the gift within, in his own time he brought me into a consistency, for I could not wear dyed garments; and though my reproach seemed great, the Lord was my refuge and hiding place, who knew I wore white clothes in obedience to his will much in the cross—and could say I thank thee Oh! Father Lord of heaven and Earth for thou hast hid these things from the wise and prudent of this world and revealed them unto babes.</p>
<p>I likewise thought I saw, in the clearness, the inconsistency of the use of the East India tea, and that it sprang from an evil Root and was never the dictates of truth but fruits of the corrupt tree. For we have <del>have</del> plentifully in our fields and garden’s herbs which, it’s thought, suits our constitution better than those herbs growing in hot different climates, and we go to great expense for those teas while we have plenty at our finger ends.</p>
<pb n="015"/>
<p>Foreign teas were at first used to honor great folks, as it was held a point of honor to have a dish of tea, but now how universal even among those who know not where to get the next meal. So strong is custom, some say they cannot do without it twice a day. I have mourned for the captivity of those whom Satan has bound to this custom—I have been ready to say vanity of vanity, all is vanity.</p>
<p>For how can any <del>whom</del><add>whose eyes</add> the Lord has anointed to see the emptiness of this practice but mourns to see the tea table set in the custom of the times with the cups, saucers, tongs etc. etc., the needless meals this introduces, and the paleness of face, weakness of nerves, and train of other evils brought on the people.</p>
<p>I kept my little gift in the ministry, though stammeringly, and not in the wisdom of this world, having often to testify against the spirit of this world which many seemed wedded to. I looked like a shrub to many tall cedars who lived in worldly greatness. I feared I should fall, but looked not far backward nor forward but to the inward guide, which was counsel superior to all the contrivance or counsel of this world, being wisdom and strength, for my exercise was such I had but few to counsel with, for it was the general sentiment I was led astray, and some said I should come to nothing: others that the Lord was on my side and would carry me through if I was faithful. But I saw the foundation of God stands sure, and if I could keep thereon, nothing could harm me. And blessed be his name, he pleads the cause of those his little ones, who have none in heaven or Earth they love in comparison to him. He will cast up away for these where there seems no way.</p>
<p>I find my mind engaged, some hints to posterity, of some things which I believe opened to me in the true light, for things 
<pb n="016"/>
opened to square my life by much more than heretofore, and I felt the spring of pure gospel love to flow thro me, at times to my admiration, being a poor instrument, and led in a way very uncommon in this age, which has had a tendency to keep me down into a fellow feeling with the tribulated everywhere, my mind being enlarged in love to God, the brethren and my neighbors and fellow creatures throughout the world, and bowed in awful reverence! <del>And</del> Feeling that harmonizing sense that hath often attended my mind under a sense of which I believed we ought to attend to the direction of <del>of</del> our blessed Lord and lawgiver in the governing the inferior part of his creation that it might be done to his honor. Life, in all, is sweet, the taking of which has been for some time a tender point with me. These things were graciously given or rather lent to us to govern <del>under</del> in his fear. I refer my reader to God’s order and allowance in early times while all his works were in harmony and were pronounced very good.</p>
<p>Genesis 1:26. “God said let us make man in our image after our likeness; and let them have dominion over the fish of the sea and over the fowl of the air and over the cattle, and over all the Earth, and over every creeping thing that creepeth upon the Earth.”</p>
<p>29. <del>(Man’s food) </del>“God said, behold I have given you every herb bearing seed which is upon the face of <add>all</add> the Earth, and every tree in the which is the fruit of a tree yielding seed to you it shall be for meat.”</p>
<p>30. <del>(Creatures’ food) </del>“And to every beast of the Earth, and to every fowl of the air, and to everything that creepeth upon the Earth wherein there is life, I have given every green herb for meat, and it was so.”</p>
<p>God saw all he had made to be very good and we must 
<pb n="017"/>
suppose them in the order of their Creation, and the devouring nature not yet entered, but each partaking of their makers allowance, and harmonizing to his honor (like <add>the</add> days <del>yet to come</del> <add>spoken of by the prophet</add> wherein there was none to hurt or destroy in God’s Holy mountain)* <note type="authorial" place="margin">*Isaiah 65 and 25</note></p>
<p>I believe life was intended to be at the disposal of him who gave it, for the least insect has a sense of danger. Therefore, as we cannot give life, let us be cautious of taking it away, for notwithstanding the Enemy has been suffered to throw the world in confusion and out of the order of the creation so that <del>as early</del> <add>in</add> Gen 6 and 12 “God looked upon the earth and beheld it was corrupt: for all flesh had corrupted his way upon the Earth.” I have observed those who live nearest the truth are most of them tender in this point, and think those who refuse to take life or partake of animal food can hardly be thought offensive to God, and ought not to be judged of men.</p>
<p>In all my writings I wish to be cautious of dropping anything censorious, as I am led in a path much untrod in these latter days. I believed my dear Lord and Master was pleased to try my faith and fidelity to him by requiring for me to partake no longer of anything which had life, which was in the cross every way. My appetite seemed to crave flesh more than ever. I believe the enemy was suffered to try me as it were to a hairs breadth, for my chiefest friends stood aloof from me, and the wise of this world despised me. But blessed and magnified be God, he owned me and sweetened many bitter cup, standing by me in my deepest troubles and kept my head above the swelling waves when in the deeps by day and by night, in deep trouble unknown to mortal man so that I almost despaired of keeping my ground, <del>but thought flesh</del> yet at times enjoyed a quiet that no man was able to interrupt <del>even that</del> and partook of that living water that satisfies the panting thirsty soul. </p>
<pb n="018"/>
<p>But in times of weakness I was like poor Israel looking back as to the garlic and onions of Egypt where they eat flesh to the full. I had a hard fight of affliction both with my own nature and the opposition of them who would not admit <del>willingly</del> others going into things farther than they saw, and yet they must go so far. But I had a staff to lean upon superior to all the friendships of this world, even he who gave Israel the land of promise as they drove out the old inhabitants, which represents our first natures. They drove them out as we got victory over our first natures little by little. Religion is a gradual work and must be attended to day by day, for to depend today upon yesterday’s exercise will not do, no more than the manna which fed Israel in the wilderness, for it stank and bred worms on the morrow. So, trusting to former experience in religion resembles the stinking Manna. I believed it required of me to be cautious of taking life, or eating anything in the which life had been, which I did believe was the Lord’s requirings for causes best known to himself, and although evilly spoken of by many at times, as a lamb dumb before his shearer, for I had little to say. Sometimes not a word when bitter reflections have been cast on me plentifully, but endeavored to retire to the sure foundation stone through his gift within while those storms blew the very gates of Hell could not prevail, but the mind, being seasoned by the seasoning virtue of Truth, I could love them that loved not me, and wish well to those who reviled me. Those are hard sayings <del>to</del> but those who are taught in Christ’s school can bear them who feel his holy scepter to be swayed in their hearts, and can with their holy leader say in sincerity and Truth thy will not mine be done. I had often to look closely into my standing, for to leave father and mother and many experienced friends required great care in stepping along. But he who marched before Israel and was a light unto them is the same as ever he was, and never puts forth, but he goes before and prepares the way, and was never foiled in battle, though it may appear at times as though the sea was before, the Egyptian army behind, and towering mountains on each side: blessed be his name he can divide the waters and make a way when to us there seems no way, for all Nations before him are but as the small dust of the 
<pb n="019"/>
balance. Oh! That I may ever bow before him who has sweetened every bitter cup. Oh! That all would follow this safe leader through the wilderness of this world, then would he conduct them into the mansions of everlasting glory to join the saints and holy angels and the spirits of just men made perfect through suffering in praising and magnifying his holy name who liveth forever and ever.</p>

<p>I found I must not look out at others who perhaps might have nothing to do with this work and yet be in favor with God, and about their own business in their allotment. So we ought not judge one another while we are aiming to follow Christ, before whom we must all account for ourselves. Some may be called to one service and some to another and all in wisdom to the carrying on of the great cause of Truth on Earth. We ought not to set judge of another’s conscience but have love to God and one to another, which is the capstone of all, A new commandment I give unto you that you love one another, said our blessed Lord, by this shall all men know ye are my disciples, if ye have love one to another. God is love, and those who dwell in God must dwell <add>in love</add> saith the Apostle. I sometimes feel it flow from the inexhaustible fountain through me to the whole world, wishing all to harmonize in singing his praise who made all things good, <del>and</del> now maketh all good that is good, Whose pure influence I have longed for to cover the Earth as the waters do the seas. Oh! The sweetness that would be enjoyed, the hungry would be fed and the naked clothed, no hard thinking one against another, nothing would hurt or destroy. How different at this time when so many garments are soiled in blood, even the father and son against each other, and war sounds aloud, many houses great and fair left desolate, and many souls I fear hurried into eternity unprepared by those claiming the name of Christians, the expressive language <add>of whose conduct</add> is thieves and murderers whose consciences seem seared with a hot iron to take the life of men without remorse. These things I have seen with my eyes to my astonishment, and some of the expense of these cruelties born by men of peaceful minds by taxation, these taxes I could not pay though my goods were taken and sold for half value, for I saw those who would be the followers of humble Jesus must be willing to suffer, but all will be for good. Those who are sincere and upright in heart, these shall find rest where the 
<pb n="020"/>
troubles shall forever cease troubling and all Tears shall be wiped away (which I have Laboured and longed for when time to me here shall be no more) and therefore wish to be careful in disturbing the feeling of life in <del>all the</del> <del>every</del> any living Creature, and not judge my brethren for eating meat, which thro mercy I have been preserved from. 
I wish to leave some way marks for those who may be lead in the same way when I am removed<del> from</del>.</p>
</div>
<div type="year" n="1772">
<head>1772</head>
<p>In the year 1772, as I passed up and down (my business calling me much from home), I heard some complain for want of bread. This led me to consider why it was so. As our crops had not much failed, sure there must be waste somewhere and considered the best of our flour and corn went to the India’s, <del>and for rum etc.</del> and that in large quantities for rum etc. And those liquors were so plentifully used in gathering harvest, which is one of our choicest blessings, that it causes much waste, <del> and</del> rioting, and drunkenness insomuch that the cost of rum and the waste of grain which is occasioned I thought might feed <add>all</add> the poor. These considerations brought a great concern on my mind thinking of a remedy. An answer intelligible to my mind came thus, use no more rum, for it is a great evil in the country, and thou shalt have peace in so doing. But the custom was so deep rooted I could not see my way at first, as it was generally believed to be of great service in supporting men in the fatigue of hay and harvest. And I had been of the same mind, and used it liberally for that purpose. This appeared a threefold exercise to testify against my own conduct, withstand custom and endanger men’s health or lives, for I had heard of some dying instantly by drinking water for want of rum as was supposed. This was a great trial. I standing alone and must sacrifice my harvest, for I feared none would Reap for me without rum. It was practiced and commended as a support to nature, but my mind became resigned, come what might come, on me for that refusal I would use no more nor give it to my 
<pb n="021"/>
 neighbors. I had a larger harvest than was common for me and concluded if my neighbors refused to help me to gather what I could and let the rest go from whence it came believing the custom of rioting and drinking rum at such times to be an abomination in the land, I kept my exercise to myself, having none to confer with, for my friends were against me except my wife. She willingly helped and united with me a language, saluted my inward ear intelligibly on this wise, go offer Reapers the price of the common allowance of rum added to their wages, and inform them they must drink water or milk and water or the like, but have no strong drink of any kind, which I did. They made much ado. The thing was so strange, but all I asked engaged to try and as many as I needed came and seemed satisfied, for I gave them such reasons and laid the consequence of drinking before them and the much better use which they might make of the overplus money. And they saw I withheld not the rum thro covetousness. After this time I have been favored to make a full stand against rum, and have always had plenty of Laborers, though some discouraged, saying my grain ought to drop into the ground except I gave rum. Others reflected hard, and what made their reflections cut the mine they were such as ought to sympathize with me and might be compared to those who dipped in the dish with me. On my first entering my field in this way I went trembling, as my judgment of rum had been as others supposing it might hazard our lives to work in the heat without it, and if one of my hands should be sick or die it might be of sad consequence. <del>When I cam to the field</del> I took the first ridge in much fear <del>having <gap reason="deleted"/> reaped <gap reason="deleted"/> in my life without rum</del> and told them not to hurry on any account though a shower of rain should wet the grain. I provided a cup that held just half a pint and charged them to drink no more at once than that full of water. We went on moderately and completed our days work to all our satisfaction however it was much to mine I was clearly 
<pb n="022"/>
convinced rum was not that friend to men as I had supposed. Though many Goliath-like disdained my proceedings herein, I was convinced it was the Lord’s requirings, and that he would bless this testimony and carry it on, and blessed be his great name. I have since seen my opposers convinced and many advocates to this practice, some of whom make too free with strong drink themselves, which has been a grief to my mind such never will advance the cause.</p>
<p>These trials, though humbling to the will of the creature, brought self so down as of no repute among men, yet I evidently found my spirit more given up to serve God faithfully.</p>
<p>A clost trial of my Love and faith ensued in a few years after this, which nothing short of a full belief in was the requiring of my Lord and master, would induced me to have trod against so general custom (to wit shaving). This, I fully believed, was never drawn into custom by the dictates of Truth. A deep contemplation ensued on the pure order of the creation more excellent by far than all the contrivance of men. God made man upright but he has sought to himself many inventions. I believe shaving was one introduced by the author of all pride, changing the simplicity and uprightness that the all wise God formed him in, which was beyond doubt with his beard on, for causes known to himself the changing from which ought to be founded on better reasons than bare custom, which became a serious thing with me. Our Blessed Lord and his immediate followers wore their beards, no doubt at all with me, whose example I should think we might follow without being treated as offenders by any man or body of men. Must all bow to custom? Is there no better rule to go by? If so, we are wretched beings indeed. But blessed be God, he has left a better rule even the inward manifestation of his free grace or Holy Spirit, which he declared to Paul was sufficient, when he was sorely buffeted by Satan and his agents. This I have endeavored to attend to and obey for several years through good and evil report, and, in this matter I believed obedience was called for. Whoever it might offend, and great offence was taken by friends and some 
<pb n="023"/>
of the self-rrighteous amongst them throughout bitter reflections and spread false reports, yet a remnant sympathized with me and was convinced of the simplicity of the beard, though they saw not their way to forego custom in waxing their beard, and stood by me through many solid conferences. So that my adversaries could not have their desire against me, I found it safest to lay low and let the tempests beat, knowing the foundation of God standeth sure and could be a refuge to the soul while the strong will of man had power to afflict the body. Some fretted because they could not find sufficient occasion against me, yet when I had a concern to travel in Truth’s service, they raised objections on account of my singularity, and stopped my getting a certificate, but I thought the Lord took the will for the deed, as I was willing to go at his command, if I could, consistent with the order of society, and the objection was in relation to my beard, for they owned I was a useful minister amongst my home, friends, and neighbors, and if I would shave they would think well of my traveling in Truth’s service. But I thought it unsafe to transgress the Lord’s requiring to prepare to go on his errands, least I should provoke Him to leave me to the enemy, and I should bring a reproach on the Truth. For this cause I dare not shave, and if I must remain as a prisoner for conscience sake, the Lord’s will be done, for his yoke has become easy and his burthen light, and my head seemed bore up by the arm of his almighty power through all, and could magnify his name, for his ways became pleasant and his paths peace, and though a spirit unfit to judge in God’s cause as I believe hindered my going forth in God’s service, yet my case being known far and Near, insomuch that many sympathized with me in spirit that never saw me. Some of those came to see me and said I was agreeable to the sensation they had of me in their own houses, and it seemed like meeting an acquaintance, and I have believed, though I was hid as in the Cliff of the Rock, if I kept my place my service would not be lost. For those sufferings, I believe, has not been for naught, but it is the Lord’s will his work should go on, and blessed be 
<pb n="024"/>
his name. He has since brought the lofty from their seats. <del>And</del> I wish to write cautiously, for, though they might be too forward in judging another’s conscience, I preferred some of my opposers to myself, but think they had nothing to do in those singular testimonies, and wish them to <add>not</add> judge others who have, lest they be found fighters against God. We ought to keep love uppermost in all our labours, it being the capstone of all, and if we feel not this, what will our labors avail. This has preserved me in my deepest trials, finding this lesson <add>very</add> expedient, “bless them that curse you, pray for them who revile and persecute you,” and I wish feelingly to recommend it to all the tribulated everywhere of whatever name, among men of every nation and color, for we are all the workmanship of one almighty hand, and if we stand on allotments, we shall be employed all of us in his cause, and as we are faithful, love will harmonize us all together, for nothing was to hurt or destroy in God’s holy mountain.</p>
</div>
<div type="year" n="1791">
<head>1791</head>
<p>About this time, a law was made to raise money for defraying the expense of war by a duty on imported articles of almost all kinds. This was in lieu of a tax that I had refused to pay for conscience sake <add>thirty or forty years</add> because it contributed to the shedding blood, and I could see no <add>material</add> difference between paying by tax or duty. This came very close, although I had used very little, for several years, on account of corruptness of trade, and now being <del>added</del><add>added</add> this duty to bear the expense of war, all in my view being inconsistent with Truth which stands opposite to all wars and bloodshed and teacheth to do unto others as we would wish them to do unto us. As I said, I had not partook of much imported goods for some years, but apprehending salt could not well be refrained from, as I was much from home in Truth’s service and people generally used it in almost every kind of food, <del>which</del> <add>and</add> I <add>now</add> saw great difficulty in refraining the use of it now, which led me into the deeps for counsel and preservation and I thought rather than 
<pb n="025"/>
balk my testimony I would live on bread and water, for I believed my great master would not lead me on ground and not maintain it. And I made a full stand against all things on which these demands lay and my way has been made much easier than I looked for, blessed be God my savior. And it had a great tendency to renew my faith and confidence in him who had preserved me hitherto, even from <add>the will of</add> those who waited for my halting but through patient suffering. Truth has given victory insomuch that, in the general, people appear more loving to me than ever and bear coarse, plain doctrine from me much <del>easily</del> better than formerly, for such often presseth upon my spirit to deliver, though not <add>with</add> enticing words, and I can thankfully say I love the brethren and mankind universally, and God above all, <del>forever</del> praised and magnified be his great name for ever and ever amen, and amen saith my soul.</p>
</div>
<div type="year" n="1793">
<head>1793</head>
<p>I believe the vast extensive trade that has and now is carried on in this once favored land has and will prove a curse instead of a blessing. I believe better had it been for mankind if they had never attained the art of crossing the seas in ships. My mind is at this time deeply dipped and awfully and reverently bowed under a sense of the wretched state of things. The proud are called happy and the wicked are set up. Superfluities so abounds and are imported in abundance, and trade and dealing is run into, and shops set up in almost every hole and corner and the youth encouraged to eat the bread of idleness, and oppressing the poor by extortion.</p>
<p>Our land at this time appears to me as a boiling pot or troubled sea, for how abundantly doth fomenting contention abound.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="part" xml:id="dreams">
<div type="year" n="1754">
<pb n="026"/>
<head>1754</head>
<p>About this time I was in great bitterness of soul, which continued until I gave up to serve my Lord and Savior Christ Jesus. Fain would I given up my natural life, but my work was not finished. I now became willing by the power of God to become anything for peace of mind, which he accepted and said to my troubled mind peace be still. This, a time never to be forgot by me, in time I felt, as it were, new heavens and new Earth and all of God. The very thoughts of my heart was chained down, as it were, to the cross and the breathing of my mind reverently worshiped in abasedness of soul.</p>
</div>
<div type="year" n="1755">
<head>1755</head>
<p>About this time I had some remarkable dreams, and so, from time to time as the Lord was pleased to reveal or unveil <del>his mind</del><add><del>himself</del></add> to me, the substance of which I feel most easy to leave with my other writings for my children to look on when I am removed.</p>
<div><p>1st. I thought I was wandering in a dreadful wilderness, not knowing where to go, but all on a sudden was brought to a plank or pathway, one end on the Earth and the other on gradual assent up to heaven. On either side were people of all sorts and myself alone. To my inward sense or ear there seemed a voice saying walk in this way. It appeared as a shining light wherewith I was animated and not willing to be detained or turned to the right hand or left though strongly opposed by some, saying I should not go in that way but I pressed forward in much dread and fear, feeling my mind inwardly supported, and mended my pace until I ascended out of the reach of them all and awoke.
</p></div>
<pb n="027"/>
<div><p>2nd. I thought myself strayed from home and much entangled and perplexed with the things of this world and worldly cumbers, which yielded no real comfort. But trouble seemed to come from different quarters until (like poor confused Peter) I began to curse and to swear, but all of a sudden being stripped of all, I seemed in a terrible state of unutterable darkness as to the outward there was neither Sun, Moon or stars to be seen. No tongue can express the horror of my mind, believing it was the judgments of God for sin and I humbly implored God’s mercy, who was pleased to look down from his high and holy habitation, and wrought deliverance for <del>as</del> light began to appear and the Sun arose, to my great comfort and inexpressible joy <add>of soul,</add> for this my deliverance from dreadful darkness. I was brought then to a hill, glorious for situation as far as my eyes could see, and the light <add>of it</add> far exceeded the sun at noonday, for which deliverance and favor my soul did magnify God my Savor. And awoke.</p></div>
<div><p>3. I seemed walking alone in the common highway and, on a sudden, came to a deep valley with an high hill on either side. As I descended near the middle, it being some <add>considerable</add> distance across, I heard the sound of a hushing mighty wind and beheld with it a flood of great waters such as I never saw for terribleness. I was much alarmed, supposing I should be swallowed up of a sudden thereby. In my surprise I ran about in confusion and to no advantage, for the flood came with rapid force within a few rods of me and appeared as upright as a wall and as high as the tallest trees. The foaming resembled soapsuds and the roaring terrible. I found my own 
<pb n="028"/>
strivings availed nothing for there was no human probability of an escape. I sank into a perfect resignation to the divine will, trusting to God’s salvation, which was in an instant, for all vanished away and a serene calm instantly ensued and those floods disappeared. My soul melted like wax for this marvelous deliverance as translated into another world, and being led to a mountain on the other side of the valley which was all glorious, for situation laid in streets or lanes far and wide so far as my eyes could see and it was light as noon day. My soul magnified God who speaks but the word and it is so for my deliverance could come no other way.</p></div>
<div><p>4th. In a time sickness when I was thought near my end, I fell into a sweet sleep and in it thought myself in a barren, dreary land wherein nothing looked pleasant as I thought. But I was unwell, and desirous to go home, and, turning that way, I saw people I was well acquainted with who endeavored to detain me by presenting and calling attention to some worldly enjoyment, which at that time was painful to my mind, for my desire was to go home. And pressing forward in great weakness, being feeble and the way difficult, I had to pass through a narrow place where there was no turning to the right or left. In this place stood a grim looking fellow who said you shall not go this way, and, being weak, he shoved me down, but my desire being to get to my home, I got by him with less difficulty than I expected for he touched me no more. I pressed forward and got thro 
<pb n="029"/>
to my joy and saw a town near in which it was said the widows and fatherless the poor, the lame and the halt was the inhabitance thereof, and before I went home I must go and visit them. It was a little town, beautiful, for situation though the buildings, plain, simple, and low, built with logs suited to their circumstances. The ground was a beautiful green with paths from house to house. They all lived in sweet harmony and love without respect to circumstance, among which was an old man whose hair was white by age who looked much dejected. I passed up and down to my comfort feeling so great harmony as is not common. In my passing up and down I met the aforesaid Black man whose countenance yet appeared sorrowful. I asked the cause. He said he had a hard master. I offered to go see the man and try if nothing could be done to make him more easy, but on a sudden as I talked with him he appeared to be taken up to heaven out of my sight and I saw him no more and awoke.</p>

<p>N.B. I believed this Blackman was an intimation to my mind to take an ancient Black woman to my house who had been turned off in old age to shift for herself when near past her labor. She continued with me three or four years until her death and, though some thought her a great burden, to me it seemed light <del>to me</del> <add>for</add> for the peace of my mind so far outbalanced it, which I mention that others may be kind to the poor and look to heaven for pay.</p></div>
<div><pb n="030"/>
<p>5th I thought I was walking, seeking rest for my soul, but could find none. At length came to the door of a large room and was kindly invited to go in the place, being spoke well of as a place of rest, but when I took a view of the place I was much dissatisfied and turned to go out, but the door shut and I heard the bolt fly and the door lock, which was as great shock as I ever felt, for it appeared as a dark dungeon and horrible place. I advanced toward the door in horror and great surprise, supposing myself a prisoner. But all of a sudden as my mind was to God the door opened of its own accord and the person who shut me in was a Black boy. I trod him under my feet as small as dust and turned myself another way. Came by a building, whose walls seemed to reach to heaven and, as my mind became awfully bowed before God, a bright iron key twelve inches or more of an equal size every way and a keyhole sufficient for this, which I easily opened like a door to go in at. This seemed to comfort my drooping mind as it led into a well finished room, the boards seemed all of one peace without joints or superfluous work. Here I found the rest I sought, for here a stone house opened to my veins, wherein were many vessels placed in excellent order such as I had not seen before, not one interfering with another, all having (as I thought) a portion of the lever of the Kingdom in them. My orders were to give to everyone that asked, and so I did, and the principal stock was not lessened, though many came and received a little. I seemed here happy and awoke. I believed this to represent the ministerial office I was to engage in when delivered from the prison of sin. </p></div>

</div>
<div type="year" n="1788">
<pb n="031"/>
<head>1788</head>
<p>In the year 1788. I had another somewhat remarkable [dream]. I thought I was traveling in a barren wilderness in a narrow way just broad enough to walk in. I thought I saw as I went the appearance of more light as a clearing or opening, but having got through the wilderness, I came to the foot of an high mountain. Here was an increase of Light almost to the perfect day. I, being struck with wonder, and standing still, said, “Lord where am I,” and heard a voice saying “this is the Lord’s holy mountain, go forward,” but saw nobody from whence it came, but felt an unusual calm and so advanced. The Light increased until it far exceeded the brightest day, though it appeared not like sunshine but such as I cannot express for gloriousness. And when I came to the top, it still more bright and glorious, where stood such a house as I never saw before, for situation, excellency, and beauty, and a door to it to which I was invited. It <del>so</del> rang with songs of melody and praises but I saw nobody. My tongue is too short to set forth one half. Here was no need of the Sun, for it shone all over with one glorious brightness. I seemed every way happy but appeared not quite ready to join the heavenly host in songs of praise. After a short stay I heard a voice saying “thou must go out;” a very great alarm it was. And I cried, “Lord why may not I stay?” The answer was “thou must go out a short space and [hew] stones for this house.” This seemed to make it more easy, as it was but for a short space. And as the door was, I went out, and near the door lay a large stone which I thought would make a good corner if well hewed, and so I went to work on that first, and having hewed two sides and stooped down to turn it over, I awoke.</p>
<pb n="032"/>
<p>As the rough and stony hearted has been those to whom my share of the labor seemed much assigned, it has often been a comfort to me in the remembrance of this dream, and wish none to be discouraged but press through rough and smooth, for I have always found the Lord a rich rewarder in those rough, mortifying labours as faithfulness is abode in.</p>
<p>I believe I shall never enjoy such a place as I had a prospect in my dream unless I improve my time so as to finish my day’s work so as to be of the excepted of God and to have an interest where Christ is in the mansions of everlasting glory to join the angelic host in praising and Magnifying his holy name who lives for ever and ever.</p></div>
<div><p><del>These were to me more</del></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1790-06-30"><dateline><date when="1790-06-30">1790 30th of 6th Month.</date></dateline><p> I believe best to pen a dream I had last night, viz. I thought I was summoned to trial before God who appeared so just and true, there was no plea available before him, for I stood in open view before him and things mentioned and brought as plain to my view which was acted twenty or thirty years past, as if they had been done Yesterday, for things appeared so plain, my mouth was stopped and I had nothing to trust to but God’s mercy. For I heard from him who was above all saying “as the Sun on the dial varieth not, so thy trial is.” I again remembered his mercies, but saw there was no variableness nor shadow of turning with him and stood trembling to know the event, for a straight line I was to be tried by, which seemed to pierce my very soul, for as the shade turneth on the sundial so it went, and there was no avoiding divine justice. God’s mercy was all I had to depend on, but as I stood trembling and deeply affected I thought I saw the Sun just strike the line from end to end and awoke before my trial ended—But it deeply affected my mind the day following. Thought best to preserve the substance of it.</p></div>
<div>
<pb n="033"/>
<p>These were to me more than bare dreams, the sense of feeling accompanying them impressed my mind with awfulness, and as a foresight and support to my mind. In my deepest trials and baptisms, may I give God the praise as long as I live, for he is worthy who keepeth his little ones as under the hallows of his almighty hand, for nothing can harm those who live in his fear, and favor being God over all who ruleth the heavens and amongst men. Oh! That he may be pleased to turn and overturn until the hearts of the disobedient become subject to his will.</p></div>
</div>
<div type="part" xml:id="journal">
<pb n="034"/>

<head>Part Second</head>

<div><p>He for some Years past, having felt such an engagement to visit several parts of this Continent and resigning thereto, he believed it best to wholly disengage himself from the world and the encumbrances thereof, only reserving a comfortable living for himself and Wife, and dedicated himself to the benefit of his fellow mortals at large, and was almost daily engaged visiting the sick and afflicted when about home and not engaged at some neighboring meetings, in which service he was singularly useful, having knowledge of the medicinal virtue of many roots and plants, likewise into the nature of complaints, being ready to do what he could for the afflicted without fee or reward. He in the year 1793 began a particular diary of his exercises and travels which he continued to, near his close, which, being so lengthy, some of his friends thought the whole would not be best to expose to public view (which seemed to be his expectation), but said it felt most easy to him to keep it in the manner he did for the benefit of those who might travel in Truth’s service, likewise his children and near friends to peruse when he was removed, for which he desired I would transcribe the whole as I had done, a <add>considerable</add> part which he had examined and approved, and keep it by or near me, that any who desired might <del>peruse</del> <add>see</add> it.</p>

<p>And, apprehending it would be a loss to the public not to have some view of a life so fully devoted as a tried stone well squared for his great master’s use, I was willing to give up some time in extracting the substance into as little compass as I well could and cast it as on the waters hoping <del>to see</del> the benefit <del>after</del> would appear after many days.</p>

<note type="structure">This page may have been written by Evans’s son-in-law Abraham Warrington</note></div>

<div type="month"><pb n="035"/>
<head><supplied>March 1793</supplied></head>
<div type="entry" n="1793-03-18/1793-03-19"><dateline><date from="1793-03-18" to="1793-03-19">1793, 17 of 3rd Month, 18 and 19.</date></dateline><p> I had a prospect that rest where the troubler forever ceaseth troubling; love flowed to all men. Oh! That men would prize it beyond bags of gold. Had solid conversation with a couple lately married concerning the first and great choice. Too much freedom in conversation with an intimate friend. Oh! that our words may be few and tend to edification.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1793-03-20/1793-03-24"><dateline><date from="1793-03-20" to="1793-03-24">20th to 24th.</date></dateline><p> The Enemy came in as a flood through worldly objects. I labored for divine aid to cast them out of my mind, which was graciously afforded. Poverty of spirit, but got relief at our <del>meeting of ministers</del> select quarterly meeting. Some close hints were communicated respecting the advances of a worldly spirit and cautions against friends running with the multitude into extortion. I had some edifying conversation respecting feasting at these times, rich furniture, and gaudy apparel to some satisfaction, after which attended our quarterly meeting, rather dull and baptizing. <del>but</del> I had to look close into a future state in.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1793-03-25/1793-03-30"><dateline><date from="1793-03-25" to="1793-03-30">25th to 30th.</date></dateline><p> Had a feeling of that power which subdues naughtiness, but in the evening I was too light in conversation and laughed, which brought pain of mind when I lay down and looked over the day, which is my custom before I close my eyes for sleep. Oh! That ministers and elders may guard against everything which may hurt their service. Had edifying conversation with two young men who had taken a religious turn.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1793-03-30/1793-03-31"><dateline><date from="1793-03-30" to="1793-03-31">30 and 31st.</date></dateline><p> Labored with some contending about worldly interest which seemed well taken. And on first day largely opened on the necessity of a preparation for our final change, the meeting ended well.</p></div>
</div>
<div type="month">
 <head><supplied>April 1793</supplied></head>

<div type="entry" n="1793-04-01"><dateline><date when="1793-04-01">1 of 4th Month.</date></dateline><p> Met a committee to confer on a reformation who proposed visiting some of our extravagant youth which I feared would be to little purpose. I told them it was cutting the work too short, though need enough of that, but some 
<pb n="036"/>
stumbling blocks among the aged wanted me moving, such as fine <del>homes</del> moldings one about another, shining furniture, large glasses, rich and many colored hangings, fine carriages with well spaned horses etc. which exalted above the pure witness, and caused some to stand aloof lives like from those perhaps better than themselves</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1793-04-02/1793-04-08"><dateline><date from="1793-04-02" to="1793-04-08">2 to 8th of 4th Month.</date></dateline><p> Visited Evesham preparative and monthly meeting with <del>the</del> a committee appointed by the quarter to labor for a reformation in the use of spirituous liquors, and feared friends had not sufficiently got to the rest of the matter. I also had deep thoughts respecting my laborings in Truth’s service, being willing to spend and be spent if it is the Lord’s will and help is afforded, as I have some years past given up and almost left all to follow <del>the Lord’s</del><add>his</add> requirings.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1793-04-08/1793-04-09"><dateline><date from="1793-04-08" to="1793-04-09">8 and 9.</date></dateline><p> At Haddonfield and Woodbury monthly meetings, where Friends were concerned to labor against using of spirits in hay and harvest, but some plead for a substitute, but I did believe there was no need of wine, cider or any other liquor, having experience<del>d</del> of more than twenty years, and it is clearly my judgment if we keep our selfish views and convince laborers of our moderation in labor and readings to make satisfaction in wages, water will be sufficient.</p>

<p>I produced to Woodbury Monthly Meeting a minute from ours to visit the families of Friends <del>there</del> of that meeting. Several agreeable friends gave in their names to assist me in the labor.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1793-04-10"><dateline><date when="1793-04-10">10.</date></dateline><p> I have had several days favor but am now so reduced I feel no ability to proceed on our intended family visit. But (as Sampson) I cried to the Lord to strengthen me this once (for I could not see my way to flee). In this state we proceeded to some families and my good Master favored beyond my expectation to labour closely and not daub as with untempered mortar.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1793-04-11/1793-04-12"><dateline><date from="1793-04-11" to="1793-04-12">11 and 12.</date></dateline><p> The Lord renewed his bow in my hands to speak clost to a worldly spirit, and several appear much tendered <del>blessed be God</del>. </p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1793-04-13/1793-04-14"><pb n="037"/>
<dateline><date from="1793-04-13" to="1793-04-14">13 and 14.</date></dateline><p> The Lord favored to humble some who appeared as the Bulls of Bashon for stoutness, also to encourage some tender spirited ones.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1793-04-15/1793-04-16"><dateline><date from="1793-04-15" to="1793-04-16">15 and 16.</date></dateline><p> A lukewarm, likewise an over anxious spirit perplexed with the cares of this world was spoken to, which appeared well taken.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1793-04-17/1793-04-18"><dateline><date from="1793-04-17" to="1793-04-18">17 and 18.</date></dateline><p> I was enabled to speak clostly to a lukewarm state and indifference about attending meetings, <del>as</del> also a state more rich and proud which run into grandeur in meats, drinks, furniture and apparel etc. to the hindering of the growth of Truth.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1793-04-19/1793-04-20"><dateline><date from="1793-04-19" to="1793-04-20">19 and 20.</date></dateline><p> These two ends our visit and though I have had hard labour, yet I feel peace of mind, a sufficient reward, and believe we met with several sincere hearted Friends.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1793-04-21"><dateline><date when="1793-04-21">21.</date></dateline><p> Returned home thankful for the Lord’s mercy and goodness to me in enabling me to give up all to follow him at this time when so many wrong things is crept in among us. Hear heaven and be astonished, Oh Earth. How anxious are many, and how great the hurry and bustle to acquire worldly greatness many ways, in costly living and furniture and dressing in the world’s fashions, these excesses oppress the poor and I believe is a crying sin at this day and will make work for repentance sooner or later. Oh! That it may be in time. For oh! parents, how will you stand when inquision is made for the children who have prepared <add>for</add> your children a dress very inconsistent with the pure Truth as soon as they are born, and are bringing them up in fine silk or flowered stuff, formed to please the eye, and too much in their own unsubjected will, counting this and the other little things, having a pleasure in seeing them fitted for high company, and fond of rich matches in marriage. And when high company comes, the silver and chinaware is brought from your fine corner cupboards <add>with moldings one above another,</add> and feasting four times a day not only with your baked and roasted meats, but stretch far beyond the produce of our plentiful country. And curious 
<pb n="038"/>
 painted rooms with fine bedspreads and hangings, clock cases, looking glasses, carriages etc. etc. all calculated to please the vain mind, the expense of which and the idle way of bringing up children afflicts the poor, makes murmuring wives, cross husbands, hard dealing, untimely or failure in paying debts, which has caused many to leave their families and quit the parts. Yet when children run to a shameful excess, <del> and</del> then parents complain and say “my son and my daughter is so ungovernable they will not be ruled.” Oh! Where will parents and children appear who have so balked <del>their</del> the testimony of Truth when many are called from the east, west, north, and south to sit down with Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob? Will not your own hearts condemn you? I am a lover of mankind universally, and hope may be excused in being somewhat particular. The prophets and apostles were so, and it has been the concern of some to sound an alarm down to this very day. And I trust ever will be read Isaiah 3rd 16 “Moreover the Lord saith, because the daughters of Zion “are haughty and walk with stretched forth necks and wanton eyes.” Turn to it and read the whole passage <del>and mark</del> the judgments which were to follow, <del>the extremity of sorrow was so great that </del><add>the Text saith</add><del> “seven Women [perhaps those effeminate timepleasers] should take hold of one Man, saying ‘we will eat our own bread and wear our own apparel, only let us be called by thy name, to take away our reproach.’”</del></p>

<p>Like causes may produce like effects. Let us weep and mourn lest our land become a desolation.</p></div>

<div><p>I was confined at home for some time through the indisposition of my son’s wife.</p></div>
</div>
<div type="month">
<head><supplied>May 1793</supplied></head>
 
<div type="entry" n="1793-05-04"><dateline><date when="1793-05-04">5th Month 4th.</date></dateline><p> This is a trying day with me. My son’s wife departed this life. Though somewhat comforted by her quiet frame of mind, having no doubt but she has gone to Christ.</p></div>
 </div>
<div>
<pb n="039"/>
<p>1793 5 Month 5th. From this time until the 4th Month 1794 <del>he</del><add>it</add> appears by his diary he was almost daily engaged in visiting the sick and distress, excessive drinkers, those who made too much show in the world, likewise frequently at neighboring meetings and engaged in visiting families.</p>
<p>In the course of <del>these</del><add>his</add> visits to the sick, he often laments the common use of opium or laudanum, and thought the giving [of] this to people near their end deprived them of their reason in a time when <del>their reason was</del> most needed, even when they were near entering into <add>long and</add> endless eternity, and <del>thought</del> the doctors committed a great evil in giving this medicine at such time.</p>
<p>His life seems to have been a life of mourning on account of the many deviations from our ancient principles, in copying after the world, and <del>swayed by</del> being swayed <del>and</del> by custom, and drawn into the use of many things very inconsistent with our profession. And frequently mentions away things very particularly, not only in dress and furniture of houses but the courtliness of living, and the use of many needless foreign articles such as tea, coffee, rum, tobacco, fine silk, lawns and muslins etc. etc., which has a tendency of raising the mind above the Truth, and the testimony of many worthy Christians in early times <del>who</del> whose hands ministered to their necessities, and yet had much time to labour for the good of souls.</p>
<p>His austere or exemplary life, many ways, and constant <del>mortifications</del> undaunted labors for many years seemed so to open his way in the hearts of the people at large, and his friends in particular, that he found it his duty to disengage himself from every encumbrance of life and wholly and industriously to dedicate the remainder of his life in doing good. In the course of which he found an open door among all societies, even such as appeared of the nature of lions, yet all seemed at peace with him and willing to hear counsel from him, however course and cutting as he seemed, much-led to beat against those things <del>men</del><add>people</add> most delight in. He was frequently engaged in visiting the societies, to good satisfaction to the visited and peace of his own mind.
<pb n="040"/>
And, although his way seemed so opened that he could freely speak his mind in all places where his lot was cast without fear of giving offence, and those who he complained of some years back <del>who</del><add>for</add> treated him roughly now, appeared in peace with him and was some of them very helpful to him at this time, and heartily concerned with him in his labours, and freely give him certificates to travel wherever he believed his great Master called him to labor.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, he complains frequently of great Poverty of spirit and bitterness of soul, as one entirely deserted of every feeling of good, yet on the trusted scrutiny of his conduct finds no misses except talking, at time, too freely about things which did not lend to edification and laughing. And pressing by cautions Ministers and Elders, particularly against making Worldly matters the subject of conversation.
</p></div>
 </div>
 </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
