<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader></teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="01" facs="sc204156"/>
<div type="narrative"><p>I have some weeks past neglected to continue my diary and concluded to drop it thinking maybe I had done enough if not too much at it but upon trial feel not quite easy. Remember what first put me upon it was <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn's</persName> advice to his children, which was to keep an account of every day, although a day required but a line; he said many advantages flowed from it, and further he advised them to keep a commonplace book and when they read the scriptures or any religious book if they met with passages that feelingly or livingly impressed their minds to make a note of it for he says these openings and impressions come not in the will of man no more than the Scriptures did to the inspired penmen and he says they may be lost through carelessness or overgrowing cares of the world. I believe it has been something like putting wood upon the altar to keep the fire burning as we read in Scripture for Solomon says where no vision is the people perish<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 29:18</note> so I begin again</p>
 </div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-04-27"><head>April 1823</head><dateline><date when="1823-04-27">27 of the Fourth Month, 1823.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting and I thought there was some evidence of the ownings of truth to my comfort and satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-04-29"><dateline><date when="1823-04-29">29.</date></dateline><p> George Hatton from Indiana (700 miles they say westward) appointed a meeting at our meeting house and he did preach I think more than one hour. He is an amiable able minister but in the midst of all our ministerial labors a spirit of ease settled on the less which he mentioned on the lap of this world seems hard to reach and although they seemed to be attentive many were dull and heavy and it seemed like music to a sleepy man and but little animation: we read that 3000 were converted to the Christian faith at Peter's first sermon and it is said as many as made up 5000 at the next sermon: and that in <persName key="w6912v76">George Fox's</persName> day many were convinced at one meeting but it would be a rare thing to hear of one or two being reached or tendered to tears as was frequent in them days when they say at some meetings there was few dry eyes but now it is a great rarity to see a tear: but them they say tears were frequently seen to run down their cheeks and they often tremble as they sat in their meetings and so they in scorn and derision gave them the name of Quakers and at some meetings the floor looked as if there had been a sprinkling of rain with their tears a broken heart and a contrite spirit the Lord will not despise but has promised to dwell with the humbled contrite that tremble at his word but alas how far is our state from such a state of humility and contrition as <persName key="w6cg1kgr">John Churchman</persName> says oh how is the ancient plainness and simplicity of truth departed and pomp and splendid appearances taken their places.</p>
<pb n="02" facs="sc204157"/>
<p>This George Hatton appears to be the great grandson of James Hatton a great and worthy minister of whom there is an excellent account in the Memorials in England page 195 his mother was a most beautiful great minister visited America I remember her words in her young days with Mary Peasly she married Thomas Lightfoot and came from Ireland and settled with her husband here in Pennsylvania her son Robert – father to this George - used to live here in this neighborhood and took to drinking to excess in his young days but was favored to make a stand against it and take up the cross and became an acceptable minister: this his son George now with us it seems moved to the western country and now his place of abode is at the place called Indiana from there we had three very great ministers very lately Daniel Pucket, Priscilla Hunt and now this George Hatton and now they have a yearly meeting there were but a few years ago it was a wilderness inhabited by the Indians, buffalo, deers, panthers, wolves, bears, etc., surely we must say with the Egyptians the finger of God is in it<note resp="transcr">Exodus 8:19</note> In looking at this George Hatton's father when he was a poor drunken creature it has seemed to look to me it was through the prevalence of the fervent prayers of his worthy mother he was restored and preserved and this George makes me think of Paul's words to Timothy concerning the faith which he says dwelt in thy grandmother Lowis and in thy mother Eunice and I trust in thee also<note resp="transcr">2 Timothy 1:5</note> so we read in scripture that the fervent prayers of the righteous availeth much with the Lord<note resp="transcr">James 5:16</note>:</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-05-04"><head>May 1823</head><dateline><date when="1823-05-04">4 of the Fifth Month, 1823.</date></dateline><p> First Day. I went to our meeting although hardly well enough to go. Something opened to my view which made such an impression that I did not lose sight of when I got home although I kept it to myself being very poorly and one and another and another stepped in: It is said in Scripture blessed are they that hunger and thirst after righteousness they shall be filled<note resp="transcr">Matthew 5:6</note>: is there any thing of an earthly nature that can fill the desire or satisfy them that hunger and thirst after righteousness. David indeed says in thy presence is fullness of joy<note resp="transcr">Psalm 16:11</note>: But some say none but Christ can satisfy desire it is said as we read of them in Scripture in early days they all eat of that same spiritual meat and they all drank of that same spiritual rock and that rock was Christ<note resp="transcr">1 Corinthians 10:3-4</note>: who said
<pb n="03" facs="sc204158"/>
man shall not live by bread alone but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God.<note resp="transcr">Luke 4:4</note> who said my flesh is meat indeed and my blood is drink indeed except you eat the flesh and drink the blood of the son of Man ye have no life in you<note resp="transcr">John 6:53-55</note>: I am the true bread, etc<note resp="transcr">John 6:32</note>: Again labor not for the bread that perisheth but for that which nourisheth the soul up unto eternal life: If they are in a blessed state that hunger and thirst after righteousness what must be the state of those be who are hungering and thirsting after wickedness: Like some we read of drinking up inequity as the ox drinketh in water<note resp="transcr">Job 15:16</note> that say depart from us we desire not the knowledge of thy ways<note resp="transcr">Job 21:14</note> who do not like to retain God in their knowledge as it was said of Israel they would have none of me<note resp="transcr">Psalm 81:11</note>: they have forsaken me the fountain of living waters and Hewn to themselves cisterns broken cisterns that can hold no water<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 2:13</note>: That loved darkness rather than light because their deeds were evil<note resp="transcr">John 3:19</note>: who add drunkenness to thirst<note resp="transcr">Deuteronomy 29:19</note>: seeing the precious fruits and effects of righteous and the unspeakable advantages of a righteous life and on the other hand the unspeakable loss and disadvantages of the wicked not only through time but at the end of time it is matter of wonder that all the world do no hunger and thirst after righteousness like the servants of the Lord we read of who said my soul is a thirst for God as the hart panteth after the water brook so doth my soul after thee oh Lord<note resp="transcr">Psalm 42:1</note>: again see the desires the hunger and thirst after righteousness – one thing gave I desired and that will I seek after that I might dwell in the house of the Lord where I might behold his glory and enquire in his temple<note resp="transcr">Psalm 27:4</note>: again see the desire the hunger O that I knew where I might find him I would come even to his seat I would – order my cause before him and fill my mouth with arguments<note resp="transcr">Job 23:3-4</note></p>
<p>See Deuteronomy 33:23: O Naphtali satisfied with favor and full with the blessings of the Lord: But can all this world can give satisfy them that are truly hungering and thirsting after righteousness even if they had Solomon's possessions. See Proverbs 30:15: there are three things that are never satisfied and see Ecclesiastes 1:8: the eye is not satisfied with seeing nor the ear with hearing neither is his eyes satisfied with – riches for they that desire silver shall not be satisfied with silver: see Jeremiah 31:34: my people shall be satisfied with goodness.</p>
<p>Psalms 145:16: And thou satisfieth the desire of everything: is it not so that Christ only can satisfy desire and direful are the consequence of desires misplaced.</p>
<pb n="04" facs="sc204159"/>
<p>Direful indeed are the consequences of desires misplaced is it not the very cause why the world lies in wickedness for in Scripture we read that blessed are they whose minds are stayed on the Lord for they shall be kept in perfect peace.<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 26:3</note> but the Divine Master said they that love the world the love of the Father is not in them<note resp="transcr">1 John 2:15</note> and he that loveth anything more than me is not worthy of me<note resp="transcr">Matthew 10:37</note> The friendship of the world and a carnal mind is enmity with God.<note resp="transcr">Romans 8:7</note> Hence the great necessity of attention to that Scripture injunction set your affections on things above and not on things below.<note resp="transcr">Colossians 3:2</note> Blessed are they that hunger and thirst after righteousness like the prophet who said let my right hand forget her cunning and my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth if I prefer not Jerusalem to my chiefest joy.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 137:5-6</note> and like Paul who says neither heights nor depths or anything should ever be able to separate him from the love of the Lord<note resp="transcr">Romans 8:39</note> as our worthy progenitors counted nothing even life itself too dear to part with for truth's sake – but John Staupits one of the first reformers says they that prefer the creatures or anything before the Creator robs God of his highest Honor and makes that his God which he prefers: If anyone should say his temporal goods were his god he would be condemned as an heretic but how doth the daily scramble after earthly treasures demonstrate what people prefer and where their hearts is set: To them like the faithful in all ages who have preferred the truth to their chiefest joy (as James Naylor says) to those who have no other lovers whom they prefer the Lord gives himself: and with him we are rich take what he will away without him we are poor with all this world can give so that amongst all his innumerable blessings himself is the crown and all in all: If they who set their hearts on things of this world and prefer temporal treasures to God and his love rob God of his highest honor how most miserably do they rob do themselves rob themselves of the most durable riches like Achan and Gehazi<note resp="transcr">2 Kings 1:20-27</note> who coveted the golden wedding and the Babylonish garment<note resp="transcr">Joshua 7:21</note> and like Balaam who loved the wages of unrighteousness<note resp="transcr">2 Peter 2:15</note> and like Demas who preferred this present world<note resp="transcr">2 Timothy 4:10</note> or like Judas that sold his master for 30 pieces of silver<note resp="transcr">Matthew 26:15</note> and like Esau who sold his birthright for a mess of potage and then sought it with tears too late<note resp="transcr">Genesis 25:34</note> so we may see what a most miserable bargain all these had of it who set their affections on things below and have not made a wise choice like Moses who preferred affliction with the people of God than to enjoy the pleasures of sin for a season<note resp="transcr">Hebrews 11:24-25</note></p></div>
<pb n="05" facs="sc204160"/>
<div type="entry" n="1823-05-08"><dateline><date when="1823-05-08">8 of the Fifth Month, 1823.</date></dateline><p> At our Monthly Meeting. William Foster from England was there and <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName>. William preached about one hour but there seemed very little animation his voice and delivery not very clear and lively like some but it was thought his doctrine was sound searching and very pertinent. William Evans of Philadelphia also appeared pretty lively but at last <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> stood up and he did rouse up and make all shake he confirmed the prospect respecting I had of the great want of animation and life.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-05-11"><dateline><date when="1823-05-11">11 of the Fifth Month.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting open, owning, and satisfactory to me in a good degree on mature deliberation and examination.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-05-12"><dateline><date when="1823-05-12">Second Day Morning^</date></dateline><p> read George Withy's <emph rend="italic">Farewell</emph> excellent address and an excellent London Epistle of 1807 both confirmed me of the opinion I have had of the lamentable neglect of the neglect in that of training up children in the way they should go. The laws that I command thee this day thou shalt teach them diligently to thy children<note resp="transcr">Deuteronomy 6:7</note> but how lamentably do the children many suffer for want of a parental care a more guarded religious education like the shepherds of Israel was complained of they had not sought out that which was lost nor healed the sick nor brought back that which was driven away<note resp="transcr">Ezekiel 34:4</note>: But like the man who made this excuse whilst thy servant was busy hither and thither the man escaped<note resp="transcr">1 Kings 20:40</note> and like the young man John the Divine tells of made his escape and got amongst robbers so our young people are gone into a spirit of Libertinism and are robbing of God and themselves of heavenly treasures the most durable riches manifestly denying Christ and their profession before man so that George Withy says by their dress and appearance he could not except they belonged to our society so this libertine spirit leads to outgoing in marriage which increased our Monthly Meeting business last month but alas how poor dry weak and formal without a timely care to preserve prevent and restore and reclaim I dropped some hints on the subject: But as that worthy elder John Rutty says why so much complaint of bad children and bad servants when there is so little care to make them: Better nay so far from that it is to be feared that many parents are more to blame for their children's extravagancy and liberty than the children themselves and a danger of their hands being stained with the blood of their children. How poor weak dry and formal must our discipline be where there is no care to preserve prevent restore and reclaim which is for the better part of our discipline as <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says they have a right to censure who have an heart to help: and what is all our zeal for discipline good for without this heart to help which would certainly lead to a timely care to preserve restore and reclaim and which would strengthen our hands and give us authority to censure.</p></div>
<pb n="06" facs="sc204161"/>
<div type="entry" n="1823-05-15"><dateline><date when="1823-05-15">15 of the Fifth Month.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting very small. Solomon says the diligent hand maketh rich<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 10:4</note> but slothfulness casteth into a deep sleep and the idle soul shall suffer<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 19:15</note> – Hunger oh the idleness not temporal but spiritual idleness what will be the end of it will not our poverty come as one that traveleth and our want as an armed man<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 6:11</note> has not this been the sorrowful case with thousand and will not like cases produce like effects yet I thought we were not quite destitute of some tokens of a right spirit and savor of life.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-05-18"><dateline><date when="1823-05-18">18.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Our son John being in a poor state of health we went to Evesham and was at their meeting. Ann Quicksil a maiden of a poor, low family did preach most beautifully and after her I had as open owning a time as I almost ever had there to good satisfaction oh that we could so walk as to have our mercies and blessing continued oh that thou would oft bless me indeed and enlarge my coasts said Jabez.<note resp="transcr">1 Chronicles 4:10</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-05-22"><dateline><date when="1823-05-22">22.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting very small and that not the worst of it very dry and formal yet I thought not quite left some life and satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-05-25"><dateline><date when="1823-05-25">25.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting I was unwell over wearied yesterday I was hardly able to sit meeting yet was favored to come off pretty well I hope yet was led to see (soon after) what a poor frail creature I am and the need there is of continual watchfulness and prayer for preservation like Jabez of old. Oh, that thine hand might be with me and keep me from evil that it may not grieve me.<note resp="transcr">1 Chronicles 4:10</note> Last week at Fifth Day meeting and select on Sixth Day nothing material unless it was poverty and leanness although not quite destitute of life but oh how little of that to what we might experience – if we were not wanting on our part. Low mortifying times.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-06-04"><head>June 1823</head><dateline><date when="1823-06-04">4 of the Sixth Month, 1823.</date></dateline><p> On Fourth Day. Thomas Wetherill a few years from England a young man with a young family has lately lived at Trenton but lives now at Washington in Virginia has appeared but a few year in the ministry appointed a meeting at our meeting House and was very large in testimony and very pointed, pertinent, savory and acceptable amongst the very foremost but alas what fruit have ye of all this talk about religion.</p>
<pb n="07" facs="sc204162"/>
<p>I observe in reading the journals of our Friends who traveled much in the work of the ministry how they lament the want of fruit and how deeply discouraging it was to see so little fruits of their abundant labor and do we not read that Paul expressed a fear least he had bestowed labors on some in vain<note resp="transcr">Galatians 4:11</note> and what become of the people that Noah had to preach to and what become of the people Moses had to labor with and the people Christ had to deal with after all the great works and mighty miracles doth it not evidently appear that people may tend meetings in such a way all the days of their lives to little or no purpose nay as Barclay says they may tend meetings in such a way as to suffer condemnation for it: and as some have observed they may die under a living gospel ministry whilst their affections are set on things below and are contenting themselves with a name with the form without the life: But to think of the many of latter time who have visited us great and powerful ministers I suppose there are great nations filled with millions of people Papists and Mehommitans [Muslims], barbarians, heathens and savages that are not favored with such living powerful ministers as we are and have been where are the people in like degree favored like we are.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-06-05"><dateline><date when="1823-06-05">5^</date></dateline><p> was our Monthly Meeting and I believe there was some stirrings of life amongst us Nathan Smith was there and he with divers others had a lively testimony he seems to be of late just got up under sail again after being much down under the weather several years the meeting was a sweetened one to me I have a little book called <emph rend="italic">Solitude Sweetened</emph> [James Meikle] and through unmerited mercy we have some times meetings sweetened all seemed open and free sweet and pleasant at last a precious cement.</p>
<p>This afternoon at 4 o'clock we went to the burial of Charles Roberts a stout healthy young man about 25 who died with the typhus fever with about ten or twelve days illness was much out of his senses part of the time but came to have his senses at last and was very penitent and said he was willing to die and there seemed room to hope although he had given way to folly in dress but was observed to grow more sober and steady of late. I was so weary with the long Monthly Meeting I could hardly keep up. The people behaved orderly but oh the poverty amongst professing Christians: But how ministers but all shut up.</p>
<pb n="08" facs="sc204163"/>
<p>Some further thoughts concerning the burial yesterday. I do believe if there had been one half the care, concern and labor to provide for and seek after the cultivation of the inward man as there appeared as there appeared in the equipage of gilded painted curious costly carriages it seems as if there had been no cost or pains spared for the comfortable accommodations and conveniences in which accommodation and conveniences and accommodations and the greater part are entangled and bemired says <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName>, To call to a people in such a state of fullness and prosperity to seek the Lord whilst he may be found to feel after him if happily they might find him would I fear have little place with them for as Stephen Crisp says, if they in this state of friendship of this world which is enmity with God meet with that which would lead them in the ways of holiness they cannot receive it their hearts like the in of old being filled with other guest: so it is no wonder we are so very poor and destitute of savor of life and owning of truth at our burials I happened to take up <persName key="w6t72g07">John Woolman's</persName> <emph rend="italic">Word of Caution to the Rich</emph> – see page 33: To labor for an establishment in divine love where the mind is disentangled from the power of darkness is the great business of man's life: the collecting of riches covering the body with fine wrought costly apparel and may I not add and having fine houses magnificent furniture and such exceeding new invented, fine, costly, painted carriages and gilded horses operate Woolman says against universal love, and tend to feed self so that it belongs not to the children of the light to desire these things – page 34: Our hearts being thus opened and enlarged we feel content in a use of things as foreign to luxury and grandeur as that which our redeemer said down as a pattern: Humility goes before honor but pride goes before destruction and a haughty spirit before a fall<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 16:18</note> so we read and was is or can be expected: again see Woolman's words, page 43: A day of outward distress is coming and divine love call to prepare against it; page 54: Christ's example in all its parts being a pattern of wisdom the plainness and simplicity of his outward appearance may well make us ashamed to adorn our bodies with costly array or treasuries wealth by the least oppression.</p>
<pb n="09" facs="sc204164"/>
<p>There is just now an alarming account in the news of a great grand horserace at New York and it is said many thousands of dollars staked between the southern and eastern states it is not long since there was an account in the news of a great parade and great and wonderful doings in Philadelphia over a fat ox. I think such daring dismal wickedness dared not to put up its head some years ago. I think they who are favored to see the right way must see the folly and vanity darkness and ignorance of the people who can take pleasure in such daring audacious wickedness as that and distilling spirits out of grain what can be expected but it will bring down judgments upon the land as in days of old – how hardened blind deaf and stupid we are we don't consider and we will not see – the news gives account of the Hessian fly making great havoc amongst the wheat now in some parts southward – a day of outward distress is coming and divine love call to prepare against it say <persName key="w6t72g07">John Woolman</persName>, 28. It is said the fly is making great destruction amongst the wheat in Jersey and Pennsylvania.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-06-12"><dateline><date when="1823-06-12">12 of the Sixth Month, 1823.</date></dateline><p> We all went to quarterly meeting at Evesham which was very large and highly favored with a living pertinent powerful ministry first <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> then Elizabeth Barton and <persName key="w6ht6kfw">Sarah Cresson</persName> how we are favored with a living ministry beyond many great dark nations who are filled with millions of people groaning under gross darkness ignorance idolatry and superstition and how we an ungrateful backsliding people are waited on and followed and there was something lively and savory in the meeting for discipline I was preserved so as to come off with sweet satisfaction which count a great favor and mercy for we cannot preserve ourselves.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-06-15"><dateline><date when="1823-06-15">15.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting but I was so poorly I was hardly able to sit meeting out weather very warm.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-06-19"><dateline><date when="1823-06-19">19.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. A little better I got to meeting weather very warm forepart for a while I was tried with dullness but it seemed to go off like a cloud I was favored and enabled to sit and stand the meeting out to good satisfaction: But I am jealous and often think we had need to well examine this satisfaction or peace to see whether it is of the right sort for it is to be feared thousands are content with a false peace that is not permanent I was quite tired at last.</p></div>
<pb n="10" facs="sc204165"/>
<div type="entry" n="1823-06-22"><dateline><date when="1823-06-22">22.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Rainy eastwardly storm and I unwell dizziness in my head I did not get out to meeting. It has become very dry weather; no rain this several weeks although it has looked very like for rain many times it has gone off. Heavy black clouds appeared and looked like heavy thundershowers but without any thunder or lightning and all go over and vanish away without any rain it has been the case several years past I think I never seen the like in my young days: this great appearance for rain and going off so much makes me think of the pretences we are making to religion and how little of real vital religion there is among us, how little there is now in our meetings of the company of the teachings of the spirit of truth that leads into all truth and yet we go and come from our meeting as if we got what we went for even that peace the world cannot give nor take away which is the great end of all peoples meeting together to perform worship and is it not to be feared thousands are contenting themselves with a sort of peace that will not make a death bed pleasant as the true peace will: acquaint now thyself with him and be at peace again<note resp="transcr">Job 22:21</note> oh that thou hadst hearkened to my commandment then had this peace been as a river and thy righteousness as the waves of the sea<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 48:18</note> If we compare our religion with the religion of the faithful martyrs and our worthy progenitors shall we not perceive a great decay of zeal.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-06-26"><dateline><date when="1823-06-26">26.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. <persName key="w6wx87x7">My wife</persName>, daughter Abigail and I went to Haddonfield meeting which was small especially on the men's side. I believe there are yet a little remnant of the honest hearted but many very idle sit down at ease which makes hard work for the rightly concerned. I was fatigued getting there and hardly able to sit meeting yet soon after I sat down felt better and through mercy it was a favored open owning time as I ever remember. There was pleasantness sweetness feeling nearness and much inviting shew of kindness at last but I was so weary and poorly, colic, sick stomach and dizziness in my head that it was it was with difficulty I got home: we went with an intent to go to see Esther Laning an ancient afflicted widow who had sent for us but we were told she was just then at the point of death. She has seen much trouble been blind near twenty years and suffered much with a cancer
<pb n="11" facs="sc204166"/>
and great trouble with several of her children but there is some room to hope she has suffered her last that her suffering are over forever.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-06-29"><dateline><date when="1823-06-29">29 of the Sixth Month, 1823.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. I was so unwell I did not go to meeting but my mind went with them. Here are some thoughts or something of the subject that occupied my mind whilst our family were gone – we read of one who inquired what shall we render unto the Lord for all His benefits towards us,<note resp="transcr">Psalm 116:12</note>: It would be right no doubt for us to try to number our blessings although they are past numbering yet would it not be great ingratitude to never think of them like the brutal part of the creation who eat the fruit under the tree and never look up from where it comes and how many blessings and benefits are we favored with which are scarcely ever thought of or considered as favors. Some years ago it was said there was not a nation known to us but what were at war and all at once peace was made so that peace prevailed over all nations: when I consider the inflammatory spirit of war and how many goodly youth were dragged out into the army and died in the wars by hardships and sickness and how many goodly people catched the inflammatory spirit of war and how they were inflamed with it I fear too few consider the blessings and benefit of peace and well would it be if humility and gratitude had been rendered as it ought to have been but if my observation have been right there never was a greater growth in a spirit of libertinism than there has been since the commencement of peace especially in the equipage in costly carriages. At the conclusion of peace this was the language of some now we will go on as we used to do now we will do as we please, etc. But we read of a war in which there is no discharge: there is no discharge in that war: and it is said a Christian life is a continual warfare Paul says I have fought the good fight I have kept the faith<note resp="transcr">2 Timothy 4:7</note> etc., and it is said he that conquers himself conquers his greatest enemy and that a man's worst enemies are them of his own house: But what I have chiefly in view at this time is to make some remarks concerning an army which has invaded us some years past and now this season appear in an extensive manner over our country. Virginia, Pennsylvania and Jersey an army which we cannot make war with no other way than by subduing, mortifying and humbling ourselves: an army a little like that we read of in the prophet Joel the locust, the caterpillar and the canker worm. My great army which I sent among you.<note resp="transcr">Joel 2:25</note> That which the locust hath left the caterpillar hath eaten that which the caterpillar hath left the cankerworm hath eaten I mean the insect messenger which our friends call it in one of their epistles the Hessian fly which is now destroying the wheat in our alarming manner.
<pb n="12" facs="sc204167"/>
Do we not read of four sore judgments: the sword, the pestilence, the famine and the noisome beast.<note resp="transcr">Ezekiel 14:21</note> and have we not had a taste of all of them although as yet but in a very small degree to what some neighboring nations of latter times have felt – the cry for bread in Ireland in England and in Germany has been very great and grievous but as <persName key="w6t72g07">John Woolman</persName> observes the judgments of the Lord have not yet extended to the degree of famine in North America – but we may observe there have been threatening signs and tokens of cleanness of teeth and scarcity of bread season after season by various means and causes have the fruits of the field and labors of the husbandman been laid waste by divers kinds of insect and by frost and by hail by blasting and mildew: and drought and sometimes by too much wet weather as an old man once told me: they thought the staff of bread would have been cut off by the abundance of wet even after the grain had been reaped and shocked in the field: this was when I was but very young and yet hath the Lord in mercy continued to feed and shower down of his benefits and blessing on North America. John Hall an acceptable European minister once told us at Cropwell that if the crops should fail but one season in America it would cause as a great cry for want of bread to pass through the land as there was then in his native land and they say in one of their epistles the poor would long feel the pinch of that time of scarcity: but in Ireland and Germany it was said many died for want of bread although thousand and tens of thousands of pounds were raised and sent for their relief. I have heard <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> mention what he had seen of the effects of famine in Germany: he said he did not believe that they who had never felt anything of it could hardly be made to believe what a piercing calamity it was. And also <persName key="w6427nc6">William Savery</persName> who also traveled in Germany and several other old countries I believe that almost always where people have lived in fullness prosperity and plenty they have ever been prone to forgetfulness ingratitude, luxury, and pride until they have many times brought down sore and heavy judgments upon them sword pestilence famine pestilence storms of hail and terrible earthquakes which have suddenly swept them away by thousands in heaps like dung; yea, as William Edmundson says lashed them with his judgments and dunged the ground with the carcasses of men and there has been a great coming down like them we read of whom it was said she came down wonderfully her filthiness is in her skirts she remembereth not her latter end<note resp="transcr">Lamentations 1:9</note> How would their jumping chariots and glittering harness look at such a striving humbling time.</p>
<p>[marginal note] I am just now told of a man died dismal with the bite of a mad dog it was thought.</p>
<pb n="13" facs="sc204168"/>
<p>As that we read of when it was said an ass's head was sold for four score shekels of silver and the 4 part of a cob of doves dung for 5 pieces of silver.<note resp="transcr">2 Kings 6:25</note>: at such a time as Samuel Bownas, Thomas Story and divers other give account of most dreadful awful earthquakes when several thousand were destroyed in a few minutes when the people were alarmed and thoroughly humbled under a sense of fear of the heavy judgments that hung over them when they were ready to cry out what shall we do to be saved what will thou have me to do willing to change their trifling glittering gayeties (like them we read of in the 3rd Chapter of Isaiah) and put on sackcloth or humble themselves in any way they could to appease the anger of the Lord which they found lay very heavy on them. Paul says three and twenty thousand fell in one day for their wickedness<note resp="transcr">1 Corinthians 10:8</note>: how would such pride and luxury look in such times of grievous calamity? Solomon says that it is good in the days of prosperity to remember the days of adversity<note resp="transcr">Ecclesiastes 7:14</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-07-02"><head>July 1823</head><dateline><date when="1823-07-02">2 of the Sixth [Seventh]<note resp="transcr">The entries for 2, 4 and 6 July 1823 were misdated in the manuscript journal as Sixth (June) rather than Seventh (July) month.</note> Month.</date></dateline><p> A soaking heavy rain.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-07-04"><dateline><date when="1823-07-04">4 of the Sixth [Seventh] Month.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting which was small Just the beginning of harvest I was but poorly and felt the effects of old age and something of the attacks of that indolent spirit which so much besets us but seemed to get over it and had to mention the words to rain if thou dost well shalt thou not be accepted,<note resp="transcr">Genesis 4:7</note> etc. how well it would be and greatest wisdom not to sit down without experiencing acceptance for ourselves: several others appeared and I did think there was some stirrings of life and ownings of truth to some good degree of satisfaction. I find some of our weekday meeting folks think it a sufficient excuse to put by meeting on account of reaping although it is said our first Friends would keep up their meetings if their corn dropped in the ground and very great reasons they had to do so for he from whom every good and perfect gift comes they knew could yet say whither their land should or should not yield her increase – But the world's calls seems to outbid all and the Earth has opened her mouth and swallowed up the greater part<note resp="transcr">Numbers 16:32</note> Oh earth earth hear Oh earth<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 22:29</note>: It is said of the drunkard the Lord hath made the a man but thou hast made thyself a beast and how much better is it with those who have set their Hearts and affections on things below: Like Nebuchadnezzar at grass when a beast's heart was given him<note resp="transcr">Daniel 5:21</note>: Content with earthly things only.</p>
<p>[marginal note] And what miserable creatures we are without his acceptance and what a precarious situation we are in.</p></div>
<pb n="14" facs="sc204169"/>
<div type="entry" n="1823-07-05"><dateline><date when="1823-07-05">5 of the Sixth [Seventh] Month.</date></dateline><p> One of old said there is that scattereth and yet increaseth.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs</note> so I find it to be with respect to that language to Cain if thou dost well shalt thou not be accepted<note resp="transcr">Genesis 4:7</note> are there not thousands and millions who are concluding they are doing very well who are very great strangers to that feeling acceptance which the righteous so much longed and labored for: as the heart panteth after the water brooks so doth my soul after the Lord<note resp="transcr">Psalm 42:1</note>: If thou wouldest be with me in the way that I go and give me bread to eat and raiment to put on thou shalt be my God and I will serve the<note resp="transcr">Genesis 28:20</note> so we may see all along it was a feeling sense of an acceptance with the Lord which they could not be content to live without: I sat under his shadow with great delight and his fruit was sweet to my taste<note resp="transcr">Song of Solomon 2:3</note> and our first Friends say that in the beginning when friends minds were more free from the entanglements of the world the powerful overshadowings of the Holy Ghost was more frequently felt among them I will not give sleep to mine eyes nor slumber to mine eyelids until I find a place for the God of Jacob to dwell in<note resp="transcr">Psalm 132:4</note>: Let me feel thy presence or else my time is lost and my life a snare to my soul: But what poor sort of talk is this to the present generation intoxicated with prosperity and what poor advice it would be to a people besotted with strong drink to urge the apostles council feel after him if happily ye may find him for he is not far away from everyone of us<note resp="transcr">Acts 17:27</note> I know not which would be in the most unfit state to put such advice in practice: they who are intoxicated with prosperity as those besotted with strong drink oh see how many ways there are for people to be cheated out of their chiefest good which is acceptance with God: If thou doest well shalt thou not be accepted<note resp="transcr">Genesis 4:7</note> and are we not the most miserable of any part of the creation without acceptance with our maker and what a precarious situation we are in surrounded with sorrows and subject to the spoil of sickness and the sudden stroke of death and then at last acceptance with the Lord would be a treasure for transcending all the joys and pleasures riches and treasures this world can afford oh the scramble after the treasures of this world whilst the one thing needful is neglected and their chiefest good acceptance with the Lord lost the Lord's loving kindness is better than life<note resp="transcr">Psalm 63:3</note> in thy presence is fullness of Joy at thy right hand rivers of pleasures forever more<note resp="transcr">Psalm 16:11</note>: said David if thou doth well shalt thou not be accepted<note resp="transcr">Genesis 4:7</note>: go thy way eat thy bread with gladness and drink thy wine with a merry heart for God accepteth thy works<note resp="transcr">Ecclesiastes 9:7</note>: Happy for those who do so well as to experience these things for themselves but we are told that if our righteousness does not exceed the righteousness of the Scribes and Pharisees we can in no wise find acceptance with the Lord<note resp="transcr">Matthew 5:20</note></p></div>
<pb n="15" facs="sc204170"/>
<div type="entry" n="1823-07-06"><dateline><date when="1823-07-06">6 of the Seventh Month, 1823.</date></dateline><p> I went to our meeting but my mind was so much turned towards Westfield that I could think of little else I was unwell and hardly able to sit the meeting <persName key="w67b4w4h">Joseph Justice</persName> took up most of the time it was but a poor time to me: although I had – I had a very excellent lesson the apostles exhortation study to shew thyself approved in the sight of God<note resp="transcr">2 Timothy 2:15</note> what more necessary for all the world all stand in need of his favor and without it we are the most miserable of any part of the creation all had need of that same strengthening power comfort and consolation that Habakkuk speaks of where he says although the fields should yield no meat yet will I rejoice in the Lord and joy in the God of my salvation<note resp="transcr">Habakkuk 3:17-18</note> this afternoon a pretty heavy thundershower and one very hard clap next day we found a large oak tree about eighty rod from the house in the woods tore all to shivers and splinters down to the roots I have observed trees killed with the thunder almost all round us within sight of the house and I think a walnut tree was killed that stood close to the end of the barn. How frequently do we hear of people being killed with the thunder and creatures killed with it and houses torn to pieces and barns burnt how we have been mercifully spared and favored what shall we render for all his favors<note resp="transcr">Psalm 116:12</note> see Isaiah 29 and 6 thou shalt be visited of the Lord with thunder and see further in scriptures accounts what terrible times of thunder there has been and even down to our days. In New England their Presbyterian minister in his history of the judgments he gives most terrible accounts of thunder in Carolina on the road leading to the western territories where there is abundance of teams travel I think it was said in the news fourteen horses was killed with the thunder at one clap and divers of the men were on their backs and not hurt when the horses fell. Four men were killed with the thunder some years ago near Mount Holly in a meadow about hay but I suppose a history a volume might be filled with such accounts: Read the 78 Psalm and 48 verse he gave their cattle to hot thunderbolts.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1823-07-10"><dateline><date when="1823-07-10">10 of the Seventh Month, 1823.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting just in the midst of harvest I did think it was an owning time in a good degree throughout. <persName key="w6hj799d">Elizabeth Collins</persName> from Egg Harbor had savory service I was so poorly in the morning I was afraid I was not able to sit but was enabled to sit the meeting but was so exhausted it was with difficulty I got home vomiting and lax followed.<note resp="transcr">note- the bottom right-hand corner of the manuscript is missing</note></p></div>
<pb n="16" facs="sc204171"/>
<div type="entry" n="1823-07-12"><dateline><date when="1823-07-12">Seventh Day Morning, 12 of the Seventh Month, 1823.</date></dateline><p> At our last Monthly Meeting we had at last the extract of our Yearly Meeting read we have line upon line, line upon line, precept upon precept, precept upon precept – epistles extracts – advices addresses and many excellent religious tracts all excellent but as I had to remark upon it: we know it is possible to sit in a room where the clock strikes all day and not be sensible of hearing it the mind and attention being otherwise taken up and engaged and what is the reason why such abundance of labor bestowed upon us has so little effects must it not be for want of attention: Listen not to the voice of the charmer although charming never so wisely<note resp="transcr">Psalm 58:5</note> like the deaf adder Stephen Crisp tells of a way people are going on in that has filled the world with a set of Christians that do want acceptance with God and which has been the downfall of true religion at the present day and is it not a very easy matter for people to be content with a sort of religion without evidently knowing acceptance with God for themselves and what is religion good for without acceptance with God although they may shew great zeal compass sea and land to make one proselyte and carry their matters to a vast great height without acceptance with God it – will all be but as sounding brass and tinkling cymbals<note resp="transcr">1 Corinthians 13:1</note>: Be ye not as the Horse or as the mule that hath no understanding<note resp="transcr">Psalm 32:9</note> said David. I believe there is a way a possibility of attending our religious meetings even where there is frequently a lively acceptable gospel ministry and die under it yea I do believe there is a possibility of attending religious meetings all their life long in such a way as not to be able to give an account if they were asked what they went to meeting for and never ask themselves what they gotomeeting for like the horse or the mule that hath no understanding but lively and wise enough about the cares, affairs and treasures of this world so I think I have seen that children may be brought up to meetings all their days and yet be as raw about true religion as the Indians that never seen a meeting and all this for want of setting their affections on the most desirable deserving object Is there not a clear demonstration where the heart and desires are placed see the conformity to the world both amongst aged and youth as a dear youth once remarked he said he could see but few but what were more or less swayed by custom: How are blessings abused amongst us an highly favored people much more concerned for the clothing of the body than for the clothing of the mind the inward man: no wonder there should be leanness of soul: How many even of the youth for want of health are deprived of the privilege of tending meetings who would counted it a great treasure if they were able to tend meetings but are confined with lingering [indecipherable] ulcers and cancers and consumptions, etc., and some youth came to meeting on crutches.</p></div>
</body></text>
</TEI>