<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Hunt Journal, 1815 4mo. 1 - 1817 8mo. 3: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>James Truitt</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 20 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were created and/or prepared by the <hi rend="italic" >Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</hi> and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <hi rend="italic"> Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College </hi>.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2021">2021</date>
                <idno type="local">A0011528</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">
                    <title level="s" type="main">Friendly Networks</title>
                    <title level="s" type="sub">The Journals of Our Beloved Friend John Hunt</title></title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>John Hunt Papers, SFHL-RG5-240</collection>
                        <idno>A0011528</idno>
                        <idno>sc203698</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>12 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The journals of Quaker minister John Hunt are stored at the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College. With the generous support of H. David and Joyce E. Hunt, Library staff scanned and transcribed the journals, and in 2021, encoded the text in TEI. The 2021 project also included researching individuals mentioned in the text to create and update records about them in the <ref target="https://snaccooperative.org/">Social Networks and Archival Context website</ref>
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> John Hunt was a good writer, but like most 18th century authors, his punctuation, spelling, and abbreviations were not standardized or necessarily consistent. The goal of the Hunt project was to produce a text accessible to the modern reader, retaining all the words in the order they appear, but with added punctuation and capitalization to make the document readable. Some spelling of surnames and places has been corrected in order to facilitate searching. Any other additions supplied to aid the reader are surrounded by brackets. Archaic forms and spellings of words are also retained. “How art thou feeling” remains as written, not changed to “How are you feeling.” And Hunt frequently used the abbreviation “Do.” for ditto; this has not been changed. The word “sic” means that word or words are transcribed as written. Usually this marks an error in the original text. When identified by the editor, biblical references, all from the King James version, have been identified in notes. Where Hunt himself identified them as such this attribution is retained in the main body of the text.</p>
                <p>Hunt consistently used Quaker-style plain dating, avoiding the names of the months and the names of days of the week. “Monday, October 9th,” for instance, is written as “Second Day, Ninth of the Tenth Month.” The headings dividing the texts were added by the editors, using the standard names for the months, again for ease of reading.</p>
                <p>Hunt had a practice of regularly adding to a series of bound journals when he was at home, but usually recorded entries while he was at Yearly Meeting or travelling in the ministry on single sheets of paper. In publishing the entirety of the journal we have added “loose” sections where they fit chronologically.  </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written <date from="1815-04-01" to="1817-08-03">1815 4mo. 1 - 1817 8mo. 3</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <term>Quakers -- Conduct of life</term>
                    <term>Quakers -- Religious life</term>
                    <term>Quakers -- Social life and customs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#lcnaf">
                    <term ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2005064399">Hunt, John, 1740-1824</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item><date/></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="01" facs="sc203925"/>
<div><p>Tilton Bunting son of</p></div>
<pb n="02" facs="sc203926"/>
<div type="narrative"><p>Nathan Smith made the second appearance in public signified he had been under a serious concern about this yearly meeting several days past and greatly desired those Friends that had come so far from the different parts of the yearly meeting might be benefitted by coming and he seemed to be very sure they would he hoped the youth might be preserved from the many baits and snares, the many places of amusement and</p></div>

<div><list rend="numbered">
<item>1. </item>
<item>2.  Nathan Smith</item>
<item>3. </item>
<item>4. Jerusha Curtis made a prayer</item>
<item>5. <persName key="w6427ngj">George Dwylin</persName></item>
<item>6. </item>
<item>7.  <persName key="w6mw2sk8">Stephen Grellett</persName></item>
<item>8. Massey <del>Shreave</del> Brown belongs to the Western Qua wise</item>
</list></div>
<div><note type="structure">[Upside down:]</note><p>Please to make pantaloons longer in the seat so as the lower part of the seat will not bind between the legs and</p>
<p>Please to make the pantaloons longer in the seat, so as the lower part of the seat will not betwean the legs and</p></div>
<pb n="03" facs="sc203927"/>
<div type="entry" n="1815-04"><dateline><date when="1815-04">First day morning the <space/> day of the fourth month 1815</date></dateline><p> attended the forenoon meeting at the North meeting house.</p>
<p><space/> first appeared in the ministry recommending us to build upon the sure foundation Christ Jesus the rock of ages</p>
    <p><space/> Woman Friend very short space after appeared</p>
<p>Jerusha Curtis made a prayer</p>
<p><persName key="w6427ngj">George Dillwyn</persName> next appeared signified there was various opinions concerning Christ who bespoke his disciples after this manner</p>
    <p><quote type="biblical">but whom do you say that I the son of man am</quote> Oh that we could answer as Peter did <quote type="biblical">thou art Christ the son of <space/> Jesus saith unto him flesh and blood hath not revealed it to him</quote><note type="editorial">Matthew 16:15-17</note> here was the <add>right</add> foundation is to build upon which will stand in a day of trial will most surely come upon all though it might beat upon the superstructure reared up upon this Foundation yet the foundation standeth sure against which all the storms of Affliction may beat in vain to practice one gospel truth was of more worth than form to heart full of the experiences and practice of others from one end of our lives to the others</p>
<pb n="04" facs="sc203928"/>
<p>Afternoon meeting began at 4 o'clock at the same house which I attended a woman Friend named <space/> compared a true follower of Christ to be like a ship prepared for Voyage when they are willing to go and come like what storms of tribulation come as might then the vessel was prepared for life's voyage</p></div>

<div><list><item>Patience Sleeper wife of Samuel Sleeper lives at Stroudsburg</item>
<item>Morgan Judge from Indian Spring Meeting daughter of Hugh Judge and his wife they being both ministers</item>
<item>Nathan Hain from North Carolina Guilford</item>
<item>Evan Thomas from Baltimore Mo Meeting</item>
<item>Micajah Collins from Salem Monthly Meeting, Massachusetts</item>
<item>Richard Mott</item></list></div>
<pb n="05" facs="sc203929"/>
<div type="entry" n="1815-04">
    <p>At 10 o'clock meeting settled</p>
<p><persName key="w6427ngj">George Dillwyn</persName> said that communication was very helpful to build each other up in the most holy faith hope he might not when he went up to the house of the Lord he might not offer the sacrifice of fools.</p>
    <p>Richard Mott next after said if every individual was to endeavor to keep a steady mind wish desires to be acquainted with that which was good we might have a well grounded hope of his refreshing presence being sensible felt among us.</p>

<p>Opening minutes being read the representatives names were all called over and abstracts from the <add>[illegible]</add> each other. The Quarterly meeting were next read over with the name of the clerks and one representative [illegible] the clerk requested the meeting to consider which should be taken up, the Epistles from each yearly meeting or public Friends' certificates. The meeting concluded to have the certificates read which was immediately done afterwards the Epistle was read <add>some replies to them</add> and a committee was next appointed to settle the Treasurer's accounts. 3 appeals the clerk intimated was come the meeting desired that the parties might be ready the meeting would take notice of them the next sitting the representatives were desired stop at the [illegible] of the meeting and considered of Persons for clerk and Assistance</p>

<p>Jesse Kersey wished Friend not to come and obstruct the passage at the gate before he mentions as a duty he owed as a Friend</p>
<pb n="06" facs="sc203930"/>
<p>The meeting adjourned till 3 o'clock PM at which time Friends again assembled. Jonathan Evans on behalf of the representatives made a report; they were united with much unity to propose <persName key="w6b01gx6">John Cox</persName> for to serve the meeting as clerk the present year and Samuel Bettle to assist him; the meeting waited a short time for the appellants to appear; <del>and on account of</del> Margaret Boyles attended in company with a woman Friend and signified she should appeal from the judgment of <space/> Monthly Meeting confirmed by <space/> Quarter. Two <add>Friends</add> from each quarterly meeting <add>except <del>the one from</del></add> were appointed as a committee to hear the appellant pay due attention to the minutes of the quarterly meeting and monthly meeting in her case as well as what the five Friends from that quarterly meeting should say in support thereof and report when they be prepared</p></div>
<pb n="07" facs="sc203931"/>
<div type="entry" n="1815-04-18"><dateline><date when="1815-04-18">18 of the month and 3rd of the week</date></dateline><p> meeting [illegible] [illegible] pursuant to adjournment the meeting went into consideration of the state of society ascertained in the replies to the queries <del>as</del> sent up from the different Quarters consulted. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> remarked the scriptures promises were to be experienced in this life which a many thought belong to that which was to come the principle we make profession of was the same thing which the unprofitable servant hide in a napkin but there was wherein he had to account for his latest how will it be with thou who Neglect meeting the fascinating <add>visible</add> things with which the minds may engage in we so many as the talent to must be laid by but it will rise in Judgment against us sooner or later though we lay it by for the present those emanations is the same fire that consumed the rebellious captain and fishes at the prayer of Elijah yea this is the very hell fire to sinners the fire descended immediately from heaven on the alter whereon was Gods acceptable sacrifice</p>
<p>proceeded as far as to include the 5th Query then adjourned till 3 o clock Pm</p>

<p>Jesse Kersey remarked that children's minds sometimes sealed with a belief that their parents <del>were</del> are not religious</p>
<pb n="08" facs="sc203932"/>
<p>There was no power the church could make use of but the power of love if children believe their parents are religious they will love them oh how precious it would then be for children and parents in this <del>parents</del> <add>state</add> when they are by their fire sides for parents to inform their little and just opening minds</p>

<p>At the time adjourned to Friends again as the remaining queries were read and Answered <persName key="w6mw2sk8">Stephen Grellet</persName> thereto As well as the reports <del>from</del> sent up from the several quarterly meetings and as much <add>many</add> of the minutes of last year as would be likely to be considered at this time; the meetings Attention was then turned towards the consideration of the proposition sent up from the quarterly meeting respecting some part of the discipline respecting a treatment with those who may be present at marriages accomplished contrary to our rules the meetinghouse was very warm and no way appearing to come to any conclusion on the subject the meeting adjourned till 10 o'clock tomorrow morning also an abstract from Chambers Walters will was read stating he bequeathed 100$ to the care of the Year meeting for the benefit of Poor Friends at Upper Canada which the meeting agree should</p>
<pb n="09" facs="sc203933"/>
    <p>there were about 17 minister and Elders deceased since last year <persName key="w6427ngj">George Dillwyn</persName> said his mind was saturated with this language <q>be ye also ready</q> <persName key="w6427ngj">George</persName> was impressed with a belief <add>which he communicated at a former setting</add> that he thought <del>we should never</del> there were so many Friends that would never meet in a yearly meeting capacity again</p>
<p><persName key="w6wh3qkh">Nathan Hunt</persName> enjoined as though it was and all important thing not to neglect our religious duty towards God for he thou<supplied>ght</supplied> from a failure in this particular arose all the deficienies pointed out in the Answer.</p>
<p><persName key="w6427ngj">George Dillwyn</persName> remarked on the query those were unfaithful in the unrighteous manners who would commit to them the true riches </p></div>
<pb n="10" facs="sc203934"/>
<div type="entry"><p>Attended the N. Meeting First day morning at 10 O'clock the first who appeared in the ministry was a woman from <space/> These communications I thought was not acceptable to Friends: the second appearance Amos Peasly from <space/> Nathan Yarnal made a prayer</p><p>Went to the afternoon meeting at the N. Meeting the first appearance in the ministry was by a man the next by <space/> from <space/></p></div>
<pb n="11" facs="sc203935"/>
<div><note type="structure">[Upside down]</note><ab>call at Harrison's<lb/>
the first House below Cherry Street ally in 12 str</ab></div>
<pb n="12" facs="sc203936"/>
    <div type="entry" n="1817-08-03"><dateline><date when="1817-08-03">This year 1817 8 Month 3rd and First day of the week</date></dateline><p> <persName key="w68w3qrz">Edward Hicks</persName> from Pennsylvania was at Chester Meeting at Moorestown. <q>Agree with thine adversary quickly while thou art in the way with him</q><note type="editorial">Matthew 5:25: <quote type="biblical">Agree with thine adversary quickly, whiles thou art in the way with him; lest at any time the adversary deliver thee to the judge</quote></note> that when an evil thought prevents itself, repulse it and not yield while thou has strength to do so, least he deliver thee to judge, what judge the light of Christ in the heart</p></div>
</body></text>
</TEI>