<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Hunt Journal, 1824 3mo. 25: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>James Truitt</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 15 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were created and/or prepared by the <hi rend="italic" >Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</hi> and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <hi rend="italic"> Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College </hi>.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2021">2021</date>
                <idno type="local">A0011537</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">
                    <title level="s" type="main">Friendly Networks</title>
                    <title level="s" type="sub">The Journals of Our Beloved Friend John Hunt</title></title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>John Hunt Papers, SFHL-RG5-240</collection>
                        <idno>A0011537</idno>
                        <idno>sc203245</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>2 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The journals of Quaker minister John Hunt are stored at the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College. With the generous support of H. David and Joyce E. Hunt, Library staff scanned and transcribed the journals, and in 2021, encoded the text in TEI. The 2021 project also included researching individuals mentioned in the text to create and update records about them in the <ref target="https://snaccooperative.org/">Social Networks and Archival Context website</ref>
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> John Hunt was a good writer, but like most 18th century authors, his punctuation, spelling, and abbreviations were not standardized or necessarily consistent. The goal of the Hunt project was to produce a text accessible to the modern reader, retaining all the words in the order they appear, but with added punctuation and capitalization to make the document readable. Some spelling of surnames and places has been corrected in order to facilitate searching. Any other additions supplied to aid the reader are surrounded by brackets. Archaic forms and spellings of words are also retained. “How art thou feeling” remains as written, not changed to “How are you feeling.” And Hunt frequently used the abbreviation “Do.” for ditto; this has not been changed. The word “sic” means that word or words are transcribed as written. Usually this marks an error in the original text. When identified by the editor, biblical references, all from the King James version, have been identified in notes. Where Hunt himself identified them as such this attribution is retained in the main body of the text.</p>
                <p>Hunt consistently used Quaker-style plain dating, avoiding the names of the months and the names of days of the week. “Monday, October 9th,” for instance, is written as “Second Day, Ninth of the Tenth Month.” The headings dividing the texts were added by the editors, using the standard names for the months, again for ease of reading.</p>
                <p>Hunt had a practice of regularly adding to a series of bound journals when he was at home, but usually recorded entries while he was at Yearly Meeting or travelling in the ministry on single sheets of paper. In publishing the entirety of the journal we have added “loose” sections where they fit chronologically.  </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written on <date when="1824-03-25">1824 3mo. 25</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <term>Quakers -- Conduct of life</term>
                    <term>Quakers -- Religious life</term>
                    <term>Quakers -- Social life and customs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#lcnaf">
                    <term ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2005064399">Hunt, John, 1740-1824</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item><date/></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="01" facs="sc203680"/>
<div type="entry" n="1824-03-25"><head>March 1824</head><dateline><date when="1824-03-25">25 of 3 month 1824.</date></dateline><p> At our preparative meeting their was some pamphlets handed out which Friends had ordered to be printed and spread, giving an account of the enormous practice of the slave trade yet continued, notwithstanding divers nations have made laws to prohibit that most barbarous trade. The great number of vessels there is now employed in that trade so that they are bringing  the poor Negroes away from their native lands of near and dear connections by hundreds of thousands and [indecipherable] them into slavery to many of the various. One account seems to display a manifest judgement upon them. A vessel loaded with Negroes after they had got out to see, a strange disorder in their eyes came  upon them and both whites and both went quite blind so that they were unable to steer the vessel. Another vessel came up with them of whom they begged help, but attained none, they fearing their disorder, and it was believed them they all perished in the see. About twenty years ago I was traveling in the western territories on the River Ohio, we lodged at a tavern whereas some men had got fifty-two Negroes from the Southern states and were taking to a place called the Natchez some hundreds of miles westward. There were men, women and children, the men in chains and the women had two sucking babes at their breasts handcuffed with irons. To see and feel the darkness and hardness of their oppressors hearts was painful to be  in their company. I suppose to drown their sorrow: see Psalms 137 and 3rd For they that carried us away captive required of us a song and they that wasted us required of us mirth etc. Some years ago I picked up a bit of newspaper off the floor wherein was an account of a vessel with 130 Negroes (of the Mantanzes) which was struck with thunder and the vessel sunk in a few minutes and all perished but the Captain and his mate who lashed some spars together and floated on them near two weeks but was found and taken up by a wrecker * that is a vessel looking for shipwrecks. But the Captain and his mate had laid so long in the water they had quite lost the use of their limbs. Some years ago there were some men from the Southern States brought a number of Negroes to Redstone (on their way further to west). Whilst at Redstone a strange sickness on them and a number of Negroes died and one of the two brothers that had them in keeping died. The other set off back to get help and he also died. The Inhabitants being alarmed hired a man to conduct them down the river westward and he also died so the poor Negroes were left without Oppressors or Masters or Caretakers. What became of them I have not heard. But does not these appear singular judgements.</p>
<p>*[star and comment written later] Query. Does not the preservation of Captain and Mate seem marvelous?</p></div>
<pb n="02" facs="sc203681"/>
    <div type="entry" n="1824-04"><opener>A more perfect account of the Negroes brought to Redstone. Extract of a letter from Elisha Hunt of Redstone <dateline><date when="1818-05-16">5 month, 16[th day], 1818.</date></dateline></opener>
    <p>Just before we got home 4 brothers with a large company of black slaves came to town. The blacks took sick; 6 or 8 dies. The brothers took sick likewise, and 2 of them died. Here the inhabitants became alarmed and put them into a boat and started them away. One of the brothers died in the boat. The other hired a citizen of this town to navigate the boat and the other started back to Virginia for some assistance and died in the mountains of Charlestown and has left a family here. Thus 5 men have died besides the 6 or 8 Negroes. The blacks are at Charlestown in Miammi or Ohio of those that survived. Is not this an alarming hint to Negro traders?</p>
<dateline><date when="1824-04">Near the last of 4th month 1824.</date></dateline><closer><signed> J.H.</signed></closer></div>
</body></text>
</TEI>