<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader></teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="01" facs="sc203820"/>
<div type="entry" n="1806-08-23"><head>August 1806</head><dateline><date when="1806-08-23">[23rd 8th Month, 1806]</date></dateline><p> Everything we here enjoy changes, decays and comes to an end. The indulgence of harsh dispositions is the introduction of future misery.  Remember Trout[?] Haman all availed him nothing w[cut off]: Disturb in mind and hoss[?] t[cut off] Ended.</p>
<p>Gentleness is in truth the great avenue to mutual enjoyment</p>
<p>[inserted above] Great said David</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1806-08-24"><dateline><date when="1806-08-24">24th 8th Month 1806.</date></dateline><p> Although we have had a very fruitful season here in our parts vast plenty of apples, pears, cherries, fruit of every kind, watermelons, cucumbers so plenty and cheap in market that they would not pay the expense of taking there and abundance thrown away a very mortifying time to the truck mongers or truck merchants the like was never known in such vast plenty I don't doubt but many wagon loads of watermelons and cucumbers will be thrown away. They are in such vast plenty in our Jersey land and a very good harvest for rye and wheat and the greatest prospect of a vast great crop of Indian corn and buckwheat that ever was known yet I am told by eye witnesses that a little below Salem they have had a pinching time of drought so that a few weeks ago they could rub the corn leaves to snuff,  and  a Friend who lately traveled through New England Isaac C. Jones told me a great drought prevailed through that part of the country eastward especially in province of Maine so called. The drought is mentioned in the newspapers very piercing indeed in the time of this dry weather the fire broke out the wind being very high and raged to a great degree spread over and consumed a great part of the country burnt up and destroyed, many settlements so that many great farmers who had lived in affluence and plenty were now by that means reduced to poverty and want being burnt out of house and home.</p>
<p>See William Edmundson's <emph rend="italic">Journal </emph>an account of a time of great scarcity which was soon succeeded [by] a time of great plenty which was made known to him and he had to prophecy foretell and forewarn the people and told the people the Lord would lash them with his judgment and dung [?] the ground with the carcasses of men which shortly after soon came to pass,  and many died for want of bread and tuffs of rank green grass were seen on the common where carcasses of people had dunged the ground and s[missing] his prophecy was fulfilled.</p>
<p>[Marginal note, written sideways] 1807 John Haines traveling in new England this summer says they have had no harvest over a great part of that country the winter and Insects destroyed their wheat that they made bread without bottling their meal,  bran and all together and would allow but ten pound of hay a night for a horse.</p></div>
<pb n="02" facs="sc203821"/>
<div><floatingText>[Penciled "1806"]</floatingText>
<p>See <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn's</persName> <emph rend="italic">No Cross, No Crown</emph>, page 120</p>
<floatingText>LXII Heraclitus</floatingText>
<quote>I have overcome pleasure, I have overcome riches, I have overcome ambition, I have mastered flattery, fear hath nothing to object against me, drunkenness hath nothing to charge upon me.  Anger is afraid of me I have won the garland in fighting against these enemies</quote>
<floatingText>[inserted above] the worse of a mans house</floatingText>
<p>And what is the great promises in scripture to the overcomers: <quote type="biblical">he that overcometh will I give to eat of the tree of life that stands in the midst of the paradise of God</quote> and <quote type="biblical">of the hidden manna</quote> etc. etc.</p>
<floatingText>Sentiment</floatingText>
<quote>One act of triumph over the temper is worth a million of triumphs over our fellow creatures and the perfect dominion of our mind is more advantageous and laudable than the dominion over provinces and nations the one attaches merely our corporal part and is buried with us in the dust in the grave the other follows our immortal part and passes with it into eternity.</quote>


<p>As said the poet:<quote type="poem">
<l>He is more a prince that rules himself</l>
<l>Than he whom nations keeps in awe,</l>
<l>Who yields to that which doth their souls convince</l>
<l>Shall never need another law</l>
<l>He that ruleth his spirit is stronger than he</l>
<l>That taketh a city: he that ruleth not his</l>
<l>Spirit is like to a city whose walls are broken</l>
<l>Down and without strength</l></quote>: says Solomon</p></div>
</body></text>
</TEI>