<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader></teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="01" facs="sc203993"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-02-20"><head>February 1819</head><p>About the 20th of the Second Month, 1819, I went to see several ancient widows and called to see a friend or friends who had lately earnestly invited me, and they said they were glad to see me. I said that was much better than if I had conducted [myself] so that they would not want to see me. The answer was a yes. I said I had been visiting and that I could not please myself at it. They said, maybe thee is hard to please. I said I thought I ought to be so; I have long thought it would be well if we were not so easy pleased with our social visits. Soon after, the subject so arrested my mind that I thought it might be of use to make some memorandum of my thoughts. I remember some years ago I mentioned the subject of common conversation in our social visits – of how poor and unprofitable it often was – in our select quarterly meeting, and it introduced a lively conference on the subject and lively, edifying remarks were made.</p>
<p><persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says: [that] in early days, Friends spent much of their time when together in solemn silence, feeling after their own and one another's states of conditions.<note resp="transcr"><emph rend="italic">Primitive Christianity Revived</emph>, first published 1696.</note> They were then under humbling, trying circumstances, not knowing which minute their cruel persecutions would be upon them and haul them to prison. Were we under the like trials would our conversation not often be more weighty and more Heavenly than it is?</p>
<p>And <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says the time will come when every visit shall be a meeting and every family a church and every head of a family a minister, and he says in a little while and it shall be so.</p>
<p>And William Bailey says, page 518, “and take heed of discourses among yourselves which are unnecessary, for the enemy hath a secret to effect among such things to draw your mind from the living sense of the precious seed of God in yours.”<note resp="transcr">William Bayley, <emph rend="italic">A collection of the several writings of that true prophet</emph>, 1676.</note> Is not this a necessary caution in this day of ease? And see <emph rend="italic">Power of Religion on the Mind</emph>, by <persName key="w66696rh">Lindley Murray</persName>, 11 Edition concerning John Janeway: he was full of love and compassion to the souls of men, and often greatly lamented the barrenness of Christians in their concerns with each other. O, said he, what indifference to spend an hour or two together and to hear scarce
<pb n="02" facs="sc203994"/>
scarce a word that speaks people's hearts in love with Holiness! Where is our love to God and our fellow creatures all this while? Where is our sense of the preciousness of time? Of the greatness of our accounts? Should we talk thus if we believe we should hear of it again at the day of Judgment? Does not this speak aloud that our hearts are devoid of grace, and that we have little sense of spiritual and eternal concerns?</p>
<p>I have read of a worthy woman in our <emph rend="italic">Memorials<note resp="transcr">Memorial of Phebe Trimble, <emph rend="italic">Memorials</emph>, Philadelphia 1787</note></emph>  of whom they say she had a remarkable gift and disposition of mind when in company to turn the conversation on religious, profitable things. Are not such [people] much wanting amongst us? Like Amelia Nicholas, of whom it was said she would often, when in company, cry out, “Be faithful unto God; be faithful unto God,” till she was once asked if she had nothing else to say and she answered, “If I was to live an hundred years, I could not repeat it too often.”</p>
<p>I have been in company with my most intimate friends and we have slidin into what is called pleasant, innocent, though unprofitable conversation and we have talked ourselves very poor, lean, dry, and barren and I have been ready to adopt this language: oh, how seldom we do so well as we might do and should do! And have thought of the language of David to his friends: are ye the last to bring in the king?.<note resp="transcr">2 Samuel 19:11</note> And it was said to David, blessed are thy helpers.<note resp="transcr">1 Chronicles 12:18</note> and to encourage his helpers he offered to give them rich fields and vineyards. But, alas, what are such gifts compared to what the King of Kings, who stands knocking at the door of our hearts, offers to his helpers? Either grace nor glory nor any good thing shall be withheld from them. And [he] hath said, he that heareth my voice and openeth unto me, I will come in and sup with him and he with me<note resp="transcr">Revelation 3:20</note> Oh, what room there is for us to improve in our converse together, to our unspeakable advantages!</p>
<p>I have thought sometimes, respecting our common conversation in our social visits, how far might one travel that was truly hungering and thirsting after righteousness.<note resp="transcr">Matthew 5:6</note> before he would get a crumb of bread among us. O how we can spend hour after hour talking on subject to no profit, either temporal or spiritual? Is not this loss of precious time, talking and walking after things that do not profit? So we read it was formerly: many walked after things that did not profit<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 2:8</note> and loved to wander<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 14:10</note></p>
<pb n="03" facs="sc203995"/>
<p>Is not this an evidence that our affections are set on things below and not on things above? Or else would not our conversation be more on Heavenly things than they often are? But where the treasure is, there will the heart be also. I have observed how some can invite us to go out and look at their farms and their improvements, but less can say, “come and see my zeal for the Lord .”.<note resp="transcr">2 Kings 10:16</note> And if anyone is disposed to propose a religious opportunity in the family, they seem struck of dumb and out of their element – like the earthworm out of the earth, out of their element. In earthly concerns [they are] wiser than the children of light<note resp="transcr">Luke 16:8</note> and appear to be not much concerned to know any thing about anything else. Woe unto them, said the Divine Master, that cover with a covering, but not of my spirit<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 30:1</note> If thy Spirit go not with us, send us not hence. People, when they go a-visiting, mostly snug up a little – put on some clean clothes, not go ragged or dirty. Remember the ancient council was, “buy of me white raiment to cover the withall that thy nakedness may not appear”.<note resp="transcr">Revelation 3:18</note> It is under a covering of a right spirit only that our social visits can be pleasant or profitable. As [Thomas] à Kempis says and I have experienced, when Jesus is present it makes all things pleasant, like a spring season. Whose loving kindness is better than life and in his presence, said the prophet, is fullness of joy and pleasures forever more<note resp="transcr">Psalms 16:11</note>; and not in anything else this world can afford, with all its boasted treasures or pleasures. So herein I conclude it is that our social visits can be pleasant and truly profitable and satisfactory.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-02-26"><dateline><date when="1819-02-26">26, Second Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> A very snowy day. Read the 21 chapter of Job from verse 7th to the 14, concerning them that can content themselves with prosperity in things of this world and their end.</p>
<p>See [James Meikle] <emph rend="italic">Solitude Sweetened</emph>, page 123: When the Jews were settled and in a flourishing condition, Jeshurun waxed fat and kicked, yea did worse than the heathen that were round about them. So, after the Christian church enjoyed rest and tranquility, they turned to do worse than the unconverted nations around them. When Israel fell from the worship of the true God into idolatry, Babylon was the scourge that brought the church into captivity. <emph rend="italic">Solitude Sweetened</emph>, page 203: as long as I dwell on Mesheck, I may expect wars; as long as I attend on sin and vanity, vexation and trouble will attend me. As I cannot be perfect while out of Heaven, so I cannot be perfect in happiness while absent from God.</p></div>
<pb n="04" facs="sc203996"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-04"><head>March 1819</head><dateline><date when="1819-03-04">4th of the Third Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> At our Monthly Meeting. Life enough, if it was but all of the right sort. But who of us ever did a piece of work, either temporal or spiritual, so well that when we look back but what we may see where it might been mended? Or which of us ever spent one day so well but what it might have been spent better? Or who among us ever seen a meeting so well but that it might have been better? Oh, said Thomas à Kempis, that I could spend one hour after the best manner! But I thought our meeting was an open, favored, strengthening time to me. When I look over it, I can find but very little fault with it. [If our hearts condemn us not then have we confidence towards God, which is an impenetrable shield and an inexhaustible treasure which at all this world cannot give nor take away.</p>
<p>We used to say winter mostly broke up about Burlington Quarterly Meeting, which was near 2 weeks ago, but we have had very smart, freezing, cold, snowy weather ever since.</p>
<p>Snow yet thick on the ground this Fifth of Third Month but now warmer. A few days ago we heard of the death [of] Enoch Hollinshead's son near Moorestown, about twenty years of age, with a short illness they could hardly tell. He had not been brought up to attend meetings of any sort. See Isaac Penington's <emph rend="italic">Works</emph>, 2 volume page 625, on water baptism: we know, having been taught by the Lord, that there is no salvation without inward washing, which is also very demonstrable to others. But God forbid that all should be damned that are not baptized with outward water! And, I add, is there evidence, is there confirmation, is there demonstration? Or will any undertake to say all are saved that are baptized with water? But we read of a baptism which shall save them that are baptized with it. Did not Christ say to Peter, “If I wash thee not, thou hast no part in me”?<note resp="transcr">John 13:8</note>
<pb n="05" facs="sc203997"/>
I am inclined to believe there are few, if any, amongst the most zealous advocates for water baptism (about which there is nowadays very great to do) but what must allow there is evidence and demonstration that there have been in days past and in our days thousands and tens of hundreds of thousands who are saved without water baptism and that never practiced it.</p></div>
    <div type="entry" n="1819-03-06"><dateline><date when="1819-03-06">6 of Third Month 1819 – </date></dateline><p>They who so zealously plead for water baptism allow and say it is but an outward sign of an inward and spiritual grace and was it not said to Paul, “my grace is sufficient for thee”<note resp="transcr">2 Corinthians 12:9</note>: and is it not sufficient for all, as it was for Paul?</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-06"><dateline><date when="1819-03-06">6 of the Third Month</date></dateline><p> at 2 o'clock we went to the burial of Arthur Collins, son of John. In the midst of his days, [he] left a widow and two children with a short illness, which the doctors could hardly tell what to call it. There was a very large concourse of people, [who] I thought behaved very orderly. <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> had a good deal to say and thought very well and I at the grave. But I thought there was much wanting, although the words were pertinent; animation, life, and savor was wanting. Although we are so far refined as not to bury or burn the living widow with the dead husband, as we are informed they do amongst the eastern idolatrous nations, yet there is a great deal of business for the cross of Christ amongst us yet. Very many seem lulled a sleep on the lap of this world, like Sampson on the lap of Delilah, where he lost his strength and his eyesight. The breath of heaven must swell the sail or all the toil is lost. What damage there is and how prone people have ever been to sit down content with a moral righteousness, like the scribes and Pharisees we read of, like Paul before his conversion. Who could say as touching the law he was blameless?<note resp="transcr">Philippians 3:6</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-07"><dateline><date when="1819-03-07">7th was First Day.</date></dateline><p> My mind has been turned towards Cropwell several weeks past, but it seemed as if way did not open for me till now. My dear daughter, H., encouraged and opened the way by offering to go with me and a precious, owning, open time it was to good satisfaction. Openness, sweetness, and feeling nearness at parting.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Could or did the advocates for water baptism ever agree about it?
<pb n="06" facs="sc203998"/>
Second Day. 8 of the Third Month, 1819. Weather very changeable. Last Seventh day, the day before yesterday, it was so warm it swept away most of the snow and our winter clothes felt heavy and burdensome. First Day pretty cold, and at night came on a considerable snow storm and some rain. Second Day clears up fine and moderate and the snow went as quick almost as it came.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-10"><dateline><date when="1819-03-10">10.</date></dateline><p> My daughter Abigail and I went to Haddonfield select quarterly meeting. Samuel Adams [from the] State of New York and Chatlet Jones of Salem, State of Ohio, had acceptable service, but I thought it was but a low time at first. And <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> expressed [that] he thought it was a low time and said he did not know how he could get along with anything. But he did get up at last and seemed to make all shake and I thought it was as [Robert] Barclay says of the working of the spirit: it is like putting a little water in a pump and working it brings up the rest. So I thought life did arise into dominion to edification and good satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-11"><dateline><date when="1819-03-11">11.</date></dateline><p> At our quarterly meeting. A very stormy, snowy day. The strangers, especially Samuel Adams, had lively, pertinent, acceptable service, but at last <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> got up and seemed to make all quiver. And in the afternoon it was allowed to be a favored, owning, open time. What a favor continued to have such a ministry and such meetings! The like not known, perhaps, in many nations of the world at this day.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-12"><dateline><date when="1819-03-12">12.</date></dateline><p> We went to our meeting appointed by Samuel Adams at hour four [in the] afternoon. A large number of people. He began to speak as soon as they were gathered and preached till sun set with good authority and lively, pertinent matter. But alas, where or what is become of the ancient dew that formerly descended on the mountains of Zion.<note resp="transcr">Psalms 133:3</note> when, at the first of Peter's sermons, 3000 were converted to the faith? and as <persName key="w6912v76">George Fox</persName> [‘s Journal] mentions meetings where hundreds were convinced at one time. I fear the remark is too true: they go to their meetings and are pleased with fine preaching but go home and remain just the same. As we read, “they come and sit before this as my people and hear thy words but will not do them…each one returns to their covetousness”<note resp="transcr">Ezekiel 33:31-32</note> Powerful preachers but dull hearers, to whom it is as a pleasant song.</p></div>
<pb n="07" facs="sc203999"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-14"><dateline><date when="1819-03-14">14 of the Third Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Several days past, snow all day almost. Clears up – very severe cold, high harsh wind. I thought I should give out and not go to our meeting, but that it was better to wear away than rust away and to go whilst I could, that I heard one say when he went to meeting through most difficulty, he went to best purpose and of one who said on his dying bed [that] it was a comfort to him to think he had scarcely missed a meeting he could well have been at. So I bundled up and got to meeting and was glad I was there, though things seemed very low, as they mostly do forepart. Through mercy it was as open, evidently owning a time as I almost ever had – like a full tide to sweet satisfaction. Oh, the openness, sweetness, feeling nearness when we broke up, so that it appeared to be to general satisfaction. It is not always so; sometimes I think we are so poor we have hardly clothing to hide our nakedness.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-15"><dateline><date when="1819-03-15">15.</date></dateline><p> Went to see a new married couple, Joseph Brown and wife. He is my son John's wife's brother. [He] had given way to strong drink too much. It was a task, but I thought of the complaint against the shepherds of Israel, that they had not sought to bring back that which was driven away<note resp="transcr">Ezekiel 34:4</note> and of doing as we would be done by (his wife being a deceased neighbor's daughter). [The visit] came off better than I expected; met with a very open reception, had a pretty setting, and parted with good satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-18"><dateline><date when="1819-03-18">18.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. Small, but it was not the poorest to me, though not that life and savor as at some times. Came off pretty well satisfied.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-19"><dateline><date when="1819-03-19">19.</date></dateline><p> Sixth Day. We have had a very freezing, cold, snowy, winter-like time a week past, but now looks a little more like spring. When will summer come, in the best sense of the word, and the voice of turtle [is] heard in our land?<note resp="transcr">Song of Solomon 2:12</note></p>
<p>See <persName key="w6t72g07">John Woolman's</persName> <emph rend="italic">Journal</emph>, page 354: one formerly speaking of the profitableness of true humility saith, “he that troubles not himself with anxious thoughts for more than is necessary
<pb n="08" facs="sc204000"/>
lives little less than the life of angels whilst by a mind content with little, he imitates their want of nothing, [William] Cave's <emph rend="italic">Primitive Christianity</emph>, page 31. But I have often thought, when people are not content with what Christ promised – that is, all things needful to them that would seek first the Kingdom of Heaven – but will be scrambling and scuffling early and late, racking brain and back, primarily pursuing things of this world as if it was their chiefest good. I have seen they are as unhappy as if they were created with thousand and thousands of wants more than there raly [really] are – which, if rightly seen, would appear unnecessary wants. And, oh, how many drown themselves in destruction and perdition in the scramble after these unnecessary wants! Where the treasure is, there will the heart be also. And what does it amount to at last? For we brought nothing into the world and can take nothing out of it when we leave it. And although the things and concerns of this world may have assumed such a vast and mighty importance, they come to nothing at last – hardly a name left little enough to call them by. When the things of eternity appear so inconceivably real, then all the concerns and things of this world sink into an equal nothingness. A few things, simple and plain, serve a Christian; we want but little here nor want that little long. Unnecessary wants more than real ones by far.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-19"><dateline><date when="1819-03-19">19.</date></dateline><p> [marginal note] Third Month, 1819. </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-20"><dateline><date when="1819-03-20">20.</date></dateline><p> Weather very changeable, snow. Snow very frequent. Mending shoes. Soled one pair, but it is but little I can do.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-21"><dateline><date when="1819-03-21">21.</date></dateline><p> First snow. Last night cleared up, very cold and high wind. I got to our meeting. I thought [it] a low time, as R. J. says; could hardly get along, yet through mercy something like a little covering and comfort. See [<persName key="w66696rh">Lindley Murray</persName>] <emph rend="italic">English Reader</emph>, page 151: believe it, no chains bind so hard, no fetters are so heavy as those which fasten the corrupted heart to this treacherous world. No dependence is more contemptible than that under which the voluptuous, the covetous, ambitious man lies to the means of pleasure, gain, or power. Yet, this [is] the boasted
<pb n="09" facs="sc204001"/>
liberty which vice promises as the recompense of setting us free from the salutary restraints of vice blair [blare?].</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-23"><dateline><date when="1819-03-23">23.</date></dateline><p> We went to see our ancient sister <persName key="w6tq8ftp">Hannah Buzby</persName>, about 85. She is very poorly. Stayed all night, very stormy.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-24"><dateline><date when="1819-03-24">24.</date></dateline><p> Were at our cousin B. Warrington's where Hannah and [indecipherable] very low with the consumption. Had a pretty satisfactory time.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-25"><dateline><date when="1819-03-25">25.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Very small and to me very poor and shut up.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-27"><dateline><date when="1819-03-27">27.</date></dateline><p> On Seventh Day at 3, Catlet Jones and his companion, Samuel Davis from Salem, State of Ohio, appointed a meeting at Moorestown. The meeting not very large. C. Jones and H. Haines had a pretty deal to say, but it did but little for me. I hope others fared better. To me, low.</p>
<p>See Sarah Grubb's book page 146: for what is there worth living for but to be found in the discharge of our duty? And as Abraham Gibbins said, life is not worth having without peace.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-28"><dateline><date when="1819-03-28">28.</date></dateline><p> First Day. A barn and tan house burnt a few evenings ago at Moorestown, a stripping, piercing trial to a poorish man, George Matlack. And a house burnt a few evenings ago in Evesham near (or not far) from the meetinghouse, one Crispin's. Realize these things and they are piercing trials to man and beast in cold weather. Weather holds very cold, gloomy. Discouraging prospects; we are become a very helpless family by one means or another, yet have been favored so far many ways beyond very many. What our trials and troubles may be, we know not, nor how we shall strand them or be upheld. See <emph rend="italic">Piety Promoted,</emph>  page 21, Walter Raleigh's last words to his son and wife: if you can live free from want, care for no more; for the rest is but vanity. Love God and begin by times. In him shall you find true and endless comfort; without his favor, all is vanity and vexation of spirit. As Sarah Grubbs says, page 146: For what is there worth living but to be found in the discharge of our duty?</p>
<p>Went this 28 to our meeting. Open and owning and satisfactory in a good degree. Heard of the death of <persName key="w6zk9cxf">Benjamin Swett</persName>, an acceptable minister of Haddonfield who we went to see a few weeks ago. 80 or upwards.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-03-30"><dateline><date when="1819-03-30">30.</date></dateline><p> Went again to see our ancient sister <persName key="w6tq8ftp">Hannah Buzby</persName>, who is yet very poorly. It has been very changeable weather and very cold 'til this evening. A very heavy thundershower.</p></div>
<pb n="10" facs="sc204002"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-04-01"><head>April 1819</head><dateline><date when="1819-04-01">1 of the Fourth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting and I thought better than common, though smaller than common. How does it seem to look, after the visits of so many strangers (powerful preachers), our weekday meetings should grow less? Plenty makes dainty and the full stomach loathes the honeycomb.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 27:7</note> I have been forced to attend to some business several days past, till I am almost overdone.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-04-04"><dateline><date when="1819-04-04">4 of the Fourth Month.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting, and I thought it did end with something sweet and savory, gathering and uniting. This evening high wind and thunder and lightning. Clears up fine. See <emph rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine, </emph>page 323: Adam had dominion over the fish of the sea and over the fowls of the air and over every living thing that moveth upon the Earth. He had the free use of all the creatures so far as they were capable of administering to his comfort. But the summum bonum was his sweet sense of the divine favor. This is and ever will remain the confirmation both of human and angelic felicity. After all the scramble after earthly treasure, it must be confessed that no joys, no pleasures, no riches, no treasures are to be compared to that of being assured of the love and favor of God, whose loving kindness, the prophet said, is better than life. And at his right hand, rivers of pleasure and fullness of joy; but not fullness of joy in all this world can afford. See [<persName key="w66696rh">Lindley Murray</persName>] <emph rend="italic">English Reader, </emph>page 187: for worldly happiness ever tends to destroy itself by corrupting the heart. It fosters the loose and violent passions, it engenders noxious habits and taints the mind with false delicacy, which makes it feel a thousand unreal evils, says Blair. Vanity of vanities, said Solomon,<note resp="transcr">Ecclesiastes 1:2</note> after he had made trial of all the enjoyments this world could afford. Is it not said that they that live in pleasure are dead whilst they live<note resp="transcr">1 Timothy 5:6</note> and “so much the more she hath lived delicately, so much the more torment and sorrow give her”<note resp="transcr">Revelation 18:7</note> and again, “go to the rich men, weep and howl for the miseries that shall come upon you”.<note resp="transcr">James 5:1</note> It easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle than for a rich man to go to heaven.<note resp="transcr">Luke 18:25</note></p>
<p>[marginal note] Your gold and your silver is cankered and your garments, motheaten.</p></div>
<pb n="11" facs="sc204003"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-04-08"><dateline><date when="1819-04-08">8.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our Monthly Meeting. Several short testimonies, and I thought they were savory and lively, and in transacting the discipline I could not find much fault, yet great room for improvement.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-04-09"><dateline><date when="1819-04-09">9.</date></dateline><p> Sixth Day See Sarah Grubb's Letters,<note resp="transcr"><emph rend="italic">Some account of the life and religious labours of Sarah Grubb</emph>.</note> page 411: A humble resigned spirit is a gift which I believe was never refused at the altar. It is, while preserved, a continual offering, a sweet smelling sacrifice, the savor of life unto life. In those that believe, it is a bulwark or fortress where in times of desertion, temptation, and trouble the weary soul finds shelter, and all the armor of light against Satan's attacks and fiery darts. Who would not wish to be clothed with such amour and such an impenetrable shield against their grand enemy? Heard a man in town died with the bite of a mad dog, but not a full clear account.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-04-11"><dateline><date when="1819-04-11">11.</date></dateline><p> Have had very high wind. Grows rather dry, but now. First day, fine rain with distant thunder.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-04-11"><dateline><date when="1819-04-11">11.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Forepart I thought very low and poor. Thought we should have a silent meeting, but one another appeared and at last I thought it ended savory and reputedly, a great favor. Fine, warm weather. Heard further accounts about the alarm of mad dogs in Pennsylvania about Makefield and Wrightstown. Two dogs were lately killed on suspicion and a boy bit by one of them here in our neighborhood.</p>
<p>Work whilst it is called to day, was the ancient command, but labor not for the bread that perisheth but for that bread that nourishes the soul up unto eternal life.<note resp="transcr"><persName key="w6912v76">George Fox</persName>?</note> Bodily exercise, we are told, profits but little.<note resp="transcr">1 Timothy 4:8</note> Would it not be well if one half as much care and labor and time were bestowed for the care of the soul as there is for the poor perishing body, which soon returns to dust and comes to nothing, gone and forgotten as though it never had a being in this world? Your fathers, said the prophet, where are they?<note resp="transcr">Zechariah 1:5</note> It has been said truth has ever been suffered most by its professed advocates. A state of ease and lukewarmness, David Hall says, is as bad as open profaneness. And how (see Book of Memorials [1760])
<pb n="12" facs="sc204004"/>
prone people have ever been, when in a state of prosperity and fullness, to sit down in a state of ease and indifference, formality and lukewarmness, prize the gift and forget the giver, and when Israel dwelt in a land not sown, he was holiness to the Lord.<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 2:2-3</note> But when Jeshurun waxed fat, he kicked.<note resp="transcr">Deuteronomy 32:15</note> And see Job 4 and 8<note resp="transcr">Job 4:8</note>: they that sow wickedness, reap the same.
See Hosea 8 and 9<note resp="transcr">Hosea 8:7</note>: they that sow the wind shall reap the whirlwind Gall; 6 and 7<note resp="transcr">Galatians 6:7-8</note>: for whatsoever a man soweth, that shall he reap, and [he] that soweth to his flesh shall reap corruption but he that soweth to the spirit shall reap life everlasting.
Now read the 32 chapter of Deuteronomy, verse 15: but Jeshurun waxed fat and kicked, etc. See what followed to the end of the chapter: the heart cannot be reduced to a vacuum, that is, an empty void. If spiritual things do not occupy it, carnal things will. It is by walking with God and conversing with the doctrine of the cross that we shall become dead to other things and this will go to the root of the evil, while other remedies only lop off the branches (Evangelical Magazine page 151).</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-04-15"><dateline><date when="1819-04-15">15.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. Not unpleasant to think of it, but, alas, how we stand in need of daily bread and unable to keep ourselves from falling, even when only little temptations and provocations attack us. See again Evangelical magazine, page 251: we suffer most from hearts prone to rest in the cold, formal, unexperimental religion of the world, for the unrenewed heart within us is so far from being at enmity with that religion, that it likes it. Our adversary, the Devil, has no quarrel with this, for he knows well that such religion, rested in, is so far from hurting his interest that it will rather promote it.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-04-16"><dateline><date when="1819-04-16">16.</date></dateline><p> A neighbor, an old drunken man, came here very drunk, singing, bawling, and hauling us about till I was almost out of patience. He went away several times, sat down in the woods, and came back several times. It rained pretty hard. A man that kept his credit, all but that of drinking too hard. I could but think of the dismal condition of the poor captives to strong drink, but also of the danger of formalists in religion. Though high in profession, being in a more blamable state and way than they, I will spew them out of my mouth, etc.<note resp="transcr">Revelation 3:16</note></p></div>
<pb n="13" facs="sc204005"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-04-18"><dateline><date when="1819-04-18">18.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. It is said the wise man is happy when he gains his own approbation; the fool, when he gains that of others. As to gaining my own approbation, I hardly know what to say, for in times of poverty and stripping we are ready to call all in question. But as yet feel no condemnation. What others think I must leave, but I am very jealous of myself, seeing how many ways there is for us to be deceived and have cause to believe very many are greatly deceived in themselves – now as formerly, when they believed they were the children of the Lord but were told they were the children of the devil and that his servant they were, whom they obeyed and served.</p>
<p>Many persons mistake the love for the practice of religion<note resp="transcr"><persName key="w66696rh">Lindley Murray</persName>, English Reader, p. 11-12</note>: shall I reward his service with falsehood, shall I forget him who cannot forget me? If his principles are false no apology from himself can make them right; if founded in truth no censures from others can make them wrong.</p>
<p>If you seek to make one rich, study not to increase his stores but diminish his desires. [<persName key="w66696rh">Lindley Murray</persName>] <emph rend="italic">English Reader</emph>: they that desire silver shall not be satisfied with silver and there is [he] that maketh himself rich yet hath nothing. Hope, the balm of life, sooths us under every misfortune. Then is not this hope the greatest of all riches? The righteous hath hope in his death, but the wicked say there is no hope. Then what can riches do for us? He who resigns the world has no temptation to envy, hatred, malice, anger, but is in constant possession of a serene mind. He who follows the pleasures of it – which are in the very nature of it disappointing, is in constant search of care, solicitude, rumors and confusion, XVI. I have lately been reading the writings of that beautiful creature Sarah Grubb, and find many very precious, instructing remarks, especially in page 114 and 118, 119 and 20 and 21, worth treasuring up.</p>
<p>[marginal note] I have lately heard the typhus fever is very mortal at Redstone.</p></div>
<pb n="14" facs="sc204006"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-04-22"><dateline><date when="1819-04-22">22 of the Fourth Month, 1819, Fifth Day, the time of yearly meeting.</date></dateline><p> I am not able to attend it. Dizziness in my head, tottering at our meeting. Not much satisfaction. More humility fear and care is wanting; so again on First Day following. Oh, the dangers of this probationary state!</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-04-30"><dateline><date when="1819-04-30">30.</date></dateline><p> I went with <persName key="w6n05bth">Joseph Roberts</persName> to Westfield Preparative meeting. Small and poor and low, dry and formal, yet it was in good degree satisfactory to me and some others and divers expressed [their satisfaction]. We went to William Evans on the river and lodged and paid several visits, and some were to sweet satisfaction, especially at Benjamin Cox. Next day, came again to Westfield meeting, appointed by William Rickman, lately from England. He had a good deal to say, but he is a feeble old man like myself and his voice but very weak and low. There seemed not much animation, although I was so wearied and feeble I could hardly sit the meeting. I had at last a few sentences to drop to satisfaction, and it appeared to be well accepted, at least by the strangers. We dined with them at <persName key="w6jx3293">Thomas Lippincott's</persName> and got well home, but my little strength was almost exhausted.</p>
<p>They catch abundance of fish this season, by thousands – the like, they say, not known this thirty years. I got two very large indeed. Last spring fruit trees of all sorts were as white as snow with blossoms; this spring all fruit trees full of blossoms but apple trees. On apple trees there is very few blossoms, and, as Blair remarks in his address to youths,<note resp="transcr">contained in <persName key="w66696rh">Lindley Murray</persName>, <emph rend="italic">English Reader</emph></note> if there is no blossoms in the spring, no fruit can be expected in the fall, etc.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-05-02"><head>May 1819</head><dateline><date when="1819-05-02">2.</date></dateline><p> First Day. William Rickman from England was there and had good service – sweetness, savor, and some life. But, alas, how little of that do we experience! If the unlawful love of lawful things did not hinder, of which he told us. Although he is but a little preacher to what some are, I thought he was a monument of mercy, being so preserved in the innocency and humility. He is a preacher of righteousness in life and conduct. I thought it ended savory and well, yet room to improve.</p>
<p>[marginal note] We hear of a pretty deal of sickness round about us.
<pb n="15" facs="sc204007"/>
People do not consider that suffocation is as dangerous as starvation.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-05-04"><dateline><date when="1819-05-04">4 of the Fifth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> A very fine shower and much wanted.</p>
<p>I have been thinking whether suffocation or starvation, at which has proved the most afflicting or destructive to mankind, and concluded that if famine has slain its thousands, suffocation has slain it tens of thousands – especially as to the inward life, the better life, the life of the inward man. As Joseph White said, there was more seed lost on the thorny ground, suffocated and choked with the cares of the world, than any other. And as <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says,<note resp="transcr"><persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName>, <emph rend="italic">No Cross No Crown</emph></note> oh how are the greater part entangled and bemired in their accommodations and conveniences and want help out of the mire and clay, like David making temporary heavens. As Lady Guion says  and as <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says, they like them so well they would never leave them if they could help it, and adds, but divers he must go. The story is as true as sad. But is not the middle way best? The middle way to every step reveal. Let me not heights of woe nor pleasure feel. But petition like Agur we read of whose prayer was: remove far from me vanity and lies, give me neither poverty nor riches, but feed me with food convenient for me, least I be full and deny thee, or least I be poor and steal and take the name of the Lord in vain.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 30:8-9</note> As Walter Rawlie said to his wife, if you can live above want, care for no more – the rest is but vanity. The promise is, all things needful shall be added to them who seek first the Kingdom of God and his righteousness,<note resp="transcr">Luke 12:30-31</note> and that no needful or good thing shall be wished from them. But oh, the scuffle and scramble after more than is needful, wrecking both brain and back! See the voyages they make and the journey they take to lay our treasures on earth. And how many are drowned in destruction and perdition<note resp="transcr">1 Timothy 6:9</note> and how many leave them in the midst of their days and in the end become a fool, like him we read of, who concluded he had good goods laid up in store for many years: thou fool, whose shall those things be which thou hast provided<note resp="transcr">Luke 12:19-20</note> and is there not many such in our days? Strait as the gate and narrow the way that lead to pace and few find it.<note resp="transcr">Matthew 7:14</note></p>
<p>[marginal note] C.R., I am told, said he would not wish a better Heaven than he found here, but, poor man, he was of another mind at the last! Other[s] like him I have heard of.
<pb n="16" facs="sc204008"/>
Would it not be better if people would spend one half their time to please the Lord which is taken up and spent to please the eye, to gratify the lusts of the eye and pride of life, which, the apostle says, is not of the Father but of the world.<note resp="transcr">1 John 2:16</note> As <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName>.<note resp="transcr"><persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName>, <emph rend="italic">No Cross No Crown</emph></note> says, it would be well if they could find one half the time to please the Lord which they spend to please a vain mind, gratifying the lust of the flesh and pride of life. Oh, the growth of pride in fifty years, especially in that of carriages! May we not say with the prophet: their idols are upon their beasts and upon their cattle; their carriages are heavy laden, they are a burden to the weary beasts<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 46:1</note> As <persName key="w6t72g07">John Woolman</persName>,<note resp="transcr"><persName key="w6t72g07">John Woolman</persName>, <emph rend="italic">Journal</emph></note> observed, how he has sympathized with them under their heavy loads and unfeeling drivers. Although the command is positive, be ye not conformed to this world<note resp="transcr">Romans 12:2</note> and many, very many, have deeply suffered for this testimony, even unto death and the most cruel dreadful deaths, even by fire, and stuffed in jails and dungeons, whipping, wracking, stoning, sawing asunder and on the ignominious gallows and banishment. Yet at this day, how blind are the professors of Christianity grown, at this time, respecting the danger of transgressing this command? So very many can take their full swing in gratifying the lusts of the eye and pride of life and still persuade themselves they are Christians, the meek followers of him who said follow me who am meek and lowly of heart,<note resp="transcr">Matthew 11:29</note> who wore a garment without a seam. And respecting these things, oh, how is blindness in part happened to Israel? Pride, it is said, goes before destruction.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 16:18</note> If so, what may we not justly look for or expect? See the 28 chapter of Deuteronomy and 27 of Ezekiel.
[marginal note] Weather very warm and growing.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-05-06"><dateline><date when="1819-05-06">6 of the Fifth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> At our Monthly Meeting our ministers all appeared. As for my part, I was so unwell I could hardly sit, but yet afternoon seemed better and ended satisfactory to me. The weather has been very warm, hot like harvest-time some days past. Some summers past it was said there was frost in every month.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-05-07"><dateline><date when="1819-05-07">7.</date></dateline><p> At about 10 at night a man came and informed us of the death of our ancient sister <persName key="w6tq8ftp">Hannah Buzby</persName>, who seemed to strangle in a fit of coughing and spitting of blood. She had been very poorly and we paid her several visits, as I noted a little back, but was got brave so as to go to her cousin Benjamin's.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Weather very warm and growing.</p></div>
<pb n="17" facs="sc204009"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-05-09"><dateline><date when="1819-05-09">9th of the Fifth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Stormy. We were invited to the burial of our ancient sister <persName key="w6tq8ftp">Hannah Buzby</persName> in the morning, very early. I was taken with a very sick stomach and violent vomiting, but after some hours got some better, but was not able to go to her burial. Our daughter Hannah and granddaughter Mary went, and all seemed well – a large concourse of people. At her desire, they took her over to Ancocas and buried her by her husband. A few weeks back she had been very poorly, but had got quite brave and was out to several neighbors Sixth Day evening. [She] eat supper quite hearty and about 8, was taken with a fit of coughing and spitting of blood. Supposed to have broke a blood vessel in coughing and died in about 3 minutes time. Aged about 85 years. She stood in the station of an elder many years and supported a good name, which Solomon says is better than precious ointment; and the day of their death better than the day of their birth.<note resp="transcr">Ecclesiastes 7:1</note> A great thing to get well through this world and well out of it. She never had any children.</p>
<p>On Seventh Day last Zilla Haines, daughter of our neighbor John Haines, was buried. A blooming youth about 16 years old, she laid ill about ten days or two weeks with a disorder, a fever – they hardly knew what to call it. A few weeks ago I gave her a hint about curling her hair over her forehead. Read 3 of Isaiah. This of curling the hair over the face is much in fashion amongst our youth, but none of them would wish to be laid out in their coffins in such a dress. They live best who live nearest that in which they would wish to die, although too few do so.</p>
<p>First Day morning I was taken with dizziness in my head, sickness at stomach, puking and so could not get to meeting. Very poorly. Latterly some time past, a long spell of cloudy, stormy weather.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-05-20"><dateline><date when="1819-05-20">20.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Month. Fifth [Day]. I got out to our meeting, which I thought was some better than common – some life and savor. It seemed to end in to satisfaction.</p>
<p>See that worthy minister Charles Osborn's papers of Ohio, called the <emph rend="italic">Philanthropist,</emph> select sentences: a great talker will always speak, though nobody minds him or does he mind anybody when they speak to him Zeno? of all virtues made his choice of silence. For by it, said he, I hear other men's imperfections and hide my own (or conceal my own, rather).</p></div>
<pb n="18" facs="sc204010"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-05-23"><dateline><date when="1819-05-23">23 of the Fifth Month, 1819, the First Day.</date></dateline><p> I got so much better as to get to our meeting and through mercy a precious one it was to me. Something evidently owning, and it opened the way for a feeling, uniting nearness and sweetness in parting. Not very lately seen the like.</p>
<p>See Sarah Grubb's letters page 114: divers of the younger sort amongst them have been visited with affliction. The day of the Lord hath come upon all that was lifted up and the projects like the ships of Tarsish, which were intended to go to fetch gold, have been broken early in their setting out, as at Eziongeber, and all their pleasant pictures spoiled. Which have evidently been permitted in mercy, that their affections might be loosened from things transient and perishing and instead thereof things durable and riches and righteousness become their inheritance.</p>
<p>See <emph rend="italic">Evangelical magazine</emph>, page 473, The Constitution of the first Church in Jerusalem: the first Church was constituted. Utility and simplicity distinguished its organization. The officers essential to its prosperity were elders who exercised the pastoral function and deacons who superintended its temporal concerns. These were chosen by the suffrage of the people. The apostolic office, though by far the most eminent and adapted to the exercise of the Church, in its infant state. We have the testimony of one, who was never suspected of partiality for the gospel “that the primitive Church was united only by the ties of faith and charity; independence and equality formed the basis of its construction.” To the morals of its members the most rigorous attention was paid and discipline in all its awful inflexibility was impartially maintained. The disciples of the immaculate Jesus trod in the footsteps of this glorious leader, and emulated each other in zeal for good works. What humility, what forbearance, what brotherly love, what self denial, what kindness towards all men and devotion towards God marked the character of the primitive believers! The doctrine of the first Church, the divine energy of the Holy Ghost in the renewal of the sinners' mind to repentance, the experimental enjoyments of divine truth and its influence upon our lives and tempers were constantly inculcated and the absolute necessity of faith in these doctrines was invariably urged upon all who were admitted into Christian communities. Something more serious, deep, and weighty than barely dipping the body in water. No oppressor, no extortioner among them, but a spirit and disposition quite contrary to that. A great difference between that and a state of ease and bear formality and lukewarmness now prevalent.</p></div>
<pb n="19" facs="sc204011"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-05-27"><dateline><date when="1819-05-27">27.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. I went to the burial of our neighbor Arthur Burdil's daughter, nearly grown up to a young woman. Her disorder was much like Haines's daughter, who died a few days ago. She was much out of her senses whilst she lay ill about two weeks with a kind of a fever. She was buried at our graveyard and then we went to our meeting, and through mercy I was favored both at the graveyard and at our meeting to come off without condemnation – a feeling of something that costs out fear. But alas, what a hard thing it is, as <persName key="w6b38kp0">Thomas Ross</persName> says, when we are right to keep so<note resp="transcr">Wagstaffe, <emph rend="italic">Piety Promoted</emph></note> of ourselves we cannot. Watchfulness and prayer.</p>
<p>A lad, Moses Watson's son, six or seven, next neighbor, has a son who has lain very ill two weeks past, but is getting better. These somewhat new cases but seem not much alarming.</p>
<p>To keep right, what humility, what fear, patience, what watchfulness, what resignation it requires. But as [Edward] Young on Resignations says:<quote type="poem">
<l>What cannot resignation do?</l>
<l>It wonders can perform</l>
<l>That powerful charm thy will be done</l>
<l>Can lay the lowest storm.</l></quote>
<note resp="transcr">Edward Young, “Resignation”</note></p>

<p>Again, see Evangelical Magazine, page 373: as God is a perfect being, he cannot act amiss; as he is a sovereign, he has a right to dispose of the affairs of his creatures as he pleases; as he is infinitely good, he wills in all things the happiness of his people, creatures here, and their eternal bliss hereafter.</p>
<p>That it is the Christian's privilege follows of course; what is his duty is also his privilege. Duty is also his privilege. It is his privilege as it is his happiness, and we are so far only truly happy as we are truly and resigned to the divine will. As to be given up to our own wills is misery and distress, so to know no will but God's is the summit of our happiness. Know, my son, says Thomas à Kempis that nothing hurts thee so much as thy own will. Self [is] the greatest enemy; they that conquers self conquer their greatest enemy.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-05-30"><dateline><date when="1819-05-30">30 of the Fifth Month, 1819, First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting although hardly able to go or sit, I thought it but a low, poor, shut up time to what some are. Yet I thought it ended pretty well and I was glad I was there.</p>
<p>We read in Scripture that the Lord's will is our sanctification and preservation,<note resp="transcr">1 Thessalonians 4:3</note> but has not self-will in men proved their destruction? Not only in the case of Haman, but [in] numberless numbers of instances it has proved their destruction.</p></div>
<pb n="20" facs="sc204012"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-06-01"><head>June 1819</head><dateline><date when="1819-06-01">About 1st of the Sixth Month 1819.</date></dateline><p>I have had a very poorly spell of dizziness and swimming in my head. Sick stomach and puking, could hardly walk.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-06-03"><dateline><date when="1819-06-03">Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting silent and shut up. As to myself, poorly.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-06-06"><dateline><date when="1819-06-06">6 was our select meeting.</date></dateline><p> Very poor and destitute of life, as I thought. Forepart perhaps some fared better, but poorly as I was. At last I ventured and was helped, and it ended savory and satisfactory, a sense of feeling nearness. I would thought there were a state and disposition of mind prevalent that could say with the prophet, the zeal of thy house hath eaten me up,<note resp="transcr">Psalm 69:9</note> etc. Come and see my zeal for the Lord,<note resp="transcr">2 Kings 10:16</note> etc. Many can say, come and see my improvement on my farm, etc., but too few disposed to say, come let us go up to the House of the Lord, etc.</p>
<p>First Day. At our meeting, a poor, low, shut up time to me. One of our ministers took up all the latter part of the meeting, but still if there was any life or animation it was hid from me, although I was not destitute of suitable matter. Lowness. 3rd hour we went to the burial of Dr. Joshua Hollinshead. In the midst of his days, a captive to strong drink, to be feared; shortened his days with it. Taken in fits and lay a few days unsensible. Left a wife and several children. It is wonderful to think and see how full of people our country is got to be. There was a great concourse of people of goodly appearance, as to the outward evident demonstrations of a sufficient care for the body, and as much evidence and tokens of unconcernedness for the soul. I ventured to break silence amongst them and have cause to repent it. This evening, my cousin Henry Warrington and I, being nominated by our Monthly Meeting, had an opportunity whilst a young man who lately brought a certificate from Plainfield. To good satisfaction; something owning and savory. So the day closed in peace, though very feeble and tottering.
<pb n="21" facs="sc204013"/>
As to the state of religion in the present day, in too general [of a] way, people seem to treat it with such a trifling indifferent way and so intoxicated with prosperity that they seem to be settled down at ease and fallen a sleep on the lap of this world, like Sampson on the lap of Delilah, where he lost his strength and his eyesight. And how unfit are they to hear whilst in such a state of intoxication and slumber. I wonder if they are not in a state harder to reach than the people were in Peter's days, when 3,000 were converted to the Christian faith at the preaching of his first sermon, 2,000 at the next. But what people did ever bear prosperity? See John Hoyland's works,<note resp="transcr">John Hoyland, <emph rend="italic">An Epitome of the history of the world</emph></note> page 49, 2 volume, the dreadful judgments denounced upon the Jews for their wickedness, infidelity, and unbelief: their hearts shall be made fat and their ears heavy and their eyes shut. See also the dreadful judgments, 32 chapter of Hoyland's works, against the greatest most flourishing cities that ever were greeted in the world and the most populous nations, as Babylon, Egypt, Tyre, Sodom, Ninevah and many others. As <persName key="w65q5g7f">Samuel Fothergill</persName> says, luxury and pride has been the downfall and ruin of the most flourishing kingdoms that ever were in the world.<note resp="transcr">Fothergill, <emph rend="italic">The necessity and divine excellency of a life of purity and holiness</emph></note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-06-10"><dateline><date when="1819-06-10">10.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting. Edwin D. Utley of Philadelphia and <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> were there and both had considerable acceptable service and I thought if I had time and ability, I had pertinent matter –but we must give way to strangers. It appeared to be a lively time. I had some satisfaction, although at last I was so overcome with faintness and dizziness they were forced to help me out of meeting to a friend's house before the meeting concluded, and it was with difficulty I got home. But after some rest, got better. See the words of Elisha, 2 Kings verses 2 and 14: Where is the Lord God of Elijah? When I think of our meetings and the abundance of preaching we have and the little growth and affects, I am ready to say; what is become of the ancient dew we read of that descended upon the Mountains of Zion<note resp="transcr">Psalm 133:3</note> and the celestial showers that our first Friends so frequently mention, which was frequently witnessed in their meetings to the tendering and contriting their hearts, even to tears, so that in some of their meetings there was scarcely a dry eye?</p>
<p>As Richard Davies says (see his Book page 35), we wished to feel the Lord amongst us in all our coming together. When the First Day of the week came we went to a meeting at W. Panes, at the wild copse, where we had a silent meeting, and, though it was silent from words, yet the word of the Lord God was among us; it was as a hammer and a fire; it was sharper than any two-edged sword; it pierced our inward parts. It melted and brought us into tears [so] that there was scarcely a dry eye among us. The Lord's blessed power overshadowed our meeting and I could have said that God alone was master of that assembly. But alas, where are we and how is it with us in these days of peace and plenty?</p>
<p>[marginal note] A pinching time of dry weather. It is like it will cut off thousands of loads of hay. So warm it was very oppressive.
<pb n="22" facs="sc204014"/>
When the First Day of the week came we went to a meeting at W. Panes, at the wild cop [?], where we had a silent meeting, and, though it was silent from words, yet the word of the Lord God was among us; it was as a hammer and a fire; it was sharper than any two-edged sword; it pierced our inward parts. It melted and brought us into tears [so] that there was scarcely a dry eye among us. The Lord's blessed power overshadowed our meeting and I could have said that God alone was master of that assembly. But alas, where are we and how is it with us in these days of peace and plenty?
Our first Friends tell of heart-tendering times they had at their meetings. At one, they say, the floor where they sat was so sprinkled with tears that it looked as if there had been a sprinkling of rain upon it. But alas, how rare a thing it is nowadays to see a tear or tokens of contrition or brokenness of heart. For under the most powerful ministry that we have instead of a tear they are often seen to be drowsy and sit nodding. Powerful preachers and dull hearers. As it was said to the Prophet, they come before thee as the people cometh; they sit before thee as my people; they hear thy words but will not do them; each one returns to his covetousness.<note resp="transcr">Ezekiel 33:31</note> As a certain writer observes, they go to meeting and are pleased with their fine preaching return and remain just the same. A broken heart and a contrite spirit, it is said, the Lord will not despise [Psalm 51:17], but he loathes lukewarmness, formality, mockery, and hypocrisy.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-06-13"><dateline><date when="1819-06-13">13.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Very feeble, but I got to our meeting. Forepart I thought was very poor and low and I hardly able to stand the torrent of idleness and prescribing indifferences, but it grew better and at last I thought it end savory and satisfactory. See [<persName key="w66696rh">Lindley Murray's</persName>] <emph rend="italic">English Reader</emph>, page 256: no worldly enjoyments are adequate to the high designs and powers of an immortal spirit. Fancy paints them at a distance with splendid colors, but possession unveil the fallacy. 257: for worldly happiness ever tends to destroy itself by corrupting the heart. It fosters the loose and violent passions. It engenders noxious habits and taints the mind with false delicacy, which makes it feel a thousand unreal evils.</p></div>
<pb n="23" facs="sc204015"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-06-16"><dateline><date when="1819-06-16">16 of the Sixth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> Our daughter Abigail and I went to the quarterly select meeting at Evesham, and an open, owning, favored times it was. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> had large, extensive, pertinent service. I was favored to keep up.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-06-17"><dateline><date when="1819-06-17">17.</date></dateline><p> Was our quarterly meeting, which was very large abundance of young people. I thought forepart the waters seemed very low and no wonder. Very many very idle they are no pottererors inwardly concerns they are not trifling and indifferent about earthly treasures but to wait to feel the Lord amongst, as our first Friends say they did in all their comings together. Is strange sort of talk nowadays, although the Divine Master has promised to be with the two or three gathered in his name. Yet <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> was raised in great eminence in the exercise of his most distinguished gift, and I thought it brought the meeting into a precious state of feeling solemnity and it was on the whole a favored, open, good meeting. Sweetness and feeling nearness at parting. I know no people favored in like manner with such a powerful living ministry. May the ancient complaint never be applicable to us: they come before thee as the people cometh they hear thy word but will not do them; each one returns again to his covetousness.<note resp="transcr">Ezekiel 33:31</note> And again, as one observes, they got to their meeting and are pleased with their fine preaching but go home and remain just the same, without improvement. Were unto the Corasin [Chorazin] and Bethsaida if the great and mighty works which have been done in Tire [Tyre] and Sidon they would have repented long ago in sackcloth and ashes,<note resp="transcr">Luke 10:13</note> and is it not probable many who have not had the like opportunities would have better improved?</p>
<p>We now hear of great alarms in Philadelphia of mad dogs; that they have resolved to kill all found in the streets and that several have died of late in divers places with the bite of mad dogs. And it is in the news that there have been of late most terrible hail storms in divers places and the grain much destroyed.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Many weeks very dry weather. Although divers times great signs, but went of with very little. Crops of grass very light, indeed.
<pb n="24" facs="sc204016"/>
See Ezekiel 14 and 21: when I send my four sore judgments upon Jerusalem: the sword and the famine and the noisome beast and the pestilence. I know not what these noisome beasts were and whither or not these mad dogs may not be called noisome beasts, with which the City of Philadelphia is at this time so much alarmed (several having lately died with the bite of mad dogs). So they come to a resolve to kill all the dogs found in the streets. In the time of the Revolutionary war, when the English army lay in the City, many were pinched and straitened to get bread and it was said some of the nobility, gentry, or highest class were seen to carry a sack of meal. In the time of the pestilential Yellow Fever, they say several thousands were swept away in a few months and many fled till the streets looked desolate. Many houses great and fair were left desolate without inhabitance [inhabitants]. So we may observe they have had a taste of these 4 sore judgments, although as yet but very light to what former ages and nations have felt of them. Read the Lamentations of Jeremiah.
[marginal note] 10: Tenth Month the City of Baltimore visited with the Yellow Fever so that they encamp in the fields, says an eyewitness.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-06-20"><dateline><date when="1819-06-20">20 Sixth Month was First Day.</date></dateline><p> I have had a thought of attending Cropwell meeting some weeks. <persName key="w6mt4j9v">Joseph Cowperthwaite</persName> came this morning and took me there, although I was so poorly I could hardly keep up on my feet. The meeting but small and religion very low, yet there is a remnant of choice friends. Although things seemed low and I very poorly, it was at last an open, owning, satisfactory time in general. Openness, sweetness, unity, and feeling nearness at parting. The fatigue, I could hardly bear.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-06-23"><dateline><date when="1819-06-23">23.</date></dateline><p> We have had a spell of very dry weather. No rain many weeks; prospect of great scarcity of hay and grass. See Deuteronomy 28 and 12: Blessings promised for obedience and curses for disobedience. 12: the Lord shall open unto thee his good treasure the heaven to give the rain unto thy Lord in his season, etc. And see Jeremiah 4 and 25, a Lamentation for Judah: I beheld and lo all the birds of the Heavens were fled. I have admired how scarce very few birds there are now. When we used to have such great multitudes flocks of various sorts, now they are very few indeed.
<pb n="25" facs="sc204017"/>
There is a language, a voice, in the signs of the times. As it was said, if they will not hearken to the first sign, they will hearken to the voice of the other sign.<note resp="transcr">Exodus 4:8</note> The death among the hedges, just after they had got in the way of fencing their farms with hedge fence, which they concluded would endure always and so save the timber; the death amongst the peach trees, our most choice delicious fruit (a worm growed at the root like Jonah's gourd); a death amongst the trees of the woods, the hickory, the most choice for fuel; a death among the white oak timber, the most excellent for building houses or carriages; a death among the black and Spanish oaks, whose bark is the best for tanning leather. Then came a destroying insect among the bees and deprived us of our honey, our chiefest sweet. Now this summer there appears a kind of an uncommon worm on the cherry trees that threatens their destruction. Doth these things seem like blessings for obedience, or like threatenings and judgments for disobedience? Do they not seem like the tokens of divine displeasure?
See Canticles 2:12 verse: the time of the singing of birds is come.<note resp="transcr">Song of Solomon 2:12</note> I remember when the singing of birds was charming and very pleasant. I have stopped on the road to hear the mocking birds and threshers and other sorts sing. And then whippoorwill in the evening used frequently to come close to our doors and sing, but there has no such thing been heard this season. As the prophet said, the summer or birds of the heaven birds are fled.<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 4:25</note> But these are frivolous things, hardly worth notice with very many, although we see the prophets noticed them. See the prophet Joel: the locust and the caterpillar and cankerworm, my great army, which I sent among you.<note resp="transcr">Joel 2:25</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-06-24"><dateline><date when="1819-06-24">24.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our preparative meeting. Although idleness, indifferency, formality, and lukewarmness seems to threaten us with desolation there seems yet a little stirrings of life, although I am so poorly I can hardly keep up. Yet at last I thought it ended with a degree of life and savor.</p>
<p>It holds yet very pinching, hot, dry weather. Grass is much scorched. Such a prospect of scarcity of hay has scarcely been seen.</p></div>
<pb n="26" facs="sc204018"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-06-27"><dateline><date when="1819-06-27">27.</date></dateline><p> Sixth Month, 1819. First Day. At our meeting. Our beloved friend <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> – she has been confined at home unwell several months – took up most of the time of the meeting. Had acceptable service, but to me it was a low time. I had no ability to say a word, although I thought I had pertinent matter.</p>
<p>See 2 volume Hoyland's work, page 322. After a relation of the miserable, degraded state of the idolatry of many nations and the notorious principles of some abominable infidels and deists and atheists, opposing the Christian religion and the law's reasonable and holy institution, he says: oh, Israel, happy are we; for the things that are pleasing to God are made known unto us. He hath not dealt so with any nation.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-06-29"><dateline><date when="1819-06-29">29.</date></dateline><p> See Leviticus 26 chapter: blessings promised for obedience; curses threatened for disobedience – very great on both hands. See again Deuteronomy, 28 chapter: the blessings for obedience very great indeed, and the curses for disobedience as great. And have they not been verified in nations and ages to these days?</p>
<p>See and read the Lamentations of Jeremiah, the dismal, distressed state of the people because of their disobedience.</p>
<p>The prophet said: though the fig tree shall not blossom, neither [shall] fruit be in the vine (scarcely any blossoms on our apple trees this season), the labor of the olive shall fail and the fields should yield no meat, yet will I rejoice in the Lord and joy in the God of my salvation.<note resp="transcr">Habakkuk 3:17-8</note> This was a religion worth something more than mere name, talk, or poor, dry form. We have had no rain many weeks; grass pasture much scorched up, even where they had marled and manured their meadows. And where, a few weeks a ago, their creatures were up to their eyes in pasture, it is now dried up scorched brown with the drought. The state of those in these days riding in their jumping chariots is very different from the state of those when an ass's head was sold for 5 pounds or four score shekels of silver and 4 part of a cob of Dover dung for 5. See the 27 or 28 Chapter of Ezekiel: the fall of that great nation there attended for their disobedience.</p></div>
<pb n="27" facs="sc204019"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-07-01"><head>July 1819</head><dateline><date when="1819-07-01">1 of the Seventh Month, Fifth Day, 1819.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Small harvest time. To me satisfactory. I had a feeling that cast out fear, like one who said, “I feel as if you could not hurt me after he had been delivering some very close doctrine.”</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-07-04"><dateline><date when="1819-07-04">4 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. We had a great deal of preaching, but it was a shut up. Poor time to me. This afternoon at 4 we went to the burial of Sarah Warner, just arrived to the age of a young woman. She fell out of a tree picking cherries, broke her arm, and bruised her breast so that she died after laying in great affliction a few days. She sent for me and I went to see her several times, but had not much satisfaction. <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> had something to say amongst the people, but I thought it was but a poor time as to any things of life. They are a most exceeding poor family lately moved near us. Most of the family seem to have very little care or concern for either body or soul. This the third young woman that died now within a few days or weeks, the houses in sight of one another, just as they arrived to the age of young woman.</p>
<p>I have observed at burials how ready and handy many are to do anything wherein the creaturely part can be active, such as carrying the corpse, or covering it up. But as to a travel of spirit for the arisurings [arising? assuring?] of life, oh, how ignorant! And what a strange, mysterious thing it is in these days, although many goodly people! I thought the commendable Christian care of the neighbors towards this poor girl in her affliction and towards the poor family deserved encouragement.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-07-08"><dateline><date when="1819-07-08">8.</date></dateline><p> Seventh Month. Fifth Day. At our Monthly. I thought on the whole it was pretty well.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-07-09"><dateline><date when="1819-07-09">9.</date></dateline><p> I went to Evesham Monthly Meeting. Waters very low. It mostly is so in harvest time; people work hard. Very dry, warm weather. I found it hard getting along, but through mercy got through to good satisfaction, although I was not able to sit the meeting till quite the conclusion.</p>
<p>We now hear much talk and alarm of the Yellow Fever in town. Dry weather yet continues, although we hear of rain east and south some distance. Clouds have gone round us, and the grass is very much scorched up with the drought. I am told some are forced to begin to fodder, and that like to be very scarce. I think I have hardly ever seen the like, although I have seen near eighty years. The harvest generally very good and now nearly over. The Indian corn look very well yet.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Confusion in town about killing their dogs.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Dulled, as with opium (as M. Mollineaux says), settled on their lees and sat down at ease.</p></div>
<pb n="28" facs="sc204020"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-07-11"><dateline><date when="1819-07-11">11 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting, but not to much satisfaction. And without it, time and labor seems lost.</p>
<p>We are busily engaged getting hay. Weather here very hot and dry; grass and pasture very much dried up. I do not remember the like prospect of scarcity of hay and pasture. It is said many are forced to begin to fodder already.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-07-15"><dateline><date when="1819-07-15">15.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting, but so unwell I was not fit to go there. Wearied myself over much look[ing] after my hired men. I thought it was a very poor, low time and I had a feeling and near sympathy with the lukewarm, worldly formalists which spirit now threatens us with dissolation. I said in my heart, shall we fall victims to this spirit of ease after so much has been done for us – the suffering of the martyrs and our worthy predecessors paving and making the way smooth and easy for us? I believe it's true, it is harder to stand wheedle proof than battle proof; some who stood faithful under suffering fell in times of prosperity.</p>
<p>Last week we were invited to the burial of Mary Ann Stokes, my half sister, Hope Stokes's daughter, a blooming young woman. Died with a disorder in the head; was ill but a few days and much out of her senses. Our horses were gone to market and we could none of us go to the burial.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-07-18"><dateline><date when="1819-07-18">18.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. It has been remarked that where there is many to eat and few to work it brings the labor hard on a few. Forepart was hard work to stand against the prevailing stream and current of idleness, but through mercy it growd better and ended at last lively, reputably, savory, and satisfactory to me and I believe to others generally.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-07-22"><dateline><date when="1819-07-22">22.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our preparative meeting, to me poor and low. It holds very dry weather here, although after a show for rain. The creatures begin to be much pinched for pasture, and I am told that some hogs have died for want of water.</p>
<p>[marginal note] I have no account of any rain since the middle of the Sixth Month here, except a little sprinkling but like a dew.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-07-25"><dateline><date when="1819-07-25">25.</date></dateline><p> I got to our meeting though very poorly, having had a severe spell of vomiting and lax, which it said is much complained of. It is a great thing to be truly resigned to be anything or nothing, to be like the clay in the hands of the potter or like the ax or the saw in the hand of him that shapeth it, to [be] taken up or laid by at the master pleasure. A shut time to me, but an open time to <persName key="w67b4w4h">Joseph Justice</persName>.</p></div>
<pb n="29" facs="sc204021"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-07-26"><dateline><date when="1819-07-26">26 of the Seventh Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> We are favored with a fine shower of rain! I believe not such a rain this six or eight weeks. But the ground is got so dry it will take a great deal to soak it. I do think I never did see the fields look so mournful and the grass so scorched up, yet the Indian corn has stood it admirably where it was well tended and it looks as if there might yet be a good crop if it should be wet enough. But we must needs see how easily all our labors can be blasted or blessed. What a pity it is poor mortals cannot bear prosperity, that the fruitfulness of the land should cause barrenness in the minds of the people, as it appears it has ever been apt to do. Fullness of bread and abundance of idleness charged on Sodom; so we read Jesuran waxed fat and kicked.<note resp="transcr">Deuteronomy 32:15</note> The full stomach loathes the honey comb.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 27:7</note> And as the old proverb says, plenty makes dainty. And the prophet said, when thou has eaten and art full then beware lest thou forget the Lord.<note resp="transcr">Deuteronomy 8:10-11</note> Oh, sorrowful! The more we are favored to live in fullness, the more forgetful, unthankful, and ungrateful. See the word of the prophet: oh, ye foolish people and unwise! Do ye thus requite the Lord?<note resp="transcr">Deuteronomy 32:6</note> I think I remember seeing some words of one of our worthy first Friends, on this wise: oh prosperity, prosperity, what hast thou done? Not all the persecutors or open apostates that ever rose up against us has ever done us that hurt that prosperity had done. Many stood firm in suffering and fell by prosperity.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-07-29"><dateline><date when="1819-07-29">29: Seventh Month Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting, and a lively, open, owning time it was to me to good satisfaction. What an unspeakable favor, for I have felt so poorly and feeble of late that I have thought it was almost over with me and of laying by.</p>
<p>Very hot, dry weather again, although a few days ago we had a fine shower.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-01"><head>August 1819</head><dateline><date when="1819-08-01">1 of the Eighth Month First Day.</date></dateline><p> We went to Evesham meeting on a very dry time; I thought it was inwardly and outwardly like Mount Gilboa – neither dew nor rain nor fields of offering. I can make no account of such meetings without it is in the advantage and necessity of suffering.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Heard of the death of Jane Cooper the Second of Woodbury, and of Benjamin Lippincott's wife of Evesham (died of a consumption as did one of her sisters a few years ago).</p></div>
<pb n="30" facs="sc204022"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-04"><dateline><date when="1819-08-04">4.</date></dateline><p> Eighth Month, 1819. See [Thomas Clarkson's] <emph rend="italic">An Essay on Slavery, </emph>page 102: what is imprudence or what is vice but a departure from every man's own interest? And yet these are the characteristics of more than half the world! There are sins of omission and sins of commission, and it may be that sins of omission make up far the greatest part of the catalogue of the crimes of very many. See <emph rend="italic">Evangelical Magazine.<note resp="transcr"><emph rend="italic">The Beauties of the Evangelical Magazine</emph>, vol 2.</note></emph>,  page 322: Adam had dominion over the beast of the field, fowls of the air, and fishes of the sea. He had the free use of them, of all the creatures so far as they were capable of ministering to his comfort. But the Summum Bonum, or greatest chiefest and superior happiness, was his sweet sense of the divine favor this is and ever will remain the confirmation both of human and angelic felicity. I believe this sweet sense of Divine favor was intended for the chief happiness of mankind and nothing short of it. Is not this sweet sense of the Divine favor that the righteous in all ages have hungered and thirsted after, and nothing else could ever satisfy or fill them? This was the gift of the Divine Master: my peace I give unto you; this it is that can make a prison as pleasant as a palace, or bread and water as satisfactory as the most delicious dainties. This sweet sense of Divine favor, the prophet David says, is better than life<note resp="transcr">Psalm 63:3</note> and in his presence fullness of joy<note resp="transcr">Psalm 16:11</note> But it is not so with all this world can afford. Set your affections on things above and not on things below or in the earth.<note resp="transcr">Colossians 3:2</note> Oh, the dismal and miserable state of men formerly and down to these days, for want of setting their hearts on heavenly things – miserable here and hereafter, unspeakable.</p>
<p>[marginal note] What is it that can make a death bed pleasant to the righteous but peace of mind?</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-05"><dateline><date when="1819-08-05">5.</date></dateline><p> Eighth Month was our Monthly Meeting, and I believe it was a favored, open, owning, satisfactory time.</p>
<p>See [John] Everard's <emph rend="italic">Sermons</emph>, page 232: know a minute's feeling spiritually is worth seven years speaking. To feel these things spiritually is to be a door keeper in the house of God, to talk of them or only to know them are but the tabernacle of Mesheck and the tents of Kedar, etc.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 120:5</note>
<pb n="31" facs="sc204023"/>
See [John] Everard's works, page 25: Satan is like a thief, and therefore steals away and departs in the night, even while the good man of the house is asleep. Security is the bane of the soul, when men are careless and in the night of ignorance. And again, see Solomon's words: how long will thou sleep, oh sluggard? How long will it be ere thou awake out of sleep, a little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands to sleep? So shall thy poverty come as one that traveleth and thy want as an armed man.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 6:9-11</note> <persName key="w6cg1kgr">John Churchman</persName>,<note resp="transcr"><persName key="w6cg1kgr">John Churchman</persName>, <emph rend="italic">Present state of church discipline in our society</emph></note> on the training up of children, says: prepare their minds to receive the power of truth, without which they never can be happy. Without this, there will be a want which all this world cannot satisfy, with all its boasted treasures or glittering pleasures.
[marginal note] Whilst men slept, the enemy sowed tares.<note resp="transcr">Matthew 13:25</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-08"><dateline><date when="1819-08-08">8 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. As to me, shut up in silence; but not so with several others. Pretty well at last, though not that clothing and sweetness as at some other times.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-10"><dateline><date when="1819-08-10">10.</date></dateline><p> <persName key="w6wx87x7">My wife</persName> and me and Hannah went to see our sister Hope Stokes and her children at Upper Evesham. We found one of her daughters very poorly with the dysentery, (which is now a frequent complaint, particularly towards and at Salem), but she is getting better. We had a pretty little satisfactory religious opportunity with them, which I found hard to come at; it is so much out of fashion. They told me of a lad, about 19, was sitting on his horse talking with some others and some hogs came running by, frighted his horse, [which] flung him down and sat his foot on his belly and he died in a few days near Upper Evesham meeting house.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-13"><dateline><date when="1819-08-13">13 was Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting there was several spoke, but if the dead are not raised preaching is vain, said the apostle.<note resp="transcr">1 Corinthians 15:14</note> Life and savor I thought was wanting; without it, all is in vain.
<pb n="32" facs="sc204024"/>
I will send grass into your fields for your cattle,<note resp="transcr">Deuteronomy 11:15</note>; ten acres of vineyard shall but one bath<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 5:10</note> etc.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-13"><dateline><date when="1819-08-13">13 of the Eighth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> The weather continues very hot and dry. Pasture very much dried up, so that the creatures (horses, cattle, and sheep) begin to be very much pinched for pasture. And I never remember such a complaint of a scarcity of hay for next winter, and many forced to begin to fodder. It look[s] as if there will be great scarcity of hay before next spring. Many poor people cannot get any hay for their cow, and are offering to sell them now, but cannot except at a very low price. Many farmers complain of very poor crops of hay, and some are buying hay now at twenty dollars a ton, but I believe it is a rare thing to find any to be sold at any rate. Milk cows gone dry for want of pasture, it is said.</p>
<p>See my Memorandums two years ago, in 1817: what dreadful destruction in divers places by the vast floods of rain, many mills of various sorts and even dwelling houses swept away, and many lives lost, and very many reduced to poverty and dizziness by the great floods of rain. Happy for them who have such a religion as the prophet Habbakuk had, who could say, although the fields should yield no meat, yet will I rejoice in the Lord and joy in the God of my salvation.<note resp="transcr">Habakkuk 3:17</note> Now read the 5th chapter of Job, particularly 22 verse: at destruction and famine thou shalt laugh. Neither shalt thou be afraid of the beasts of the earth. Lo this, we have searched it, so it is hear it and know it for thy good promises to the righteous. Here is a religion worth something, a righteousness that will do not only in fair weather but in the greatest storm. Jonah said, when he went down to the bottom of the mountain, yet will I look again towards thy holy temple.<note resp="transcr">Jonah 2:4</note></p>
<p>[marginal note] Again see Job 12 chapter and 15 verse: Behold, he withholeth the waters and they dry up; also, he sendeth them out and they overturn the earth.</p></div>
<pb n="33" facs="sc204025"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-15"><dateline><date when="1819-08-15">15th of the Eighth Month 1819 First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. To me, a very poor time. Another stepped in as one of old said. We went to see our cousin Henry Warrington, who is just going to set of to Ohio Yearly Meeting with Henry Hull of New England. I was poorly, poor inwardly and outwardly. Hardly clothing to hide my nakedness.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-19"><dateline><date when="1819-08-19">19.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> was there and had acceptable service, and after him I had an open, owning, satisfactory time. Openness, sweetness, and feeling nearness at parting. What an unspeakable favor.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-22"><dateline><date when="1819-08-22">22 of the Eighth Month, First Day.</date></dateline><p> I went to Haddonfield meeting, which was a suffering time to me. Religion [has] dwindled into the poor, dry formality in too general a way, though there are a remnant of solid, worthy, Friends. They have been striped of several acceptable ministers of latter years. I found it hard work to stand up amongst them, but at last I did attend it and whilst I was speaking, a young man was taken in a violent convulsion fit, which so disturbed and unsettled the minds of the people that the meeting soon concluded. And I had no satisfaction being thus prevented, yet they appeared loving and kind.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-23"><dateline><date when="1819-08-23">[23] Second Day.</date></dateline><p> See religious tracts,<note resp="transcr">Hunt is in error. In 1819, the Female Tract Association of Friends (Philadelphia) issued a tract including accounts of two English Quakers, Ann Knight and Mary Weston. The material referred to concerns Mary Weston (1771-1797) rather than Knight. </note> words of a young woman who died about 15 years of age, Ann Knight. She was convinced that applying the mind to some useful branches of knowledge proportionate to its capacity greatly contributed to preserve it from the love of dissipation by opening a source of superior enjoyment. Is not this very greatly wanting amongst our youth at this present day?</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-24"><dateline><date when="1819-08-24">[24] Third Day.</date></dateline><p> I went and mended two pumps, one for Joseph Evans and one for Joseph Rogers. I have not earned so much money in a day for several years past.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-25"><dateline><date when="1819-08-25">[25] Fourth Day.</date></dateline><p> I thought I would try the truth of what Solomon says, that it is better to go to the house of mourning than the house of mirth.<note resp="transcr">Ecclesiastes 7:2</note> So went to see a very poor old widow and also to see a poor old man many years very much crippled with the palsy. I left them in tenderness and tears. A neighbor was showing where the frost had killed his vine tree. <persName key="w6n87x9b">Job Scott</persName> mentions a frost in the Eighth Month.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Although we have had very much hot, dry weather after a heavy shower about the 22 Eighth Month, they say there was frost. <persName key="w6n87x9b">Job Scott</persName> takes notice of a frost in the Eighth Month as something like a threatening. How many ways there are to blast or bless!</p></div>
<pb n="34" facs="sc204026"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-26"><dateline><date when="1819-08-26">26 of the Eighth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our preparative meeting. I thought it was a lively good meeting throughout to my satisfaction, except answering our queries – the waters seemed low and things very dry and dull, yet there were many lively pertinent remarks. The love of this world hath wounded us, and very many are like those who have taken too much opium or anodine [anodyne], as one says, dulled with opiates. But as for the taking care of temporal interest and accomodations for the poor body, bright and lively enough, no cost or pains spared. Many now come to meeting in such painted carriages as their fathers would have been ashamed to ride in, and their testimony against pride and superfluity almost trodden under foot, which our first Friends suffered so greatly for, is almost lost sight of amongst many of this young generation. For as a dear, innocent youth said when I spoke to him about his very high, crowned, narrow brimmed hat, he cryed out, law, I did not know that anybody thought there was any harm in such things as that! And his father said it was very difficult to get any other sort. So people may go on and conform to this world contrary to that express command: be not conformed to this world<note resp="transcr">Romans 12:2</note> and yet persuade themselves they are the follower of Christ and very good Christians. But as our ancients used to say, surely will not the Lord visit for these things.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-28"><dateline><date when="1819-08-28">28.</date></dateline><p> Pinching, dry weather. The little rains seems but like dews, soon gone, and there seem like to be but very few potatoes or buckwheat, but do not know. This night, a fine rain again like an eastwardly storm. See Psalms 32: 9th verse: be ye not as the horse or the mule, which hath no understanding. See the worldling and the drunkard – how degraded below the brutal part of the creations, and how many of such degraded beings there are, like Remus, embraced the present world. I have known several who have said they did want a better Heaven than what they had here in their earthly enjoyment. And as <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says, they would never leave them if they could help it and have their way.<note resp="transcr"><persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName>, <emph rend="italic">No Cross, No Crown.</emph></note> I think there is good instruction in what an old drunken man said to his neighbor, who asked him to go with him to look at his meadow, which was heavy loaded with the choicest of grass. Walking amongst it, the old drunkard said: well, I should not like to have such meadow as this. The other says: No? Why?
<pb n="35" facs="sc204027"/>
Why, if I had, I think I should not be willing to die and leave it and I think you won't be willing to leave it. The love of this world operates like opium or annodine [anodyne], stupifies and besots and – as the Scriptures says – drowns people in destruction and perdition.<note resp="transcr">1 Timothy 6:9</note> And how many captives and victims there are who are snared in these two traps, drunkenness and worldly mindedness? If drunkenness has slain its thousands, may it not be said that earthly mindedness has slain its ten thousand? Have not many degraded themselves beneath the brutal part of the creation? As I heard a worthy Friend once tell his drunken brother, thou art worse than the brute beasts. So like the heath in the desert know not when good cometh,<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 17:6</note> the ox knows his owner and the ass his master's crib, but my people do not know nor consider,<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 1:3</note> like the horse or the mule that hath no understanding.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 32:9</note> They are not enamored with that blessing which makes truly rich and adds no sorrow, or with that merchandise which is better than silver and the gain thereof than fine gold.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-08-29"><dateline><date when="1819-08-29">29.</date></dateline><p> First Day. We went to the burial of James Thorington's infant child and then to our meeting. David Comfort of Byberry had acceptable service.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-02"><head>September 1819</head><dateline><date when="1819-09-02">2 of the Ninth Month.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting, which was in a good degree satisfactory to me. Then went to see Jacob Hollinshead, who seems near his end, near 87 years of age. Has been a very steady, examplary, constant attender of meetings as long as he was able to go. Then me <persName key="w6wx87x7">my wife</persName> and Abby went to see our cousin James Thorington's wife, whose infant child was buried last First Day. She is in a very weak, low state. There were a number of women, some old and some young ones. I had them together at last with the sick woman, which was hard to come at; full of trifling talk, but none seemed to have any concern to bring back the King. It was to my relief and satisfaction on retrospection on my bed.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Weather continues very hot and dry.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-05"><dateline><date when="1819-09-05">5 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting, which was through mercy an open, owning time to me to good satisfaction. This afternoon I attended their First Day or, as some call it, the Sunday school newly set up. About eighty children, some black ones, some young men and young women. Some quite small, but mostly about 9, 10, 12, etc. years old.
<pb n="36" facs="sc204028"/>
The school appeared in very good order. Divers of our young Friends – several young men and young women – give up their time and attend as teachers. I had good satisfaction in being with them and encouraging them, although I think I see a better way. <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says reading is good, but meditation is better.<note resp="transcr">Advice of <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> to his Children</note> If parents were examplary and kept their children and those under their care to reading the Scriptures and other good books and above all meditating in the law of the Lord, they would find a satisfaction far transcending any other way of spending their time. <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says he could not wish any one better than that he was in a way of making the best use of his time, and what way can be better? See the blessings promised to it – blessed is the man whose delight is in the law of the Lord and in his law delights to meditate both day and night and blessed are the people that are in such a case.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-09"><dateline><date when="1819-09-09">9th of Ninth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> At our Monthly Meeting, which was to my satisfaction, although I think their is great room for and need of improvement in deep, solid, weightly concern. There has been frequently showers round about us, but not such heavy thunder, I think, as in summers I have known. But it is said in the news there has been much thunder and lightning in some places. A few days ago, Josiah Evan's barn was burnt down with the lightning a few miles eastward of Moorestown, and it is said another further eastward. Likewise, these showers reach but very little ways and seem like dew soon gone, and it continues with us very pinching, opressive, hot, dry weather. The scramblers are much tried; they are hard beset to plow. It is so dry they cannot go on preparing their ground for seed corn. So we read, the plowmen hung their heads and were ashamed. If it should hold so dry a while longer, we should soon see that of ourselves we can do nothing, either in a temporal or spiritual relation.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-10"><dateline><date when="1819-09-10">10.</date></dateline><p> I was at Evesham Monthly Meeting. A door of utterance may be opened and not a door of entrance. I had not that satisfaction as at some other times of late. In meeting for discipline things seemed low, dry, and formal: a want of life. But little room for labor, yet at last some savor.</p></div>
<pb n="37" facs="sc204029"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-11"><dateline><date when="1819-09-11">11 of the Ninth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> [Inserted:] Now 10th of the Tenth Month I hear Benjamin White is take to the asylum at Philadelphia. We hear that Benjamin White, son of Joseph White, a worthy minister, has returned from a religious visit to England. He is under very great depression and lowness of mind, seems in great danger of loosing his reason on account of omitting some meetings which he thinks he ought to have visited. This, the second visit he has paid to England.</p>
<p>John Estaugh (of unblemished character) it is said was struck with a fit of the apoplexy as he was preaching at Haddonfield but survived it. Thomas Cox in England, after preaching about half an hour, was struck with a fit and died immediately in meeting. Robert Jordan, a very great minister, was struck with a fit as he was waiting for the hour of meeting at a friend's house in Philadelphia. See <emph rend="italic">Memorials.<note resp="transcr">Memorials, Philadelphia, 1787</note></emph> : several young men and one very lately I have seen have violent convulsion fits in meeting. See the many awful calls and many things that call for humility and fear. The fear of the Lord is a fountain of life, keeps the heart clean and preserves from the snares of death<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 14:27</note> And yet how much that fear is wanting!</p>
<p>[marginal note] What an awful call for humility in the case of Benjamin White, and many others!</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-15"><dateline><date when="1819-09-15">15.</date></dateline><p> My daughter Abigail and I went to select meeting at Haddonfield. Forepart was a poor dull time, yet I ventured to break silence and had no cause to repent it, and life did arise into dominion at last. And a downright searching, lively time it was as I ever seen, till at last we were in danger of overdoing the matter. However many lively remarks were made tending to stir up to more faithfulness.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-16"><dateline><date when="1819-09-16">16</date></dateline><p> was quarterly meeting. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> was raised in very great eminence. Jacob Ritter, a Dutchman, had considerable, acceptable service. Solemnity and weight attended. And on business it was an open, solemn downright searching time, I think, as I ever seen. To my satisfaction, I was enabled to sit it out a highly favored meeting.</p>
<p>William Flanner of Ohio has returned from England, who went there last spring with the full unity of his friend to pay religious visit. He is a famous, well-approved minister. He was in England about six weeks; the cause of his unexpected return is not yet known.</p>
<p>See a little book called <emph rend="italic">The Destruction of Jerusalem<note resp="transcr">George Holford</note></emph> , page 140: the sky gathers blackness; we hear the distant thunder that forebodes the storm approaching, but no salutary dread prevails.
<pb n="38" facs="sc204030"/>
No radical, no general reformation is discernible; an atheistical disposition of mind, a sensualizing gaiety of manners pervades and awfully infatuates the country.
People seem to think they can get to Heaven without taking up the cross or obeying Christ's commands. Although he said to one, if those wouldst enter into life keep the commandments.<note resp="transcr">Matthew 19:17</note> Be ye not conformed to this world.<note resp="transcr">Romans 12:2</note> was one of his positive commands, but how is it disregarded by professing Christians, who can take their full swing in conforming to this world in all its growing pride and prevailing fashions! No cost or pains spared to gratify the lusts of the eye and pride of life. So count that command nothing. Although thousands of the Lord's faithful servants have suffered very greatly for their testimony against pride and superfluity and chose to follow the example of their self denying Divine Master who, for our example, wore a garment without seam<note resp="transcr">John 19:23</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-18"><dateline><date when="1819-09-18">18 of the Ninth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> We hear that the Yellow Fever rages in an alarming manner at Baltimore. They say seventy died there in one week. And now their yearly meeting draws near (it comes 11 of next month), and divers of our friends propose to be at it, and many strangers, great ministers from New England: Henry Hull and our cousin Henry Warrington and his companion <persName key="w6rj4s40">Elias Hicks</persName> and divers others.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-19"><dateline><date when="1819-09-19">19 of the Ninth Month, First Day.</date></dateline><p> I went to Ancocas meeting, <persName key="w6mt4j9v">Joseph Cowperthwaite</persName> with me. Went to see my old friend Samuel Haines, who has been very sick and yet very poorly; the visit seemed very acceptable. Then we went to their meeting, and an open, owning, favored time it was, to my sweet satisfaction. There were divers ministers from Pennsylvania: Dinah Hillis, an ancient woman, had acceptable service. John Man and Samuel Gomery were silent. Openness, nearness, kindness, and sweetness at parting. Dined at Benjamin Ridgway's; had a good time with the family at parting with the young people and parents, then called to see an old Scotchman who is quite childish with age. Then called to see our cousin James Thorington's wife, a blooming youth but now faded and seems near her end. Got home in good season with satisfaction.</p></div>
<pb n="39" facs="sc204031"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-20"><dateline><date when="1819-09-20">20th Ninth Month.</date></dateline><p> But as <persName key="w6b38kp0">Thomas Ross</persName> said, the hardest thing ever he found in his life when he was right to keep so<note resp="transcr">Thomas Wagstaffe, <emph rend="italic">Piety Promoted</emph>, vol. 9</note>; oh, what humility, what fear came and prayer and watchfulness it does indeed require when we are right to keep so!<quote type="poem">
<l>If I am right, thy grace impart</l>
<l>Still in the right to stay;</l>
<l>If I am wrong, oh teach my heart</l>
<l>To find the better way.</l>
</quote><note resp="transcr">Alexander Pope, “Universal Prayer”</note></p>
<p>See again <emph rend="italic">The Destruction of Jerusalem</emph>, page 132: it is said of the Jews that they rejected and denied Christ, who promised or offered a release from the captivity of sin and Satan, a spiritual salvation and everlasting glory in heaven, and therefore he was rejected. Thus they manifested their preference of the pleasures of sense and earthly grandeur before holy enjoyments and the glories of an unseen and future world. Now what are professing Christians preferring? Is it heavenly or earthly treasures? Where the treasure is, there will the heart be also.<note resp="transcr">Luke 12:34, Matthew 6:21</note> How is it at this day, amidst all the great talk about religion?</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-22"><dateline><date when="1819-09-22">22.</date></dateline><p> Like for a storm: see Hosea 8th 3 verse: Israel hath cast off the thing that is good; the enemy shall pursue him. It has been said we may in general trace back our troubles till we find they originated in a departure from the paths of piety and rectitude, but not so always. Many innocent women and parent suffer grievous trouble on account of the bad conduct of their husbands and children. But they that willfully cast off the thing that is good, all religious restraint – oh, in how many sorrowful instances do we see the saying verified: on the heels of folly treadeth shame, remorse of conscience, of most bitter repentance and after too late, like Esau who sold his birthright for a mess of potage.<note resp="transcr">Genesis 25:30-32</note> and afterwards sought it with tears but could not find it. Oh, if I had begun in time! The frequent great show and signs of rain and going off with very little has caused me to think of the state of religion; great talk and great signs of religion but like clouds without rain go over and very little vital religion. I have this morning read of a class of beings who could not be affected with any thing so much as the loss of property. Where the treasure is, there will the heart be also<note resp="transcr">Luke 12:34, Matthew 6:21</note></p>
<p><persName key="w61p2c7g">Robert Valentine</persName>, a worthy minister, said, oh, if I had begun in time I might have been a clever fellow by this time! And also Job Thomas, a most worthy minister, often lamented his not giving up sooner to seek and serve the Lord.<note resp="transcr">Joseph Gurney Bevans, <emph rend="italic">Piety Promoted</emph>, vol. 9</note> You did not begin soon enough, said an old Negro to his young master, who was much alarmed with a cancer in his mouth. Oh, that I had embraced the opportunities I had in time to make my peace with the Lord, said a poor criminal.
<pb n="40" facs="sc204032"/>
See the Journal of Peggy Dow – my black man brought it here – page 87, printed 1814, wife of Lorenzo Dow when at Georgia: while we were here the earthquakes began and alarmed the people very much. It was an awful scene, to feel the houses shaking under us as sensibly as one could feel the motion of a vessel when it was moving over the water; and the trees, as it were, dancing on the hills. All nature seemed in commotion. This was enough to make the stoutest heart to tremble. But when people get so hardened that mercies nor judgments cannot move them, we may conclude they are in a bad or dangerous way. These earthquakes were sensibly felt here in Jersey and in our neighborhood. Clocks, it said, were stopped in divers places and there was accounts in the news of light shocks of earthquakes were felt in many places from Georgia through Virginia, and a long way through the western territories. John Rutty in his diary mentions an earthquake that shook England, Ireland, France, perhaps Spain and Germany! Fear ye him who can terribly shake the earth and has many times done it and many thousands have perished by earthquake in a few minutes. If I be a master, where is my fear? If I be a father, where is mine honor?<note resp="transcr">Malachi 1:6</note> And yet how very little of this there is, to what there should be.
[marginal note] About 1814.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-23"><dateline><date when="1819-09-23">23.</date></dateline><p> Ninth Month, 1819. Fifth Day morning. A stormy, rainy night. I think we have not had such a one [of] these Sixth Months or more.</p>
<p>See again Peggy Dow's Journal, page 112:<quote type="poem">
<l>How tedious and tasteless the hours,</l>
<l>When Jesus no longer I see.</l>
<l>Sweet prospects, sweet birds, and sweet flowers</l>
<l>Have all lost their sweetness to me.</l>
<l>The midsummer sun shines but dim;</l>
<l>The fields thrive in vain to look gay –</l>
<l>But when I am happy in him,</l>
<l>December as pleasant as May.</l>
<l>His Name yields the richest perfume,</l>
<l>And sweeter than music his voice.</l>
<l>His presence disperses my gloom,</l>
<l>And makes all within me rejoice.</l>
<l>I should were he always thus right</l>
<l>Have nothing to wish or to fear –</l>
<l>No mortal so happy as I;</l>
<l>My summer would last all the year.</l>
</quote></p>

<p>Thomas à Kempis says while Jesus is present all things are pleasant. His kindness is better than life, said David.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 63:3</note> In his presence is fullness of joy<note resp="transcr">Psalm 16:11</note> without which none can ever be happy.</p></div>
<pb n="41" facs="sc204033"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-23"><dateline><date when="1819-09-23">23 Ninth Month, 1819. Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our preparative meeting. I hardly know what was the matter; I had not that satisfaction I could wish. I fear self, self, self has some secret lurking place and deprives us of that peace which is the sum and substance of a gospel minister's wages year and of all the laborers of every class in the vineyard. John Crook's words on some he quoted: when the mind thinketh nothing and the body acteth nothing and the soul craveth nothing contrary to the will of the great Creator, then there is true peace and solid satisfaction.<note resp="transcr">John Crook, 1617-1699, <emph rend="italic">The design of Christianity testified in the books, epistles, and manuscripts of that ancient faithful servant of Christ, John Crook</emph>. London, printed by James Phillips, 1791.</note> But what a great thing it is to attain to this state of nothingness of self and true resignation of our own wills and say not my will, etc.</p>
<p>This fine rain will open the way for seeding, which many have been waiting for weeks past. The earthly-minded, like the earth worm, can get into the earth, their element, again and not much consider what is written in Scripture. Ye have taken out much and brought in little because I did blow upon it.<note resp="transcr">Haggai 1:9</note> Ten acres of vineyard shall yield but one bath, and the seed of an homer shall yield but an ephah,<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 5:10</note> not considering there is one that can say our fields shall or shall not yield their increase; can open the windows of Heaven and shower down blessings till there is hardly room to contain them.<note resp="transcr">Malachi 3:10</note> or, as the prophet said, shut up heaven so that the land yield not her increase<note resp="transcr">Deuteronomy 11:17</note></p>
<p>Seventh Day evening. Again, a very heavy rain thunder shower. It came down like a torrent or flood. Not the like this Sixth Months – for all summer it has come very sparingly till now. And as Job says, he withholdeth the waters and they dry up; again he sendeth them out and they overturn the Earth.<note resp="transcr">Job 12:15</note> Our mills have been shut up for want of water till now, so that we have been forced to go 10 miles or more to get our grain ground, and much complaint of wells getting dry, etc.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-26"><dateline><date when="1819-09-26">26 of the Ninth Month.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. I found hard work getting along. Words and life are two things; if the dead are not raised, preaching is vain,<note resp="transcr">1 Corinthians 15:14</note> yet at last something lively and savory. See <persName key="w6cg1kgr">John Churchman's</persName> <emph rend="italic">Journal</emph>, page 105: Where was at four or five meeting, most of which meetings truth seemed to be professed, but too few had the life thereof in possession, which occasions hard, dry meetings.
<pb n="42" facs="sc204034"/>
[Part of page added]</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-26"><dateline><date when="1819-09-26">26 of the Ninth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> See [Thomas Clarkson's] <emph rend="italic">An Essay on Slavery,</emph>  page 102. Why does not the general conduct of men afford us a better picture? What is imprudence or what is vice but a departure from every man's own interests? And yet these are the characteristics of more than half the world. In page 107 it is said: the cruel treatment of slaves is such that every obstacle is placed in the way of their improvement. How vastly different is our circumstance, when every means is offered for our improvement, which thousands neglect and disregard and too late cry out, oh, that I had embraced the offers and opportunities of improvement.</p></div>
<pb n="43" facs="sc204035"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-09-30"><dateline><date when="1819-09-30">30th of the Ninth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. Something more open, more owning, more savory and sweet than common – uniting, strengthening, and satisfactory. The rain, for many months past, has come very sparingly, but now very freely. A few days ago, it was so dry we could not sow our seed corn, and now so wet some cannot sow. The fields, meadows, and lanes have been scorched brown with the drought; now the grass has sprung up so that pasture looks more fresh and green than it has for weeks and months past.</p>
<p>It is said to be, both in town and country, a very dull time for business. Very many now out of business and are very much straitened to get bread. Some are offering to work for their victuals, and some with families of children. These are trying circumstances, and it looks likely to be more so. I don't know who can account for these ups and downs and changes of season. I can remember when laborers' wages in harvest time was generally 2 and 6 per day; and now, of latter years, wages has been at times and places as high as a dollar and a eleven penny bit. But so, we read in Scripture, it was formerly, and so it has been down to these days: markets some times excessive high and then again very dull and low.</p>
<p>I have seen an account of such great changes in our first Friends writings. John Burnyeat, a worthy minister, prophesied and told the people they had seen a time of great trial and striving, and of losing their earthly treasures. But a time would soon come wherein they would be as much tried in getting riches. And it came to pass in a wonderful manner in about twelve months, and then they fell to scuffling and scrambling after this world's goods until they were in as much danger of suffocation as they were before of starvation. See the state of poor mankind: never safe nor satisfied, full nor fasting. Agur's prayer was, remove from me vanity and lies; give me neither poverty nor riches, but feed me with food convenient for me, least I be poor and steal or least I become rich and deny thee and say, who is the Lord?<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 30:8-9</note></p>
<p>Sixth Day morning. Clears up again.</p></div>
<pb n="44" facs="sc204036"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-10-03"><head>October 1819</head><dateline><date when="1819-10-03">3rd of the Tenth Month was First Day.</date></dateline><p> <persName key="w6mt4j9v">Joseph Cowperthwaite</persName> went with me to Cropwell meeting. We called to see five families on the road and invited them to go to meeting. The first asked if there was to be any strangers there. I answered: no without it was me. We are all too much strangers to the commonwealth of Israel. The next were not at home. The next we got the man and his wife along to meeting with us. The next were not at home (I believe they take the First Day to visit their friends or relations). The next were family of people lately come from England, professing to be of the Church of England – but some of them attend Friends meeting. I asked the young man if he would go to meeting. He said no, not without there was some preaching. He said he could not bear to go and sit there and hear nothing said, and I could not promise or say there would. So we left him, but his father and four sisters went with us to meeting. And a door of utterance was opened as much so as I ever seen there; though very dull, low, and poor at first, there was openness, feeling nearness, and sweetness at last.</p>
<p>Then we went to see Joel Evans, an ingenious young man in a deep consumption. Had a pretty sweet opportunity with him, then went to see Eli Evans, my sister's son, who has most grievously given way to strong drink. Has a valuable wife and seven fine children. We had them together; his wife's mother happened to be there, who had lately very pressingly urged me to come and see the family. I thought it was in a good degree an open, owning time to good satisfaction. Returned in peace and got home in good season. There was three families more I wanted to stop and see, but time was too short for it. One was Thomas Homes, many years afflicted with lowness and despondency of mind; another was a miserable captive to drunkenness; the other has been many years a poor abject with the palsy.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-10-06"><dateline><date when="1819-10-06">6.</date></dateline><p> A friend brought me a newspaper giving an account of the dreadful eruption, disorder, revolution, and confusion in England on account of state affairs, oppressive taxes – the mob raised and dismal murdering work amongst them. See the danger people are in when and where vital religion prevails not. In said paper is this instructing remark: to be able to bear provocation is an argument of great wisdom; and to forgive it of a great mind.</p>
<p>Day 7 morning. See 1 of Peter – read to the end of the chapter – 2 and 19 verse: for this is thankworthy, if a man for conscience towards God endure grief, suffering wrongfully. So this is acceptable to God. But alas, alas, see for want of this forgiving inquires how has the fire of Hell kindled on individuals and whole nations, how have the potsherds of the earth dashed one against the other
<pb n="45" facs="sc204037"/>
and grievously tormented and destroyed one another, and made a dismal rattle in nations and ages past, even down to these our days, and as it is at this time in England, and other places.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-10-07"><dateline><date when="1819-10-07">7 of the Tenth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> At our Monthly Meeting, I thought the forepart was lively and ended savory; that for discipline also pretty well.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-10-08"><dateline><date when="1819-10-08">8.</date></dateline><p> Having some temporal business, it opened my way to get to Evesham Monthly Meeting, which was a very open, owning, strengthening, healing time to me, to sweet satisfaction on my pillow.</p>
<p>N.B. know, my friends, that he who best deserves my favors is he who best improves the talents I have given to him. To him and to him alone I give my honors, my power, and my riches; for he who waits with patience for my favors shall hence forth be my regent, and I never will appoint a power above him. So says the Scripture: they that honor the Lord, them will he honor.<note resp="transcr">1 Samuel 2:30</note></p>
<p>A young man, Stacy Haines, son of Evesham, on his return from Ohio came by Baltimore and says they are encamped a distance from the town on account of the prevalence of the Yellow Fever. A distressing, trying time it must be to those who are in health. How the sick fare we have not lately heard.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-10-10"><dateline><date when="1819-10-10">10.</date></dateline><p> First Day morning. Last night a soaking rain again.</p>
<p>See [<persName key="w66696rh">Lindley Murray's</persName>] <emph rend="italic">English Reader, </emph>page 243: the influence of devotion on the happiness of life. Let us consult our experience and we shall find that the two greatest sources of inward joy, comfort, and lasting happiness are the exercises of love directed towards the most definable deserving object. As one said to this effect, I know no joys, no pleasures, no riches, no treasures comparable to that of being assured of the mercy, favor, and Love of God. His loving kindness is better than life and in his presence [is] fullness of joy, said David.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-10-10"><dateline><date when="1819-10-10">10 of the Tenth Month First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Not the poorest and lowest to me, although something was wanting. I could not get along. As Abel Thomas said, we cannot preach when we please. And as William Brown said, we do not know that ability will be given to get through with our openings. I had, as <persName key="w6028wf4">N. Waln</persName> said, considerable pertinent matter, but life and ability was wanting; although mortifying, it might be needful and profitable to keep humble.</p></div>
<pb n="46" facs="sc204038"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-10-12"><dateline><date when="1819-10-12">12th of the Tenth Month 1819.</date></dateline><p> This evening several of our friends and neighbors were here to see us. About 8 or 9 o'clock they went away, and as we went out there appeared a bright light in the north, with streams of vapors or streaming lights like them that appeared in the sky in the north about thirty years ago. As soon as our neighbors were gone I went to bed, but <persName key="w6wx87x7">my wife</persName> and children came and earnestly desired I would get up to see a bright white cloud, about the width of a common road, in the midst of the sky right over us. It reached from east to west as far as we could see. It was quite clear star light. Such a thing to be sure of never seen before, although I have seen near eighty years. It being something so new and strange was somewat awful, and I thought displayed something like almighty power. Some undertook to assign natural causes for them lights in the north about thirty years ago, and said it was the sun shining on the great banks of ice in the north caused them northern streaming lights. But such reasons will not do for me – for if so, why not seen by us before or since until now? And now this bright narrow cloud in the midst of the sky and from east to west, something entirely new to us. Some thought it was the brightness of the light, like as of a great fire caused the white narrow cloud in the sky, some what like the rainbow. But why not ever seen so before now? I must leave as it was something supernatural. I believe many will be ready to say, with the Egyptians of old on a certain occasion said, surely the finger of God is in it.<note resp="transcr">Exodus 8:19</note> Perhaps we may have to think of it again.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-10-14"><dateline><date when="1819-10-14">14.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. I don't know what to say so middling. A lad about 16, by the name of Petit, died very sudden after eating some honey. He told them he had swallowed a bee and it is said the doctor thought it stung him in the stomach. He died in great pain and about two hours illness. He had lived with <persName key="w6d01xtv">Darling Conrow</persName>, and died at Joseph Brown's. Oh, how many ways there are for people to be taken away! But one way to come into this world, but many ways to go out of it. What solemn calls to all sorts.</p>
<p>[marginal note] See [Holford's] <emph rend="italic">Destruction of Jerusalem</emph> page 36 and 37: fearful sights and great signs shall there be from heaven, many of which are there mentioned, before the destruction of Jerusalem.</p>
<p>See Luke 21:11 verse.</p></div>
<pb n="47" facs="sc204039"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-10-17"><dateline><date when="1819-10-17">17th of the Tenth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> First Day. I had a meeting at Joseph Brown's, in a neighborhood about two miles south, [with] about twenty families that seldom ever pay any attention to religion of any sort. Having obtained liberty of our Monthly Meeting, [and] I having requested Edwin Atley, a minister of Philadelphia, to bear me company, which he freely did, and had acceptable service. The forepart was very poor, low, and trying. A set of people who seem to know nothing of the necessity of silent waiting, but altogether looking out for words. No preaching, nothing to be done with them. Some were such strangers to the commonwealth of Israel that they were ashamed to be seen and chose to sit in the kitchen. And I believe several families, or heads of them, have been so long out of the way of attending any places of worship that I believe they were ashamed to come. But however we were favored at last with a good degree of the evident ownings of truth, to a good degree of satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-10-21"><dateline><date when="1819-10-21">21.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our preparative meeting. I have no cause to repent being there, for sometimes I have been ready to obey the command of the angel, which was: Curse ye, Meroz, said the angel of the Lord. Curse ye bitterly, the inhabitance [inhabitants] thereof, because they come not up to the help of the Lord, to help of the Lord against the mighty,<note resp="transcr">Judges 5:23</note> etc. The subject was on the great business of education of children:</p>
<p>‘Tis education forms the tender mind;</p>
<p>Just as the twig is bent the tree is inclined.<note resp="transcr">Alexander Pope</note></p>
<p>
etc., etc. One says the world is contaminated for want of a right care in education of children. Prepare their minds to receive the power of truth, without which they can never be happy, says <persName key="w6cg1kgr">John Churchman</persName>. How hearts condemn us not, then have we confidence towards God.<note resp="transcr">1 John 3:21</note>
Last Fifth Day at our preparative meeting a complaint was brought against Thomas Parry, who has been with us but a few years, a native of Pennsylvania, for not paying his just debts. And it appeared Friends were disposed to make short work in disowning him, although he has been an industrious, innocent, orderly, exemplary man as far as appears. But not
<pb n="48" facs="sc204040"/>
have that faculty of dealing for himself as many others have; and the turning of times and things working against him, his creditors falling on him and broke him up and his plantation sold for a great deal less than he gave for it but a few years ago.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-10-24"><dateline><date when="1819-10-24">24 which was First Day.</date></dateline><p> After meeting, which was but a poor, low time, I went to see Thomas Parry and had a tendering time with him; I think he shed tears, and I had satisfaction. See II Kings 4th: thy servant, my husband, is dead and thou knowst thy servant did fear the Lord and the creditor is come upon me.<note resp="transcr">2 Kings 4:1</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-10-28"><dateline><date when="1819-10-28">28.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. A shut up time to me, but not so to several others.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-10-29"><dateline><date when="1819-10-29">29.</date></dateline><p> Went to the burial of Joel Evans, a young man in the bloom and prime of life, of a singular character – very still, quiet, industrious, and remarkably ingenious and deep sighted about accumulating wealth. There was a very large number of people, and behaved orderly. At last I had sweet satisfaction at parting at the grave. We hear that John Tatham's wife, of Woodbury, is to be buried today. Both these died of consumption; she lingered a long time, but he languished but a short time with it.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-10-31"><dateline><date when="1819-10-31">31 of the Tenth Month 1819 First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting better than common; to me, open and owning, to sweet satisfaction on my pillow. I thought there was an unusual solemnity felt by all, although they might not know from whence it came or what to call it.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-11-04"><head>November 1819</head><dateline><date when="1819-11-04">4 of the Eleventh Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting, which I thought was a lively, good meeting throughout to me. (<persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> had acceptable service.) But alas, poor we, as Abel Thomas used to say – when we are right, how unable of ourselves we are to keep so. How few bear prosperity unhurt, either in a spiritual or temporal relation. As Isidore used to say, he that grows better, let him beware lest he grow proud and vain; gladly give him a greater overthrow than his former vices, for pride is as apt to grow on our virtues as our vices. And so I find it to be true. I had need to adopt David's petition: Restore me to the joy of thy salvation and uphold me by thy free spirit<note resp="transcr">Psalm 51:12</note> or else down we go, old weaknesses prevail.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Grows very dry weather again; no rain for many weeks.</p></div>
<pb n="49" facs="sc204041"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-11-07"><dateline><date when="1819-11-07">7 Eleventh Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. As to me silent, though one had a pretty deal to say. Yet if the dead raised, it [was] hid from me; though not the poorest as to my own mind. We hear a few weeks ago that our dear, sweet, worthy minister <persName key="w6ht6kfw">Sarah Cresson</persName> has lost her reason again. She was so, some years ago, but got out again as bright and as acceptable as ever. It appears a family weakness.</p>
<p>My cousin who I went to see a few months ago, Hezekiah Stokes, my half sister Hope's son, a young merchant at Medford, Upper Evesham, has broke and run away and left a wife and three small children. A most sorrowful circumstance. It makes me think of the words of one of our great European ministers. He said, and so it is: Rent rules over rent, ruin overtakes ruin, and desolation overtakes desolation. So it is. Oh, the trouble, sorrow, misery, affliction, disgrace, and ruin we see people bring on themselves and their friends for want of keeping to that preserving principle, the law written in the heart, the law of the spirit of life, which Paul said had set him free from the law of sin and death.<note resp="transcr">Romans 8:2</note> Which, if obeyed, would do for all as it did for Paul.</p>
<p>Fifth Day. At our meeting. Lydia Lippincott had savory service, and I thought something savory attended the meeting. Afternoon, I went to see our ancient friend Jacob Hollinshead, about 87, who seems drawing near to close, but at present some better. And I went to see my old friends, Samuel Laning and wife and G. Matlack.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-11-13"><dateline><date when="1819-11-13">13.</date></dateline><p> Heard of two remarkable deaths. A young man, Levi Lippincott, near Cropwell meetinghouse was digging marl and it caved in upon him and buried him alive in an instant. The other was a child about four years old below Haddonfield: got a bean in its wind pipes and it died suddenly. What instructing obsessions and warnings. One young man drowned, two died with consumption, and two with uncommon disorders in the head unsensible.</p>
<p>[marginal note] A young man lay dying at J.H. 21. Died after we came away.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-11-14"><dateline><date when="1819-11-14">14.</date></dateline><p> First Day. A precious, open, favored, owning time it was, to sweet satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-11-15"><dateline><date when="1819-11-15">15.</date></dateline><p> Went to see my sister Hope in her troubles. Lodged at <persName key="w69h6c86">Job Collins'</persName> and <rs key="w6hj799d">wife</rs>, my old fellow traveler, is visiting families. Weather fine and warm, like spring. </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-11-17"><dateline><date when="1819-11-17">17.</date></dateline><p> A fine small shower. Heard of four or five men being shot, one designed by the others accidental – some gaming, sporting, etc. Almost daily, or very frequent, we heard of bankruptcies. Never was the like in our land.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Rain goes off again, and again grows very dry weather.</p></div>
<pb n="50" facs="sc204042"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-11-25"><dateline><date when="1819-11-25">25.</date></dateline><p> Eleventh Month, 1819. At our preparative meeting. After meeting, went with William Roberts to visit one English, a young man who brought a certificate. Both were to satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-11-28"><dateline><date when="1819-11-28">28.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Some life and savor as I thought, but how difficult it is to retain it, as one of experience once remarked.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-11-29"><dateline><date when="1819-11-29">29.</date></dateline><p> Last night a pretty smart snow, but clears up fine and warm. See a book called<emph rend="italic"> The Conquest of Canaan</emph>, by John Martin, page 143: All men are happy as they know and approve the true nature, the appointed means, and final end of being so and miserable as these are unknown, neglected, and despised. See again page 144: the command and credentials given to Joshua without a clever call and a good conscience. What can any man do for God? But with these, what has not been attempted, what has not been performed? An attention to God's commands is both our duty and our strength and the only way in which the divine presence can be expected and enjoyed. Joshua was to meditate on the revealed will of God. Day and night he was to observe and do according to all that was written. He was to be what some would call obstinately right. Thus was he to be strong and of good courage. In the exalted character he sustained, and thus only can we be endued with the same courage and strength in ours. And see page 252: Evil persons make evil time, and there have been always a sufficient number of such in the world to try the patience of the upright and to manifest that those who are unholy will always be unthankful, and in proportion as they are so, will always be unhappy. Page 80th: Devotion, if genuine, will always shine in every situation and will at all times teach us benevolence and discretion. And see page 177, concerning the hardened rebellious Canaanities: what a dreadful situation are such people in, to whom every warning is despised, every caution is an offence, and to whom every entreaty is vain. deplorable state! For that which melts others into tenderness and submission fires them with rage and fills them with resentment. Unhappy men, all but themselves see their guilt and lament it, behold their approaching ruin and shudder at the thought, while they (shocking idea) rush forward to destruction with as much unconcern as the ox goeth to the slaughter or the fool to the correction of the stocks.</p></div>
<pb n="51" facs="sc204043"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-11-29"><dateline><date when="1819-11-29">29.</date></dateline><p> Concerning the physical causes of the fertility of the land of Canaan, Socrates himself has somewhere ventured to declare that what makes objects fire is the presence or approach or communication of what he calls the original fire being. Whatever be the way of that communication – the way he observes is various and often mysterious – but the thing is certain. Let me add that persons are as dependent on the Divine Being as things. Them whom he careth for and whom his eyes are to bless and prosper from one end of the year to the other,<note resp="transcr">Deuteronomy 11:12</note> they, like the land of Canaan, are more excellent than the rest. May this blessing be yours. Page 28: you must not wonder therefore that they who dishonor God are injurious to men and enemies to themselves. Page 32: I cannot forbear observing that an increase of people peaceful among themselves, intelligent, and industrious will by art and labor improve the most barren situation and make the most of what is fruitful. And these, let me tell you, are some of the solid advantages which religion diffuses wherever she is embraced. First she fertilizes the mind and then extends her benign influence to all its operations.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-03"><head>December 1819</head><dateline><date when="1819-12-03">3rd of the Twelfth Month.</date></dateline><p> At our select meeting. Poor and dull, want of savor and life. Not lively and wise and knowing as in temporal affairs, yet at last I had some satisfaction. Where nothing is to be had the King must loose his right.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-04"><dateline><date when="1819-12-04">4.</date></dateline><p> Killing some of our hogs. 4 weighed near 200 a piece. Markets very low and dull, pork 5d [pence] a pound and 4 dollars a hundred; a few years ago pork three friperry bits a pound and twelve dollars a hundred. A great stagnation of trade and business of all sorts. Who can account for these extreme ups and downs? We hear of the dreadful eruptions and increase of confusion, wars, and destruction in England on account of the oppression of taxes etc. That spirit of rebellion has spread in to France, Germany, and Spain and that in one of the capital cities in Spain the pestilence rages that near one hundred die in a day. So we read thine own wickedness shall correct thee and thy backsliding shall reprove thee, that it is an evil thing and bitter to forsake the commandments of Lord.<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 2:19</note></p></div>
<pb n="52" facs="sc204044"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-05"><dateline><date when="1819-12-05">5 of the Twelfth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting and a precious, evidently owning, open, cementing, uniting, strengthening, memorable time it was. All seemed alive with love, openness, sweetness, and feeling nearness after meeting. After meeting 3rd hour went to the burial of Jacob Hollinshead, aged about 87, a very constant steady attender of meetings. Has supported or attained good name, which Solomon says is better than precious ointment and the day of their death better than the day of their birth.<note resp="transcr">Ecclesiastes 7:1</note> There was a vast concourse of people and [they] behaved very orderly, becoming to [the] solemnity of the occasion. I had good satisfaction, both at the house and at the grave. He left ten children, five sons and five daughters.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-09"><dateline><date when="1819-12-09">9.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting, and I am not alone in thinking it was a good meeting. Amos Hilburn of Bibery [Byberry] had sweet, acceptable service. A satisfactory meeting to me.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-10"><dateline><date when="1819-12-10">10.</date></dateline><p> Very cold, high wind which we have had very little of this fall. I went to Mill at Haddonfield. And see [<persName key="w66696rh">Lindley Murray's</persName>] S<emph rend="italic">equel to English Reader</emph>, page 273: it is observed by a late celebrated author that he who hopes to look back hereafter with satisfaction upon past years must learn to know the value of single minutes, and endeavor to let no particle of time fall useless to the ground. By practicing these lesson[s], many have rose to great eminence in oppositions to all the obstacles this tumultuous, treacherous world could place in their way; by daring and determing to be obstinately right at all times and on all occasions, [they] have died honored, lamented, and regretted. Page 267, Franklin: I have always set a greater value on the character of a doer of good than any other kind of reputation. He possessed the rare talent of drawing useful lessons from the commonest occurrences, which would have passed unimproved by the generality of observers. I add like the busy bee gathers honey from every flower.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-12"><dateline><date when="1819-12-12">12.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. A low, poor time; yet a little life. Our son Joseph and his daughter Deborah were here to see us, and [he] informs me that his neighbor John Letchworth, a minister, and his companion Isaac Pennock have returned from a very
<pb n="53" facs="sc204045"/>
long journey in the western territories among several nations of Indians, and as far as Kentucky. And that it has been so dry that the waters in the wilderness, where there is often great abundance, was so dried up that their horses suffered very much for want of water and that there was a disorder among their horses. Their mouth[s] and throats got sore and tongues swelled and was very catching; of which many died, and the cows and hogs catched and some people, I think he said, had died with it – and that this disorder had spread along the road near or quite to Philadelphia. There is an awful language in the voice of the signs of the times, solemn awful calls after divers ways and after divers manners. The Lord speaks once, yea twice, but man perceveth it not, said Job of old [Job 33:14]. I have called but ye have not answered; when you call I will not answer, but will laugh at your calamity and mock when your fear cometh.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 1:25-28</note> So we read in Scripture.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-15"><dateline><date when="1819-12-15">15 of the Twelfth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> Was at select meeting at Evesham. Forepart I thought was very low and poor, but <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> got to work and seemed to raise the life. As [Robert] Barclay says, by throwing a little water in a pump and working it, it fetches up the rest.  I had at last to think of an old woman I have heard of, who said: I have got the penny and I don't care a halfpenny for all of them. And like Robert Nesbit of New England, after he had been delivering some very close doctrine, he said; now I feel as if you could not hurt me.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-16"><dateline><date when="1819-12-16">16.</date></dateline><p> Was quarterly meeting and very large. The house, I believe, [was] completely filled. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> stood up nearly as soon as the meeting was settled and held it till it was time to go on business. Very large, powerful, pertinent, and lively, and at last said he thought it had been a favored, well-concluded, meeting. To me it was sweet and pleasant to think of it on my pillow.</p>
<p>My son Joseph informs me that Jesse Kersey, one of our very greatest ministers, lately had a fall and broke his jaw bone, but was like to get well. But see what great calls there is for humility with all sorts! Jacob Lindly, a great and worthy minister, not long ago – just after he had been preaching – powerfully was throwd [thrown] out of his carriage and broke his neck. How true is the saying no man but is liable to be reduced to poverty in a moment.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-18"><dateline><date when="1819-12-18">18.</date></dateline><p> Killing the rest of our hogs.</p></div>
<pb n="54" facs="sc204046"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-19"><dateline><date when="1819-12-19">19.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. Having got liberty of our Monthly Meeting, I appointed a meeting at New Hopewell, about 1 miles on the way to Egg Harbor, up in the barren pine woods. There was a meeting settled there some years ago, but a number of the fore rank among them having moved to the western country, the meeting was dropt and the house has stood desolate, unoccupied some years. Friends a little time ago, met to sell the house, but some tender people agreed with them to let them have the house for a school house and to hold meetings in it if any Friends should be disposed to visit them. It was a very rainy, stormy day, which was thought to be the cause of the meeting being smaller than it might have been (many of them being poor and no carriages). Yet the house was nearly full. Forepart felt low and poor, but it growd better and I believe ended to general satisfaction. Some were very pressing, kindly inviting us to dine with them. Joseph Evans and wife and John Haines and wife – elders – were with us (that is, my daughter Abigail and me). We came on our way four miles to long a coming and dined with a new married couple, Samuel. After diner, at parting, we had a little sitting for the better, I believe. Got back to Joseph Evans's about dark, and I very weary, but he wished that we might have an opportunity with his large family of children and servants, which I was not easy to put by although very much exhausted. The family sat down together and we fared better than I expected. All ended to good satisfaction, and we got well home.</p>
<p>Clears up fine and moderate. Some remarks of learned noble writer: the riches of the mind, like those of fortune, may be employed so perversly as to become a nuisance and pest instead of an ornament and support to society. <emph rend="italic">Dialogues of the Dead</emph>, page 297, eddition 1765: But alas, what is distinguished ability if not wedded to integrity?</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-23"><dateline><date when="1819-12-23">23.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. A poor, mortifying time to me, and perhaps needful.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-26"><dateline><date when="1819-12-26">26.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Came off middling.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-27"><dateline><date when="1819-12-27">27.</date></dateline><p> Helping my son Benne kill hogs. Very fine and moderate weather.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-28"><dateline><date when="1819-12-28">28.</date></dateline><p> Went to my son John's, got horses shod. Grows cold.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-29"><dateline><date when="1819-12-29">29.</date></dateline><p> I went to see <persName key="w6mt4j9v">Joseph Cowperthwaite</persName>, who is in a deep consumption; a young man who of latter time has been out with me at our neighboring meetings. Had a sweet satisfactory time with him.</p></div>
<pb n="55" facs="sc204047"/>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-30"><dateline><date when="1819-12-30">30 of the Twelfth Month, 1819.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. A most violent, stormy, snowy, cold, severe freezing storm. meeting but smallish; came off without condemnation and remembered these words: if our heart condemn us not, then have we confidence towards God.<note resp="transcr">1 John 3:21</note> I have had some humbling, mortifying seasons of late, very gloomy prospects. [I am] ready to adopt the language of the prophet when he said, one day I shall fall by the hand of Saul<note resp="transcr">I Samuel 17:1</note>; myself my greatest enemy. But the clouds seem to break away.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1819-12-31"><dateline><date when="1819-12-31">31.</date></dateline><p> Great snow and very cold.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-01"><head>January 1820</head><dateline><date when="1820-01-01">1st of the First Month, Seventh of the week, 1820.</date></dateline><p> Clear and very cold. Great snow on the ground. I was thinking this morning that it is likely that millions there be [who] never will see another New Year's Day and none knows who of us will make up one of the number. But one thing we know and that is, as Job of old says, when a few years are come I shall go the way whence I shall not return.<note resp="transcr">Job 16:22</note> What is your life, said the apostle, but a vapor that appeareth but a very little while and soon vanisheth away [James 4:14]. And when once gone, soon forgotten, as our forefathers are. Your fathers, where are they? said the prophet.<note resp="transcr">Zechariah 1:5</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-02"><dateline><date when="1820-01-02">2nd of the First Month, First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Evidently favored, open and owned, or I am mistaken. Oh, that I could walk worthy of such continued favors.</p>
<p>Second Day I went to see <persName key="w6mt4j9v">Joseph Cowperthwaite</persName>, who seems better. Had a pretty satisfactory little sitting in his room, and called to see Ebenezer Roberts, in a very poorly way as to his health.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-03"><dateline><date when="1820-01-03">3rd.</date></dateline><p> Went to the burial of Mary Roughn, our next neighbor, who died very suddenly with an apoplectic fit, it was thought. A large concourse of people who were very orderly, still, and quiet. I had a satisfactory opportunity with them. All ended sweet and well. Very severe freezing weather. We hear they cross the river on the ice, and that a man from Egg Harbor it was that was overcome with the cold and died at the ferry.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-06"><dateline><date when="1820-01-06">6.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting. <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> and Lidia Lippincott had acceptable, savory service and I thought something sweet and savory attended throughout, though great room for improvement in solid weight.</p>
<p>We hear that our cousin Henry Warington Jr's barn, which was very large, was all burnt down* by taking out fire to dress flax. What heavy strokes and heavy trials! And unexpected they often come, and yet how soon forgotten. The horses run away with the wagon, William Hooten's wife in it, a few days ago, but [she] got no harm. And how many such accidents could I mention and divers, yea, numbers suddenly killed.</p>
<p>[marginal note] * Loss in grain and hay thought to be 1000 dollars.
<pb n="56" facs="sc204048"/>
Henry Warrington's loss in grain and hay and building was thought to be one thousand dollars. And now also we hear that Joseph Bonaparte – a French man, brother to Bonaparte the great French warrior – who not many years ago came here and brought very great riches, purchased lands near Burdentown and erected vast buildings, is now all burnt down from a spark from the stove, and the whole establishment consumed. How many instances there are, which evidently demonstrate the truth of that saying that there's no man so much out of the reach of trouble but he is liable to be reduced to poverty and beggary in a moment.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-09"><dateline><date when="1820-01-09">9.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. At our meeting. I seemed almost left alone – <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> removed to Westfield, Ebenezer Roberts sick, I.I. [indecipherable] shut up and some others unwell. Although it was silent till near the last, it was not the poorest to me. Came off without condemnation. I count it a great favor to be so far preserved as to look back on past time with pleasure, comfort, peace, and hope.  Another snow storm.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-11"><dateline><date when="1820-01-11">11.</date></dateline><p> We went to the burial of Samuel Stokes about seventy or upward at Moorestown, whose wife is my father's sister's daughter. His father, his uncle, his brother, and himself all grievously hurt themselves with strong drink there was a large gathering of people and conducted orderly and well I had a few sentences to drop at last which I hope will do no hurt to any; myself or others. I feel no cause to repent being there.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-12"><dateline><date when="1820-01-12">12.</date></dateline><p> We now hear that Josiah Lippincott is to be buried today. He has lain long in a drearying, lingering, consumptive way. Numbers of his family or generation have gone in that way. Left, they say, eleven children. A very cold, great snow.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-13"><dateline><date when="1820-01-13">13.</date></dateline><p> I was reading the book called <emph rend="italic">New England Judged</emph>, by George Bishop of the most cruel laws and most cruel whippings, banishments, imprisoning, and hanging of our Friends, and yet how they prevailed over all their almost unheard of cruelties. What wonderful testimonies there are of men, women, and some young in years. What an alarming thing it would be if such laws were made in our days.</p>
<p>[marginal note] See page 37: 1650, first called Quakers. First appeared in 1644 in Leicestershire, six years before they were called Quakers.
<pb n="57" facs="sc204049"/>
And yet it is said that some stood faithful under the deepest sufferings, who afterwards grievously fell away when tried with prosperity. I have heard it said that it is harder to stand wheedle proof than battle proof. But we seem not much alarmed at the wheedling spirit of the world, although we see many are taken in the snare and fall grievously by it. And multitudes of the dear blooming youth in eminent danger now a days, trampling upon the testimony [of] our worthy predecessors, [which they] so grievously and deeply suffered for, in compliance with divine command, which is: Let your moderation appear in all things, for the Lord is at hand,<note resp="transcr">Philippians 4:5</note> and again, be ye not conformed to this world<note resp="transcr">Romans 12:2</note> etc. Suffering themselves to be persuaded that they can now be very good Quakers without taking up the cross or obeying Christ's commands, as if it was a very silly thing in our first friends to suffer so grievously for these trifling little things, as they call them in these days, and to agree and unite together! To trample on their testimony and call it nothing! But they remain to be the little foxes that crop the tender vine<note resp="transcr">Song of Solomon 2:15</note> and buddings of truth in the blooming youth, and indeed are the seeds of desolation and at this time threaten us with desolation as to the life and power of true religion far more than the most frightful cruel laws made and most bitterly executed against our friends in New England did. For they growed and prospered in the truth under their most grievous sufferings, whilst we, under great prosperity and fullness, have too much lost the life and power of truth, which they were so evidently favored with, to the confounding their most cruel enemies and to the stopping the mouths of their greatest scoffers and gainsayers. It was a saying in the days of the martyrs that the blood of the martyrs was the seed of the church Tertullian.
But what does one of our worthy ancient say concerning prosperity? I think this was the language: Not all the persecutors or open apostates that ever rose up against us has ever done us that hurt that prosperity has done. The charge was to Israel former: when thou hast eaten and drunken and art full, then beware – as if it was the time of greatest danger. Then beware lest thou forget the Lord thy God<note resp="transcr">Deuteronomy 8:10-11</note> who had done such great things for him.
Friends first appearance in 1644. Not called Quakers till 1650. Now 1820 – 170 years since they were called Quakers in derision.
[marginal note] As the Christians were at Antioch in derision called Christians at first.</p></div>
<pb n="58" facs="sc204050"/>
</body></text>
</TEI>