<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader></teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="01" facs="sc203917"/>
<table>
<row>
<cell>1815 mo 9</cell>
<cell>Gave John Blake a Negro man who had lost his 2 cows</cell>
<cell>50</cell></row>
<row><cell>5 Mo 14</cell>
<cell>Gave Thomas Johnson who was going to the state of Ohio
in necessitous circumstance</cell>
<cell>100</cell></row>
<row><cell>7 Mo 28</cell>
<cell>Paid George Matlack's towards building our cillsting [?]
House</cell>
<cell>124</cell></row>
<row><cell>8 Mo 16</cell>
<cell>Paid Jeremiah Matlack son: the sum I was assess on
account of Poor</cell>
<cell>100</cell></row>
<row><cell>9 Mo 28</cell>
<cell>Paid Nathan Middleton my tax for the year 1810 being</cell>
<cell>176</cell></row>
<row><cell>1811</cell>
<cell>Gave a Black woman 6c who came along with a brief
Ministering for the support of a poor old Black man and
living near or in Mansfield</cell>
<cell>06</cell></row>
<row><cell>10 Mo 10</cell>
<cell>Paid Samuel Roberts senior the sum I was assessed for
the poor and meetings use</cell>
<cell>150</cell></row>
<row><cell>10 Mo 10</cell>
<cell>Also Elizabeth Matlack's' sum for the same use as
above expressed</cell>
<cell>100</cell></row>
</table>
<pb n="02" facs="sc203918"/>
<table><row>
<cell>1811</cell>
<cell>Paid Nathan Middleton by the hands of Isaac Bunting
my Tax for the year 1811</cell>
<cell>228</cell></row>
<row><cell>1812 2 Mo 15</cell>
<cell>Enoch Roberts Johns: son had his house reduced to
ashes about the 6th of this month I subscribed towards
making up the loss
3 sickles paid it</cell>
<cell>200</cell></row>
<row><cell>6 Mo</cell>
<cell>Gave a Blind man who was led about by his little daughter</cell>
<cell>12 1/2</cell></row>
<row><cell>8 Mo 4</cell>
<cell>subscribed and paid to John Collins
for Humphrey Owen living in Ohio state
who wrote in here to J.C. wishing him to
Get some money for him</cell>
<cell>37 1/2</cell></row>
<row><cell/>
<cell>Paid Samuel Haines by the hands of Elizabeth Matlack
my Tax for 1812</cell>
<cell>228</cell></row>
<row><cell/>
<cell>Paid Samuel Roberts senior the sum I was Assessed
for the poor of Chester Meeting</cell>
<cell>100
</cell></row>
<row><cell>1813</cell>
<cell>Paid Enoch Roberts (John Roberts son) the sum
I was Assessed for the Meetinghouse</cell>
<cell>100
</cell></row>
<row><cell>10 Mo 8</cell>
<cell>Paid Samuel Haines my Tax for 1813</cell>
<cell>232</cell></row>
</table>
<pb n="03" facs="sc203919"/>
<div type="entry"><p>Sitting by my fire this evening I was brought into a state of reflection about a small visit I performed in the neighborhood of North Wales in the State of Pennsylvania and thinking some of my kind young friends in that place would like to know how I come to do it and advantage I thought to receive by it and not knowing but an account of it writing would be of use to them I thought I would just sit down and relate the as near as my recollection would serve all the occurrences that was pleasing and those that were not. I left home on Second Day in the morning went I Rowland's in order to get some necessary things that should want while I was on the visit but being detained there three or four hours longer than I expected did not get to Josiah Roberts house till they had just done dinner Josiah's wife Mary informed me that Jos[indecipherable] had gone in his chair to</p>

<p>After taking dinner at Josiah I walked to uncle Joseph Matlack's enquiring if Josiah had come. My cousin informed me that Henry Warrington Jr. had taken the pains to assist them in getting to the river and making no stay walked on till I met Henry returning back in the chair who seemed a little surprised at seeing me come so late. I told him the reason, asking him if he thought I might cross the river handy and after a little more conversation with him</p>
<pb n="04" facs="sc203920"/>
<p>I told him I had come to this conclusion: if when I come to the river and there was so much ice or it was so much I could not get across I would just turn about and go home and be content, he told me I must not be discouraged to but if it so happened that I did not cross come back to his house and he would take me early next morning in time to the river that I might get to Byberry Meeting. I signified to him I would go to the river and wait for and opportunity to cross and if should fall out that I got over safe then I would look upon it as a good sign for me to think I was going [last word indecipherable]so biding him farewell</p>
<p>When I got to the river the ferryman said I was a lucky man to come just in the right time for good crossing.</p>
<p>I asked if he thought there was any such thing as luck. Getting into the boat we had a long discourse on what luck was when I reached Pennsylvania shore I gave him 25 cents for my ferriage bidding him farewell.</p>
<p>From here I walk up to Byberry and staid all night at my father-in-law's, not going to bed until I had inform them how I had crossed the river</p>
<pb n="05" facs="sc203921"/>
<p>The meeting then adjourned till 9 o'clock tomorrow morning.</p></div>

<div type="entry"><dateline><date>19 of the month and Third of the week,</date></dateline> <p>Friends again assembled pump and to adjournment.
Samuel Smith spoke a few words as the opening of this sitting the meeting then proceeded to the queries and answers. After the 1st query was read and answers from the several quarters to the same some very good remarks were made to the deficiencies that appeared in our members by the answer by William Flanner, Jesse Kersey and several other Friends. Kersey observed that if parents were rightly concerned for themselves other souls being made alive in truth that children would be benefited by observing that was the case with the father whose soul and that of his on would come to be bound in one and the same communion.</p>

<p>2nd query and answer thereto being read, Christopher Healy was engage to make an observation on this and the former one.</p>

<p>3rd query was read and its answer. John Baldwin very lovingly recommended a strict adherence to primitive plainness.</p>

<p>4th query and its answers were read,</p>
<p>5th one also with and next after the sixth Jacob Lindlay said there was abundance of publications in this age of the world but the Scriptures outweighed them all.</p></div>

<note>[[A0011527_005 - A0011527_007 are bound upside down and backwards. Reading sequence is: A0011527_007, A0011527_006, A0011527_005]]</note>
<pb n="06" facs="sc203922"/>
<div type="entry" n="1814-04-17"><p>Leaving home first day morning the 17th of 4th Month 1814 at 6 o'clock walked to William Copper's ferry landed at Ann Street ferry and proceed to Joseph Stokes' near the North Meeting house, where I attended meeting, beginning at the 10th hour, also at 4 o'clock afternoon.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1814-04-18"><dateline><date when="1814-04-18">18th of the month and Second of the week.</date></dateline><p> After about ten minutes spent in solemn silence the introductory minute was read- the representatives from each of the quarterly meetings were called and they answered; some few sent reasons for their not being present.</p>
<p>It was then proposed for Friends who had certificates to produce them to the meeting early which being done. They were next read epistles from all the yearly meetings with which this [yearly meeting] usually corresponds were produced and read much satisfaction and a large committee appointed to make and prepare replies to each of them. The representatives were desired to propose to the meeting a suitable person for clerk and one to assist him. Meeting adjourned till 3 o'clock in the afternoon at which time Friends again assembled. <persName key="w6nk4g54">Thomas Scattergood</persName> on behalf of the representatives proposed John Cox for Clerk and Samuel Beddle to assist him which the meeting concurred with and they were accordingly appointed for this year. The minutes of last year was read over and such parts of them as needed to be considered was done. Next the minutes from the Meeting for Sufferings were read over.</p></div>
<pb n="07" facs="sc203923"/>
<div type="entry" n="1814-04-31"><dateline><date when="1814-04-31">On second day the 31st of the late month 1814</date></dateline><p> going from my own home to J. R. was detained there in procuring some necessaries for my accommodation while on a little visit I intended to perform in the Neighbor of North Wales in the state of Pennsylvania; expecting to have the desirable company of my much Esteemed uncle Joseph Matlack and Josiah Roberts for I had had some conversation with them a few days before about my going with them desiring of them if they thought I had better not go with them [crossed out "they"] [i and crossed out "to w[indecipherable]"] use great freedom and put me of for I had no desire to go on</p>
<p>Leaving J.R. I walked on to Josiah Roberts where I took dinner. His wife Mary informing me that he had gone in his chair to meet with uncle Joseph I was still</p>
<pb n="08" facs="sc203924"/>
<p>On second day the thirty first of the First month 1814 I left home intending to perform a visit in the neighbourhood of North Wales in the state of Pennsylvania and be at Byberry, Horsham and Gwynedd Monthly Meetings. Leaving home in the morning I got over the river to my father-in-law's and lodged there.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1814-05-01"><dateline><date>2nd nigh</date></dateline><p> went with him in his carriage to Byberry Monthly Meeting. After meeting took dinner at Asa Walmsley's and lodged at father-in-law's again.</p></div>

<div type="entry" n="1814-05-02"><dateline><date>Fourth Day morning</date></dateline> <p>having one of his creatures I rode to Horsham Monthly Meeting when</p> </div>
</body></text>
</TEI>