<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader></teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="01" facs="sc203682"/>
<div type="entry" n="1824-06-27"><head>June 1824</head><dateline><date when="1824-06-27">27 of the Sixth Month, 1824.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Asa Matlack went with me to Haddonfield meeting. I remember in my youthful days the name of Haddonfield meeting sounded very savory – there were many famous standard bearers who had attained a good report but they are now very much stripped of their standard bearers and many are become like a standard bearer when he fainteth: yet there are a few name as in Sardis of old preserved<note resp="transcr">Revelation 3:4</note>: I was very poorly and hardly able to keep up but having my mind turned towards them and way opening I went in hopes I should feel better by going out in the fresh air as I have often experienced but was not so this time but thinking it was better to wear away than rust away as many do and as one said when he went to meeting through the most difficulty he had experienced that he went to best purpose the meeting to me was pretty open and satisfactory although I was hardly able to sit much less to stand. I was so poorly all day I was hardly able to keep up but got home and after a refreshing night's sleep and looking over the day I thought I experienced what one formerly said there is that which scattereth and yet increaseth<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 11:24</note> I thought if things had flowed so into my mind when with them I could have done much better and I don't know when I should have done Just now 84th: year of my age Second Day morning as well as usual a rainy morning and I believe much hay catch in the wet weather we have some out in the wet there is token of much rain although the winter was very hard on the winter grain but very little snow yet the spring season has been very favorable and wheat and rye and grass seldom if ever looked more promising well will it be if it has an humbling effect as it should have instead of the contrary: and we be like the man we read of whose ground brought forth plenty fully and he concluded he had goods laid up in store for many years and he would say to his soul eat drink and be merry but God said unto him thou fool this night shall thy soul be – required of thee then whose shall these things be which thou hast provided so shall it be with all those that lay up treasures for themselves and are not rich towards God<note resp="transcr">Luke 12:16-21</note>: it is said in Scripture Ephraim is an empty vine he bringeth forth fruit unto himself<note resp="transcr">Hosea 10:1</note> and is it not to fear that there is very many such in these days of great plenty and prospects.</p></div>
<pb n="02" facs="sc203683"/>
<div type="entry" n="1824-06-29"><dateline><date when="1824-06-29">29 of the Sixth Month, 1824.</date></dateline><p> We were informed that our dear dutiful affectionate son John was very ill with convulsion fits he had been afflicted with some light ones a considerable time past at times but now more violent. Third Day went to see him and <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> told us he had had twenty fits since he came about 11 o'clock last night. They came upon him every hour but not so hard afternoon he seemed to revive and appeared sensible but could say but very little I asked him if he knew <emph rend="italic">make</emph> said Father: but the fits soon came on him again and continued till about 11 o'clock. On Third Day night he died: on Fifth Day. At 4th hour people met to the burial and a solemn time it appeared to be. Ann Quicksill, an acceptable young minister, had something to say to the people very savory and acceptable, and there was something satisfactory at last and comforting. He was about 46 years old, has left a worthy widow and five children, and they buried one a daughter a few years ago. He told his daughter Susannah when he was first taken poorly he did not expect to live much longer and he said he hoped he should suffer his last here and hopes he should go where – trouble would be no more and we have no doubt but he is gone out of the reach of trouble where the wicked cease from troubling and the weary are at rest for he has been preserved from the spots and stains of his world in a good degree: I never knew him tell a lie nor swear nor steal or cheat. He joined his friends in testimony zealously against drunkenness and the excessive use of strong drink unchastity and profane language he appeared to stand very clear of. He has left three sons and two daughter as comely, innocent, sweet spirited, well disposed children as I know of. If he had shortened his days with hard drinking as many do or in rioting lightness or vanity in superfluities as many do his latter end might have been very different from what it was.</p>
<p>Heard of the death of Joseph Scattergood, son of the worthy Thomas. Middle aged. Left a large family of children his wife was William Roger's his daughter: and of the death of John Field both of Philadelphia and oh we see how the fashion of this world passes away and how transitory it is how many can say with one of old, few and evil have been the days of thy servant [Genesis 47:9].</p>
<p>[marginal note] Short and wearisome pilgrimage many have here </p></div>
<pb n="03" facs="sc203684"/>
<div type="entry" n="1824-07-08"><head>July 1824</head><dateline><date when="1824-07-08">8 of the Seventh Month.</date></dateline><p> At our Monthly Meeting. Middling, not much animation.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-07-11"><dateline><date when="1824-07-11">11.</date></dateline><p> First Day the first time we met at 10 o'clock which prevailing party had concluded all our meetings should begin at 10. It was quite silent and not satisfactory to me: go and learn what these things meaneth etc. was what arrested my mind but the waters seemed too low to say anything.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-07-15"><dateline><date when="1824-07-15">15.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. <persName key="w6wx87x7">My wife</persName> so unwell as to keep her bed all day and Hannah has the ague and fever and myself very poorly none of us got to meeting. Weather very warm.  It tries me more than the cold weather I am so feeble I can hardly crawl about.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-07-18"><dateline><date when="1824-07-18">18.</date></dateline><p> First Day. My granddaughter Mary went with me to Evesham meeting but I was so poorly it was hard for me to keep up on my feet yet the meeting was to some satisfaction although I seemed not able to clear myself I thought it ended some savor I wanted to see my dear grandchildren and their mother my son John's worthy widow who seemed to bear their loss commendable.</p>
<p>A few days ago Josiah Roberts's house was burnt down by burning the chimney: where his tenant lives on the old homestead place where the dear old Israliteish friend <persName key="w6wh4nqv">Robert Frinch</persName> used to live. See the way and fashion of this world how it passes away. Second Day morning a fine shower a prospect of a very plentiful season may it prove a blessing – for what man's condition can be worse whom plenty starves and blessing curs prosperity and great plenty has ever proved the greatest trial on virtual or true religion all along in the accounts of the suffering of the martyrs when ever they were tried with ease and prosperity they began to differ amongst themselves about trifles about the meaning of a passage of Scripture their creeds and ceremonies so amongst our first Friends when they were released from sufferings frailties and deficiencies prevailed among them which could not when under the greatest suffering.  Hence it is said few ever bore prosperity unhurt or without loss of the best life few ever made better by great riches yet they might be as rich as Job or Abraham if they were as faithful as they were.</p></div>
<pb n="04" facs="sc203685"/>
<div type="entry" n="1824-07-20"><dateline><date when="1824-07-20">20 of Seventh month.</date></dateline><p> See memorial concerning Sarah Morris, page 344. But too many are contented without witnessing the renewings of divine life in which only there is life – if they are but preserved from gross evils and go on in prosperity: they sit down easy and think all is well; but oh that they may (not too late) find their mistake and that they have pleased themselves with favors which they have unthankfully received and so stop short of greater by not desiring them: see here the dangerous state of prosperity, peace, and plenty – has not many more been cheated out of their chiefest good in this way than by the love of strong drink which <persName key="w6s1844s">Anthony Benezet</persName> supposes fifty million are destroyed yearly by the excessive use of strong drink. The unlawful love of lawful things some of the greatest experienced say is the greatest snare the crafty devil ever had to catch religiously inclined people, greater than that of strong drink, says <persName key="w6b38kp0">Thomas Ross</persName> and Thomas Shillitoe in his late excellent address, hence the advice of the apostle, set your affections on things above and not on things below<note resp="transcr">Colossians 3:2</note> – for as we see direful are the consequence of desires misplaced: a rainy day.</p>
<p>One of my neighbors brought me a newspaper to shew me a sermon preached by our kinswoman Priscilla Hunt at New Bedford in New England, Fourth Month 15, 1824, where I see several accounts of some being killed with thunder and vessels struck with the lightning in a terrible manner: in a thunder shower last week near Portsmouth, New Hampshire the electric fluid struck the south schoolhouse in which were about seventy scholars more than half the number were knocked down and many were stunned. Eight or ten were unable for some time to rise up and six or seven when first taken up by the master were apparently dead. Twelve or fourteen were more or less injured the clothes of one took fire and he was considerably burnt and the hair of another singed. All are however recovered or hopefully recovering except two who were instantly deprived of life: two lads, one eleven and the other seven years old. Scarcely a summer but we hear of such awful accounts.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-07-22"><dateline><date when="1824-07-22">22.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting smaller than common about thirty on the men's side a very busy time getting hay. Harvest mostly got in. A number of this small number very sleepy yet to me it was a time of renewal of strength and on deliberation satisfactory although I feel so much of the infirmaries of old age.</p>
<p>[marginal note] [indecipherable] or open apostates ever did us that hurt that prosperity has done</p></div>
<pb n="05" facs="sc203686"/>
<div type="entry" n="1824-07-30"><dateline><date when="1824-07-30">30 of the Seventh Month, 1824.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting middling large and to me I thought I was an evidently owning, satisfactory, favored meeting more of that precious cement than I have known some time feeling nearness and uniting regard when we came out and parted.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-07-29"><dateline><date when="1824-07-29">Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting very small and very poor and silent a busy time getting hay and oats etc., and some sick. No signs of the stirrings of life, a state very different from that our first Friends speak of when they say the powerful over shadowings of the Holy Ghost were frequently witnessed among them when their hearts were tendered even to tears in their silent waiting so that sometimes there was scarcely a dry eye amongst them and they sat trembling in such a solid manner that their very enemies were convinced and the mouths of gainsayers stopped. Religion is not such a trifling thing that there is neither good nor harm in it though very many treat it as if it was so: no worth troubling themselves about it so pay little or no regard to it: until all earthly comforts fail – which we see they often do fail which we see the often do and surely must there is a way of attending meetings to the greatest and most glorious of purposes and there is a way of attending them to no purpose as Paul says not for the better<note resp="transcr">1 Corinthians 11:17</note> may we no certainly conclude that if we tend our meetings as not for the better it will be for the worse: the best of meats taint the soonest and the best of things misused become the worst: among our first Friends the privilege of attending meetings was among their best thing for they attended them at the hazard of their lives and their persecutors said they would keep up their meetings if their corn dropped in the ground they could – rejoice in the reward of peace: which is the wages of the faithful more than the increase of corn, wine, or oil: or all earthly treasure they knew that would sustain uphold and support them when all earthly treasures would fail but how can we sit down easy with the performance of a round of religious duties without the life or an answer of peace which is all we meet together for and is enough: But to tend meetings in a trifling, indifferent, dry, formal way in a dull drowsy loathsome lukewarm way as Priscilla Hunt told was an abominable sacrifice what can operate or mitigate more against the cause [it] was profess[ed]  to espouse. It has been said that truth has ever suffered disgrace to any trade or business even market people got nothing by it.</p></div>
<pb n="06" facs="sc203687"/>
<div type="entry" n="1824-08-01"><head>August 1824</head><dateline><date when="1824-08-01">1st of the Eighth Month 1824.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting pretty large and an open favored time to me and there was tokens of its being satisfactory to others there appeared openness feeling nearness in some however the lukewarm were stirred up and those in a striving way encouraged I was much exhausted when I got home my son Joseph's wife was here and his son <persName key="w6jn3260">Nathan</persName> and his wife and child one of the sixth generation in my family I have now lived to see my grandson <persName key="w6jn3260">Nathan Hunt's</persName> little daughter my son's grandchild.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-08-05"><dateline><date when="1824-08-05">5.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting I thought smaller than common and I thought it was a low time and no wonder to see the easy indolent state of us high professors: rich wise diligent and careful and full of earthly treasures but poor dull and unconcerned respecting that of witnessing the renewings of divine love in which only there is life yet poor and low as things seemed to be we seemed not altogether destitute of some stirrings of life and tokens of the ownings of truth for my friends seemed to own me although I dealt very close and plain with those at ease in Zion and are trusting in the mountains of Samaria,<note resp="transcr">Amos 6:1</note> etc.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-08-08"><dateline><date when="1824-08-08">8.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. At our meeting I had something very close and striking but kept it to myself another stepped in and took up all the latter part of the meeting.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-08-12"><dateline><date when="1824-08-12">12 was Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting very small and very poor till last then appeared some stirrings of life and ownings of truth several of our you ministers appeared savory and it ended to my satisfaction in a good degree of sweetness and savor.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-08-15"><dateline><date when="1824-08-15">15.</date></dateline><p> First Day having a desire to see my daughter-in-law my son John's widow and her children we went to Evesham meeting which I think was more lively than common (Ann Quicksil a granddaughter of that worthy elder Ephraim Tomlinson<note resp="transcr"><emph rend="italic">Friends Miscellany</emph> 3 (1832): 145-152, includes a lengthy “Testimony” by John Hunt on Ephraim Tomlinson, dated 17th of 8 Month, 1824, and an “Extract of a Letter from the same” dated 8 Month 24, 1824.</note> an Israelite indeed of unblemished character) spoke very beautifully and Elizabeth Balderston also and after them I had a favored open time to good satisfaction – something owning feeling nearness and uniting regard appeared at parting I came home very much tired and expected being very poorly afternoon dined at Hinchman Haine's and called to see Samuel Lippincott at Asa Roberts who is very poorly lately had a stroke of palsy but now chill and fever.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-08-19"><dateline><date when="1824-08-19">19.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting nothing material.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-08-22"><dateline><date when="1824-08-22">22.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting almost not quite overwhelmed with a dull indolent spirit the sluggard shall be clothed with rags his own righteousness which are as filthy rags.</p></div>
<pb n="07" facs="sc203688"/>
<div type="entry" n="1824-08-29"><dateline><date when="1824-08-29">29 of the Eighth Month, 1824.</date></dateline><p> At our preparative meeting very small about thirty or forty on the men's side has been the number of late although it may be with us as it was with Israel of old when it was said the Lord gave them their heart's desire but sent leanness into their souls.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 106:15</note> Although leanness and poverty did abound in a great degree yet there was something of the stirrings of life and savor of truth at last. But oh: the dullness and want of life in answering the queries. As Thomas Shillitoe says it is painful to sit and hear and see and feel the feebleness in transacting this business. Many or divers families sick with chill and fever and many deaths we lately hear of Sarah Haines an elder, wife of Job, died with very short illness and five or six others we hear the death of: within a few days and divers in the very bloom of life: I have heard that the flux is very mortal at Julitown a few miles above [Mount] Holly it is said five were buried in one day in one graveyard: one would think it was an alarming awakening time: but it seems as if nothing but death itself can awaken the people fallen asleep in the lap of this world and rocked in the cradle of ease and carnal security: as a certain minister said the time will come when the enemy can rock the no longer: and as Solomon says how long will thou sleep oh sluggard how long will it be ere thou awake out of sleep yet a little sleep a little slumber a little folding of he hands to sleep so shall thy poverty Come as one that traveleth and thy want as an armed man<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 6:9-11</note> although possessed of thousands: Abraham Cole very rich and Isacar Meeks very poor both buried today but I was so poorly I was hardly able to keep up: both young men between 20 and 30 Isacar Meeks worked for us last season: very thoughtless about leaving this world to all appearance many many many appear to be.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-09-01"><head>September 1824</head><dateline><date when="1824-09-01">1 of the Ninth Month.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. William Forster from England was there lately returned from his visit in New England since last spring and he had a great deal to say stood an hour or more but I could hear but little of what he said but I am told it was very pertinent and excellent. But I could perceive but little or no animation tenderness or contrition nothing like what our first Friends tell of two or three hundreds convinced at one meeting where they say there was scarcely a dry eye amongst them at some meetings and they trembled as they sat the tears running down their cheeks. His voice and delivery not so pleasing as some. Many very dull and drowsy whilst he was preaching: and although the language of mortality sounds louder and louder daily. We hear of burials: Charles Towns a young man to be buried this afternoon of Evesham and we hear of divers now very ill of a fever male and female. Better to see ten men weeping in meeting than one a sleeping like Euticus when Paul was preaching till midnight.<note resp="transcr">Acts 20:9</note></p>
<p>[marginal note] Sarah Haines was at my son John's burial last of the Sixth Month cheerful and well. Little did she think her time was so short: she spoke encouraging to me.</p></div>
<pb n="08" facs="sc203689"/>
<div type="entry" n="1824-09-31"><dateline><date when="1824-08-31">31 of the Eighth Month, 1824.</date></dateline><p> On Third Day I went with my neighbors Josiah Roberts and wife and Samuel Church to Burlington Quarterly Meeting a very rainy stormy morning the house pretty well filled. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName>, William Forster and many others great ministers there but it seemed to be a poor low time no less than five small appearances in the forepart who seemed to love to paddle in shallow water but at last <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> rose up but did not rise very high but seemed to help in the time of answering queries things seemed to me to be very old fashioned dry and formal they are scholars and capable of transacting their business like lawyers or casting up merchants accounts. I had some close remarks to make on the state of society but there seemed neither time nor heart room to do much in the present state yet it end better than some of us expected as some expressed I had sweet satisfaction in the company of many of my friends and relations and we returned with good satisfaction as several expressed: seen and heard from divers of my friends in Pennsylvania and distributed divers letters to good satisfaction one to William Forster and divers others in viewing the day's work after a refreshing sleep felt peace and satisfaction and I was favored with strength to keep up although a rainy stormy day. I hear that the dysentery or flux is or has been very mortal in Egg Harbor in divers places and the fever and chill and fever in many places. Divers very ill.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-09-02"><dateline><date when="1824-09-02">2 of the Ninth Month.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting small poor and low yet at last I ventured to stand up with a prospect of saying a few words and was evidently helped beyond prospect or expectation to good satisfaction. I stayed at Moorestown all night lodged at Morgan Hollinshead's whose wife and Mary Lippincott who lives there were very exceeding kind to me. I visited several families to sweet satisfaction to myself and them as they expressed.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-09-03"><dateline><date when="1824-09-03">3 Sixth [Day] of the week</date></dateline><p> was at our select meeting at Moorestown an owning strengthening time to me I believe: however openness feeling nearness and sweetness appeared amongst us: some clothing to cover my nakedness although life seems so low and I so feeble I seem hardly able to totter about. But oh the dryness and dullness in answering our queries is painful indeed as Thomas Shillitoe remarks but bright and wise in temporals.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-09-05"><dateline><date when="1824-09-05">5.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Having a desire to see my son John's widow and children I went to Evesham meeting. I was so unwell and feeble I could hardly keep up. A poor time hardly clothing to cover our nakedness no satisfaction except that of seeing my grandchildren and their mother.</p></div>
<pb n="09" facs="sc203690"/>
<div type="entry" n="1824-10-07"><head>October 1824</head><dateline><date when="1824-10-07">7th of the Tenth [sic.</date></dateline><p> Ninth] Month 1824.<note resp="transcr">Ann Quicksall's death, cited in the passage below, was in 9th month 11th 1824, not 10th month; she was aged 33 and was buried in Friends burial ground in Evesham. John Hunt died less than two weeks later.</note> Was our Monthly Meeting rather smaller than common but it was a strengthening, favored time to me if I am not mistaken both in the first and last meeting for discipline although in answering our queries as usual want of life and savor: superficial dry formality trifling indifferency and loathsome lukewarmness now when the fruits of the field of every sort are in abundance especially apple and peaches more than can be used and abundance rot on the ground we hear of much sickness and frequent deaths and in particular amongst the youth one about nineteen near Cropwell died with a fever with about three days illness divers such instances there have been lately of lads or young men suddenly snatched away in their full strength and divers we hear of laying now very ill but it seems to make very little impressions on those left behind.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1824-10-10"><dateline><date when="1824-10-10">10 of the Tenth [sic.</date></dateline><p> Ninth] Month. First Day. We went to the burial of Ann Quicksil at <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines's</persName>. She died of a fever with a few days illness about twenty years of age or more she was a very hopeful minister of an unblemished character she preached to us at my son John's burial last of the Sixth Month. Sarah Haines was also there in usual health now both gone to their long homes and room to hope they are gone to a better world. <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> and myself had something to say to the people at the house and Ebenezer Robert and Hannah Warrington took up most of the time at meeting. The day ended to my satisfaction in a good degree: there was another burial of an ancient woman at the same time about a quarter of a mile off.</p></div></body></text>
</TEI>