<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader></teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="01" facs="sc203817"/>
<div type="entry" n="1805-05-11"><head>May 1805</head><dateline><date when="1805-05-11">Seventh Day the 11th of the 5th Month, 1805.</date></dateline><p> Commenced a journey to Pennsylvania in company with Uncle William M[missing].  We met at Glou[ce]ster at 11 o'clock, crossed the river from there to the point, House from there we rode up to Philadelphia which is about two miles through very pretty meadows. Come in the city of the lowest end of Front Street a few sq[uares] then turned up to 2nd Street to Draw Bridge still along Second Street to Walnut Street, up Walnut Street to 3rd street, along s[ai]d to M[arket] Street, up M[arket] Street to the sign of the spread Eagle kept by John Tomlinson on the N[orth] side where we had our horses put to hay and took dinner with Jacob Trasel's next door above s[ai]d tavern. After dinner we walked up M[arket] Street to Evans steam engine for sawing stone, grinding plaster etc. S[ai]d engines are made here. Mill stones stone cutting etc. carried on in the best manner I presume. Being satisfied with seeing returned back to Trasels had our horses up and proceeded up said street and went to the Water Works on Schuylkill. Then crossed over the bridge and up the hill. [crossed out] were 3 roads that come together. Then took the West Chester road leaving how I shall take name all the taverns we passed by the first from Schuylkill is the sign of William Penn kept by Lewis Lewis next is Joseph Baldin sign of the King of Prussia 3 M[iles] next is Phillip Williams sign of the Red Lion 2 next James Pilt no sign next Wm Bittles Spread Esq  next</p></div>
<pb n="02" facs="sc203818"/>
<div type="entry" n="1805-05-12"><p>[written upside down at the top] Started from [crossed out] first day evening in company with Poli Lewis</p>
<p>[12] This morning we arose as usual and having spent the morning in looking at his building &amp; apparatus</p></div>
<pb n="03" facs="sc203819"/>
<div><p>[top of page missing]
[missing] we [missing] long [missing] [indecipherable] then take the [indecipherable] [missing] to the Institution [missing] mill about 1 1/2 m[ile] [missing] small village called [missing] consisting of [indecipherable] Tavern sign Wheat Sheaf kept by James Jefferies Mill on State Road in Goshen Township Chester Creek crossed below s[ai]d Matlack is 21 miles from Schuylkill</p> <figure>[sketch of map]</figure></div> 
</body></text>
</TEI>