<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader></teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="01" facs="sc204051"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-16"><head>January 1820</head><dateline><date when="1820-01-16">16th of the First Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> First Day. I went to our meeting, concluding [that] it would be right for me to quite shut up, and so we sat till late. Then I stood up in diffidence and fear, thinking I would only express a few sentences without I should find strength to go through, and was helped evidently to good satisfaction. Oh, what a favor continued!</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-17"><dateline><date when="1820-01-17">17.</date></dateline><p> A great storm of rain and snow together, and high wind. Of high winds we had but very little of late. Clears up fine and moderate. See [Thomas] Clarkson's 1st volume, <emph rend="italic">Memoirs [of] <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName></emph>, page 245, in a letter to his wife just as he was going off to America: My mind is wrapped up in a saying as thy father's: I desire not riches, but to owe nothing – and truly that is wealth and more than enough. To live is a snare attended with many sorrows. But how few in these days are much afraid of this snare, although very many are made to feel the sorrowful effects of it. As the old saying is:<quote type="poem">
<l>Of the love of wealth beware,</l>
<l>A little is enough; too much a snare.</l>
</quote></p>
<p>As one of the ancients said: man wants but little here, nor wants that little long. As divers of our worthies have said and we have seen that leaving children great possessions has proved a great snare to very many, and proved a curse instead of a blessing. The prayer of Agur was: remove far from me vanity and lies; give me neither poverty nor riches, but feed me with food convenient for me.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 30:8-9</note> The middle way to every step reveal, nor let me heights of woe nor pleasure feel.</p>
<p>Read an account of the poor benighted Africans, now groaning under the grossest ignorance, superstition, and idolatry. What shall we render for all our benefits and blessings, both temporal and spiritual? What people are under greater obligations than we are? Be thou instructed, oh Jerusalem, lest I make thee desolate a land not inhabited, and my soul depart from thee.<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 6:8</note> And let it be remembered that Jerusalem and Antioch were once the churches of Christ, but where are they now? So we read: oh, Jerusalem, Jerusalem, how oft would I have gathered thee; but ye would not behold. She is left desolate.<note resp="transcr">Luke 13:34-35</note></p>
<p>There is a satisfaction in doing but a little good, [even] if it is only in mending shoes, which has been my employment this cold snowy weather. And making brooms.</p>
<p>[marginal note] * Some are starving, and [others] suffocating, smothering with abundance.</p></div>
<pb n="02" facs="sc204052"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-20"><dateline><date when="1820-01-20">20 of the First Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. Not the poorest to me, though silent. A considerable opening if I had had command and commission and ability. Seeing and feeling the advantage of it, may I never move without it.</p>
<p>I think for several weeks past we have heard of burials almost daily, and sometimes two of day. Our doctors seem to have full employ, although in general it seems not a sickly time. But our country is getting very full of people, and many die with the consumption and palsy suddenly, and many aged people have lately been taken away. Joseph Witherwil of Burlington, eighty or upwards, had been a healthy man. Went to bed as well as usual, died with an apoplectic fit suddenly. A reputable friend, Josiah Foster – also of Haddonfield about eighty – has been affected with a palsy complaint of latter years. And <persName key="w6zx2b7v">Isaac Andrews</persName>, seventy and upwards of Evesham – all within a few days buried, and many more.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-23"><dateline><date when="1820-01-23">23.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Waters but lowish; not that savor of life and evident ownings of truth as at some other times. Yet not much cause of complaint. Thou shalt follow after thy lovers, etc.<note resp="transcr">Hosea 2:7</note> What we love best, what our desires, hearts, and affections are placed and fixed upon [is] of vast importance. The direful effects of desires misplaced, etc. Very dry still. Severe, freezing weather.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-25"><dateline><date when="1820-01-25">25.</date></dateline><p> A few words of advice of <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> to his friend, page 233, [Thomas] Clarkson's 1st volume: sink down into the seasoning, [settling] gift of God and wait to distinguish between thy own desires and the Lord's requirings.</p>
<p>Same book in 1682 and 1683. Rapid improvements in building of Philadelphia and the country near it. Page 273, he says, As to outward things, we are satisfied; the land good, the air clear and sweet, the springs plentiful, and provision good and easy to be come at an innumerable quantity of wild fowl and fish. In fine, here is what an Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob would be well contented with, and service enough for God – for the fields are here white for harvest. O, how sweet is the quiet of these parts, freed from the anxious and troublesome solicitations, hurries, and perplexities of woeful Europe!
<pb n="03" facs="sc204053"/>
This was the blessed and happy state of the people in the first building of Philadelphia and in the first settling of this country. It brings to my mind that beautiful passage of Scripture where it is said: mercy and truth are met together; righteous and peace have kissed each other; truth has sprung out of the earth, and righteousness looks down from heaven.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 85:10-11</note>
But in page 274, he says: If Friends here keep to God in the justice, mercy, equity, and fear of the Lord, their enemies will be their footstool. If not, their heirs, and my heirs too, will loose all, and desolation will follow. But blessed be the Lord. We are well, and live in the dear love of God and the fellowship of his tender heavenly spirit. And our faith is for ourselves and one another, that the Lord will be with us, a king and councilor forever.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-27"><dateline><date when="1820-01-27">27.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our preparative meeting. First silent as to me. J. Justice appeared in meeting for business. Report was made of the state of our schools, on which subject I had a right, satisfactory time.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Our committees give favorable accounts of our schools, but I fear we shall lose sight of what our schools ought to be or teachers in them.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-28"><dateline><date when="1820-01-28">28.</date></dateline><p> I read over a book of 125 pages before 10 o'clock, very beautiful <emph rend="italic">Poems</emph> by Charlotte Richardson.<note resp="transcr">Charlotte Richardson, Poems Written on Different Occasions. Kimber, Conrad, &amp; Company, no. 93, Market street, and no. 170, South second street, 1806.</note> Very cold again.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-01-30"><dateline><date when="1820-01-30">30.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. At our meeting, which some thought was in a good degree a favored, an open, owning time, and ended reputably. I thought there was pleasantness and feeling nearness after meeting. Very freezing, cold weather.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-02-03"><head>February 1820</head><dateline><date when="1820-02-03">3.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. Not the poorest to me. Though silent as to me, there was a pretty deal said, and I thought it ended pretty savory.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-02-06"><dateline><date when="1820-02-06">6 of the Second Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Came off pretty well, I thought. Yesterday, 5 of the Second Month, our dear Friends Henry Warrington Jr., <persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Collins</persName>, <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName>, and Ann Stokes were crossing the river at Wright's Ferry on the ice, in their wagon, and the horses and wagon broke through the ice and <persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Collins</persName> and <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> were drowned. Henry and A. Stokes were saved. <persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Collins</persName> and <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> were two of the most unblemished characters of any we have amongst us. It is near twenty years since <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> came forth among us. <persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Collins</persName> was a very lusty woman and Ann a very small woman.
<pb n="04" facs="sc204054"/>
<persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Collins</persName>, 68, left five children. <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName>, 46, never married. They were crossing the river to Byberry to see their kinsfolks, James Thorington and his mother. Both very sick, and have been so a considerable time. This is one of the heaviest strokes to very many, and the most alarming accidents that we have heard of. Where could we have picked out any seemingly more safe from danger? Oh what need there is to be prepared to meet trials and troubles! They were here to visit us, several of them, lately, and now they, their horses and wagon all in the river under the ice!
<persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Collins</persName> was my brother Joshua's wife. Left four sons and a daughter. She was an elder, in universal esteem amongst her Friends. <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> was a minister universally beloved.
[marginal note] No less than six Friends had remarkable dreams just before these women were drowned, so that one said, what is a-coming?</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-02-08"><dateline><date when="1820-02-08">8 of the Second Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> We went to see divers of our friends under great trouble for the loss of their and our dear friends (<persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Collins</persName> and <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName>). First we went to see E.C.'s daughter Rachel Roberts. Silence for a time – like that of Job of old and his friends –prevailed. Although there was such great cause of mourning, yet not without hope, for there seemed no cause to doubt but our loss was their everlasting gain. It was a sweet, solacing time. We were informed that <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> was lively and savory in her appearance in the ministry at Westfield, but a few days before they were drowned.</p>
<p>We then called to see Joseph Cowperthwaite, in a deep consumption. Had a pretty little time with the family, then called to see the widow Stokes, who was pulled out of the water when E.C. and <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> were plunged under the ice. We had a solemn, savory, satisfactory time with their family, then went to our cousin Benne Warrington's and dined. And then to our cousin Henry Warrington's who was with and had the care of our drowned, deceased friends, and lost his wagon and horses and all – all together a very dreadful, heavy stroke to him. But we had a sweet, satisfactory time together, and I do not remember when I went to bed under a feeling sense of more sweetness and peace of mind. Storm came on, and we stayed all night.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-02-09"><dateline><date when="1820-02-09">9.</date></dateline><p> We went to see Josiah Lippincot's widow, who was buried but a few weeks ago. Lidia Lippincott and Ann Quicksil was with us, and had acceptable service in the family of eleven children. All seemed to end very well. Then we went to see our cousin, Henry Warrington, who lately had his barn burnt, then got well home.</p></div>
<pb n="05" facs="sc204055"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-02-10"><dateline><date when="1820-02-10">10th of the Second Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> Was our monthly meeting, and a favored, open, owning, satisfactory one it was to me. Though through close plain dealing, precious was the feeling nearness and sweetness when meeting broke up. A great snow fell last night it is thought it awful, believing many poor would suffer much, as well as the beasts of the field.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-02-11"><dateline><date when="1820-02-11">11.</date></dateline><p> Reading George Fox's <emph rend="italic">Journal</emph>. See page 434: All take heed of sitting down in the earth and having your minds in the earthly things, coveting and striving for the earth. For to be carnally minded is death, or brings death, and covetousness is idolatry. There is too much strife and contention about that idol, which make[s] too many go out of the sense and fear of God, so that some have lost morality, humanity, and true Christianity and charity. Therefore be awakened to righteousness and keep awakened; for the enemy soweth his tares while men and women are asleep in carnal security.<note resp="transcr">Matthew 13:25</note> Therefore so many slothful ones go in their filthy rags and have not the fine linen, the righteousness of Christ. Again, 435: Have a care to keep down that greedy earthly mind that raveneth and coveteth after the riches and things of this world, lest ye fall into the low region like the gentiles or heathen and lose the Kingdom of God that is everlasting – but seek that first. And God knows what ye have need of, who takes care for all, both in heaven and in earth. Thanks be unto God for his unspeakable gifts, both temporal and spiritual.</p>
<p>Yesterday, I had something to say on that of earthly mindedness, which might not go down very pleasant to all. But I do not feel uneasy about it, so I spend my time – as some say – in wasting of paper. Again see page 460, second volume, G. Fox's <emph rend="italic">Journal</emph>: What good doth all your profession of religion and the Scriptures do without life?</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-02-13"><dateline><date when="1820-02-13">13.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. Three of their ministers from Burlington were at our meeting (Abigail Barker, Margaret Allinson, and Hannah Smith) and they did do beautifully, famously, and worthily. But I kept my lesson to myself, though I think it was too good to be lost. Behold, said Job: he knoweth the way that I take,<note resp="transcr">Job 23:10</note> which was the way the Lord's people formerly took. Upon the most secret search shall we not find they were a thinking, considering, musing, listening, harking, studying, contemplating, meditating people? Exercised in this inward home work, not loving too wander nor walking after things that did not profit, etc., etc., etc.?</p></div>
<pb n="06" facs="sc204056"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-02-14"><dateline><date when="1820-02-14">14 of the Second Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> My daughter Abigail and I went with Samuel Church and his wife to Haddonfield Monthly Meeting, which was large. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> was raised in great eminence in the exercise of his most distinguished gift. After him, Elizabeth Barton appeared large in prayer, and two or three more appeared, and at last I thought there was a solemnity not commonly felt at meeting, crowned with savor and life.</p>
<p>I said in my heart, O, how are these people favored with manifold blessings, both spiritual and temporal! Oh, the labor bestowed upon us, to gather us as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings but they would not.<note resp="transcr">Luke 13:34</note> All seemed sweet, loving, and inviting at parting. O, that we might be willing to be gathered not like Jerusalem, of whom it was said: O, Jerusalem, Jerusalem, how often would I have gathered thee as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings.<note resp="transcr">Matthew 23:37</note></p>
<p>We have had very freezing cold weather [for] many weeks or months, and much snow. But now, 15 of the Second Month, it grows so warm winter clothes feel burdensome. And it swept away the snow and looks like spring. Although we have lately and but few days ago had so much very cold weather and much snow, yet now, 16 of Second Month, there was a shower and thunder and lightning.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-02-17"><dateline><date when="1820-02-17">17.</date></dateline><p> Fifth day. We – that is, my daughters, Abigail and Hannah – set off to Westfield meeting through a very heavy rain [for] the Young Women's Association society of the care of the poor (in which they show a lively zeal, having appointed to meet). There the waters seemed low, as they mostly do and  hardish getting a long [in the] forepart, yet it was at last an open time to good satisfaction; it was not unpleasant to think on it on my bed. At this meeting an invitation was given to the burial of <persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Collins</persName>, to meet at her son-in-law's, David Roberts's, tomorrow at 2 o'clock. She was found this morning about 10 o'clock in the river, just against Market Street and in the wagon body (<persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> and the horses not yet found).</p>
<p>After meeting at Westfield we went to see Adam Riche, a poor man who who has lain several months under great affliction from a wound with a knife in his thigh when killing his hogs, and now his recovery seems doubtful.</p>
<p>This afternoon</p></div>
<pb n="07" facs="sc204057"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-02-18"><dateline><date when="1820-02-18">this 18 of the Second Month 1820, at 2 o'clock</date></dateline><p>, the people met at David Roberts's to the burial of <persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Collins</persName>. His wife's mother and a vast concourse of people there was; seldom, if ever, so many people seen together before – <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> and divers others ministering friends, both men and women. But all were shut up in silence till we came to the grave. There, a friend of Burlington appeared in prayer. As she was drowned and had lain so long under the ice, the people seemed uncommonly anxious to see the corpse, which was preserved perfectly in its natural appearance. For I thought I [had] never seen a corpse so little changed from is natural appearance. As I thought, there was not ever that paleness usually seen in corpse or flesh shrunk with sickness, but more like one in a sweet sleep in health. The people crowding and pressing so earnestly to see the corpse left no time for stillness, quiet, and composure, and I believe was a hindrance to the solemnity, solidity, and weightiness which might have been experienced if the people's minds had been rightly turned and rightly engaged. I have often thought at burials the time might be better employed than it often is, in so much crowding to look at the corpse.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-02-20"><dateline><date when="1820-02-20">20 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Large, open, owning, and satisfactory. We spent this afternoon at Josiah Roberts's, where was divers of the near connections of <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> and <persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Collins</persName>, whose countenances were marked with deep sorrow for the loss of our and their deceased Friends. We had a sitting with them and several sympathizing letters read. Comforting and satisfactory, and it was not unpleasant to look over the day after I got to bed.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-02-24"><dateline><date when="1820-02-24">24.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our preparative meeting to good satisfaction, strengthening. Fine, moderate, showery, spring-like weather.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-02-27"><dateline><date when="1820-02-27">27.</date></dateline><p> First Day. With the approbation of our monthly meeting, I appointed a meeting at West Chester schoolhouse. Forepart, waters seemed low and dull and trying. Without something extraordinary, how can it be otherwise expected, in the state of mind in which people come to meeting? But through evident help in the needful time it growd better, and ended to general satisfaction. I believe it was pleasant to look over the opportunities at several families.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-03-02"><head>March 1820</head><dateline><date when="1820-03-02">2 of the Third Month, Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Elizabeth Kirk and her companions from Pennsylvania were there, and she had savory, acceptable service. All seemed to end well.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-03-05"><dateline><date when="1820-03-05">5.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Elizabeth Kirk was at our meeting again; finding herself not clear, came back and had pertinent, savory service.
<pb n="08" facs="sc204058"/>
<persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> was also there, but said nothing. It was rather a mortifying time to me, and alarming. Ready to abhor myself under some apprehension of the secret deceptions of self and Satan, the worst of all deceivers.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-03-09"><dateline><date when="1820-03-09">9th of the Third Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting, and I believe there was great need of more of it in answering our queries and in handling the discipline, although by the accounts we make out, we seem to conclude all is pretty well.</p>
<p>We have had, a few days past, very severe cold, freezing weather, and now a very great and very cold rain, so that it froze as it fell and the ground was so covered with ice it was difficult and dangerous to walk across the yard. The fences and buildings were covered with ice and all hung with icehickls [icicles] to every rail etc. The trees were so loaded with ice that it broke off many of the tops of trees and limbs, so that the road was blocked up in divers places. Fruit trees were torn to pieces and the trees of the woods were so loaded with ice that they looked in color at a distance like a solid mass of silver, with their tops much bowed down. One of the children brought in a twig of the weeping willow not bigger than a knitting needle, but covered with ice as big as a man's thumb. I thought it might be seen if it held on raining and freezing how easily the trees of the woods might have been destroyed, though the wind was very still. I believe the oldest man living might safely say he never seen the like. One of our trees before the meeting house door was turned up by the roots, and the tops of others in the yard almost all broke off. A token of a bowing time, say the Methodists.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-03-12"><dateline><date when="1820-03-12">12.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. Simon Gilum of Pennsylvania was there and had sweet, savory, acceptable service. A gathering solemn, covering some thought, although some were overwhelm[ed] with drowsiness. To these, an alarm was sounded.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-03-15"><dateline><date when="1820-03-15">15.</date></dateline><p> Was our select meeting at Haddonfield. Charles Osborn, from the state of Ohio, a very great minister, was there and had a great deal to say. Came off middling well, though I thought life did not rise as at some times.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-03-16"><dateline><date when="1820-03-16">16.</date></dateline><p> Was our quarterly meeting. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> first, and then Charles Osborn, were both very large in testimony. The meeting large. I had some share in the labor in last meeting, and not the smallest part, but came off with satisfaction, without condemnation.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-03-18"><dateline><date when="1820-03-18">18.</date></dateline><p> We went to see our cousin Eli Evans and wife. Her mother very low and weak.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-03-19"><dateline><date when="1820-03-19">19.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Some covering without condemnation.</p></div>
<pb n="09" facs="sc204059"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-03-20"><dateline><date when="1820-03-20">20th of the Third Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> Charles Osborn, a native of Carolina or Tennessee, but now lives in the Indiana country, appointed a meeting at Moorestown and preached and prayed near two hours. And no doubt very acceptable to most or all, but I thought life and animation was wanting. Our first Friends tell of meetings where there was much tenderness and contrition, sometimes even to trembling and tears, scarcely a dry eye. But, alas, how far is our state from this! Instead of tokens of tenderness and tears, numbers could not keep awake. So it seems it is as one prophesied: it would be powerful preachers, but dull hearers. Good sermons should be as music to a sleepy man. Is it not so, as Scott says: they go to meetings and are pleased with their fine preachers but go home and remain just the same? And so it is said it was in the days of the prophet: thy voice is to them as a pleasant song of one that hath a pleasant voice; they hear thy words but will not do them; each one returns to his covetousness.<note resp="transcr">Ezekiel 33:31</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-03-23"><dateline><date when="1820-03-23">23.</date></dateline><p> Was our preparative meeting. All pretty well. This afternoon at three we went to the burial of Evans Dudley, died of a typhus fever in midst of his days. Left a wife and family of young children. <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> (just returned from a several months journey in Pennsylvania) had a pretty deal to say and [also] Ann Quicksil and myself. We dined at old Thomas Hooton's; had a satisfactory little time there. It was satisfactory to look over the day – but alas, as Thomas à Kempis says, we are not to depend on any one disposition of mind with which we feel ourselves affected. He says this is fickle and of short duration and so it seems to be a little like the weather: calms and storms, etc.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Weather fine, spring-like.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-03-26"><dateline><date when="1820-03-26">26.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. At our meeting. Ebenezer Roberts out again after being confined all winter. I hope it ended pretty well and generally satisfactory.</p>
<p>See the writings of Hannah Moore, 8th volume, page 274: The voice of conscience is drowned by the clamors of the world. Prosperous fortunes, unbroken health, flattering friends, buoyant spirits, a spring tide of success: these are the occasions when the very abundance of God's mercies is apt to fill the heart till it hardens it. Loaded with riches, crowned with dignities, successful in enterprises, beset with snares in the shape of honors, with perils under the mask of pleasures, then it is that the already saturated heart tomorrow shall be as this day and more abundant; is more in unison than what shall I render to the Lord. And as we read, how hard it is for a rich man to enter the Kingdom of Heaven.<note resp="transcr">Luke 18:25</note></p>
<p>See Hannah Moore, 8th volume, page 322: Every disorder, irregularity, and excess which religion prohibits is as contrary to our comfort, health, and happiness here as it is fatal to our eternal interest and should be especially avoided on the ground of natural and spiritual judgment. Again, 323: our apostle frequently includes lovers of their own selves in his catalogue of grievous offenders; he considers selfishness as a state of mind inconsistent with Christianity. Yet may we not venture to assert that among the prominent faults of our age is a growing selfishness? In a <emph rend="italic">Collection of Religious Tracts</emph>, page 107, the words of William Law: That is pure unmixed idolatry that lives wholly to self and not to God, etc. 108: For self love, the greatest of all thieves, being now cast out and all that he hath stolen and hidden thus taken from him and put into the hands of Divine love, every mite becometh a large treasure, etc.</p></div>
<pb n="10" facs="sc204060"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-03-30"><dateline><date when="1820-03-30">30th of the Third Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting to me not the poorest. Upon the closest inspection I am capable of, I have no cause to repent being there, although I fear it is with us as <persName key="w6dn68k9">William Hunt</persName> once told the people, that they looked to him to be very lazy, idle pack. I am very jealous of self deception, the greatest of all deceivers. Although we are not altogether forsaken and cast off, yet I fear we are far from being what we should be and might be, of enjoying the favors and precious fruits and effects of the Christian religion. I once heard that dignified servant of the Lord, Joseph White, once say in his public testimony that he never found that when I will did predominate in him that he ever stood rightly situated for Divine instruction. But as Young says:<quote type="poem">
<l>What cannot resignation do?</l>
<l>It wonders can perform.</l>
<l>That powerful charm thy will be done</l>
<l>Can lay the loudest Storm.</l>
</quote><note resp="transcr">Edward Young, “Resignation”</note></p>

<p>What wisdom to begin with it in time and not put off too late, as it is to be feared too many do. Page 104: every one, wherever he be, that liveth unto self is still under the fall and great apostasy from God. And he says, the heresy of all heresy is an earthly mind. O earth, earth, hear, O earth!<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 22:29</note></p>
<p>[marginal note] Very cold again.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-02"><head>April 1820</head><dateline><date when="1820-04-02">2nd of the Fourth Month 1820, First Day.</date></dateline><p> A very cold snow storm snowed all day and froze smartly. I thought at first I was not well enough to go through the storm, but did get to meeting. And although smaller than common and silent as to myself, I had no cause to repent going. I heard a friend once say when he went to meeting through the most difficulty, he went to best purpose.</p>
<p>An invitation to the burial of Solomon Haines of Upper Evesham, aged 93, it is said.</p></div>
<pb n="11" facs="sc204061"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-03"><dateline><date when="1820-04-03">3 of Fourth Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> Second Day morning. Snow enough to go a-sleighing. See George Fox's <emph rend="italic">Journal</emph>, volume the first, page 98: at a great meeting in the street, among the soldiers I opened unto them that all the traditions they had lived in all their worships and religion and the profession they made of the Scriptures were good for nothing while they lived out of the life and power which those were in who gave forth the Scriptures. See page 85: at a great meeting, the truth had great dominion that day so that those great men present did generally confess to it, saying that they believed this principle must go over the whole world. Daniel speaks of a stone cut out of the mountain without hands and filled the whole earth.<note resp="transcr">Daniel 2:45</note> Again see page 87: The Lord had said unto me if but one man or woman were raised up by his power to stand and live in the same spirit that the prophets and apostles were in who gave forth the Scriptures, that man or woman should shake all the country in their profession for ten miles round.</p>
<p>See page 94: G.F. says, I went to Captain Sands, who, with his wife, seemed somewhat affected with truth. And if they could have held the world and truth together, they would have received it, but they were hypocrites. But alas, is it not to be greatly feared that this is the case with very many? They would receive the truth if they could have held the world and truth together, but none can serve two masters. Ye cannot serve God and Mammon.<note resp="transcr">Matthew 6:24</note>; his servants ye are whom ye obey, whether of sin unto death or of righteousness unto life<note resp="transcr">Romans 6:16</note></p>
<p>Thomas Chalkley, in his journal, tells of a meeting he had at the governor's house on one of the islands. At the close of which, he says, the governor stood up with his Bible in his hand and said: here, if people believe the Scriptures, I am able to prove by this book that the Quakers' principles are the most consistent with the writings of the patriarchs, prophets, and apostles of any people in the world.</p>
<p>George Whitefield, in his journal, says that the Quakers are the best regulated society in the world. But alas, what will all this do for us, without the immediate quickings [of] life and power of truth? As one observes, people of sound principles and bad practices are self-condemned and lie under an highly aggravated guilt. George Fox says all your profession of religion and the Scriptures is good for nothing without the life.</p>
<p>The weather has been very changeable. The appearance of things demonstrate it: although the icicles and the snow, the willow tree is quite green with leaves. My father once told me that the Indians used to say when they had hard winters and unfavourable seasons, the Great Spirit was angry with them. So it appears the Indians did believe in an almighty, overruling power that superintended the universe and presided over the seasons of plenty and scarcity, of health and of sickness, and of heat and of cold. When I am sick, he, if he please, can make me well and give me ease. This has been evident in many instances, in individuals, nations, countries, and cities – Sodom and others.</p></div>
<pb n="12" facs="sc204062"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-05"><dateline><date when="1820-04-05">5th of the Fourth Month 1820.</date></dateline><p> It holds very cold weather, very changeable and trying, but I think it a great mercy we are so well as we are. Many and grievous are the troubles, heart-piercing scenes of sorrow all around us. We hear that John Tathams Jr.'s son of Woodbury, lost his reason a few months ago and was taken to the asylum and made his escape from there and cannot yet be found, and many other scenes of sorrow.</p>
<p>See Murray's <emph rend="italic">Sequel</emph>, Section X, The Benefits of Religious Restraint, page 139 : Let him who wishes for an effectual cure to all the wounds which the world can inflict retire from intercourse with men to intercourse with his Creator, etc. An excellent piece by Blair. See same book, page 145, on seeing the sun set: such is the longest day of human life or existence; before we have learned to use it, we find it at an end.</p>
<p>A certain writer says: the most fatal evil in the world is the sad indifference of mankind to their eternal concerns. Oh, that they were wise, that they understood this, that they would consider their latter end, said the Prophet.<note resp="transcr">Deuteronomy 32:29</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-06"><dateline><date when="1820-04-06">6.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting. I did think there was some fresh stirrings of life among us. Many pertinent remarks, yet great room for improvement. For, alas, when we compare ourselves with our worthy predecessors, how poor, how dry, how dwarfish and formal we appear!</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-07/1820-04-08"><dateline><date from="1820-04-07" to="1820-04-08">7 and 8.</date></dateline><p> Holds very cold for the season.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-09"><dateline><date when="1820-04-09">9.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. I wanted to go to Evesham because Charles Osborn was to be there, but I believe it was well I did not, for we had a precious, good, owning meeting at Moorestown – but seldom the like. Like a full tide, as <persName key="w6dn68k9">William Hunt</persName> sometimes said, the Lord owned up. What an unspeakable mercy continued; we are upheld till this day.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-11"><dateline><date when="1820-04-11">11.</date></dateline><p> Was Third Day. Mildred Ratcliffe from Ohio appointed a meeting at Moorestown, which was large, and she had sweet, savory, acceptable service, and I had a share in the time to good satisfaction; a good meeting.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-12"><dateline><date when="1820-04-12">12.</date></dateline><p> A certain writer says it was an observation of an heathen moralist that no history makes mention of any man who hath been made better by riches, and I doubt if histories of a later date can give a better account, but sure I am – many have been the worse for riches. Thousands have been suffocated, smothered, drowned to death in the embraces of a smiling world, and many good men have been wounded with outward prosperity and stood in great need of being helped out of the mire and clay and cured by the cross.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-13"><dateline><date when="1820-04-13">13.</date></dateline><p> Sixth of the week. At our meeting, Josiah Lippincott and Lidia Matlack were married. Let all things be done decently and in order.<note resp="transcr">1 Corinthians 14:40</note> This, I thought, was observed; and it was an open, satisfactory time to me in a good degree. An invitation was given to the burial of Samuel Hulings, tavern keeper next the meeting house.
<pb n="13" facs="sc204063"/>
He died very unwillingly, they say, in the midst of his days with a short illness with the typhus fever. He has been but a few weeks well recovered of a lingering, dangerous illness. He never made any pretences to religion of any sort, had been a libertine young man and run through his estate, which was considerable. I felt no openness to attend the burial till it was time to go, and then my mind was turned that way and I could not be easy to omit going, although when ever I looked that way the words of the prophet occurred. See Jeremiah 22 and 19: He shall be buried with the burial of an ass, etc. There was not a very large number of people as is common, although in the midst of Moorestown and a tavern keeper. The people were mostly not of our society, but behaved solid and well and I had a pretty solid, open time with them to good satisfaction. I am just now told that the typhus fever is prevalent at Ohio, that three or four died lately in one week and most of them from Jersey, Evesham, etc.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-15"><dateline><date when="1820-04-15">15 of the Fourth Month, Seventh Day.</date></dateline><p> We hear that <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> is found in the river near Kingsington. She has lain in the water ever since the 5th of the Second Month.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-16"><dateline><date when="1820-04-16">16.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At 9, the people met at her burial at her old home in Moorestown. I had good satisfaction, both at the house and the grave, in imparting a few sentences. There was very little or no offensive smell, and they say she was very little marred, but the corpse was shut up in the coffin. The meeting was very large. Granvil Woolman and Ebenezer Roberts and Joseph Justice had a pretty deal to say, and I believe a good degree of savor and life attended, and all ended well. The drowning and sudden death of these two dear, worthy women, <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> and <persName key="w6gj3q0h">Esther Collins</persName>, has been the most solemn and alarming extensive call that has been known in our day, for it seemed to reach from east to west. And some think it may be of more use than if they had lived years longer, although Ann was a worthy, acceptable minister and Esther a well-esteemed elder.</p>
<p>Weather warmer, more spring-like. Shad, it is said, has been sold for three dollars a hundred and for three cents apiece. Yea, they say they sell them out upon trust. About four dollars a hundred was the price for shad fifty years ago. Now a few years ago, shad has sold as high as twenty dollars a hundred. What strange turns and ups and downs! Who can account for these things? Of latter years the wages of laboring people have been as high as 120 dollars a year, and from ten to fifteen or sixteen dollars a month; now good hands are hired for seven dollars a month and less. Yea, many, it is said, this last winter have offered to work for their victuals, being quite out of business. These ups and downs makes me think of John Burnyeat's prophecy when he told Friends they had been tried with persecution, great striving, and loss of goods and worldly treasure; but the time would come when they would be as much tried getting money and earthly treasure. Which, it is said, came soon to pass and very unexpected, by such sudden changes, ups and downs we read of in Scripture.</p></div>
<pb n="14" facs="sc204064"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-18"><dateline><date when="1820-04-18">18th of the Fourth Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> The time of our Yearly Meeting. I have, I suppose, attended our Yearly Meeting forty years or upwards, but now I am not able to go. I have been thinking of my friends there; what a time of feasting it is both, spiritual and temporal. I do not doubt but a number will be brought to the banqueting house and experience the Lord's banner to be over them in love.<note resp="transcr">Song of Solomon 2:4</note> and have to partake of heavenly bread and of the wine of the kingdom, as I with them at times have experienced. But with very many may we not say with John Churchman, oh, how is the ancient plainness departed from and pomp and splendid appearances taken their places! And with many it is made a time of outward feasting, forgetting how it felt when the fever and English army were there, not remembering the plainness and humility of our worthy predecessors, who followed their Divine Master who wore a garment without a seam<note resp="transcr">John 19:23</note> and dined on barley bread and fish<note resp="transcr">John 21:13</note> And as <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says, not likely there was much curiosity or delicacy in cooking them! How would many be ready to snuff up their noses to sit down to such a dinner, forgetting the example of them we read of, of whom it was said the world was not worthy of them. It is said of John the Divine that he wore a garment of goats skins, of camel's hair, and his meat was locust and wild honey.<note resp="transcr">Mark 1:6</note> They wandered in sheep's skins and goats' skins, and lived in caves and dens of the earth,<note resp="transcr">Hebrew 11:37-38</note> having no certain dwelling place.</p>
<p>See Solomon's Song: the time of singing of birds is come, and the voice of the turtle is heard in our land.<note resp="transcr">Song of Solomon 2:12</note> But see Jeremiah 4:25, a lamentation over Judah: he says all the birds of the heaven were fled. I can but take notice of the very great scarcity of birds and any sort, when in my young days, at this time of the year, the woods ringed with the noise of the singing of birds, very great variety of sorts, songs and noises at times and places enough to din one's ears. But now, especially this spring, there is very few birds to be seen of any sort. And as to the frogs, we used to hear them sing in abundance very early in the spring, but now, this spring, I have scarcely heard and not seen one frog. I can but notice it when I consider how our ears used to be dinned with their singing and croaking, and of the puddles full of them. I don't know who can account for these things, but I can but look upon it as no favorable sign or token. And the lopping and stripping off the tops of the trees and abundance of branches stripped off by the late storm and ice freezing on the trees! If there should come a time of bowing, lopping, and striping of the lofty and high-minded, it would be an alarming, humbling, and an awakening time. The Lord can bring down the stoutest individuals, and even whole nations. And were there not threatening signs and tokens of it in the general drought from east to west last summer? As it was said formerly, when thou tillest the ground, it shall not yield to thee its increase.<note resp="transcr">Genesis 4:12</note> Many fields were cut off.</p></div>
<pb n="15" facs="sc204065"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-20"><dateline><date when="1820-04-20">20 of the Fourth Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> Very warm weather, some little rain and thunder. At our preparative meeting, which was small, many being gone to Yearly Meeting. But the meeting was a satisfactory one to me.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-23"><dateline><date when="1820-04-23">23.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting quite as good as we commonly have. I do not perceive but it ended to general satisfaction, which I count a favor but I am longing that we should experience something like the primitive Christians. <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> mentions, in his conclusion to his <emph rend="italic">No Cross No Crown</emph>, he says: I shall conclude with a short description of the life and worship of the Christians within the first century or hundred years after Christ. What simplicity, what spirituality, what holy love and communion did in that blessed age abound among them! For it behooveth as well the Grecians as the barbarians to be partakers of this absolute goodness. And further, it is reported that at their meeting houses the most part of the day was employed in worshiping God. Like David, who said: on thee will I wait all the day long.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 25:5</note> Not get quite tired and impatient sitting an hour and half or 2 hours to wait upon him, as it is to be feared some are, and sometimes through impatience and unsettledness leave the meeting, as divers – both youth and others – have done, as if they could not endure silence. Oh, the room and need there is of improvement, although we seem not quite forsaken.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Weather very dry. Rain goes off like it did last summer.</p>
<p>I have not heard the voice of the turtledove or whippoorwill this spring, and I have seen but two frogs. I cannot say I ever seen the like before, though I have seen eighty years. Last spring there was very few blossoms on the apple trees; other fruit trees were pretty full. Now this season, fruit trees are in full bloom and all full and as white as snow with blossoms.</p>
<p>[marginal note] I have seen but two frogs.</p>
<p>We read in Scripture perhaps the word of Job: one dieth in his full strength<note resp="transcr">Job 21:23</note> etc. We hear of three women dying very, very suddenly: one at Salem, one here in Evesham, and one in Pennsylvania. And several women, three near here, who are or have lately been very ill with disorders in the head, and some much out of their senses, and some have not long since died with it.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-27"><dateline><date when="1820-04-27">27.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day morning. See [Lindley Murray's] <emph rend="italic">Sequel</emph>, page 88: the writings of sages point out a private path of virtue and show that the best empire is self government, and subduing the passions the noblest conquest. Went to our meeting, which was very small, but I should not dare to say it was quite destitute of life, but I want to feel more of that.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-29"><dateline><date when="1820-04-29">Seventh Day</date></dateline><p> morning cloudy and cold. See Clarkson's <emph rend="italic">Memoirs of <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName></emph>, page 328 second volume: The great end of punishment was undoubtedly to deter or prevent others from the commission of crimes; but on the other hand, it was the great object of the Christian religion to reclaim. Christ came principally for this purpose on Earth; he came to call sinners to repentance, to restore, prevent, and reclaim. I have often told Friends [this] was for the better part of our discipline, and they only have a right to censure who have heart to help. And what is a zeal for discipline without this heart to help worth? Is it not like Paul's zeal before his conversion? An ounce of prevention is worth a pound of cure.
<pb n="16" facs="sc204066"/>
David says: thy rod and thy staff hath sustained me,<note resp="transcr">Psalm 23:4</note> but disciplinarians whose ill have nothing to but with the rod are like the boys with their tops, which are to be kept up only by whipping. John Rutty says: we have many zealous executioners and excommunicators; but to strengthen the weak, comfort the feeble-minded, heal the sick, and to seek that which is lost and bring back that which is driven away, they have no skill at all. And what is discipline in the hands of such, but a bare name and poor, dry formality? See the complaint against the shepherds of Israel, Ezekiel 34 and 4: nor have ye sought that which was lost etc., etc.
Edward Collins of Newtown cut his own throat, and it is said two murders there [are] connected.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-04-30"><dateline><date when="1820-04-30">30 of the Fourth Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. I wanted to go to Cropwell, but way did not seem to open for it, so I went to our own meeting. And I was glad I was there, for it was an open, satisfactory time at last, although the waters seemed very low forepart. How little matter it is where we are if we can but obtain an answer of peace, the pearl of great price.<note resp="transcr">Matthew 13:46</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-05-02"><head>May 1820</head><dateline><date when="1820-05-02">2nd of the Fifth Month, Third Day.</date></dateline><p> Very dry weather; rain much wanted, like last summer. It clouds up often and looks like for rain and often goes off with very little or none, I think. Solomon says: He that withholdeth corn, the people shall curse him.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 11:26</note> Now there are stout, healthy young men strolling about like vagabonds looking for work, and can find none, and cursing the farmers because they will not employ them. It is really a pinching, trying time with many poor people. There is such a very great stagnation in business, both in town and country markets, so exceeding low that people, they say, take their meat to market – both fresh and salt – and are forced to bring it home again. Frequently of late do we hear of such things. It is strange to me to think of these great changes. But a little time ago markets and wages were so excessive high, the like was never before heard – and now so exceeding low, the like was never heard! Nor is it creditable to, tell some, undertake to account for these things but I have a jealousy that there is something in it that very few, if any, clearly see through it or the cause of it.</p>
<p>It is but a little while ago I thought farmers were imposed upon by laborers, giving them extortionate wages. Now many would be glad to work for their victuals, even in planting time, the most busy season. And markets, but a little time back, were so high I thought it was a shame to hear tell the prices they got for their market truck of all sorts [of] meat, both salt and fresh. And now, it is said, fifty shad were sold for a pair of fowls and for a cent a piece, and the best for four cents a piece. For a shad, year back, generally a quarter dollar a piece for the best.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-05-04"><dateline><date when="1820-05-04">4 of the Fifth Month.</date></dateline><p> Was our monthly meeting. <persName key="w6hj799d">Elizabeth Collins</persName> had savory, acceptable service. Although I thought there was some misses, on the whole it was pretty well.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-05-07"><dateline><date when="1820-05-07">7.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Moriah Embree of Trenton had acceptable service, and I came off without condemnation, which is a mercy. All seemed to end well. Had pretty little rain. Great show for rain, but it goes off again and again with but little.</p></div>
<pb n="17" facs="sc204067"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-05-10"><dateline><date when="1820-05-10">10th of the Fifth Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> I went to the burial of Rebecah Crispin, whose daughter is my sister Abigail son's wife, Eli Evans. I was to see her in her illness several times, which has been long and lingering. They have of latter years gone to the Baptist meeting, which is near their house, but of late seem more turned and leaning towards Friends. There was a large number of people, I expect of divers sorts – Baptist, Methodist, and Friends, and behaved very orderly. She was buried at the Baptist's burying ground. I had an open, satisfactory time with them, both at the house and at the grave. But the fatigue was almost more than my state of health and strength could bear, but returned in peace.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-05-11"><dateline><date when="1820-05-11">11.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. At our meeting. Although the waters seemed very low, yet at last I should not dare say there was no life nor savor with us.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-05-14"><dateline><date when="1820-05-14">14.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting, idleness and poverty very prevalent. J. Justice had a good deal to say, and at last I ventured and a venture it seemed to be, as one expressed it; but was mercifully helped with ability beyond expectation, and to good satisfaction. But several grumbled because they said I held meeting too long. So it is – if meeting happens to hold a few minutes longer than common, they get quite out of humor and impatient. What would they do with such a one as Paul, who continued his speech till midnight?<note resp="transcr">Acts 20:7</note> And how far are they from David's state, who said: on thee will I wait all the day long?<note resp="transcr">Psalm 25:5</note> Or like the primitive Christians <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> tells of, who spent most of the day at their religious devotions? In the afternoon I visited both the boys' and the girls' First Day school. About forty scholars in each and divers black boys and girls. To good satisfaction, but almost overcome with the fatigue and feebleness.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-05-18"><dateline><date when="1820-05-18">18.</date></dateline><p> Was Fifth Day. At our meeting. Rather smaller, I thought, than common – but I hope and believe favored with some savor and life, though great room and need of improvement. It has been cloudy and cold and stormy several days. Rain comes very gently but now at last it comes down pretty freely and plentifully, but very cold.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-05-21"><dateline><date when="1820-05-21">21.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. A poor, dry, shut-up time to me. Although we had a pretty deal of preaching, it did nothing for me. Rain, rain, rain, day and night in abundance. But a few days ago, so dry people could not go on with their business; now so wet they cannot go on with it. So it has been; sometimes the fruits of the field and labors of the husbandman have been cut off by too much rain, and sometimes by too little. Without me ye can do nothing,<note resp="transcr">John 15:5</note> says Christ.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-05-25"><dateline><date when="1820-05-25">25.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our preparative meeting. We had a pretty deal of preaching, but I thought not that savor of life and sweetness as at some times. We went to see a young woman in a deep consumption at Widow Stokes's, a good degree in a state of innocency. I was there very poor.</p>
<p>[marginal note] No rain up in Evesham, very dusty. This evening, a little more rain.</p></div>
<pb n="18" facs="sc204068"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-05-25"><dateline><date when="1820-05-25">25 of the Fifth Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> Dr. Spencer of Moorestown told me there was an account in the newspapers, and he thought no doubt of the truth of it: there was eighteen men to be hanged at New Orleans this day for conspiracy and robbery at sea and murder, and one by the name of Smith. He had been acquitted within Philadelphia! Four were hanged last week at Baltimore or Charlestown for conspiracy, robbery, and murder at sea.</p>
<p>See a book called <emph rend="italic">New England Judged</emph>, page 173: the nations of them that are saved shall walk in the Light of the Lamb. By the true faith and belief of which (as George Keith said of these two principles: of the light within and immediate revelation) the nation that now is as a barren wilderness, as to fruits of righteousness would become as the garden and paradise of God. The glory of Lebanon and excellency of Carmel would be given unto it,<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 35:2</note> and it would become a married land and nation<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 62:4</note> unto the Lord, and so would all other nations if they would come and walk in the Light of the Lord. Again George Keith's words since he left Friends in page 175: The true doctrine and sense of the light within as a Divine and supernatural gift of God, given to all faithful Christians, etc., is a doctrine well-warranted by Scripture and consented to by the generality of professors of Christianity, although very many rigid, zealous Presbyterians most horribly and blasphemously deny it – contrary to express Scripture terms, many times repeated.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-05-28"><dateline><date when="1820-05-28">28.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. I thought the forepart was very low and poor, indeed. And how can it be otherwise where so much idleness prevails? In and under a sense of lowness, I at last ventured to stand up and was mercifully helped beyond all prospect or expectation, to good satisfaction. Openness, sweetness, and feeling nearness at parting. There is said one of old, that which scattereth and yet increaseth.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 11:24</note> I see wherein I might have done better.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-05-29"><dateline><date when="1820-05-29">29.</date></dateline><p> I went with divers others to visit William Hooton on a Monthly Meeting errand. To some satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-05-30"><dateline><date when="1820-05-30">30.</date></dateline><p> Whilst we were dressing a calf for market a heavy cloud came up out of the south with heavy wind and blew down several apple trees and other fruit trees and some in the woods with heavy rain and hail. In divers places the hail broke their windows. About Moorestown, sixty pairs of glass in one house, and in several places cut down the rye very much. There was no thunder.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-05-31"><dateline><date when="1820-05-31">31.</date></dateline><p> A very stormy day. Rained almost all day. I went to the burial of Hannah Haines, widow of Noah Haines (her maiden name was Thorn); my old school mate, they say about 85. Returned with peace and satisfaction.
<head>June 1820</head>
[marginal note] The hail cut down fields of rye a little east of Moorestown.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-06-01"><dateline><date when="1820-06-01">1 of the Sixth Month, Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. A very low, poor time, I believe, with most a time of mortification rather than satisfaction – and it may be that is the food most convenient for me. We hear more and more of the destruction by the hail.</p></div>
<pb n="19" facs="sc204069"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-06-02"><dateline><date when="1820-06-02">2 of the Fifth [illegible] Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> 6 Day. At our select meeting. To me, a poor low time.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-06-03"><dateline><date when="1820-06-03">3.</date></dateline><p> Having some business at my son John's, I went there and was at their select meeting at Evesham. Although things were low, yet some life. I came off with satisfaction.</p>
<p>See a book called <emph rend="italic">The Rights of God</emph>, by Thomas Branagan, page 300, his account of Matthew Franklin in 1815, Friend of New York, how he fell down dead whilst he was preaching in meeting in an extraordinary manner. And, as I have noted heretofore, an account of Thomas Cox in <emph rend="italic">Piety Promoted</emph>, how after he had been preaching about half an hour, sat down and died immediately. <persName key="w63n434v">Jacob Lindley</persName> lately, after he had been preaching powerfully as he was going from meeting, was throwd out of his carriage and broke his neck. George Fox was seized with coldness and chill as he came out of meeting where he had been preaching powerfully and died in a short time. John Estaugh at Haddonfield, I am told, was struck with an apoplectic fit as he was preaching in that meeting but survived it and died in Tortula in his travels. And see<emph rend="italic"> Memorials</emph> how Robert Jordan, that great and worthy minister, was struck with a fit as he was going to meeting and died in a few hours. Is it not strange such things do not keep us more in humility and fear? First Day morning.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-06-04"><dateline><date when="1820-06-04">4 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. To me, a poor, low time. Search for the cause: poor disconsolate; as doves without their mate; are some when left hardly clothing enough to hide our nakedness ashamed to be seen poor creatures and when a little clothed can hardly keep from pride and enough humble.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-06-08"><dateline><date when="1820-06-08">8</date></dateline><p> was our monthly meeting. <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> was there, and Mariah Embree from Trenton, and both had acceptable service; and the meeting for discipline well-conducted, lively, and satisfactory. Came off without condemnation. See  <emph rend="italic">Memoirs of <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName></emph>, by Thomas Clarkson, volume 2nd, page 122, an extraordinary account of the death of his eldest son, Springet Penn. Well worth preserving and reading. Weather fine – warm and growing.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-06-11"><dateline><date when="1820-06-11">11 was First Day.</date></dateline><p> [Thomas] Branagan, in his book (page 251), quotes some words of Cicero, an heathen philosopher: In a word, the universal, immutable, and eternal law of all intelligent beings is to promote the happiness of one another, like children of one father, observing the universal law of all nations – that of doing as we would be done by. But, alas, how has this law been violated in the dismal destructive ways amongst men, and yet justified by professing Christians!</p>
<p>Then went to our meeting, and a precious, owning, strengthening one it was to me. Oh, what a mercy continued to this day! What shall we render, etc.?</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-06-12"><dateline><date when="1820-06-12">12.</date></dateline><p> Second Day I was invited to attend the burial of Mary Quicksil, wife of Jonathan, who has lain long in a decaying, lingering way. She was a descendant of old Ephraim Tomlinson, a worthy friend. It was a rainy day and the company not very large but very orderly. Came off middling – not that evidence of life and ownings of truth as at some times, yet not much cause of complaint. There were many moral, formal professors, and they abound in our day.</p></div>
<pb n="20" facs="sc204070"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-06-14"><dateline><date when="1820-06-14">14 of the Sixth Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> 4 of the week. At select meeting at Evesham, but low water with us. Yet I had some satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-06-15"><dateline><date when="1820-06-15">15.</date></dateline><p> Was quarterly meeting. Forepart, I think, was but low and poor. But that great man and dignified minister, <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName>, rose up and was raised in great eminence, indeed, in the exercise of his most distinguished gift; generally allowed to be one of the greatest ministers in America. He preached a great deal and very excellent in the last meeting. But alas, what good does it do? Where is the fruit of his labor? The ointment of his right hand betrayeth itself.<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 27:16</note> Really, is not this wanting among us?</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-06-18"><dateline><date when="1820-06-18">18.</date></dateline><p> First Day. Thomas Davis of Piles Grove, Salem County was there and preach[ed] one hour and a half some reckon and it was thought did worthily and famously. He has come forward not many years ago. And James Emlen's wife – from Pennsylvania, near Westtown school – spoke very lively at last meeting, held half an hour longer than common. But if instrumental means are made use of for our help, it is intended to turn our minds towards their employer, so that in time we should have no need of them. But alas, as that great minister <persName key="w6dn68k9">William Hunt</persName> once said, it was deeply discouraging to see so little good fruits of ministerial labors. As was said to the prophet, they hear thy words but will not do them..<note resp="transcr">Ezekiel 33:31</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-06-22"><dateline><date when="1820-06-22">22.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. But small weather, very warm, many very drowsy. It was hard to stem the powerful current and prevalency of it, yet through mercy I did come off with some satisfaction and clothing. I did not feel afraid of being had up or called to an account thankfulness. See William Smith's <emph rend="italic">Works</emph>, page 89: for that which makes people all happy and every condition sweet is to answer the light of Christ Jesus in their consciences. So to be single to the light is a joyful state, and none to be had without it.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-06-25"><dateline><date when="1820-06-25">25.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Not satisfactory to me, although it seemed to be to some. A very heavy thundershower and heavy rain southward, but not much here. Very dry, hot weather.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-06-29"><dateline><date when="1820-06-29">29.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting very small and poor, yet ended to my satisfaction. Oh, how do many – now, as formerly – sacrifice to their nets and drags, making gods of them! And what can they do for them? At last they will be willing to cast them to the moles and to the bats<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 2:20</note>; [they] afford no help in the time of greatest need.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-07-02"><head>July 1820</head><dateline><date when="1820-07-02">2nd of the Seventh Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Joseph Justice had a good deal to say. Thomas Matthews of Philadelphia was there but said nothing. To me the meeting ended satisfactory. Heard of three burials: James Robertson, the great tanner in Moorestown, and Thomas Buzby, and a child.
<pb n="21" facs="sc204071"/>
This 2nd of the Seventh Month, 1820, First Day. My daughter Abigail borrowed John Gratton's journal, I having had a sight of it many years ago and have lately enquired after it. This afternoon and Second Day morning before 8 o'clock, I read it through, containing 224 pages. And [a] precious piece of work it is, giving an account how strangely and wonderfully he was convinced, raised up, carried, or led through this world of dangers and troubles to a blessed and happy end at last. And of his great labors in the work of the ministry, and his being instrumental to the convincement of very many, and of his preaching four hours at time at divers times, and of the great growth and spreading of truth in them days, and the blessed, glorious meetings they often had! Oh, what a pity that the professors of that same blessed principle should loose sight of it after the Lord has raised up such worthies and they have suffered so much, and purchased our privileges at so dear a rate – even the loss of property, liberty, and life itself! Many died in prisons for their testimony. See English Reader XV: The wise man is happy when he gains his own approbation [and] peace; the fool, when he gains that of others.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-07-06"><dateline><date when="1820-07-06">6 of the Seventh Month.</date></dateline><p> Was our Monthly Meeting I was happy in that I did gain my own approbation, for the meeting was to my satisfaction. Although the weather was very hot and dry and many tried with drowsiness. Midst of harvest many worked hard, and, as <persName key="w6b38kp0">Thomas Ross</persName> says when overwearied nature calls for rest. I wonder our Monthly Meetings are favored as they are, although great room and need of improvement. </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-07-07"><dateline><date when="1820-07-07">7.</date></dateline><p> Very hot, dry weather. Height of harvest, but I can do nothing at it. But yet favored much with health beyond many of my age, a little turned of eighty. See <emph rend="italic">Solitude Sweetened</emph>, page 15, on degrees of nearness, union and communion with God. He says (to this effect) that every truly religious, sanctified soul has communion with God. And do not the Scriptures throughout abundantly confirm it? He says: to be permitted to have communion with God is like sitting down with the king to the feast made by him for the joy of his chosen. So we read, one said: Let me hear thy voice, for thy voice is sweet and thy countenance is comely.<note resp="transcr">Song of Solomon 2:14</note> And again says another: I sat under his shadow with great delight and his fruit was sweet to my taste.<note resp="transcr">Song of Solomon 2:3</note> But, alas, how tasteless are these things to very many who never want to think of anything of the sort, but are careful about many things and neglect the one thing needful. But the joy of true religion, he says, excels the worlding's gladness as far as light excels darkness, and the joy of it akin to the joy of the saints in glory, heavenly bread, true peace. Again, see do, page 168, on the excellency of grace and the entrancing excellency of it. 169: let gold be the portion of the miser's, honor to the ambitious; pleasure to the voluptuous; but let grace be mine. For thus my afflictions are sweeter than the prosperity of the wicked, my reproaches preferable to the applauses of a giddy world, and my very death more desirable than the life of the most splendid, if impious, monarch.</p></div>
<pb n="22" facs="sc204072"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-07-09"><dateline><date when="1820-07-09">9th of the Seventh Month, 1820, First Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting, which I thought was very destitute of life, and it seems as if it would be quite destitute of words till late. At last I had to express a few words, and then another and another, a little and a little, and I thought it ended with some degree of savor. I have thought we have mostly dull, heavy, poor meetings in harvest time, especially when it is such very hot, dry weather as it is now.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-07-10"><dateline><date when="1820-07-10">Second Day.</date></dateline><p> Finished reaping what we left on Seventh Day. Harvest very good, but ours was a good deal tangled with the hail storms. What a mercy it was no worse destroyed!</p>
<p>See John Churchman's journal, page 191, at a meeting at Bristol. He queried with them thus: Are you sound in faith and practice? I was led to set forth that to profess and acknowledge even sacred truths without a life of self denial, with[out] an answerable honest conduct, was no way sufficient, that being a dead faith, which produceth no good works in him who saith he believeth, showing what stumbling blocks the nominal professors are, who by their example plainly manifest that they are not professors of what they profess to have and are the greatest enemies the truth hath; which I was doubtful was the case with some among them. I had peace in this plain dealing. Alas, is it not to be feared that vital religion is at a very low ebb, and that dry formality abounds in very many meetings, very destitute of the life and power of truth? These things rightly considered. Had not professors of our principles and tenders of meeting need to tremble least they become the greatest enemies the truth hath? What can meditate more against the cause we profess to espouse than to see people at meeting overwhelmed with dullness and drowsiness? </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-07-13"><dateline><date when="1820-07-13">13.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. Very dull and poor indeed, as I thought. Weather very hot and dry and dusty. Dust almost hid the horses on the road. Some said they never seen the like. I was so unwell I was hardly able to sit meeting. Just the finishing of harvest and by accounts a greater, finer harvest there has not been many years. One farmer, it is thought, will have fifteen hundred bushels; A. Hulings and another, a thousand a [stem?] and it appears to be well filled, full grain. See <persName key="w6t72g07">John Woolman's</persName> <emph rend="italic">Caution to the Rich</emph>, page 23: the frequent use of strong drink works in opposition to the celestial influence on the mind. This is plain: when men take so much as to suspend the use of their reason and though there are degrees of this opposition, and a man quite drunk may be farthest removed from that frame of mind in which God is worshiped, we read that men may be drunk and not with wine or strong drink, but pleasures or the intoxicating spirit of this world, which unfits him for divine worship and works as strong drink, in opposition to the celestial influence on the mind. Be ye not as the horse or the mule that hath no understanding, said the prophet David.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 32:9</note> A man drunk or besotted with the love of this world are not in a capacity to receive the advantage of the inspiration any more than a mule.
<pb n="23" facs="sc204073"/>
This 13 of the Seventh Month, Fifth Day. Now a very fine, soaking rain after three or four weeks of very hot, dry weather. I fear we are too much like the horse or the mule David speaks of that have no understanding, no gift or capacity, to consider divine favors and mercies, but like it is said of the hog, who eats the fruit under the tree but never looks up from whence the fruit comes from. Be ye not as the horse or the mule that hath no understanding.<note resp="transcr">Psalm 32:9</note>
See Stephen Crisps' <emph rend="italic">Epistle</emph> concerning the present and succeeding times, page 7: for a day cometh that truth will look into the fig tree for fruit, and leaves will not defend it from the curse and blasting. Poor miserable creatures, we are [it] seem[s] never safe, full nor fasting. If we are blessed and favored to live in fullness, then [there is] the danger of becoming overwhelmed with a spirit of ease and lukewarmness – which David Hall says is as bad as open profanity – and our blessings become curses. Woe unto them that are at ease in Zion.<note resp="transcr">Amos 6:1</note> Were they not threatened punishment that were settled on their lees and sat down at ease?<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 48:11?</note>
See <emph rend="italic">Memorials</emph>, page 344: Sarah Morris says if they are but preserved from gross evils and go on in prosperity, they sit down at ease and think all is well. But Oh, that they may not too late find their mistake and that they have pleased themselves with favors they have unthankfully received and so stop short of greater, by not desiring them. As Lady Guion says, make temporary heavens here, and as <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says: Like them so well they would never leave them if they could help it. But <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says dives  he must go the story is as true as sad. I could name several who lived in great prosperity, who said they did not wish for any better heaven. Ingratitude is said to be not one of the least of sins.
See [Lindley Murray's] <emph rend="italic">Power of Religion on the Mind</emph>, page 83, shall ingratitude to man be looked upon as the blackest of crimes, and not ingratitude to God? Shall an injust[ice] offered to the king be looked upon in the most offensive light, and yet no notice taken when the King of Kings is treated with indignity and disrespect?</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-07-16"><dateline><date when="1820-07-16">16.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. Idleness, trifling dangerous indifferency, and lukewarmness abound; on which subject I had a few sentences to mention, which afforded good satisfaction. This afternoon, I – with others, men and women friends, on an appointment of our Monthly Meeting visited John Lippincott's family (who lately came from Philadelphia) to some satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-07-20"><dateline><date when="1820-07-20">20.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting small, very destitute of life and power. I fear many know not what it is or hardly look or long for it or expect it. Oh, formality!</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-07-21"><dateline><date when="1820-07-21">21.</date></dateline><p> It looks like wet weather coming. See <emph rend="italic">Solitude Sweetened</emph>, page 62: one thinks least on what he loves last. Oh mournful conclusion, that I love God least since he is least in my thoughts! As the Scriptures say, of some God is not in all their thoughts,<note resp="transcr">Psalm 10:4</note> and what is it to be done with those who forget him? As <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says, poor man minds nothing less than that which he should most mind. It is an easy matter to think on that we love best.</p></div>
<pb n="24" facs="sc204074"/>
<div type="entry" n="1820-07-22"><dateline><date when="1820-07-22">22 of the Seventh Month, 1820.</date></dateline><p> On Seventh Day, 4 hour, we went to the burial of Mary Roberts, daughter of Joseph Roberts, near about fifty. An innocent body, never married. She died with the dropsy. A large number of people, decent and orderly. <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> was there, but there was nothing said. I thought I had pertinent matter for the people, but waters were so low, [I had] no ability to get along at the grave. Though late in the day, I had a few sentences to satisfaction. I thought it was a shame we should be so poor for want of a willingness to work after so much has been done for us.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-07-23"><dateline><date when="1820-07-23">23.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting. To me, open, owning, and satisfactory – better than common or some others, as well as I, was mistaken. Harvest and hay nearly over, I believe. Barns here away were seldom, if ever, better filled. See [James Meikle's] <emph rend="italic">Solitude Sweetened</emph>, page 174: Finally, if God be the portion of his saints, why such a struggle to fill their coffers with perishing things, and why so disquieted if they do not succeed? A friend, A.M. from Pennsylvania, tells me it is reported that there is vast quantities of old wheat up the Susquehanna River that it might be had for half a crown a bushel. Two dollars and upward has been the price years past! And it is said rye is brought down the river in great quantities and sold for three shillings a bushel. J. Hollinshead, a man not very zealous for religion, once came to borrow some wheat off his neighbor, where I happened to be. I told him I thought he used to raise wheat to sell. “Why so I did, but you know the crops fail sometimes.” I said “O, yes.” He said, “It should be so sometimes or else we should forget there was any God.” One mentioned the great price wheat was sold for. He cried out, “O, I should be afraid to ask such a price for fear I should have none next year!” “O, I would not take the sin on my soul to ask such a price,” said another on a like occasion. Extortion, covetousness, and oppression are numbered all along amongst the blackest of crimes. When thou buyest ought of thy neighbor or sellest ought to thy neighbor, ye shall not oppress one another.<note resp="transcr">Leviticus 25:14</note> Thou hast death by oppression, thou hast greedily gained of thy neighbor by extortion. Can thine heart endure or thine hand be strong in the day that I shall deal with thee?<note resp="transcr">Ezekiel 22:12-14</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-07-26"><dateline><date when="1820-07-26">26.</date></dateline><p> Finished getting hay (grow[s] dry again). As far as I can learn, it is general a healthy time, both in the city and country. But our country is getting full of people, and our doctors still seem to have full employ. A fine rain again.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1820-07-27"><dateline><date when="1820-07-27">27.</date></dateline><p> Fifth Day. At our meeting. So poorly I was hardly able to sit meeting or get home. Had a spell of vomiting and very sick stomach, but soon got better. Our daughter came from market and tells how low cheese, butter, and eggs and all things are and meat of all sorts. [People] have to bring it back; no sale at all for it. Her mother said, “I never heard the like, though near eighty.”</p>
<p>[marginal note] We hear tell of the hail [that] lately destroyed fields of Indian corn near Woodstown. It must have been very violent to destroy Indian corn now it is got so big.</p></div>
</body></text>
</TEI>