<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Hunt Journal, 1818 5mo. 13 - 1818 9mo. 17: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>James Truitt</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 75 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were created and/or prepared by the <hi rend="italic" >Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</hi> and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <hi rend="italic"> Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College </hi>.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2021">2021</date>
                <idno type="local">A0011530</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">
                    <title level="s" type="main">Friendly Networks</title>
                    <title level="s" type="sub">The Journals of Our Beloved Friend John Hunt</title></title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>John Hunt Papers, SFHL-RG5-240</collection>
                        <idno>A0011530</idno>
                        <idno>sc203700</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>24 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The journals of Quaker minister John Hunt are stored at the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College. With the generous support of H. David and Joyce E. Hunt, Library staff scanned and transcribed the journals, and in 2021, encoded the text in TEI. The 2021 project also included researching individuals mentioned in the text to create and update records about them in the <ref target="https://snaccooperative.org/">Social Networks and Archival Context website</ref>
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> John Hunt was a good writer, but like most 18th century authors, his punctuation, spelling, and abbreviations were not standardized or necessarily consistent. The goal of the Hunt project was to produce a text accessible to the modern reader, retaining all the words in the order they appear, but with added punctuation and capitalization to make the document readable. Some spelling of surnames and places has been corrected in order to facilitate searching. Any other additions supplied to aid the reader are surrounded by brackets. Archaic forms and spellings of words are also retained. “How art thou feeling” remains as written, not changed to “How are you feeling.” And Hunt frequently used the abbreviation “Do.” for ditto; this has not been changed. The word “sic” means that word or words are transcribed as written. Usually this marks an error in the original text. When identified by the editor, biblical references, all from the King James version, have been identified in notes. Where Hunt himself identified them as such this attribution is retained in the main body of the text.</p>
                <p>Hunt consistently used Quaker-style plain dating, avoiding the names of the months and the names of days of the week. “Monday, October 9th,” for instance, is written as “Second Day, Ninth of the Tenth Month.” The headings dividing the texts were added by the editors, using the standard names for the months, again for ease of reading.</p>
                <p>Hunt had a practice of regularly adding to a series of bound journals when he was at home, but usually recorded entries while he was at Yearly Meeting or travelling in the ministry on single sheets of paper. In publishing the entirety of the journal we have added “loose” sections where they fit chronologically.  </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written in <date when="1818">1818</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <term>Quakers -- Conduct of life</term>
                    <term>Quakers -- Religious life</term>
                    <term>Quakers -- Social life and customs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#lcnaf">
                    <term ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2005064399">Hunt, John, 1740-1824</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item><date/></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="01" facs="sc203969"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-05-13"><head>May 1818</head><dateline><date when="1818-05-13">13 of the 5 month 1818.</date></dateline><p> We have had a very cold winter and but very little snow. The winter grain very in many places was much killed and froze out and very cold backward spring yet now a very wet time and several heavy thunder showers.  The fruit trees in full bloom, all sorts as white as snow, seldom ever the like seen of the abundance of blossoms.  </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-05-13"><dateline><date when="1818-05-13">13 [14].</date></dateline><p> This fifth day went to our meeting. Very poor. Ready to say woe is me that I dwell in Mesech and sojourn in the tents of Kedar.<note resp="transcr">Psalms 120:5</note> Great heights and in great depths and great heats in great cold as John Richardson remarks. Our meeting rather small (yet not the poorest).  Some things presented to my view which, as <persName key="w63g5dz0">John Parrish</persName>, said I thought too good to be lost: viz I have long believed there was a blessed happy safe state attainable in silent meditation in communion with our own hearts and with our maker and I thought great cause I had so to believe because I think is has been evidently confirmed in the lives and conduct of thousands of the faithful in ages past and down to these days. Yea in countless numbers: in the faith and conscience of Noah, Job, Daniel, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. Yea, throughout all the patriarchs, prophets, apostles and faithful martyrs.  [John] Hoyland says the righteous need not fear the crush of world and Seneca says if the earth should open under them and show them all the secrets of the infernal pit they would look down upon it without dismay fear not them that kill the body said the divine master and indeed it appears clear they did not when the most dismal cruel deaths was threatened them. Is this not a blessed happy safe state, because if it should be their lot to be suddenly taken away as many are, all would be well with they and they landed safe where the wicked cease from troubling and the weary are at rest.<note resp="transcr">Job 3:17</note> Simple as it appears to very many
<pb n="02" facs="sc203970"/>
and insignificant to sit still and say nothing, yet if rightly seen into and practiced will it not be found to be the most exalted dignified state, the most safe and happy mankind can ever be favored or honored with our friends say in one of their epistles, say that to have communion with our maker in our silent meetings is the superior excellence of the Christian religion and Seneca says it is the highest pitch of Christian perfection.  Surely it must be the more excellent way Paul mentions,<note resp="transcr">1 Cor. 12:31</note> for how is it possible there ever was or ever can be a better that that David petitioned for when he said, Oh! Send out thy light and thy truth. Let them lead me and  let them teach me,  etc.<note resp="transcr">Psalms 42:3</note> and to have the company of the good remembrances which was promised should come and  bring all things needful into remembrance,  who teaches as never men taught and  has the words of eternal life the wonderful councilor and  prince of peace . Surely this must be the more excellent way for how is it possible for any other way to exceed it?  Is not this the mystery hid from ages but revealed unto us, said the apostle.<note resp="transcr">Col. 1:26</note> So I came believing as it then appeared to me that if we were favored to see our own states and conditions who should allow that the ancient language was applicable to us—Arise, depart hence for this is not the place of your rest it is polluted etc.<note resp="transcr">Micah 2:10</note></p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-05-16"><dateline><date when="1818-05-16">16 the 7th day.</date></dateline><p> A very uncommon great rain northeast storm.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-05-17"><dateline><date when="1818-05-17">17 First Day.</date></dateline><p> Storm continues. At our meeting.  Small but not the poorest to me.  I thought it ended savory.</p></div>
<pb n="03" facs="sc203971"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-05-23"><dateline><date when="1818-05-23">23 day.</date></dateline><p> at our meeting. Small but I believe there was some life stirring among us the mystery hid from ages. Came off middling but did not get through to full satisfaction. When shall I learn to be deliberate enough?</p>
<p>Old people used to say formerly that the leaves always got to or nearly to their bigness by the 21st of their [?] month but they are far from it now.  I think I never did see so backward a spring. One thing I can but notice that is the fewness of the summer birds singing as formerly how very few to be seen to what there was in my youthful says at this season of the year-- very very few indeed. It brought to mind the Lamentations of Jeremiah See 4th [chapter], the grievous lamentation for the miseries of Judah See Jeremiah 4:25.  I beheld and all the birds of the heavens were fled etc.  and so setting forth the dreadful dissolution. It is so cold that it is remarked that we have no flies nor mosquitoes  as formerly to trouble us.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-05-25"><dateline><date when="1818-05-25">25 was first Day.</date></dateline><p>  my daughter Abigail, myself and my cousins Benjamin Warrington and his wife went to Woodbury meeting which was very large but as in other places a right labor was much wanting although they sat very still and orderly.  I found <persName key="w6b38kp0">Thomas Ross</persName>, his words, to be true that is when the body is over much fatigued, when we come to sit down still nature calls for rest and I was hard by able for religious travel or exercise yet through and I believe it ended reputable and well; all seemed sweet loving and pleasant at last we dined at John Tatham Jr. had a satisfactory time at parting he was not at home.</p>
<p>[marginal note] I believe I did not get so fully clear as I might have done if I had not been over much wearied in getting there</p>
<p>We got well home to my house in good season but I was very much wearied.</p></div>
<pb n="04" facs="sc203972"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-05-28"><dateline><date when="1818-05-28">28 Fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting. I thought there was something pretty savory [and] lively forepart but for want of something it was a poor mortifying time to me.  I was so poor and naked [that] I was ashamed to be seen. Not like some meetings of late-- sweetness and feeling nearness when we came out. As Catharine Phillips said, he had clothed me and he had a right to strip me. Words and life are two things and words without life are idols.  See <emph rend="italic">Memories of the Life of Catharine Phillips,</emph> 334 page.</p>
<p>There is no happiness here equal to perfect redemption from the world, its spirit and ourselves.  To have no hopes, no desires but in the will of God is fully giving ourselves into his holy hand and to be swallowed up of him. James Nayler says to them who have no other lovers the lord gives himself and among his innumerable blessings himself is the crown of all so then to miss of this is the greatest loss of all. See page 151 of C. P. [Catharine Phillips] journal an account of a prospect of a very plentiful harvest being much injured with by the heavy rains. <persName key="w65q5g7f">Samuel Fothergill</persName> in one of his testimonies noted it as a threatened judgment from him who openeth the floodgates of heaven or stayeth them to the effecting his own righteous purposes.  The rains continuing so long so much grain was spoiled or damaged as to occasion an extreme scarcity before the next harvest. How many ways there is for the fruits of the field and labors of the husbandman to be cut off by too much or too little rain. With the hail, fields often cut off. Blasting and mildew, locusts and caterpillars, cankerworms, Hessian flies, etc. </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-05-29"><dateline><date when="1818-05-29">29.</date></dateline><p> at our select meeting. A lively, satisfactory to all I believe although great room and great need of improvement.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-05-30"><dateline><date when="1818-05-30">30.</date></dateline><p> heard of the death of <persName key="w6wt9jhx">Enoch Evans</persName>. He has been long very poorly.   Died very suddenly alone in his chair.</p></div>
<pb n="05" facs="sc203973"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-05-31"><dateline><date when="1818-05-31">31 of the 5th month 1818.</date></dateline><p>  We went to the burial of our brother in law,  <persName key="w6wt9jhx">Enoch Evans</persName>, an elder whose last wife was <persName key="w6wx87x7">my wife's</persName> sister Elizabeth. He has been very poorly some years past with paralytic dropsy and a variety of disorders. At last died very sudden in his chair alone. He had a few minutes before he was found dead been out in the yard talking with their carpenter. There was a great concourse of people-- Nathan Smith of Philadelphia, <persName key="w6g77m31">Hannah Yarnall</persName> and Elizabeth Balderston of Pennsylvania. It was a pretty open time however to me and on the whole satisfactory. [Inserted: 75 [years] old] Nathan Smith and <persName key="w6g77m31">Hannah Yarnall</persName> had very acceptable service at the meeting. Elizabeth Balderston was very poorly</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-06-04"><head>June 1818</head><dateline><date when="1818-06-04">4 of the 6th month was our Monthly Meeting.</date></dateline><p>  Horton Howard and <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> were there, just returned from New York Yearly Meeting, and both had acceptable service. The meeting on the whole was a satisfactory one to me although very great room and need of improvement. See Hoyland's <emph rend="italic">Works</emph>, page 254, old age and virtue are honored with royal regard and attention.  Royalty is instructed, admonished, and blessed by the wisdom of the sage, by the miseries of the man, by the piety and prayers of the prophet.  Jacob's last days are by far his best after all his abundance of trouble. But see page 83 concerning Cain.  He who is smitten with his own conscience is continually surrounded with enemies.  A wounded conscience who can bear but he that makes or takes conscience for his counselor will find it his greatest comforts when all other stand aloof or fail conscience unpleasant truths may tell best mark her sacred lessons well he that lives with her at strife parts with his better friend for life. A quiet conscience is the best, has only peace, has only rest our best friend or greatest enemy</p></div>
<pb n="06" facs="sc203974"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-06-07"><dateline><date when="1818-06-07">7th of the 6th month, 1818 First Day.</date></dateline><p> Although a few weeks ago there was a gloomy prospect in looking at the winter grain, rye and wheat etc., it being much killed with the severe winter yet now there has been a fine growing warm time and both grass and grain has got up beyond all expectation and it now looks very flourishing and promising.  Alas how little do we know or consider of the power of him who can open or shut the windows of heaven: bless a little and blast a great deal in many ways hid from us.</p>
<p><rs key="w6wx87x7">my wife</rs> [and] daughter Abigail with our ancient sister, <persName key="w6tq8ftp">Hannah Buzby</persName>, went to Westfield Meeting which was small. Seems declining rather than increasing. Waters very low although there is a remnant of valuable friends.  Like the gleaning of a vintage, one or two berries in the tops of the uppermost branches, yet at last I had a pretty open time though hard heavy getting along I came off without condemnation but some satisfaction, although not altogether that sweetness and feeling nearness as at some other times of late. This evening a very heavy thunder shower, some very sharps claps of thunder.  I hear there is accounts in the news of a terrible hail storm southward that cut down the grain very much. Horton Howard of the state of Ohio and <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> came to see us.  H. Howard is now set off homeward.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-06-09"><dateline><date when="1818-06-09">9th  6rd Day morning.</date></dateline><p>  I feel but poorly, hard beset to totter about: see <persName key="w60006f4">George Dillwyn's</persName> <emph rend="italic">Youth Instructor</emph>, page 64, “Resignation being a cessation from the workings of self-will, is an approach to the sanctuary of silence, whose truth is revealed, assurance obtained and peace enjoyed.”  Assurance and peace. Does he say obtained? What then follows: Amen, Hallelujah in the Highest, something very great indeed for transcending all this world can afford.”
<pb n="07" facs="sc203975"/>
But page 65, he says, “In proportion as we are attached to our possession we are distressed with losing them.” Here then is the difference between the workings of our own wills and  true resignation to the divine will and although the fields should yield no meat yet will I rejoice in the Lord and joy in the God of my salvation said Habakkuk.<note resp="transcr">3:18</note> Oh death, how bitter is the thought of thee to the man that is at ease in his possessions, but as <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says, Divers he must go. The story is as true as sad and as it was said to the man who concluded he had goods laid up in store for many years and say to his soul, eat, drink, be merry but what follows thou foot this night shall thy soul be required of thee and then whose shall those things be which thou hast provided. </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-06-09"><dateline><date when="1818-06-09">9 of the 6 month.</date></dateline><p>  I hear of the death of Benjamin Morgan's daughter about 17. It is said she had been some unwell with a cold and a pain in her head and a little flighty or unsettled in mind, but went at last and took a large dose of anodyne (which her father kept and frequently took to ease him of the gout). It is said she immediately told her mother that she had taken two ounces of the anodyne. Her mother asked her why she did it.  She said she did not like to do it but it seemed as if she was forced to do it.  She died in a few hours and buried this afternoon. Oh to think of the scenes of sorrow and the slippery places we stand in if there is such a thing as a preferring principle how needful to endeavor to early instill it into youth to build upon that rock against which the gates of hell can never prevail: the preserver of the righteous in all ages.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-06-10"><dateline><date when="1818-06-10">10.</date></dateline><p> My daughter Abigail and I went to select meeting at Evesham which I thought was a pleasant time to me but <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> seemed to think it was a low however he was raised in great eminence in the exercise of his famous gift. There were many strangers from different parts: Horton Howard from Ohio and divers of Pennsylvania. Had very savory, lively service.  I was not alone in thinking it was a pleasant time.</p></div>
<pb n="08" facs="sc203976"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-06-11"><dateline><date when="1818-06-11">11th of the 6th month 1818.</date></dateline><p> We all went to our quarterly meeting at Evesham which was very large and many worthy ministers and divers had savory acceptable service but <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> was silent and life did not rise to that degree as at some other times-- yet no cause of complaint but great cause of humble gratitude which it is to be feared is much wanting on the whole it was satisfactory in some good degree to me although I did not please myself altogether. </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-06-14"><dateline><date when="1818-06-14">14 first Day.</date></dateline><p> at our meeting. Favored to come off without condemnation. What an unspeakable mercy it is that I have been preferred to the day in any degree of reputation seeing so many fall into disgrace and withering yet when I retrospect I think how much is wanting and the many weaknesses and frailties of depraved nature. I think of the command of the angel which was curse for condemn, judge down etc. the Meroz because they come not up to the help of the Lord [Judges 5:23]  everything that tends to deprive us of our chiefest good, peace of mind, peace with the Lord.  I hear that the Hessian flies have destroyed the wheat in divers places both in Pennsylvania and Jersey and that the worms have cut off the Indian corn very much in some places although they have not hurt ours this season as last.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-06-13"><dateline><date when="1818-06-13">13.</date></dateline><p> I am told the thunder has struck Enoch Roberts' house, tore the roof some and several rooms and broke two looking glasses and some windows glass 120 panes but the people not hurt though some stunned so as to fall and it is said three horses were killed under a tree at Vincentown and some sheep in Evesham all lately with the thunder.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-06-18"><dateline><date when="1818-06-18">18 fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> at our meeting.  Small but I do think there was life and savor, sweetness more than common but alas the great thing is when we are right to keep so though we feel as though we could run through a troop or leap over the wall of opposition. The breath of heaven must swell the sail or all the toil is lost.</p></div>
<pb n="09" facs="sc203977"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-06-20"><dateline><date when="1818-06-20">20 of the 6th month 1818.</date></dateline><p> My friend Samuel Church and I went up to my friends and his relations John Haines and <persName key="w6vv2hnp">Clayton Brown's</persName> his son in law and my relation who live together and we enjoyed one another's company with sweet satisfaction John Haines is an exemplary elder and  <persName key="w6vv2hnp">Clayton Brown</persName> an able acceptable minister.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-06-21"><dateline><date when="1818-06-21">21 first Day.</date></dateline><p> They went with us to Vincentown Meeting. They have lately built a new meeting house and I was in hopes there was some more life and zeal among them but alas the meeting was small and the waters very low. We found Amos Kilburn there from Byberry, Pennsylvania but we all sat shut up till late then I ventured but alas the waters were so low I could do but little. Then Amos Kilburn stood up and said a good deal but the people who were chiefly young and very raw and awkward and sleepy. Even whilst he was speaking there seemed to be no savor, life or animation so to me no satisfaction. I thought they were like the gleaning of a vintage, but one or two berries in the tops of the uppermost branches as John Griffith remarks.  Some meeting quite died away and others very sickly, not likely to live long. Oh the deadness, dryness, poverty, leanness and formality that prevail. Although as to the outward the prospect of a very great harvest and grass is now very flourishing and promising but is it so the fruitfulness of the land cause barrenness in the minds of the people as of old fullness of bread and  abundance of idleness ingratiated and  forgetfulness prize the gift and forget the giver.  Has it not too generally been so there was evidence enough of abilities and industry outward in farming and agriculture? Ours alone can near prevail to reach the distant coast. The breath of heaven must swell the sailor. All the toil is lost. Of your selves without ye can do nothing, said the Divine Master.</p></div>
<pb n="10" facs="sc203978"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-06-05"><dateline><date when="1818-06-05">5 Day.</date></dateline><p> at our meeting. Very small and very poor dull and drowsy. I dare not venture to move but several did.  I thought there was a little sign of breathing or a little and but little sign of life. I was a good deal unwell. Very hot, dry weather yet showers near round about several days past.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-06-28"><dateline><date when="1818-06-28">28 first Day.</date></dateline><p> at our meeting. <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> appeared favored, lively and savory but all were not so to me mortifying. It is very hot dry weather here but showers near</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-06-30"><dateline><date when="1818-06-30">30.</date></dateline><p>  3rd day Elizabeth Balderston of Pennsylvania was at our meeting and had a pretty deal to say to us but I thought life and animation was wanting. Weather very hot. People work hard. Many very drowsy even whilst she was preaching to them in a zealous, powerful manner yet not so I hope with all.  I ventured to try again at last and have had no cause to repent it. A strengthening time. Said David have I run through a troop. Feeling a little like it after a bitter trial; a mercy continued.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-07-05"><head>July 1818</head><dateline><date when="1818-07-05">5 Day.</date></dateline><p> at our meeting. Small. It is well if it was better than none at all. Very poor and destitute of life and savor; shut up. </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-07-06"><dateline><date when="1818-07-06">6th Day.</date></dateline><p> Huldah Hoag of Long Island<note resp="transcr">Hunt is mistaken, Huldah Hoag was from Vermont</note> and her companion was at our meeting.  Huldah had a very great deal to say the forepart of her testimony I thought was very extraordinary lively, pertinent and savory but I thought not so much so at last I was fearful whither or no she did not stand too long and  say the full stomach the honeycomb Lo though a plenty makes dainty too much.   Thus we have had three meetings this week. My Black man says he thinks we should be very good going to meetings so much. So they who have their eyes upon us are looking for fruit but alas I fear after all the precious fruits of the spirit is too much wanting among us and if there is no fruit we are worse off than they who go none to meeting at all. How alarming. </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-07-05"><dateline><date when="1818-07-05">5 of the month  1st Day.</date></dateline><p> at our meeting. Some savor and life but it was a shut up time to me as to words though not as to thoughts.  Blessed are the undefiled in the way. Oh that I were one of they. Paul's advice to Timothy take heed to thyself etc.<note resp="transcr">1 Tim. 4:16</note> and blessed are the pure in heart</p>
<p>[marginal note] I will send a famine among you not of bread but of the word; but here now three meetings [and] two strangers this week. The full stomach loaths [loathes] the honeycomb<note resp="transcr">Proverbs 27:7</note> and plenty makes dainty. </p></div>
<pb n="11" facs="sc203979"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-07-06"><dateline><date when="1818-07-06">6 of the 7th month 1818.</date></dateline><p>  I am informed that William Hopkins of the family of Hopkins at Haddonfield is raving crazy distracted and that they took him to the new asylum this morning near Philadelphia. His grandfather was a man in great account.  Since my memory he was clerk of Haddonfield Monthly Meeting if not quarterly meeting too. Has a wife and a large family of children; has been most of his life much in the neglect of attending meetings; took to hard drinking; now gone as crazy as to threaten of killing his wife and others about him.  Oh! the scenes of sorrow, destruction, dissolution and ruin. Again I am informed that Joel Middleton near Moorestown has lost his reason. Quite crazy by hard excessive drinking;  a youngish man and few years married and settled.  Rent rolls over rent and ruin overtakes ruin and dissolution overtakes desolation. What a world of confusion and discord it is without attention to that universal regulating principle which has appeared unto all men and if attended to would do for all as is did for Paul. </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-07-09"><dateline><date when="1818-07-09">9.</date></dateline><p> was our monthly meeting which was an healing, open, owning, strengthening time to me yet not altogether as I could wish. Oh the need of continual watchfulness and prayer for preservation, especially after times of favor. Mordecai after he had been clothed with the king's apparel returned and sat at the king's gate and Daniel, we read, sat at the king's gate. Blessed is the man that is found watching at wisdom's gate etc.  </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-07-11"><dateline><date when="1818-07-11">11.</date></dateline><p> 7th Day. It is a very pinching time of dry weather here although there has been many showers and heavy thunder almost all round us.   So we read he caused it to rain upon one city and not upon another city and they wandered to the city on which it rained to drink water. Although I am get so old and feeble and Hannah so lame in her arms that we can do but little yet we have been favored to get in our harvest and hay beyond all expectation. So far eleven horse loads of hay and several loads of rye and wheat. What a mercy it is.</p></div>
<pb n="12" facs="sc203980"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-07-12"><dateline><date when="1818-07-12">12 of the 7th month.</date></dateline><p> First Day morning. Very hot still clear dry weather. Reading [John] Hoyland's work concerning Abraham and page 189 his descending from the mountain after offering up his son Isaac. He says, “Who ever sacrificed to God and was a loser, whoever hardened himself against God and prospered?” Went to our meeting and a very very poor one it was, I believe, all shut up not a word among us all four: several could not bear silence and left the meeting some time before it concluded.  I could have expressed words suitable and instructing but there was no life, no ability, no strength, no authority, so poor I fear it was hardly reputable. What a pity seeing blessings are still showered down upon us a plentiful harvest and fine weather to get it in; whereas there has been seasons so wet that it has been spoiled even after it has been shoked in the field and fine crops of grass. Afternoon reading <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn's</persName> <emph rend="italic">Select Works</emph>-- see page 688 “For until men receive, and are quickened, by this divine principle, they are hypocrites and not Christians; bastards and not sons.  Neither can they have true living Faith whatsoever they profess; nor can they truly worship God, whatsoever they perform” and page 689, “For out of Christ, out of his Spirit and nature verily we cannot have peace,” and I add what sort of living is it this world without their peace and what sort of dying will it be without it? Oh how little people consider the unspeakable value of peace and for what mere trifles we part with it for and then at last this is the cry, Oh,  ten thousands of words would I give if it was in my power for peace with the Lord.  I have called and ye have not answered was the language to some of old.  Dreadful state. Page 692 <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> mentions a poor Indian that desired not to go to heaven if the cruel Spaniards went there. I heard of an old Negro who said he could not believe his master was gone to Heaven because he never heard him talk about or make any preparation for it. When Masse go to Baltimore to New York and Boston he get ready, he get new cloths, he talk about it. He not gone to heaven.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Gardens, fields and meadows look very languishing with the drought.</p></div>
<pb n="13" facs="sc203981"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-07-15"><dateline><date when="1818-07-15">15 7 month 1818.</date></dateline><p> See Hoylands works 1st volume, page 277 he says, “religion which is the life, the joy, the guide, the support of the universe.”  I have just been reaping until I am tired and a very little work tires me so that I can hardly get over it. We have of late had uncommon hot dry weather here although very great signs and tokens of rain and showers near all round us. The heat has been very oppressive to man and beast and we may say as they of old, the vine of Hesbon languishes<note resp="transcr">Isaiah 16:8</note> Again see Hoyland's works, page 344, Moses did not descend from the mount with ingrained strength though he had been upon it forty days fasting. The Jewish rabbis consider the unabated vigor, the unfading luster of the latter years of the life of Moses as the effect of having been forty days in familiar intercourse with God. What a sublime idea does this suggest of communion with God. To what a height of glory can it raise a fallen creature.  By this intercourse man becomes transformed into the image of God! The change may be seen and felt in the serenity of the countenance, in the kindness of the eye, in the melody of the voice and in the sweetness of the whole deportment.  It is easy to conceive what the world would be destitute of the modes and offices of religion when we consider what men are with the advantages of line upon line, precept upon precept, revelation upon revelation. I have often thought what a pity it is we do not avail ourselves of the great privileges and advantages of religion. The means offered for our help are far beyond those of many nations and ages past and present.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-07-05"><dateline><date when="1818-07-05">5 Day.</date></dateline><p> at our meeting and I believe something lively and satisfactory, healing and strong. See Hoyland's book, 1 vol, page 246 on the history of Joseph's life and faithfulness, “the fear of God is the best security for a man's good behavior in every situation. And that he is not to be trusted in anything who has not conscience in everything.” Very busy getting in hay and rye and wheat etc. I picked up a little book on Christian education called <emph rend="italic">Paternus and Eusebia</emph>, page 6, As all wisdom, love and goodness proceeds from God so nothing but love and wisdom and  goodness can lead to God. Again see page 9.</p>
<p>[marginal note] Heard of the death of Simeon Ellis who has several years been afflicted with a cancer.  John Hollen buried with a cancer lately and now Benjamin Bishop bad with a cancer.</p>
<pb n="14" facs="sc203982"/>
<p>As a father's advice to his son he says, remember that there is but one man in the world with whom you are to have perpetual contention and be always striving to exceed him and that is yourself.<note resp="transcr">Paternus</note> Oh this self, he that conquers himself conquers his greatest enemy. He that ruleth himself is stronger than he that taketh a city, saith Solomon. A selfish spirit is Satan's spirit, says <persName key="w6086z81">Benjamin Lay</persName>. Cursed self says <persName key="w69891jc">Thomas Chalkley</persName> and Alice Hayes. Very dry weather, no rain or very little five weeks. I work among the hay till I am tired down then come in, read and write. [Pierre] Charron says it was a proverb among the Spaniards: Preserve and deliver me from myself. Know thyself was written in letters of gold among the Athenians say Charron. See Hoyland 1st volume, page 281. The man that fears God is raised above all other fear in the confidence of faith. This has been verified in the example of Daniel and Shadrach, Mesach and Abednego and thousands of the martyrs since. Oh what a blessed state. Fear not them that kill the body, said the Divine master. How great that power that can inspire above the fear of death and blessed the state of those who are enriched with its favor. A never failing helper in greatest need. See Hoyland, page 222, on Jacob's faithfulness. He says, “Herein is the world instructed, that he who fears and follows God, will, sooner or later, find his reward,” but he who does not fear nor follow God (as it is to be feared very many do how then).</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-07-19"><dateline><date when="1818-07-19">19 was first Day.</date></dateline><p> Rainy morning.  I am wearied down helping getting in hay and grain but went to our meeting although hardly fit to go I thought very great poverty dryness and formality overwhelmed us.  <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName>, <persName key="w67b4w4h">Joseph Justice</persName> and I quite shut up but E.R. and A.H. had something to say, savory and lively.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-07-20"><dateline><date when="1818-07-20">20.</date></dateline><p> Rainy Morning after five or six weeks very dry hot weather. Heard that a tavern keep died distracted at Haddonfield</p>
<p>[marginal note] [indecipherable] says know that nothing hurts thee so much as thy self, or, once delivered from self, free from Satan. Was it not said to Israel, thy destruction is of thyself?</p></div>
<pb n="15" facs="sc203983"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-07-23"><dateline><date when="1818-07-23">23 fifth Day.</date></dateline><p> at our preparative meeting. Exhausted with old age fatigue and weariness, could hardly stem the tide and flood of ease, indifference and lukewarmness. Weather warm. People work hard over wearied and as Thomas Cross says, Nature calls for rest. When this is the case very dull, dry, poor and formal. Not crowned as formerly with manifestations and evidence of life and zeal. Not many can say the zeal of thy house hath eaten me up but something else has they don't get to sleep in their fields and meadows: there is evidence of zeal there however I had some satisfaction at last. With hard labor finished getting hay which always has been a fatiguing laborious job favored to get through better than I could expect considering how weak handed and helpless I am.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-07-27"><dateline><date when="1818-07-27">27 first Day.</date></dateline><p> This language occupied my mind: great is Diana of the Ephesians<note resp="transcr">Acts 19:34</note> and is not this the general way in the language of conduct in the general scramble after the things of this world give give and never satisfy? See Hoyland volume 1st page 147, “When we behold men of like passions with ourselves, placed in situations similar to our own practicing, virtue within our reach; discovering a temper and disposition, which if we please to cultivate, we may attain; then, if we read not with profit, as well as delight, it must be, not because we want the power but the inclination to improve.” But see, says Hoyland, how the temple of mammon is crowded, but it is said ye cannot serve God and mammon. Went to our meeting although I was so unwell I was not fit to go. A very poor low time, all shut up. People work very hard getting hay. Weather very hot. So I have thought when this is the case our meetings are mostly dry and formal and destitute of life. The world's calls seems to outbid all and carry all before it.</p></div>
<pb n="16" facs="sc203984"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-08-06"><head>August 1818</head><dateline><date when="1818-08-06">6 of the 8th month.</date></dateline><p> at our monthly meeting.  Very large, three couples passed meeting: <persName key="w6096wx2">James Thornton</persName> and Dr. [John H.] Stokes' daughter [Rebecca Stokes], Joseph Morgan and William Burrough's daughter [Rachel C. Burroughs], William Cowperthwaite and <persName key="w67b4w4h">Joseph Justice</persName>s' daughter [Martha C. Justice]. The first part was an open, healing, owning time to me and I believe to others. Rebeckah Price of Philadelphia, an ancient minister had lively service and <persName key="w6g77m31">Hannah Yarnall</persName> whose son passed meeting the last meeting mostly pretty well and to me satisfactory and strengthening, yet there was something one while very unpleasant to me and that was a number who had not a right came to see their near connections pass meeting and some of our friends could not be easy till they turned them all out before the couples passed meeting which I fear gave great offence to many. It brought an unpleasant feeling for a time but we seemed to get over it.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-08-08"><dateline><date when="1818-08-08">8.</date></dateline><p>  On 7th day. I took my daughter to Moorestown at our meeting house to meet some friends, chiefly young women.  Joseph Clerk of Philadelphia had a concern to establish a society of young women to take care of the poor as he has done at several monthly meetings round about us and I thought there was something owning lively and savory attended. They have long or sometime past had such a society to take care of the poor in Philadelphia and I have long believed it would be of use to our young women to come under such a concern and exercise for they that help others help themselves: they that labor receive wages and gather fruit unto eternal life and seeing the ups and downs of the uncertainty of all earthly things none of us know but that we may become objects of and need the sympathy and care of such a society.  I think there are many instances that demonstrate the truth of this remark.</p>
<pb n="17" facs="sc203985"/>
<p>Many great and precious promises there are in Scripture to them that consider the poor: Blessed is the man that considers the poor, the Lord shall preserve him and keep him alive and he shall be blessed upon the earth, said David<note resp="transcr">Psalms 41:1-2</note> etc. etc.  I have a hope it is a seed planted that will take root downward and spring upward and bring forth much good fruit that will never wither or die and I believe it will not whilst and where there is a right religious concern prevails.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-08-09"><dateline><date when="1818-08-09">9.</date></dateline><p> First Day at our meeting came of pretty well satisfied I had to bear my testimony against friends and their children running to the tavern to see a shew [show] of a lion, pelican and several other birds, natives of other nations which were to be exhibited there. It is likely many will query what harm can there be in going to see these strange creatures and parting with our money to see them. They are the works of the great Creator.  I answer there is no harm in going to see them if the people did not make harm of it, but who can say they do not make harm of it in collecting much people to the taverns where many drink to excess. There have been such shows of strange creatures every once in awhile both in the city and through the country and some of our foremost friends and elders have borne their testimony against them in print and otherwise as corrupting practices tending to encourage idleness and corrupt the youth. There was a company some years ago brought along what they called a learned pig and from tavern to tavern collected much idle people to see some strange things. They had learned the pig but up in Burlington County one friend stood up with a furious zeal and drove them out of the county and as one friend said he did not doubt but one of these shows would collect more money than would pay the county's tax, which would be much better laid out for the use of the poor and be an acceptable sacrifice to the Lord.</p></div>
<pb n="18" facs="sc203986"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-08-12"><dateline><date when="1818-08-12">12.</date></dateline><p> Fourth Day. 1818. My old friend and  his new wife Nathan Smith of Philadelphia and  our cousin Benjamin Warrington and wife paid us a visit and I went with them to see several neighbors and  to Benjamin Warrington's and to see our old aunt <persName key="w6tq8ftp">Hannah Buzby</persName> poorly but now better.</p>
<p>Fifth Day. We went to Easton meeting which was very small and very poor indeed but after a long time I ventured to stand up and a venture it seemed to me then. Nathan had considerable to say and it ended lively, savory and satisfactory. Dined at <persName key="w6553d40">Samuel Roberts</persName> then came down to Moorestown. Visited Benjamin Bispham -- very bad with a cancer in his mouth of which a number have died of latter years and divers [indecipherable]. Lately it seemed hard coming at anything serious, solid, savory and weighty: but through favor came off with satisfaction. Had a little time with a sick friend at Easton  <persName key="w6n05bth">Joseph Roberts'</persName> wife at Easton. Left my friends at Moorestown at John Matlack's where we had a silent setting. We have had of late much rain and  it is that there has not been such a great prospect of a great crop of Indian corn many years if ever and  harvest mostly pretty good and  seldom greater crops of grass. Now see my notes in the 8th month 1816. A pinching dry season far and wide, east and west. Do the people see great plenty and great prosperity to be dangerous? Oh no, the language is give give: but see fulness of bread and idleness was the complaint against Sodom. Prize the gift and forget the giver. Has it not too generally been so of old? </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-08-07"><dateline><date when="1818-08-07">7th day.</date></dateline><p> I went to my son John's to get a plow fitted up and my cousin Henry Warrington came there and went with me to see William Hulings, a miserable captive to strong drink but they seemed not willing I should see him. I suppose he was not fit to be seen.</p>
<pb n="19" facs="sc203987"/>
<p>Then we want to see Samuel Balinger, an innocent old Friend eighty-five years old; has been a constant attender of meeting till of latter years. Had a satisfactory setting with the family, He expressed it was satisfactory to him. Then we went to see Tibbila Duril who has lost her reason and has been kept chained twelve years or more.  She knowed me and called me by name but I think she is the most miserable object I know of.  Some weeks past I have thought of visiting some of those under affliction, remembering Solomon's words. It says, he is better to go to the house of mourning than to the house of mirth, so I had a mind to try it and  have been to see several and  there are divers others, yet one distressed creature, Levi Lippincott, died before I got to see him. He has lain in a most miserable condition with the palsy years past. </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-08-16"><dateline><date when="1818-08-16">16 was first Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting.  Nathan Smith was there but oh how were we overwhelmed with indolence and loathsome luke-warmness yet through unmerited mercy I believe it ended well and savory but oh what hard work it was to rise among them. Nathan found it so as well as I. It is a very fine growing time for grain and grass but alas as to religion it is a dry time. As Elizabeth Morris says, if they can but live in prosperity they sit down at ease and conclude all is well if they keep clear of gross enormities but as to the new and living way we read of the inward life, the hidden life, the life that is hid with Christ in God the life of God in the soul of man. This is strange talk to many in these days. They seem [not] to know nor care to know anything about it more than the horse or the mule. As David says, be ye not as the horse or the mule that hath no understanding.<note resp="transcr">Psalms 32:9</note> Many I observe who appear to be most knowing and wise about cultivating the earth seem more stupid about religion. Take no thought for the body, what we shall eat or drink or put on, said the great master.  Seek first the kingdom and all these things shall be added. Now if there had been no more care taken for the body than there has been for the soul, would there have been such
<pb n="20" facs="sc203988"/>
such improvements and accommodations and conveniences as there are now to be seen: fine houses, rich furniture, gaudy apparel, gilded glittering carriages, some they tell me cost five hundred dollars and some seven hundred dollars and in arts and sciences and agriculture a wilderness turned into fruitful fields and as to the outward the deserts and solitary places blossom as the rose but as to religion I fear we are going into captivity and choosing bondage and slavery: when freedom and liberty is offered to us. Going back into our worthy predecessors coming up out of the wilderness (out of the bewildering spirit, customs and fashions of this world). Clear as the sun, fair as the moon and terrible as an army with banners. Alas what sort of a state would our poor moldering bodies have been in if there cares and concerns for the body and our temporal Interest had been treated with such trifling indifferency and indolence as their spiritual interest and care and concern for the inward man has been treated. Should we not have been in a very poor, naked, starving condition as it is to be feared the inward man with many now is destitute of a right clothing as them of old poor miserable blind and naked. It has been a very hot summer. A few summers past it was remarked to be very cool.  Some said there was frost in every month or nearly every month in the summer. How little do many think of that Almighty power that superintends the universe and presides over the seasons of wet and dry, heat and cold, plenty and scarcity, health and sickness etc. etc. </p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-08-21"><dateline><date when="1818-08-21">21 of 8th Month fifth day.</date></dateline><p> at our meeting. Small and very low and poor forepart, yet I thought at last is ended pretty lively,  attended with some savor. If a plant or a vine or a seed should be brought amongst us that made every one rich, happy and safe that cultivated and propagated it would be a wonder if everyone did not try to avail themselves of it.  Seeing all desire to be happy but more to be admired if any should neglect it etc.</p>
<p>[marginal note] 130 dollars for a chair an elder gave for to ride in gilded, shining like silver. I fear we are leading our children into trouble.</p>
<pb n="21" facs="sc203989"/>
<p>It was said to a people formerly, I planted the a noble vine, wholly a right seed.<note resp="transcr">Jeremiah 2:21</note> This I believe might be applied to us,  a noble vine, wholly a right seed came one over in the first settling of our land with <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> and precious was the fruits of the Spirit it produced and  brought forth etc. satisfactorily. What a pity I thought it would be this seed should be lost and what an unspeakable loss it would be to the succeeding generation. This was the language of old: I planted thee a noble vine, wholly a right seed, but how art thou turned into a degenerate plant of a strange vine unto me. Many bringing forth sour grapes, wild fruit etc. etc.  Something owning at last and satisfactory in a good degree uniting</p>
<p>[marginal note] Our son Joseph and wife and son and Benne here to see us from Fallowfield, Pennsylvania.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-08-23"><dateline><date when="1818-08-23">23.</date></dateline><p> First Day. At our meeting, pretty large,  Thomas Mathews and George Gibbins of Philadelphia and <persName key="w6md9qck">Hinchman Haines</persName> were there, <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> and myself and daughter Abigail all had something to say and we thought there was some solemnity, savor and life attended the meeting more than common. There was a very open pleasant feeling when it broke up, however it was more so to me than common: uniting.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-08-27"><dateline><date when="1818-08-27">27.</date></dateline><p> at our preparative meeting. To me pretty lively and satisfactory. I after meeting with <persName key="w6xt6kpr">Ann Edwards</persName> visited the wife of Joseph Hays in the prime of life has almost destroyed herself with strong drink so infatuated and desperate after it as to break locks to get it. She seemed to take the visit kindly. At 4 o'clock <persName key="w62n51qq">John Comly</persName> of Byberry, Pennsylvania appointed a meeting at our meeting house and had a very great deal to say. Preached about two hours with good authority, sound and very pertinent matter. A youngish man has been a minister but a few years: power full preacher and dull hearers like a pleasant song and each one returns to their beloved way.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-08-30"><dateline><date when="1818-08-30">30 8th month 1818 was first Day.</date></dateline><p> My daughter Abigail went with me to Upper Evesham. Abraham Lower of Philadelphia was there. I think I was careful not to sit or stand in his way and it was a pretty open time at last though very low at first as is often the case. Abraham is an amiable able minister though youngish. Dined with my sister, Hope Stokes.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-08-31"><dateline><date when="1818-08-31">31.</date></dateline><p> I went to the select meeting at Burlington a satisfactory time I lodge with my old friend <persName key="w6b01gx6">John Cox</persName> and very pleasantly. We did enjoy one another's company did not talk ourselves poor, Went to see <persName key="w60006f4">George Dillwyn</persName> and several other old acquaintances.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-08-31"><dateline><date when="1818-08-31">31.</date></dateline><p> was quarterly meeting. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> chief speaker but there were a number of others and several young ones. Very savory and hopeful;  an owning satisfactory time.</p></div>
<pb n="22" facs="sc203990"/>
<div type="entry" n="1818-09-03"><head>September 1818</head><dateline><date when="1818-09-03">3 of the 9th Month 1818.</date></dateline><p> We hear there were three young people drowned at Egg Harbor, going into the sea to bathe, one young man and two young women. Since our daughter Hannah was there for her health but a few weeks ago and went into the sea at the same place on the beach and we have frequently heard of their being drowned there.</p>
<p>3 at our week day meeting: open, owning, uniting, satisfactory</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-09-04"><dateline><date when="1818-09-04">4.</date></dateline><p> was our select meeting at Moorestown. Very poor indeed as I thought at first and answering our queries. Very poor, dry and destitute of life and savor. I was shut up till the latter part and yet through mercy it seemed to me a lively time. As [Robert] Barclay says, by throwing a little water in a pump and working it, it fetches up the rest. So it seemed to be and it ended to my satisfaction. As <persName key="w6nk4g54">Thomas Scattergood</persName> said, it seemed sometimes as if he could run from one end of the continent to the other and as David said, by thee have I ran through a troop and by thee have I leaped over a wall etc.<note resp="transcr">2 Samuel 22:30; Psalms 18:29</note> When I was at Burlington I was crowded up between <persName key="w60006f4">George Dillwyn</persName> and <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName></p>
<p> which made me feel uneasy to sit with these our very greatest men. Yet fear was so taken away that I had something to say to satisfaction.  Oh what an unspeakable mercy I am thus far preserved.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-09-06"><dateline><date when="1818-09-06">6 was first Day.</date></dateline><p> At our meeting I had a feeling which made me think of Peter when he attempted to walk on the water and began to sink. So I had like to but was helped and seldom ever had a more open evidently owning time: “if our hearts condemn us not then have we confidence toward God” (Said the apostle)<note resp="transcr">1 John 3:21</note> A satisfactory time after noon.  Reading <emph rend="italic">Solitude Sweetened</emph> page 180: Remember benefits, forget injuries: forgive reproachful tongues; overlook affronts, wish well to every individual, pray for all for whom prayer ought to be made and be a child of God in temper and conduct in spite of corrupt nature earth and hell, aiming at perfection as thy father which is in Heaven is perfect.  A precious lesson if we could but learn it</p>
<pb n="23" facs="sc203991"/>
<p>Second day morning. Again see <emph rend="italic">Solitude Sweetened,</emph> page 159. Is it not so as he says? After this divine entreaty Christ is dearer to me, self more loathsome, sin more odious, the world more vain, religion more pleasant, my affections more refined, my desires more on spiritual things and heaven more desirable.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-09-03"><dateline><date when="1818-09-03">3rd day morning.</date></dateline><p> Again see <emph rend="italic">Solitude Sweetened,</emph> page 54, Frames of soul variable of such a place and such a time one may say it was Bethel the house of God and a time of love, but neither the Bethel of God nor the time of love is to be the confidence of the soul whatever comfort it may afford. The God of Bethel, the God of unchangeable love is to be the strong tower to which every believer must always resort—Oh, deplorable imperfection. When he is absent despair begins to appear, when perfect spiritual pride is ready to spring up.  But while he in wisdom comes and goes it keeps my soul in exercise, going backward and forward to the right hand and to the left, restless till I find him.  Thus the soul is prevented from setting down on a sinful security or falling asleep in the arms of downy delusion. these things I know to be true. How ready to spring up is spiritual pride after times of favor and not keep humble enough like Mordecai and Daniel.  Return and sit at the king's gate. Blessed is the man that is found watching at wisdom's gate, waiting at the posts of her doors and prosperity is a very intoxicating thing and few brains are strong enough to bear it.  I have suffered much in this spot a want of keeping humble after times of favor. Oh Judah keep thy solemn feasts, perform thy vows we know a feast of the most delicious dainties will serve us but a very short time we must have daily bread or perish: Give us this day our daily bread etc. Christ in all and all.  And man shall not live by bread alone but by every word that proceeds out of his mouth. Then there is bread to eat the world knows not of. Without me, said Christ, ye can do nothing, and Paul says he could do all things through Christ that strengthened him.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-09-10"><dateline><date when="1818-09-10">10.</date></dateline><p> Our monthly meeting, an open lively time.  I was afraid we should get to babbling. The business pretty well and lively yet one thing was mortifying to me and perhaps I needed it: a prospect of visiting the families of Moorestown.</p>
<pb n="24" facs="sc203992"/>
<p>An invitation was given to the burial of Eli Roberts, a lusty young man about 19, son of <persName key="w60h49r3">William Roberts</persName> of Moorestown. He had been out with his gun. In the evening complained of being chilly went to bed and was found dead in the morning. The doctor thought it was a fit of the apoplexy.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-09-11"><dateline><date when="1818-09-11">11.</date></dateline><p> At 3 o'clock met at his burial a great concourse of people and a number of able ministers, but all shut almost.  I had some little remarks to make at last to good satisfaction. Last week a woman died very suddenly, the wife of an honest industrious German.  She had been in a poor state of health some time but her husband left her as well as usual about her business and  when he came home found her dead on the bed alone.</p>
<p>Thomas Kite of Philadelphia was at our meeting and I thought did famously and worthily; a young minister but lately recommended and most rapidly improved. He came here to see us sixth day and we had a setting and he made a notable prayer and I thought it ended for the better.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-09-16"><dateline><date when="1818-09-16">16 of the 9 month 1818.</date></dateline><p> was our select meeting at Haddonfield. First part very poor and low. All quite shut up but at last it ended lively and savor to my satisfaction.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1818-09-17"><dateline><date when="1818-09-17">17.</date></dateline><p> We all went to our quarterly meeting and a precious highly favored time I thought it was throughout.  <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> was raised in great eminence, life and authority and I thought I seldom if ever seen a more open time for labor and close plain dealing in dipping into the state of meetings. <persName key="w6gq882n">Richard Jordan</persName> expressed he thought it was a favored, owning time of close searching labor. Oh how does mercy and goodness follow us. </p></div>
</body></text>
</TEI>