<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader></teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="01" facs="sc203680"/>
<div type="entry" n="1824-03-25"><head>March 1824</head><dateline><date when="1824-03-25">25 of 3 month 1824.</date></dateline><p> At our preparative meeting their was some pamphlets handed out which Friends had ordered to be printed and spread, giving an account of the enormous practice of the slave trade yet continued, notwithstanding divers nations have made laws to prohibit that most barbarous trade. The great number of vessels there is now employed in that trade so that they are bringing  the poor Negroes away from their native lands of near and dear connections by hundreds of thousands and [indecipherable] them into slavery to many of the various. One account seems to display a manifest judgement upon them. A vessel loaded with Negroes after they had got out to see, a strange disorder in their eyes came  upon them and both whites and both went quite blind so that they were unable to steer the vessel. Another vessel came up with them of whom they begged help, but attained none, they fearing their disorder, and it was believed them they all perished in the see. About twenty years ago I was traveling in the western territories on the River Ohio, we lodged at a tavern whereas some men had got fifty-two Negroes from the Southern states and were taking to a place called the Natchez some hundreds of miles westward. There were men, women and children, the men in chains and the women had two sucking babes at their breasts handcuffed with irons. To see and feel the darkness and hardness of their oppressors hearts was painful to be  in their company. I suppose to drown their sorrow: see Psalms 137 and 3rd For they that carried us away captive required of us a song and they that wasted us required of us mirth etc. Some years ago I picked up a bit of newspaper off the floor wherein was an account of a vessel with 130 Negroes (of the Mantanzes) which was struck with thunder and the vessel sunk in a few minutes and all perished but the Captain and his mate who lashed some spars together and floated on them near two weeks but was found and taken up by a wrecker * that is a vessel looking for shipwrecks. But the Captain and his mate had laid so long in the water they had quite lost the use of their limbs. Some years ago there were some men from the Southern States brought a number of Negroes to Redstone (on their way further to west). Whilst at Redstone a strange sickness on them and a number of Negroes died and one of the two brothers that had them in keeping died. The other set off back to get help and he also died. The Inhabitants being alarmed hired a man to conduct them down the river westward and he also died so the poor Negroes were left without Oppressors or Masters or Caretakers. What became of them I have not heard. But does not these appear singular judgements.</p>
<p>*[star and comment written later] Query. Does not the preservation of Captain and Mate seem marvelous?</p></div>
<pb n="02" facs="sc203681"/>
<div type="entry" n="1824-04"><p>A more perfect account of the Negroes brought to Redstone. Extract of a letter from Elisha Hunt of Redstone 5 month, 16[th day], 1818.
Just before we got home 4 brothers with a large company of black slaves came to town. The blacks took sick; 6 or 8 dies. The brothers took sick likewise, and 2 of them died. Here the inhabitants became alarmed and put them into a boat and started them away. One of the brothers died in the boat. The other hired a citizen of this town to navigate the boat and the other started back to Virginia for some assistance and died in the mountains of Charlestown and has left a family here. Thus 5 men have died besides the 6 or 8 Negroes. The blacks are at Charlestown in Miammi or Ohio of those that survived. Is not this an alarming hint to Negro traders?</p>
<dateline><date when="1824-04">Near the last of 4th month 1824.</date></dateline><p> J.H.</p></div>
</body></text>
</TEI>