<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Hunt Journal, 1788 2mo. 10 - 1788 2mo. 23: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>James Truitt</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 12 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were created and/or prepared by the <hi rend="italic" >Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</hi> and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <hi rend="italic"> Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College </hi>.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2021">2021</date>
                <idno type="local">A0011520</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">
                    <title level="s" type="main">Friendly Networks</title>
                    <title level="s" type="sub">The Journals of Our Beloved Friend John Hunt</title></title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>John Hunt Papers, SFHL-RG5-240</collection>
                        <idno>A0011520</idno>
                        <idno>sc203242</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>1 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The journals of Quaker minister John Hunt are stored at the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College. With the generous support of H. David and Joyce E. Hunt, Library staff scanned and transcribed the journals, and in 2021, encoded the text in TEI. The 2021 project also included researching individuals mentioned in the text to create and update records about them in the <ref target="https://snaccooperative.org/">Social Networks and Archival Context website</ref>
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> John Hunt was a good writer, but like most 18th century authors, his punctuation, spelling, and abbreviations were not standardized or necessarily consistent. The goal of the Hunt project was to produce a text accessible to the modern reader, retaining all the words in the order they appear, but with added punctuation and capitalization to make the document readable. Some spelling of surnames and places has been corrected in order to facilitate searching. Any other additions supplied to aid the reader are surrounded by brackets. Archaic forms and spellings of words are also retained. “How art thou feeling” remains as written, not changed to “How are you feeling.” And Hunt frequently used the abbreviation “Do.” for ditto; this has not been changed. The word “sic” means that word or words are transcribed as written. Usually this marks an error in the original text. When identified by the editor, biblical references, all from the King James version, have been identified in notes. Where Hunt himself identified them as such this attribution is retained in the main body of the text.</p>
                <p>Hunt consistently used Quaker-style plain dating, avoiding the names of the months and the names of days of the week. “Monday, October 9th,” for instance, is written as “Second Day, Ninth of the Tenth Month.” The headings dividing the texts were added by the editors, using the standard names for the months, again for ease of reading.</p>
                <p>Hunt had a practice of regularly adding to a series of bound journals when he was at home, but usually recorded entries while he was at Yearly Meeting or travelling in the ministry on single sheets of paper. In publishing the entirety of the journal we have added “loose” sections where they fit chronologically.  </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written <date when="1788">1788</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <term>Quakers -- Conduct of life</term>
                    <term>Quakers -- Religious life</term>
                    <term>Quakers -- Social life and customs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#lcnaf">
                    <term ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2005064399">Hunt, John, 1740-1824</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item><date/></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="01" facs="sc203591"/>
<div type="entry" n="1788-02-10"><head>February 1788</head><dateline><date when="1788-02-10">10th of the Second Month, 1788.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day. Went <rs key="w6wx87x7">my wife</rs> [page missing] which was a solid favored time I think. Went to see <persName key="w6wt9jhx">Enoch Evans</persName>.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1788-02-11"><dateline><date when="1788-02-11">11.</date></dateline><p> At work at screws for cheese press.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1788-02-12"><dateline><date when="1788-02-12">12.</date></dateline><p> Was our weekday meeting. William Venable and Rachel Croshan was married. <persName key="w63s1j4g">Solomon Gaskill</persName> was there and I think it was lively good meeting. I am ready to think the scoffer and gainsayer, if any was there, was put to silence.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1788-02-13"><dateline><date when="1788-02-13">13.</date></dateline><p> Went to make a pump for William Wright. <persName key="w63s1j4g">Solomon Gaskill</persName> went with us to <persName key="w6c82qz0">Joshua Evans</persName>.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1788-02-14"><dateline><date when="1788-02-14">14.</date></dateline><p> Was weekday meeting at Newtown and Solomon and I was there. It was a pretty lively time. <persName key="w6c82qz0">Joshua Evans</persName> having given notice of our being there, the meeting was larger than usual. Came off pretty well I hope. It was a time of favor and improvement to me. We finished Wright's pump, 10 feet long, boxes and all, comes to 26 Shillings.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1788-02-15/1788-02-16"><dateline><date from="1788-02-15" to="1788-02-16">15 and 16.</date></dateline><p> Very stormy. <persName key="w63s1j4g">Solomon Gaskill</persName> was with us.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1788-02-17"><dateline><date when="1788-02-17">17.</date></dateline><p> Was First Day at our meeting. <persName key="w63s1j4g">Solomon Gaskill</persName> was there and I thought we came off pretty well, a favor.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1788-02-18"><dateline><date when="1788-02-18">18.</date></dateline><p> About home at work in the shop.</p></div>
<div type="entry" n="1788-02-19"><dateline><date when="1788-02-19">19.</date></dateline><p> Was our weekday meeting. Joshua Stokes and Deborah Hooten was married. <persName key="w63s1j4g">Solomon Gaskill</persName> was favored and I had satisfaction. Came off bravely considering all things. Many spectators and a light company but I think I have seen since where it might have been better though no cause of complaint.</p></div>
    <div type="entry" n="1788-02-20/1788-02-23"><dateline><date from="1788-02-20" to="1788-02-23">20:21:22:23.</date></dateline><p> About home except visited D. Higbe. <persName key="w6hf8m7k">Joseph Thorington</persName> was to see us and Jo Buzby to Quarter.</p><p>[Page cut off at the bottom.]</p></div>
</body></text>
</TEI>