<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Hunt Journal, 1805 5mo. 11: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>James Truitt</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 10 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were created and/or prepared by the <hi rend="italic" >Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</hi> and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <hi rend="italic"> Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College </hi>.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2021">2021</date>
                <idno type="local">A0011523</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">
                    <title level="s" type="main">Friendly Networks</title>
                    <title level="s" type="sub">The Journals of Our Beloved Friend John Hunt</title></title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>John Hunt Papers, SFHL-RG5-240</collection>
                        <idno>A0011523</idno>
                        <idno>sc203693</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>3 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The journals of Quaker minister John Hunt are stored at the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College. With the generous support of H. David and Joyce E. Hunt, Library staff scanned and transcribed the journals, and in 2021, encoded the text in TEI. The 2021 project also included researching individuals mentioned in the text to create and update records about them in the <ref target="https://snaccooperative.org/">Social Networks and Archival Context website</ref>
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> John Hunt was a good writer, but like most 18th century authors, his punctuation, spelling, and abbreviations were not standardized or necessarily consistent. The goal of the Hunt project was to produce a text accessible to the modern reader, retaining all the words in the order they appear, but with added punctuation and capitalization to make the document readable. Some spelling of surnames and places has been corrected in order to facilitate searching. Any other additions supplied to aid the reader are surrounded by brackets. Archaic forms and spellings of words are also retained. “How art thou feeling” remains as written, not changed to “How are you feeling.” And Hunt frequently used the abbreviation “Do.” for ditto; this has not been changed. The word “sic” means that word or words are transcribed as written. Usually this marks an error in the original text. When identified by the editor, biblical references, all from the King James version, have been identified in notes. Where Hunt himself identified them as such this attribution is retained in the main body of the text.</p>
                <p>Hunt consistently used Quaker-style plain dating, avoiding the names of the months and the names of days of the week. “Monday, October 9th,” for instance, is written as “Second Day, Ninth of the Tenth Month.” The headings dividing the texts were added by the editors, using the standard names for the months, again for ease of reading.</p>
                <p>Hunt had a practice of regularly adding to a series of bound journals when he was at home, but usually recorded entries while he was at Yearly Meeting or travelling in the ministry on single sheets of paper. In publishing the entirety of the journal we have added “loose” sections where they fit chronologically.  </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written on <date when="1805-05-11">1805 5mo. 11</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <term>Quakers -- Conduct of life</term>
                    <term>Quakers -- Religious life</term>
                    <term>Quakers -- Social life and customs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#lcnaf">
                    <term ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2005064399">Hunt, John, 1740-1824</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item><date/></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<pb n="01" facs="sc203817"/>
<div type="entry" n="1805-05-11"><head>May 1805</head><dateline><date when="1805-05-11">Seventh Day the 11th of the 5th Month, 1805.</date></dateline><p> Commenced a journey to Pennsylvania in company with Uncle William M[missing].  We met at Glou[ce]ster at 11 o'clock, crossed the river from there to the point, House from there we rode up to Philadelphia which is about two miles through very pretty meadows. Come in the city of the lowest end of Front Street a few sq[uares] then turned up to 2nd Street to Draw Bridge still along Second Street to Walnut Street, up Walnut Street to 3rd street, along s[ai]d to M[arket] Street, up M[arket] Street to the sign of the spread Eagle kept by John Tomlinson on the N[orth] side where we had our horses put to hay and took dinner with Jacob Trasel's next door above s[ai]d tavern. After dinner we walked up M[arket] Street to Evans steam engine for sawing stone, grinding plaster etc. S[ai]d engines are made here. Mill stones stone cutting etc. carried on in the best manner I presume. Being satisfied with seeing returned back to Trasels had our horses up and proceeded up said street and went to the Water Works on Schuylkill. Then crossed over the bridge and up the hill. [crossed out] were 3 roads that come together. Then took the West Chester road leaving how I shall take name all the taverns we passed by the first from Schuylkill is the sign of William Penn kept by Lewis Lewis next is Joseph Baldin sign of the King of Prussia 3 M[iles] next is Phillip Williams sign of the Red Lion 2 next James Pilt no sign next Wm Bittles Spread Esq  next</p></div>
<pb n="02" facs="sc203818"/>
<div type="entry" n="1805-05-12"><p>[written upside down at the top] Started from [crossed out] first day evening in company with Poli Lewis</p>
<p>[12] This morning we arose as usual and having spent the morning in looking at his building &amp; apparatus</p></div>
<pb n="03" facs="sc203819"/>
<div><p>[top of page missing]
[missing] we [missing] long [missing] [indecipherable] then take the [indecipherable] [missing] to the Institution [missing] mill about 1 1/2 m[ile] [missing] small village called [missing] consisting of [indecipherable] Tavern sign Wheat Sheaf kept by James Jefferies Mill on State Road in Goshen Township Chester Creek crossed below s[ai]d Matlack is 21 miles from Schuylkill</p> <figure>[sketch of map]</figure></div> 
</body></text>
</TEI>