<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Hunt letter to Redstone, 1820 11 mo 18: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Lyra Ederington</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. XXXXX KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were created and/or prepared by the <hi rend="italic" >Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</hi> and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <hi rend="italic"> Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College </hi>.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
                <idno type="local">A00187140</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Friendly Networks</title>
                <title level="s" type="series">
                    <title level="s" type="main">The Correspondence of John Hunt and Joshua Evans</title>
                </title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>John Hunt Papers, SFHL-RG5-240</collection>
                        <idno type="local">A00187140</idno>
                        <idno type="IslandoraNodeid">457113</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>12 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The correspondence of Quaker ministers John Hunt and Joshua Evans are stored at the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College. With the generous support of H. David and Joyce E. Hunt, Library staff scanned and transcribed these letters in 2023 and encoded the text in TEI. The 2023 project also included researching individuals mentioned in the text to create and update records about them in the <ref target="https://snaccooperative.org/">Social Networks and Archival Context website</ref></p>           
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written <date from="1820-11-11" to="1820-11-28">11th to 28th of the 11th month, 1820</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <term>Quakers|Religious education of children|Children--Religious life|Simplicity--Religious aspects</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item><date/></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="001" facs="457113"/>
            
            <opener>
                <salute>To the youth <add>and parents</add> of Redstone and parts of Ohio where it has been my lot to travel.</salute>
            </opener>
            <div><p>Dear youth who are called the beauty of the present &amp; hopes of the succeeding generation: Is it not unto you <add>we</add> must look when we look for a succession in the church? For a succession of standard bearers &amp; judges as at the first and councilors as in the beginning; such there were raised up in the days of our worthy predecessors? And is not the way; the right way as open for us as it was for them: if we were willing to walk in their Footsteps might we not arrive to their [attainments?]: Hath not the same means <add>been</add> to us as was to them and gifts &amp; talents bestowed on the present young generation if rightly improved to qualify for judges as at the first &amp; councilors as in the beginning? See Genesis 49 &amp; 26: <quote type="biblical">the blessing of thy father have prevailed above the blessing of my progenitors unto the utmost bounds of the everlasting hills.</quote> Here we may see the blessings of Jacob to his sons. And have not many very precious blessings been bestowed upon you, which would make you as bright stars in the firmament in the lord’s power and as polished shafts in his quiver &amp; as stars of the first magnitude, as some through mercy have been made in our northern hemisphere? If your <gap reason="illegible" /><add>inquire,</add> Our worthy progenitors, what sort of a people were they? And how &amp; by what means were they brought forth? May we not adopt the ancient language, <quote type="biblical">by whom shall Jacob (or the true seed) arise, for he <add>is</add> small</quote>? Were not our worthy progenitors: A people, like the church we read of, who were <quote type="biblical">coming up out of the wilderness [leaning] on the breast of her beloved</quote>: (mark, not on the breast of this world) clear as the sun, fair as the moon &amp; terrible as an army with banners: Coming up out of the wilderness, out of all the bewildering customs, never-settled fashions, and spirit of this world: And they were brought to a safe and blessed happy state: For they not only believed what they read in the scriptures of truth but were made willing to take up the cross &amp; put them in practice so they &amp; all the obedient since, witness their promises verified If ye know these things, happy are ye if ye do them &amp; again; they that do my will shall know of my doctrine &amp; oh how wonderfully was the scriptures opened to them &amp; the mysteries of the kingdom of heaven too. It is said of our worthy progenitors that plainness was their distinguishing Badge, they professed a renunciation of superfluity of all kinds because their divine master for their &amp; our example wore a garment without a seam: and the apostle exhorted to let their adorning not be that of putting on a costly array of etc.: They read the 3rd of Isaiah where there is such dreadful woes &amp; judgment against those that pride themselves in such things &amp; gave way to such folly: &amp; which has brought misery on many
                
            <pb n="002" facs="457113"/>
            of our dear worthy friends on their death beds &amp; in their writings have lamented the great departure from plainness, <persName key="w6cg1kgr">John Churchman</persName> says oh! how is the ancient plainness &amp; simplicity of truth departed from &amp; pomp &amp; splendid appearances: taken their places: &amp; <persName key="w6wr0v4m">John Woolman</persName> laments a giving way amongst us by little &amp; littles until superfluities are become common amongst us: might not a volume Be filled with such testimonies of our friends lamenting the degeneracy &amp; falling away in our day: that dignified minister E. Walker at a late quarterly meeting told us of what some of other societies said to her viz. we have read Fox &amp; we have read Barclay &amp; we have read Penn are you a changed people: see Frederick Smith's advice to parents reflecting the education of children, page 3rd. It must be obvious to those who will look impartially at the outward appearance of our Society, that it has lost much of that plainness which distinguished our ancestors, and that many of late years have shown so increasing a tendency to a conformity with <add>the</add> world that, were as great alterations progressively to take place, I fear few vestiges would remain of that simplicity which the truth leads into &amp; which had been as a waymark to many and the means of incalculable preservation to the dear youth of both sexes. Further he says, but I am grieved to add, that I apprehend this declension is much to be attributed to the spiritual weakness &amp; indulgence of parents: having yielded to the youthful inclinations of their children, they have paved the way for their gradual uniting with the pleasures, fashions, and maxims of this world which in their natural consequence lead to a total distaste for religious duties, a distaste to those worthy pursuits &amp; employments which should yield them the purest delights. He further says (page the 4th), <said>a religious education is the richest gift a parent can bestow on a child, the want of it can never be made up by any wealth it may be in his power to give him. It is a great thing for parents to stand clear of the blood of their children And an awful thing not to stand clear of their blood &amp; many have found it so when it has been too late to remedy the will that negligence has accomplished.</said> I do therefore earnestly desire that it may be the living core of concern of such parents as have young children who are yet uncontaminated <add>that it may never become their own distressing</add> reflection that the blood of their dear children may be required of their hands. <quote type="biblical">Train up a child in the way he should go and when he is old he will not depart from it,</quote> <add>says Soloman</add>. If so then is not the world contaminated for want of a parental care? <quote>Prepare their minds to receive the power of truth without which they never can be happy,</quote> <add>says [Samuel] Fothergill</add>. I have observed parents who have treated dangerous trifling indifference like Esau formerly who sold his birthright for a mess of potage &amp; afterwards sought it with tears but could not find it, &amp; I have seen their children and grandchildren follow their example to their unspeakable &amp; everlasting loss, loss one generation after another: I have never seen them have to say with one of old to his sons, ye have made me to slink amongst the inhabitants of the land, amongst the Canaanites &amp; Perizzites, yea I have seen them bring down their gray hairs with sorrow to the grave &amp; shorten their days with grief
                
            <pb n="003" facs="457113"/>
            and I have observed what true religion has done <add>who has given </add><gap/><add>their preference</add> they have had To say with the apostle, <quote type="biblical">I have no greater joy than to see my children walk in the truth,</quote> &amp; when both children and parents have walked in the truth, they have seen one another’s joy in the lord and the children have been as a staff for the aged parents to lean upon in old age &amp; in the decline of life. May both parents &amp; children unite in endeavoring to suppress the seeds of pride, which are the seeds of desolation—&amp; have they not had a great <add>&amp; rapid</add> growth in our nation? <quote type="biblical">Be ye not conformed to this world</quote> was the Positive command, but how lamentably has it been trampled upon. May we not say with the prophet, <quote type="biblical">pride hath budded, iniquity hath blossomed,</quote> and brought forth a plentiful crop, and is it not grievous ingratitude? Let the advocates for a conformity to the world judge. And must they not allow that following the fashions &amp; never-settled customs of the world is not confessing Christ before men but openly denying him before men? And is it <add>not</add> written for our caution, &amp; that he will deny such that deny him in the most dreadful time before his father &amp; the holy angels? And oh, sorrowful to think &amp; behold, how a great part of our youth have given way to a conformity to the world’s fashions, so that even many children of worthy ministers &amp; elders cannot be known from other societies by their outward appearances. <quote>Surely</quote> (this was the language of our first Friends in many of their long epistles, they wrote &amp; called them epistles against pride) <quote>Surely will not the lord visit for these things?</quote> Be ye alarmed, dear youth, for desolation threatens us—well would it be if the youth of the present day manifested such a zeal for the lord’s cause as it is said the youth did formerly, for it is said that when the prisons were filled all over the nation that the dear youth kept their meetings, and many were beautifully brought forth in the ministry even in their minority—sons grew up as plants of renown &amp; daughters polished &amp; polishing after the similitude of a palace. This indeed was beautiful polished furniture for our meetinghouses much wanted in our days. It is agreed that that society of people who do not recur to their first principles will surely go to decay. If so, is it not high time <add>to</add> wake up &amp; consider &amp; see whereabouts we are before desolation overtakes us? For it surely threatens us. We may observe some meetings appear very sick &amp; wealthy, some have quite died away, &amp; many seem to have the consumption, not likely to live long. I have observed some places of worship left desolate, unoccupied, &amp; the rats have gnawed holes in them &amp; the little hawks &amp; owls have been their inhabitants. Would not this be sorrowful, after so so much has been done for us? What is that we read of the Bats<add> &amp; moles</add>, owls &amp; screech owls, etc.

            <pb n="004" facs="457113"/>
            David says in his days they burnt up all the synagogues <add>of God</add> in the Land; they might do that &amp; not be able to destroy their zeal for the Lord. For it is said, when they destroyed &amp; pulled down their meeting houses our first Friends would keep up their meetings on the rubbish as near the spot as they could, so that it was out of the power of their enemies to destroy their zeal for the lord. But this spirit of pride, luxury, ease, indifference, &amp; lukewarmness which now threatens us <add>with</add> desolation destroys the very heart, desire, &amp; zeal for the lord’s cause, so that they have no taste, desire, zeal, or relish for to attend meetings or to have any meeting houses at all.</p>
            <p>We read in scripture that the people served the lord all the days of Joshua &amp; of the elders that outlived Joshua, but afterwards there arose a people that knew not the lord &amp; of some that were strangers to the covenant of promise &amp; aliens to the commonwealth of Israel, &amp; of one that could say, <quote type="biblical">come &amp; see my zeal for the lord,</quote> &amp; of some that said unto God, <quote type="biblical">Depart from us, we desire not the knowledge of thy ways.</quote> And Job speaks of some that rebelled against the Light that knew not the ways thereof neither abode in the paths thereof, although the prophet invites, <quote type="biblical">Oh! House of Israel, come let us walk in the Light of the Lord</quote> and the Divine master says <quote type="biblical">whilst ye have the Light, walk in the Light,</quote> etc. And of Enoch, of whom it is said he walked with God—&amp; have we not the same offer of Privilege if we choose to attend to the reproofs of instruction, which is the way of life, <quote type="biblical">when thou goest it shall lead thee, when thou sleepeth it shall keep thee &amp; when thou awaketh, it shall talk with thee.</quote> <quote type="biblical">For the law of the lord is pure, enlightening the eyes, the law of the lord converting the soul &amp; making wise the simple.</quote></p>
            <p>But it is said many formerly (&amp; is <add>it</add> not so now?) walked after things that did not Profit, Pursued Lying vanities &amp; forsook their own mercies. And what was said of such? Why, they that <quote type="biblical">cast off the thing that is good, the Enemy shall pursue them.</quote> &amp; so have we not reason to think that <quote type="biblical">many live not half their days by cleaving unto wicked ways</quote>? <quote type="biblical">Like a partridge that sitteth on Eggs &amp; hatcheth them not, so he that getteth riches &amp; not by right shall leave them in the midst of his days &amp; in the End become a fool,</quote> said the Inspired penman. It is wonderful to think of rapid progress in the settlement, planting, &amp; cultivating the western territories, the building &amp; settling &amp; establishing meetings where but a few years ago <del>it</del> was an oft howling wilderness inhabited by the Indians, wolves, bears, &amp; panthers, etc. It seems as if we must say with the Egyptians formerly, <quote type="biblical">Surely the finger of God is in it,</quote> &amp; that he intended great and good things for the people of that land. But through carelessness &amp; the overgrowing care of this world, people may lose the greatest and best of blessings intended for them. May the dear youth, the rising generation, lay it <add>to</add> heart &amp; consider how much depends &amp; lays upon them in their faithfulness to the pure preserving Principle we profess. For he that planted can pluck up, as we read he said formerly, <quote type="biblical">that which I have planted will I pluck up even this whole Nation.</quote> Read the 2nd of Deuteronomy &amp; the 27: &amp; 28 of Ezekiel.</p> <closer><signed><persName key="w6n9820p">John Hunt</persName></signed> <dateline><date when="1820-11">11mo. 1820</date></dateline></closer></div>

            <div><pb n="005" facs="457113"/>
                <p>Is it not a dreadful &amp; lamentable thing to have children lose their Reason, as is the case with many? Bacon, that great Physician, says the loss of Reason is the greatest loss that can befall a human being. But is not the Abuse of Reason still worse? The most direful, doleful, miserable condition of any I have had any account of, is some of those who have been endowed and gifted with a great share of natural abilities, gifts, &amp; talents. By abusing their precious gifts and talents, they have fallen into such a state of sorrow of heart, remorse of conscience, &amp; bitter repentance, that they have wished they could change conditions with a dog or any the most despised reptile because they had no sin to answer for. So it is Queried in scripture, <quote type="biblical">what would a man give in exchange for his soul?</quote> Again, <quote type="biblical">a wounded conscience who can bear?</quote> Rejoice, O young man, in thy youth, &amp; let thy heart cheer thee in the days of thy youth, walk in the ways of thine heart &amp; in in the light of thine eyes, but know thou that for all these things, God will bring thee into judgment, when as one say, e.g., he heard such words uttered not fit to be repeated or ever forgot, but he mentions some of one who said to them around him, <quote type="biblical">if you did but feel one one half the mountain that lays on me, you would struggle with the martyr for his stake &amp; bless God for the flames that were not everlasting &amp; for the fire that was not unquenchable.</quote> It is said <add>of</add> some that under the burden of a wounded conscience have wished they had been born blind, deaf, or dumb if <add>it</add> might have prevented their plunging themselves into that doleful state of sorrow of heart &amp; tremors of conscience. That it seems they were in a more dreadful condition than the young man we read of in scripture who would fain have filled his belly with the husks the swine had left, would not a serious consideration of their things show us the necessity &amp; unspeakable importance of a guarded religious education <quote type="poem">’tis education forms the tender mind, just as the twig is bent so it’s inclined</quote> which would have prevented such destruction &amp; ruin, if Soloman says true: <quote type="biblical">train up a child in the way he should walk &amp; when he is old, he will not depart from it.</quote> There are many under very miserable, humbling circumstances. There are many serious calls to a devout &amp; holy life. There are many idiots, silly, foolish, have not common sense. Some lose their eyesight, some lose their hearing, I have seen a young woman with a withered arm struck with the palsy, could not make any use of it pleating the hair or putting on of apparel. Very many are consuming away with the consumption, cancers &amp; ulcers in the very prime &amp; flower of their age. These things rightly considered, how solemnly do they call on all to make right use of their time &amp; these precious blessings? What shall we render?

            <pb n="006" facs="457113"/>
                See Ezekiel 19th: 1st: <quote type="biblical">Moreover take up a lamentation for the princes of Israel.</quote> &amp; see <gap/> 14, <quote type="biblical">and a fire is gone out of a rod of her Branches which hath not devoured her fruit, so that she hath no strong rod to be a scepter to rule. This is a lamentation &amp; shall be for a lamentation.</quote> Is it not a lamentable thing to think of, that so many <add>thousands of</add> children, both white &amp; black, in their minority, who have souls to be saved or lost, should have none to look over them? None that have any care or concern for their preparation or religious improvement? Who are exposed from their infancy to corrupting company of evil communications which corrupts good manners? Under such circumstances, what can be expected to come forth but <quote type="biblical">a generation of vipers</quote>? See Matthew the 3rd, &amp; see Jeremiah says <quote type="biblical">a den of dragons.</quote> Our savior &amp; John the Baptist called the scribes and Pharisees <quote type="biblical">a generation of vipers</quote>. &amp; see Isaiah 30 &amp; 6, <quote type="biblical">from whence comes the viper &amp; Serpent.</quote> &amp; again see Isaiah 59 &amp; 5, <quote type="biblical">they hatch cockatrice eggs &amp; weave the spider’s web: he that eateth of their eggs dieth, that which is crushed breaks forth into a viper.</quote> And George Fox says when the lord sent him forth to labor in his vineyard, to awaken a drowsy world, the world was like to a wilderness &amp; no right way found out of it. Like to a wilderness filled with briars &amp; thorns, and the spirits of many were like wolves, bears, lions, &amp; tigers ready to devour him and all the lambs &amp; sheep of Christ. This may show us what vast importance a guarded religious education is, &amp; the necessity of attending to Solomon’s counsel, <quote type="biblical">train up a child in the way he should go &amp; when he is old he will not depart from it,</quote> &amp; of John Fothergill’s advice &amp; counsel to parents, <said>prepare their minds to receive the power of truth without which they can never be happy.</said> Oh how is this of a religious education enforced when we consider how capable the young generation are  vast improvements &amp; vast refinement which will appear to us if we read the accounts of Saint Paul concerning the great attainments &amp; blessed &amp; happy state of the Churches to whom he wrote. Paul in his Epistle to the Corinthians, told them that <quote type="biblical">their bodies were the temples of the holy ghost</quote>. He told the Ephesians that they were <quote type="biblical">fellow citizens with the saints &amp; of the household of God</quote>.  He told Phillipians that <quote type="biblical">their conversation was in heaven</quote>. He told the Colossians that they were <quote type="biblical">delivered from the power of darkness and translated into the kingdom of the dear son of God</quote>. He told the Hebrews that they were <quote type="biblical">come to the city of the living God, the heavenly Jerusalem</quote>. And Peter, in his epistle to the Churches, told them they were <quote type="biblical">a chosen generation, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a peculiar people</quote>. Oh blessed state &amp; glorious attainments! How vastly different from the state of a generation of [sinners?] or the state of those whose spirits are like wolves, bears, lions, &amp; tigers. Call after call has been given. Warning after warning has been sent from heaven.</p></div>

            <div>
            <pb n="007" facs="457113"/>
            <dateline><date when="1820-11-11">11th of the 11th month, 1820. </date></dateline><p>A cold snows winter-like day Is it not so now? As we read, the call of the lord has gone forth to the ends of the earth. All have heard, but all have not obeyed. Dreadful will that state be now, as it was formerly, to whom it was said, <quote type="biblical">I have called but <add>ye</add> have not answered, therefore when you call I will not answer but will not laugh at your calamity &amp; mock when your fear cometh.</quote> Hath not this been the direfull condition <add>of</add> very many giddy, unguarded, unstable youth who <quote type="biblical">pursue lying vanities &amp; forsake their own Mercies</quote>? Who have <quote type="biblical">cast out the thing that is good &amp; the enemy has pursued them,</quote> so we may see <quote type="biblical">many live not half their days by cleaving unto wicked ways</quote>? One very remarkable <add>instance</add> <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> mentions of a young woman of the family of Penn delighting in the finery and pleasures of the world was seized with violent illness that proved mortal to her. In the time of her sickness, she fell into great distress of soul, bitterly bewailing the want of that inward peace which makes a death bed easy to the Righteous. After several days languishing a little consolation appeared after this manner: she was some hours in a kind of a Trance. She apprehended she was brought into a place where Christ was; to whom, could she but deliver her petition, she hoped to be relieved. But her endeavors increased her pain, for as she pressed to deliver it, he turned his back on her &amp; would not so much as look towards her. But that which added to her sorrow, was that she beheld others admitted. However, she gave not over, importuning him and when almost ready to faint &amp; her hope to sink, he turned one side of his face towards her &amp; received her petition or request, at which her troubled soul found immediate consolation. Turning to the those about her she repeats what had befallen her, adding, <said>Bring me my new clothes, take off the lace &amp; finery,</said> and charged her relations not to deck and adorn themselves after the manner of the world, for that the Lord Jesus whom she had seen appeared to her in the likeness of a plain country man without any trimming or ornament whatever, and that his servants ought to be like him. <quote type="biblical">Be ye not conformed to this world</quote> is a positive command in holy writ, and for want of obedience to it, many—very many—have been the sorrowful instances of our dear youth like this about mentioned I believed could collect enough to fill a volume. <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says conformity to the world in their never-settled fashions, cuts, &amp; modes, their unending flaps &amp; capes &amp; whiskers &amp; outlandish dresses, etc. is the mark of the Beast, &amp; where they prevail, the Beast rules the man. And he says they are fallen souls that prefer the invention of a tailor or tradesman to the workmanship of the great all-wise creator. See their high crowned hats not in the shape of their heads &amp; other parts of their clothes do they look fit for company <add>of</add> him who for our Example wore a garment without a seam?

            <pb n="008" facs="457113"/>
            I have read accounts &amp; seen diverse religious societies of people who set out in their beginning with a full clear a testimony against superfluity as ever the people called Quakers did, and yet gave way to a conformity to the world’s fashions til they lost sight of that testimony, until there was not the least vestige, sign, or token of it to be seen amongst them. John Wycliffe, who was called the morning star of the reformation, testified that all ostentation &amp; show in dress was prohibited by the gospel in these words: <quote type="biblical">Be ye not conformed to this world.</quote> And is it not so? I have been informed that the Baptists were in their beginning <del><gap/></del> as plain a people as ever Friends were, the Mennonites, &amp; some others I could mention, but all fallen away to a conformity to the world’s fashion. And as many worthy Friends have noticed &amp; lamented the deviations in that respect amongst us, as was formerly said, <quote type="biblical">blindness in part hath happened to Israel.</quote> Indeed, many are so blind they can plead &amp; palliate for it, although our dear worthy ancestors suffered so deeply for the testimony on that account &amp; growed in the truth under their sufferings. And does it look likely we should grow in the truth whilst we are trampling upon that testimony for which they so deeply suffered? A testimony which they undoubtedly believed Christ &amp; his apostles &amp; prophets called upon them to bear by their examples? Do we not read that <quote type="biblical">where much is given much will be required</quote> &amp; <quote type="biblical">they who know their master’s will &amp; do it not are to be beaten with many stripes</quote>? If so, what are we to expect? Oh, how have we been favored, with line upon line, precept upon precept, here a great deal &amp; there a great deal! Favored with the upper &amp; the nether spring, with the dew of heaven &amp; the fatness of the earth! But instead of inquiring what we shall render to the lord for all his benefits, is it not the express language of conduct, <quote type="biblical">What shall we eat, what shall we drink, and wherewithal shall we be clothed?</quote> <quote type="biblical">We will eat our own meat &amp; wear our own apparel, only let us be called by thy name.</quote> What an unspeakable favor it is that our lot has been cast in a place, a day, &amp; time wherein the light of Gospel &amp; the Christian Religion hath so far prevailed, whilst thousands &amp; hundreds of thousands are groaning under the grossest darkness, idolatry, &amp; superstition like the barbarian we read of: practicing things amongst themselves as dreadful as them we read of when <quote type="biblical">they caused their children to pass through the fire to Moloch,</quote> things which the Lord never commanded them to do. How many nations are there wherein there is not such ministers raised up amongst them as we have amongst us? As of old it is said, <quote type="biblical">Also I set watchmen over you, saying <said>hearken to the sound of the trumpet,</said> but they said <said>we will not hearken.</said></quote></p> <signed>John Hunt</signed></div>

            <div><pb n="009" facs="457113"/>
            <p>See Acts 11:26: <quote type="biblical">the Disciples were called Christians first in Antioch</quote>. Since that time it appears by an account my dear worthy ancient friend <add>George Dilwyn</add> gave some years ago of the names of the different sects of professing Christians that there have been 374 risen up since the Christian [era?]. We read of diverse in the New Testament: of Herodians &amp; the scribes &amp; Pharisees &amp; Sadducees Essenes etc., and it is probable very many have sunk into oblivion &amp; quite forgotten. Some of these different sects were most monstrous in their opinions &amp; practices, as some of them are at this day, particularly the sect called the Shaking Quakers &amp; diverse others too tedious to mention. Their unaccountable opinions &amp; practices (many of them after making a great noise about religion) fell away &amp; went to decay, and I find some of our greatest writers, Barclay &amp; Penn, believe that some of these sects of professing Christians in their beginning <add>were</add> very bright &amp; [clear?] &amp; run well for a time and for a time were as burning &amp; shining lights, and some stood their ground for a long time. The Waldenses, <persName key="w6p55q0b">William Penn</persName> says, maintained their religious principles for five hundred years wherein they suffered all the most cruel persecutions of all sorts, yet after all this the Enemy made an inroad upon them by seducing them &amp; drawing them into a conformity to <add>this</add> world &amp; its spirit, customs, maxims, &amp; manners. James Naylor, I think, says to this effect, through Pride, Luxury, &amp; Ease hath the life of true Religion been slain from the foundation of the world and Samuel Fothergill says to this effect, through the giving way to pride in rulers &amp; teachers &amp; the want of humility, destruction, &amp; desolation has been the Lot of some of the greatest, fairest, most flourishing empires &amp; kingdoms that ever were erected in the world. One reformation &amp; kingdom hath it destroyed after another. Read the 28th chapter of Deuteronomy, &amp; the 29th of Ezekiel: <quote type="biblical">the fall of Tyrus threatens that greatest &amp; most wealthy nation</quote>. And how many of the ancient greatest nations do we read of, Babylon, Egypt, &amp; Jerusalem, &amp; many others, who were not only threatened but quite destroyed, so that there is not least vestige of them to be found. Our first Friends say in one of their most excellent epistles, say that that society of people who do not look back to their first principles will surely go to decay. If we look back to our beginning (then say they) great concerns were a great trouble &amp; great trade, a great burden all heedless things such as fine houses, rich furniture,

            <pb n="010" facs="457113"/>
            gaudy apparel—these things were an eyesore. But are they so now with us? Our eyes <add>say they</add> being single to the Lord and the in-shinings of his <add>light</add>, it so stained the glory of the things of the world in our view that they bore no mastery with <add>us</add>, neither did they lay near us. Our concern was chiefly to live near to the Lord and attain his favor, like the Royal Psalmist who said the Lord’s Loving kind<add>ness</add> was better than Life—and many of our first Friends suffered death in noisome, stinking prisons &amp; dungeons, &amp; thereby manifested they preferred the Lord’s favor before their lives, property, or liberty, counting nothing too near or too dear to part with for the lord’s favor, &amp; could say with Job of old, <quote type="biblical">thy ways have I kept &amp; not declined neither have I gone back from the commandment of his lips but have entered the words of his mouth more than my necessary food.</quote> Divers of them I could name said they desired to make so little do for the body as would relieve nature that they might have the more time to wait upon &amp; serve the Lord &amp; be helpful to their fellow creatures. They were of the same mind with one of the ancient fathers: that a few things simple &amp; plain serve a Christian: was a state &amp; disposition very different from the poor dry form <gap/> or like the gentiles contenting themselves with the bare name, and caring only for the poor moldering body, say<add>ing</add>, <quote type="biblical">What shall we eat? or What shall we drink? &amp; Wherewithal shall we be clothed?</quote> <quote type="biblical">We will will eat our own meat &amp; wear our own apparel, only let us be called by thy <add>name</add>.</quote> So like Demus we read of who forsook the lord’s cause &amp; embraced this present world: but mark the effects &amp; fruits of these two different ways. As to our first Friends who chose the lord for their portion, what amiable, able, powerful ministers many of them came to be, whose names deserve to be held in everlasting remembrance! How were they preserved &amp; upheld through all their grievous troubles &amp; trials, &amp; how triumphantly &amp; gloriously they did conquer over death, Hell, &amp; the grave! But how did it end with Demus, Dives, Judas, &amp; Gehazi, &amp; the man that concluded he had goods laid up in store for many years, &amp; that he would eat, drink, &amp; be merry or take his rest? Do we not read, <quote type="biblical">it was said to him, <q>thou fool, this night shall thy soul be required of thee &amp; then whose shall those things be which thou hast provided?</q></quote> And so shall it be with all those who lay up treasure for themselves &amp; are not rich towards God. Are not those likened to <quote type="biblical">a Partridge that lieth upon upon eggs &amp; hatcheth them not? So he that getteth riches &amp; not by right shall leave them in the midst of their days &amp; in the end become a fool?</quote> Have we not seen those things verified in many instances?

            <pb n="011" facs="457113"/>
            374, it is said, (and perhaps many more) different <add>sects or</add> denominations of professing Christians who cannot agree or unite together in performing their religious devotions, and all the while Christ says, <quote type="biblical">I am the way, the truth, and the life.</quote> Is he not all in all? And without him can anyone do anything at all that will tend to the peace of their own minds or the good of their fellow creatures? And do we not read that Christ is come the second time without sin unto salvation to teach his people himself? And can it be believed that it is he that leads his people in so many different ways? I observe the sentiments of diverse amongst the wisest of men of the greatest religious experience, that is, that there is but one only true religion in the world and that is the work of the spirit of the Lord in the hearts of the children of men, what that has done in them &amp; for them. And although many may have a religion that is very little if any better than none, yea no doubt very many have had a great zeal for a religion that is a great zeal worse than none, such as Paul was before his conversion, very many others who so grievously persecuted &amp; destroyed Christians since Cain slew Abel. Yet undoubtedly it is true what one says, see <title>Sequel to the English Reader,</title> page 130 &amp; 131: <quote>if these hopes and these sentiments contributed more to our happiness &amp; to the purification of our nature than anything else in the world can do, surely that religion to which alone we owe these sentiments &amp; hopes must be the greatest blessing that ever was conferred on the paternity of Adam.</quote> Again same page, <quote>Christianity, as one well observes, is a doctrine in which nothing is superfluous or burdensome and in which there is nothing wanting which can procure happiness to mankind or by which God can be glorified.</quote> See John 14 &amp; 26, <quote type="biblical">but the comforter which is the Holy Ghost whom the father will send in my name, he shall teach you all things and bring all things to your remembrance.</quote> It has been said that among all the innumerable blessings the Lord has bestowed upon his people, himself is the crown of all, the comforter which is the holy ghost. Is not this greatest blessing to mankind? So Samuel Fothergill says to those who are desirous of living to the best, wisest, &amp; happiest purposes of life - without which they had better never have have lived - and indeed without this blessed hope (this comforter) we are of all creatures the most miserable, being daily surrounded with lamentations and woe, combatting with secret or obvious distress, &amp; encountering from the cradle to the grave a perpetual succession &amp; variety of afflictions. We might therefore truly say if our hopes were only fixed upon the transitory and fleeting pleasures of this life we should be of all the animal creation the most miserable.

            <pb n="012" facs="457113"/>
            <quote>Pitch upon that way of life which is best &amp; custom will soon make it agreeable,</quote> says Pythagoras. Custom alone in time may draw the strangest things into a law &amp; make wrong seem right &amp; right seem wrong, &amp; put light for darkness &amp; darkness for light, bitter for sweet &amp; sweet for bitter. But woe to them that do so, says the scripture, as we read <quote type="biblical">the Ethiopian cannot change his skin, nor the leopard his spots, no more can they refrain that are accustomed to do evil.</quote> Mark &amp; see the power of custom. <quote type="poem">It is education forms the tender mind; just as the twig is bent, the tree is inclined</quote>; as one said, he supposed if he had been born &amp; educated among the heathen he should have been a heathen, if amongst the barbarians he should have been a barbarian, if among the Turks or Mohammedans and he should have been like them. [Peter] Charron in his Book of Wisdom on the subject of education says, <quote>take two whelps &amp; bring one up in the kitchen and the other in the forest, &amp; see if there will not be a very great difference in their conduct if not in their very nature.</quote> So true the ancient saying, <quote>in use is second nature.</quote> Take two children &amp; give one of them them a guarded religious education, let him be placed in a school like one I have read of, where the teacher was a worthy Minister &amp; deeply concerned for the children’s improvement &amp; growth in the truth as well as for their school learning, where they had meetings, often highly favored with the powerful overshadowings of the Holy Ghost, &amp; the children in their minority could speak of the mysteries of the Kingdom of Heaven more like men &amp; women experienced in religion than like children. And take the other and place him in the camp and educate him in all the arts of Military, Carnal war, exposed to company where there was continual Rioting &amp; Drunkenness, chambering, gambling, &amp; wantonness, &amp; Evil communication which corrupts good Manners, and must it not be a miracle if he is not contaminated &amp; corrupted &amp; like the company he is educated in? It is an ancient saying, <quote>a man is to be known by the company he keeps.</quote> Here we may see how unspeakably important, how great the responsibility &amp; weighty the obligations parents &amp; guardians are under who have the care of souls, the care of Lord’s glory, &amp; the Church’s peace &amp; prosperity upon them. <said>A guarded religious education is the richest gift a parent can bestow upon a child, the want of which can never be made up by all the money or earthly treasures it may be in his power to give him,</said> says Frederick Smith. <said>Prepare their minds to received the power of truth without which they never can be happy,</said> says John Fothergill, a worthy minister &amp; dignified servant of the Lord.</p></div>

            <closer>
                <signed><persName key="w6n9820p">John Hunt</persName> 28th of the 11th month 1820</signed>
            </closer> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
