<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Hannah Fry to Ann Evans, 9mo 26, 1794: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Lyra Ederington</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 9 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were created and/or prepared by the <hi rend="italic" >Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</hi> and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <hi rend="italic"> Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College </hi>.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
                <idno type="local">A00187160</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Friendly Networks</title>
                <title level="s" type="series">
                    <title level="s" type="main">The Correspondence of John Hunt and Joshua Evans</title>
                </title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Joshua Evans papers, SFHL-RG5-190</collection>
                        <idno type="local">A00187160</idno>
                        <idno type="IslandoraNodeid">457196</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>4 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The correspondence of Quaker ministers John Hunt and Joshua Evans are stored at the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College. With the generous support of H. David and Joyce E. Hunt, Library staff scanned and transcribed these letters in 2023 and encoded the text in TEI. The 2023 project also included researching individuals mentioned in the text to create and update records about them in the <ref target="https://snaccooperative.org/">Social Networks and Archival Context website</ref></p>           
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written <date when="1794-09-26">9th month 26th 1794</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <term>Travel--Religious aspects</term>
                    <term>Quakers--Doctrines</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#lcnaf">
                    <term ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2020100384">Evans, Joshua, 1731-1798</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item><date/></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
            <pb n="1" facs="457197"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>Falmouth <date when="1794-09-26">9th month 26th 1794</date></dateline>
                <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
            In a degree of that love which <del>flows</del> reaches over land &amp; seas, I now sit down to salute thee, with a few lines, to inform thee a little, of thy dear husband’s travels in our parts. The 4th of the this month at our meeting at Kittery; (the place of my abode.) it being our meeting day, he sat with us through the meeting in silence, at the loss of which, he expressed a desire to meet with friends again at the third hour, saying he thought he should be most easy therewith &amp; accordingly we did. In which I believe he had good services; being favored I believe to feel the sweet incomes of that love which desires the welfare of souls &amp; breaths forth nothing else, but pure love to God, &amp; good will to mankind. &amp; I firmly believe <del><gap/></del> that he was guided by the spirit of truth, &amp; unerring wisdom. &amp; that he was fervently engaged in spirit for the spreading of truth &amp; the enlargement of Lion’s borders, &amp; that all her travelers might be preserved in patience &amp; faithfulness.
            </p>
            <p>
            And
            <pb n="2" facs="457198"/>
            and I believe he sees the great need there is of keeping inwardly attentive to the pointings of truth, &amp; I believe his spirit <add>is</add> impressed <add>with</add> very fervent desires that truth might spread throughout the earth. &amp; that none might deviate therefrom. &amp; his labors of love is very acceptable, &amp; heart affecting, to some honest hearted, sincere Friends, a number of whom I believe there is. Scattered up &amp; down. Who are sheep of the true fold. &amp; the true shepherd’s holy eye is to them. &amp; that his heavenly care is over them. &amp; that he is a Father kind, &amp; near to all his children who daily trust in him. Oh! My dear friend, I wish thou might with thy family be comforted under the present dispensations of providence, for I believe thy dear husband has no prospect of returning home very soon. &amp; hope thou will be preserved in patience. Until his work be done, he seems very much resigned &amp; given up to do his master’s service. His love seems to flow to all. In such accents that is seems as though he would fain spread his net over all. That all might be gathered into the <del>true</del> garner &amp; true fold of rest. He seems indeed very near to me, &amp; I feel a near sympathy for him, in his many &amp; various tribulations, which no doubt he meets with as he passes along.
            </p>
            <p>    
            Yet
            <pb n="3" facs="457199"/>
            yet I believe that <add>he</add> who saw meet to send him forth in his service, is able, &amp; no less willing <add>to</add> enable him to go forward, &amp; I firmly believe that he will grant him his holy aid, &amp; the strength of his mighty arm, to bear up &amp; support him <add>in</add> every trial, although it may be hard to flesh and blood. Yet that inward peace of mind &amp; sweet consolation, which our heavenly father is pleased to favor his children with at times &amp; seasons, far transcends all outward joy. So with desires that the father of mercies may for replenish thy heart. With a sense of his goodness, &amp; also thy dear children’s, that you may <add>another</add> murmur nor pine, in his absence, but be freely <del>given</del><add>given</add> up; casting your whole care upon him, whose never failing is sufficient. For I believe he will be a husband to thee &amp; a father to thy children. Until it shall please him to say to his servant, thy work is done.
            </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>I conclude in tender love near sympathy for thee &amp; thy children &amp; remain thy poor tribulated friend</salute>
                <signed>Hannah Fry</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>N. B. Elizabeth Varney, Elizabeth Deen &amp; Lydia Windslow desire their love to thee</p>
            </postscript>
            </div>
            <pb n="4" facs="457200"/>
            <closer>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Ann Evans</addrLine>
                </address> 
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
