<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Joshua Evans to his wife and children, 6mo 26, 1795: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Lyra Ederington</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 9 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were created and/or prepared by the <hi rend="italic" >Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</hi> and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <hi rend="italic"> Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College </hi>.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
                <idno type="local">A00187162</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Friendly Networks</title>
                <title level="s" type="series">
                    <title level="s" type="main">The Correspondence of John Hunt and Joshua Evans</title>
                </title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>Joshua Evans papers, SFHL-RG5-190</collection>
                        <idno type="local">A00187162</idno>
                        <idno type="IslandoraNodeid">457206</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>2 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The correspondence of Quaker ministers John Hunt and Joshua Evans are stored at the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College. With the generous support of H. David and Joyce E. Hunt, Library staff scanned and transcribed these letters in 2023 and encoded the text in TEI. The 2023 project also included researching individuals mentioned in the text to create and update records about them in the <ref target="https://snaccooperative.org/">Social Networks and Archival Context website</ref></p>           
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written <date when="1790-06-26">26 the 6th month 1790</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <term>Travel--Religious aspects</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item><date/></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" facs="457207"/>
            
            <opener>
                <dateline>Montreal <date when="1790-06-26">26 the 6th month 1790</date></dateline>
            </opener>
            
            <p>
            I am now in the <damage><gap/></damage>als of t<damage><supplied>he</supplied></damage> city in good health &amp; more so than I have been for se<damage><supplied>veral</supplied></damage> years my dear wife &amp; children this is an inexplicable opportunity Samuel Newbole of informing you how &amp; w<add>h</add>ere I am this <damage><supplied>rning</supplied></damage> left Sapparary a little town on the south side of the riv<damage><supplied>er</supplied></damage> Saint Larants about twenty miles beyond Saint John’s &amp; rode nine miles down the river crossed a creek where was no bridge we dragged the wagon on three logs, I then swam, the horses we got well over &amp; then down the river about a mile below Montreal here we left our horses, crossed the river in a canoe the water is about a mile and a half in width where we left our horses &amp; my <del>com</del> companion to cross when a larger hole come we have met with kind usage from all sorts of people being of a strange langu<damage><supplied>age</supplied></damage> has been the most trying of all for not and in abundance ca<damage><supplied>n</supplied></damage> understand me or I them. We also visited an Indian nation or town where resided about three hundred men, women, &amp; children they looked as the natives you see t<damage><gap/></damage> d<damage><gap/></damage> former way of dress with but breeches, both men and wo<damage><supplied>men</supplied></damage> with painted faces, breastplates, earrings, &amp; nose jewels <gap reason="illegible"/> their chief was a solid, wise, good, kind man. We was kindly received by him &amp; bid us welcome in the evening he brought one son to interpret, he wanted to know my business &amp; why I left my home so far I showed my certificate he said it was very good, he said he was glad to see me &amp; to hear words from me but I should soon go away &amp; he might forget them but if I would be pleased to leave him something in writing that he could see when I was gone for he had ever heard of Quakers or Friends before &amp; should be glad to be acquainted with their principles for he was not satisfied that their priests would not let his children learn english &amp; read the scriptures &amp; wanted to know what I thought was the reason I told him, the priest as I did believe was not willing, they should think for themselves for fear they should find a better principle then his was &amp; so leave him &amp; pay him no more money he said he was of the same belief but
            <pb n="2" facs="457208"/>
            but he intended his children should learn to read english that they might read the scriptures to him &amp; other books <damage><gap/></damage> things was interpreted to him he ascented by the youth &amp; some unto would say it was good. I left him some books as a letter in writing to his satisfaction, he entertained us well that night &amp; when I parted, he bid me welcome &amp; said he hoped he should see me again at Montreal, my dear wife &amp; children I h<damage><supplied>ad</supplied></damage> as common some <gap reason="illegible"/> baptizing seasons such as I cannot describe to you in this strange kind of a language I cannot understand and yet I find some tender hearted, honest inquiries that it is to their comfort &amp; mine to though labor is hard &amp; the field wide but my dear master is a rich rewarder. I cannot say I lack anything I find I have lost all my judgment &amp; lead so contrary to my own judgment that I have left thinking today what I shall do tomorrow but believe the shepherd of Israel will not put his sheep forth, but he will prepare the way before them. I get but slowly on, for I find more to do by far than what I looked for. I have been at no great expense as yet, but now money goes fast, for things is scarce &amp; dear, but I have my hearth as <damage><gap/></damage> had I shall have a<damage><gap/></damage> I have a companion &amp; a pilot so there is three in company &amp; we travel in great harmony. My pilot is a man suitable for the task. so I conclude with my heart feeling love to you my dear wife &amp; children &amp; bid you fair well &amp; am your loving husband, father &amp; friend. But when I shall see you I cannot tell.
            </p>
            
            <closer>
                <signed>Joshua Evans</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
