<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Cox letter to John Hunt, 1824 3mo 17: Electronic Version</title>
                <editor>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Markup done by</resp>
                    <name>Lyra Ederington</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. 10 KB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</publisher>
                <address>
                    <street>500 College Avenue</street>
                    <addrLine>Swarthmore, Pennsylvania</addrLine>
                    <postCode>19081</postCode>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </address>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain. The text encoding and editorial notes were created and/or prepared by the <hi rend="italic" >Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</hi> and are licensed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit the <hi rend="italic"> Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College </hi>.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
                <idno type="local">A00187148</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s" type="project">Friendly Networks</title>
                <title level="s" type="series">
                    <title level="s" type="main">The Correspondence of John Hunt and Joshua Evans</title>
                </title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College</institution>
                        <collection>John Hunt Papers, SFHL-RG5-240</collection>
                        <idno type="local">A00187148</idno>
                        <idno type="IslandoraNodeid">457157</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>4 pp.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The correspondence of Quaker ministers John Hunt and Joshua Evans are stored at the Friends Historical Library of Swarthmore College. With the generous support of H. David and Joyce E. Hunt, Library staff scanned and transcribed these letters in 2023 and encoded the text in TEI. The 2023 project also included researching individuals mentioned in the text to create and update records about them in the <ref target="https://snaccooperative.org/">Social Networks and Archival Context website</ref></p>           
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Original written <date when="1824-03-17">3rd month 17th 1824</date></creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
                    <term>Quakers--Conduct of life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item><date/></item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="001" facs="457158"/>
            <opener>
             <dateline>near Burlington, <date when="1824-03-17">3rd month 17th 1824.</date><note type="authorial" place="margin">Received this <date when="1824-03-22">22 of the 3rd month</date></note></dateline>
             <salute>Dear Friend</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
            I should have acknowledged, long before now, thy kind token of affectionate remembrance, as expressed in a little scrip, dated the <date when="1824-01-03">3rd of 1st month</date>, had I known of any direct conveyance. For it was really pleasant once more to see the handwriting of an old friend, and to feel unity with the exercise of his spirit, at a period of life when the possession of durable riches and righteousness is beyond all price. That the love of many has waxed cold, in this day of ease and indifference, and the vital energies of faith and practice greatly abated, in comparison with ancient time, when the first and great commandment gained and kept the ascendancy more generally than in these degenerate days, will be readily admitted; yet, as under all former dispensations of infinite wisdom to the children of men, and in each and every age and generation, from the beginning to the present time, a Seed, an afflicted, travailing seed, has been, and is still preserved alive. I see not what we can do better than to use all diligence in the work assigned us, leaving the blessing on the labor of our hands to Him who hath sown the seed, and who alone can give the increase in its season, to his own praise, and to the gradual and more firm establishment of his faithful and dedicated servants on that rock which was immovably fixed before the Holy One called the visible creation into existence, and which will remain unshaken, when <quote type="biblical">the things that are seen</quote> shall all have past away. I do not write thus from the aboundings of faith, which, I am sure, is often at a
            <pb n="002" facs="457159"/>
            low ebb; but as a little is sufficient to sustain life, if we work in that little, the gracious giver can and will increase the measure, and effect concerning us, all his own wise and good purposes. Thy race, my dear friend, in the usual course of nature, is nearly at an end; mine, in the same course, cannot be of much longer duration, and therefore, in thus addressing thee, with feelings of brotherly sympathy, and with a retrospect to the trials through which we have been mercifully supported, I will venture to express a cheering hope that as we continue our endeavors to confide in Him who has sustained and fed us thus far on the journey, <add>he</add> will be our guide and protector to the end; therefore, be of good cheer, for “greater is he that is in us, than he that is in the world”. I had heard of the decease of your daughter <persName key="w68x44wf">Abigail</persName> soon after it happened, an event which, at your time of life, must be felt a great privation indeed. But in this dispensation, trying to nature as it is, you have not sorrowed as those without hope, but have felt, as in similar afflictions, of which you have had no small portion, the everlasting arm underneath. My wife unites with me in love to thee and thine. We have past through the winter more comfortably than usual, having been seldom confined a day by indisposition, which we deem a great favor.
            </p>
            <p>
            It was a satisfaction to me, to receive last fall, a letter from our old friend Abraham Hannington, containing
            <pb n="003" facs="457160"/>
            an affecting account of the sickness in that country, and of the decease of Joshua, their only remaining son, of Typhus fever. I suppose this information is not new to thee. Knowing thou art interested in the prosperity of the good cause, I may mention our English visitors are in progress, though we have heard nothing of Isaac Stevenson’s movements since his being in Rhode Island, perhaps about mid-winter. Anna Braithwaite was lately, and I suppose is now, engaged in a visit to the families of Friends in New York. A few days past. <persName key="w65d92g1">William Forster</persName> was at Bordentown, intending to pass on to Trenton thence to Grosswick, or Upper Springfield, or both, and then down toward Philadelphia. Southward of us as to, so as to reach the city in time for the meeting for sufferings on the 19th instant. Now I am about to conclude, with desires that we may remember each other for good, and <add>also</add> that a mansion is prepared in the Father’s house for everyone that holds out to the end in well doing. That is, as I understand it, doing as well as we can, in the degree of strength and light afforded; and there being thus in us a willing mind, we shall be accepted, according to that which we have. In this belief, and in commemoration of the goodness and mercy of our holy head, who hath many a time <damage><supplied>enabled thee</supplied></damage> and me to set up our Ebenezer, with a humbling and grateful acknowledgement of His saving help. I am
            </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>thy affectionate friend</salute>
                <signed><persName key="w6b01gx6">John Cox</persName></signed>
            </closer>
            
            <closer>
                <pb n="004" facs="457161"/>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><persName key="w6n9820p">John Hunt</persName> near Moorestown</addrLine>
                </address>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
